<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Lilith</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>24528992</id>
    <revision>
      <id>498312514</id>
      <parentid>498296276</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-19T09:32:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>In ictu oculi</username>
        <id>11184537</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Feminism should not be catorgized under Occult */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="92833">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=18 August 2007
|action1result=not listed
|action1oldid=152133854
|currentstatus=FGAN
|topic=philrelig
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{Wikiproject_mythology|class=B|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Bible|class=B}}
{{WikiProject Judaism|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Kabbalah|class=B}}
{{WPOccult|class=B|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Women's History|class=B|importance=mid}}
}}
{{todo}}
{{Archive box|[[/Archive 1|Archive 1]]}}

==Satanism and Lilith==

I'm wonder why, looking at the archive, why the whole church of Satan (who uses her most symbolically at least as the wife of Satan), was *complained* about on this page in the archive and then edited off. But with the popular references, such as a Narnia reference, this was allowed on this page for a very long time. This is something I don't get. If references to her in a  religious organization is not allowed, then why was popular references for a longer period of time? I think that's why too biased and unacademic for wikipedia.
[[Special:Contributions/173.171.36.206|173.171.36.206]] ([[User talk:173.171.36.206|talk]]) 03:55, 26 November 2009 (UTC)

==The Edenic Serpent as Lilith in Christian Art?==

An Opinion....flip the bas relief image180 degrees and there appears a bat, a night screech owl...  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/70.26.14.180|70.26.14.180]] ([[User talk:70.26.14.180|talk]]) 00:30, 22 June 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

There are a couple of images on the Lilith page that unambiguously identify a female serpent with Lilith.  The identification of the serpent as Lilith in the Michelangelo and Notre Dame images (and perhaps others on this page?) is a mistake.  The Edenic serpent, in the Christian tradition, is identified with Satan.  The serpent is often depicted with female attributes to point up its seductiveness and its association with Eve.  To identify such depictions as Lilith is a misinterpretation.  I notice that Alan Humm, in his webpage that is cited as support in the Lilith article, advances the association between the iconography of the serpent with Lilith tentatively and speculatively, and says that he knows of no textual basis for the identification.  The question, as they say, is in need of attention from an expert on the subject.  JEM.&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.41.28.120|24.41.28.120]] ([[User talk:24.41.28.120|talk]]) 07:53, 16 February 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Similar Themes?==
*Prototype of the [[femme fatale]] theme in which woman seduces males which results in their death/destruction-such as [[Favorite Son (Star Trek: Voyager)]];  a [[fantasy]] ''[[Twilight Zone]]'' episode &quot;[[Queen of the Nile (The Twilight Zone)]]&quot;, [[Ann Blyth]] stars as a femme fatale who keeps her youth by sacrificing human males with [[black magic]] as do fatales in episode 16 &quot;Demon in lace&quot; and episode 19 &quot;The Youth Killers&quot; on ''[[Kolchak: The Night Stalker]]''. A similar theme of a woman/women sacrificing human males for eternal youth—using [[science]]—appears in Star trek cartoon ''[[The Lorelei Signal]]'' and in episode &quot;Paradise Lost&quot; on ''[[Otherworld (TV series)]]''?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/74.83.126.88|74.83.126.88]] ([[User talk:74.83.126.88|talk]]) 14:01, 30 March 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
**Good point. Men have a history, both in fiction and real life, of distrusting and fearing women, especially powerful women. Men used to perceive women as seductresses with the potential of overthrowing the rule of males. This is why men used to keep women down. --[[User:Michaeldsuarez|Michaeldsuarez]] ([[User talk:Michaeldsuarez|talk]]) 16:07, 30 March 2010 (UTC)



== lead in  ==

There's been some activity on the lead-in.  Some parts about here role as first Adam wife got deleted and I restored those.  The scope of the article has expanded beyond her roles in Jewish and Christian books and the lead in doesn't acknowledge these views so I add a small blurb from the occultists section.
If you read through the article hew common themes are:
*Able to make any woman infertile yet she can produce hundreds of her own offspring daily.
*Induce lust in any man
*Choose who she has sex with.
*Eats or steals children.

Everyone agree these are common themes?  Am I missing some? [[User:Alatari|Alatari]] ([[User talk:Alatari|talk]]) 03:52, 19 April 2010 (UTC)
:Great job! Thank you. [[User:USchick|USchick]] ([[User talk:USchick|talk]]) 19:05, 20 April 2010 (UTC)

== Sources list of newer works on Lilith (some of which are modern interpretations not academic sources on history)==

*Sources for newer looks at Lilith
**[http://www.questia.com/googleScholar.qst?docId=96537502 Looks at changes in her myth thru modern Sci Fi authors (1970's on isn't that 'modern').  Mentions feminist bibles and other sources.]
**A compiled bliography: [http://jewishchristianlit.com//Topics/Lilith/lilith.html Lilith topics]
**[http://www.sacredspiral.com/articles/lm/lilith.htm Lilith as a Goddess with bibliography.]
**[http://www.wisdomsgoldenrod.org/publications/kdamiani/kdsop112.pdf by Kathleen Granville Damiani ''SOPHIA: EXILE AND RETURN''] a graduate students work with sources.
**C.L. Moore's &quot;Fruit of Knowledge&quot;
**Octavia E. Butler's Dawn
** Hélene Cixous and Catherine Clément's assertion that &quot;myth transmits itself making changes in accordance with . . . cultural evolution&quot; (1986, 6)
**[http://muse.jhu.edu/login?uri=/journals/childrens_literature_association_quarterly/v029/29.1-2.graham.pdf Jean E. Graham Women, Sex, and Power: Circe and Lilith in Narnia Children's Literature Association Quarterly - Volume 29, Number 1-2, Spring/Summer 2004, pp. 32-44]
**[http://www.jstor.org/pss/537379 # Lilith # Raphael Patai # The Journal of American Folklore, Vol. 77, No. 306 (Oct. - Dec., 1964), pp. 295-314] Mentions her beginnings in Gilgamesh lore.
**[http://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=XRKBH-adiC4C&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA3&amp;dq=Book+of+Lilith&amp;ots=G737vuX6uK&amp;sig=WHHrhSrLXaUf-hcw-Hu8KBcQBJc#v=onepage&amp;q=lilith&amp;f=false &quot;The Salem Witches' Book of Love Spells: Ancient Spells from Modern Witches&quot; By Lilith McLelland] A witches spell to banish a controlling lover. Has an excellent summary of the modern feminist look at Lilith. &quot;Modern women have given back Lilith her stolen divinity and honor her as the first feminist.&quot;
**[http://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=-TVIAAAAIAAJ&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA13&amp;dq=Book+of+Lilith&amp;ots=tmlDpFrlnM&amp;sig=XcmimFMBpwV-Wtk-W_qNTrhF7Fk#v=onepage&amp;q=Book%20of%20Lilith&amp;f=false &quot;Lilith: the legend of the first woman&quot; By Ada Langworthy Collier 1895 text]
**[http://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=6T9Y1EhiwDUC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA8&amp;dq=Book+of+Lilith&amp;ots=Xc0ruvmn1z&amp;sig=Q_neBHwe8pCSJI-8vz64in8rr3A#v=onepage&amp;q=Book%20of%20Lilith&amp;f=false &quot;Lilith-The First Eve: Historical and Psychological Aspects of the Dark Feminine&quot; By Siegmund Hurwitz 1999]
**[http://www.pep-web.org/document.php?id=joap.033.0198a Begg, E. (1988). Koltuv, Barbara Black. The Book of Lilith.: Yor... Pp. xii+ 127. $8.95. J. Anal. Psychol., 33:198-199.] 
**[http://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=SohkqKPGlvIC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA1&amp;dq=Lilith+Feminism&amp;ots=o-OYeTowtm&amp;sig=a5iKtDSBU14EGgKWksZHQwIZym0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Hunt, Mary E., 1951- ''The Coming of Lilith: Essays on Feminism, Judaism, and Sexual Ethics'', 1972-2003]
**[http://www.informaworld.com/smpp/content~content=a904363117&amp;db=all ''Jewish Feminism and Women's Identity'' Author: Susannah Heschel]
**[http://heinonline.org/HOL/LandingPage?collection=journals&amp;handle=hein.journals/djglp15&amp;div=17&amp;id=&amp;page= ''Rank Usurpation of Power - The Role of Patriarchal Religion and Culture in the Subordination of Women'', A; Stopler, Gila]
**(Phillips 1984 p. 39) ''The story of Lilith thus seems to embody the deepest male fears of impotence, weakness, and isolation in the face of unfettered female sexuality, assertiveness, and independence.''
**[http://fth.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/16/1/36 &quot;Lilith's Fire: Examining Original Sources of Power Re-defining Sacred Texts as Transformative Theological Practice&quot;] Kohenet Deborah J. Grenn {{quote |''This paper offers a reinterpretation of the divine as embodied by the Semitic goddess Lilith, she who has been represented and misrepresented in a variety of sacred texts. Working with Lilith as both symbol and archetype, I will analyze texts in which she appears,'' '''tracing her historical development and metamorphosis from goddess to demon to symbol of independence and open sexuality.''' ''As part of this analysis, I will discuss how Lilith's demonization was designed to keep women alienated from their own 'original sources' of power and spiritual authority. The essay concludes with an appreciation of feminist texts, including the first midrash or reinterpretation of the Alphabet of Ben Sira, and more recent work. I also bring in feminist scholars' reclamation of the Sacred Feminine through poetic/liturgical responses to damaging canonical texts. My paper argues that this literature, too, should be regarded as 'sacred text,' since these women-centered writings have become texts of empowerment for contemporary women as well as part of their spiritual practice.''}}


No offense to the above user. But the works cited aren't necessarily academic. Although they should be included in a Neopaganism/historical revisionism section of the article, I want to point out the sources. Looking at Sacred Spiral's select Bibliography, references include Walker, Barbara G.. The Woman's Encyclopedia of Myths and Secrets &amp; Stone, Merlin. When God Was a Woman. Harcourt Brace Jovanovich who aren't really academics on Mesopotamia or the myth of Lilitu. You can see this in [http://wicca.timerift.net/books_avoid.shtml some reviews]. It represents the Goddess movement, or Goddess spirituality movement, and this is where you get the assertion Lilith is a goddess or a facet of the Goddess.
[[User:Xuchilbara|Xuchilbara]] ([[User talk:Xuchilbara|talk]]) 03:58, 23 May 2010 (UTC)
:I understood the reliability of the source.  Those sources can be used to assert that there are modern interpretations of Lilith.  They can not be used as reliable sources as to Lilith's history or evolution (except amongst the pagan community).  I edited the Mesopotamia section heavily Saturday and that sources aren't relied upon.  Hurwitz, Patai and others were used.  I'll check again now but if I miss something point the section out.  [[User:Alatari|Alatari]] ([[User talk:Alatari|talk]]) 16:21, 24 May 2010 (UTC)

== Overly Broad ==
I've removed the claim of an analog in Greek myth in the lead section. It wasn't sourced. And for good reason because it isn't the case.Indeed the subsequent later paragraphs down at the bottom referring to Lamia are at best sketchy. 

I find some of the references to be graduate papers that are not peer reviewed or published in serious journals.
:In the reference list I added above?  I won't add the graduate paper as a source but they do an excellent job of compiling other sources.  [[User:Alatari|Alatari]] ([[User talk:Alatari|talk]]) 04:33, 7 May 2010 (UTC)
Overall the tendency to try and create broad analogs is a problem with obscure archetypal figures and should be avoided. [[User:Jenston|Jenston]] ([[User talk:Jenston|talk]]) 00:17, 30 April 2010 (UTC)

== Addition to the leadin ==

I want to add something like: ''The Lilith legend is still commonly used as source material in modern fantasy and horror.''  I think it is a good summary of the Modern Culture section that is regularly modified. Not an amazing amount of TV and movie appearances but she has 21 at [http://www.imdb.com/find?s=all&amp;q=lilith IMDB] starting in [http://www.imdb.com/character/ch0044672/ 1920]. Is there a similar database for book references? [[User:Alatari|Alatari]] ([[User talk:Alatari|talk]]) 05:03, 7 May 2010 (UTC)

== Dubious ==

The Kurdish translation seems wrong. The first letter in Shin, which is a &quot;sh&quot; sound.--[[Special:Contributions/72.178.134.135|72.178.134.135]] ([[User talk:72.178.134.135|talk]]) 02:51, 19 May 2010 (UTC)
:You a native Kurdish speaker and writer?  [[User:Alatari|Alatari]] ([[User talk:Alatari|talk]]) 09:13, 21 May 2010 (UTC)

==Transformation?==

Lilith is not, nor was ever, consider a deity to ancient Mesopotamians. I have plenty of actual scholarship on this. Furthermore, this section conflates Inanna's and lilitu's mythologies and makes some irrelevant statements. All this is a biased revisionist version of history to try to assert ancient worship where there is none.
[[User:Xuchilbara|Xuchilbara]] ([[User talk:Xuchilbara|talk]]) 16:32, 21 May 2010 (UTC)
:There were over 500 deities listed in some of the lists found.  The handmaiden of Inanna was one.  There are sources tying lilitu to that handmaiden.  You need to refute the sources.  [[User:Alatari|Alatari]] ([[User talk:Alatari|talk]]) 19:02, 22 May 2010 (UTC)
And while I am at it. There is more irrelevance in the fact that the previous section repeated much of what was already covered in Mesopotamia Lilitu. 
[[User:Xuchilbara|Xuchilbara]] ([[User talk:Xuchilbara|talk]]) 16:34, 21 May 2010 (UTC)

:Thanks for your help on the article.  New sections on talk pages go at the bottom. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 22:07, 21 May 2010 (UTC)
::On revisionism: If a notable number of the populace or numbers of published scholars believe in revision of any history (not just Lilith) under [[WP:NPOV]] their views must be included in the article even if it's just to mention refutation of those views.  [[Flat earth]] is refuted but is still notable.  If it's stemming from the Neopagan movement then the information can be moved into that section.   Since you have actual scholarship you would know if their are controversies about her origins and be able to edit a section on those controversies.  [[User:Alatari|Alatari]] ([[User talk:Alatari|talk]]) 13:18, 22 May 2010 (UTC)
::I reworked a few of the deleted paragraphs working from the sources and the work you deleted had many mistakes.  Lilitu wasn't the serpent but there was a serpent there in the Gilgamesh tale.  Much of the stuff deleted was information found in other articles and the last paragraph is disputed elsewhere.  I'm done re-netering and sourcing and fact checking these paragraphs.  Maybe there's more mistakes but 6 hours is enough of my day.  [[User:Alatari|Alatari]] ([[User talk:Alatari|talk]]) 19:02, 22 May 2010 (UTC)

I am thinking we should have a Neopaganism section as she's in early Wicca, modern Wicca, and the Gospel of Aradia as another form of Aradia. (And Gardner used Aradia's corrupted name in his original BOS.) I know of some groups like Lilithians, that have popped up. There's a lot to be covered there but I am limited in my Neopagan research to an extent. I almost think maybe it'd warrant another Lilith (Neopaganism) page as the views are so radically different than the historical Lilith. Either way it takes a lot of ground to cover.

I did notice, however, that someone did add a bit about the modern views on the top page.
[[User:Xuchilbara|Xuchilbara]] ([[User talk:Xuchilbara|talk]]) 03:37, 23 May 2010 (UTC)

==Major deletion==
I read through [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Lilith&amp;curid=18630&amp;diff=363410404&amp;oldid=363169854 this deletion] and agree that the section appears to be [[WP:OR]] and the sources do not support the cross cultural diffusion of Ianna into Lilith.  There is one section that is sourced and unless the sources bear out to be misquoted, should be kept.  It doesn't state that Ianna is Lilith but the sources claim that Lilith was Ianna's handmaiden.

&lt;blockquote&gt;''Babylonian texts depict Lilith as the [[sacred prostitution|sacred prostitute]] of the goddess [[Ishtar]], the [[Assyria]]n and [[Babylonia]]n counterpart to the [[Mesopotamian mythology|Sumerian]] [[Inanna]]. Similarly, older Sumerian accounts assert that Lilitu is called the handmaiden of [[Inanna]] or &quot;hand of Inanna.&quot; The Sumerian texts state that &quot;Inanna has sent the beautiful, unmarried, and seductive prostitute Lilitu out into the fields and streets in order to lead men astray.&quot; That is why Lilitu is called the &quot;hand of Inanna.&quot;&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;ref&gt;S.H. Langdon p.74&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hurwitz p.58&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt; Lilith is further associated with the [[Zu (mythology)|Anzu]] bird,&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kramer translates the Anzu as &quot;owl,&quot; but most often it is translated as &quot;eagle,&quot; &quot;vulture,&quot; or &quot;bird of prey.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt; lions, owls, and serpents, which are animals associated with the Lilitu, later reappearing in the [[Kabbalah]].''&lt;/blockquote&gt;

*What does S.H. Langdon book p74 and Hurwitz p.58 actually say and support?  
*What is the name of the ''&quot;hand of Inanna&quot;'' if not Lilith?  Then we can move the text to the appropriate Wikipedia article as we are not supposed to remove properly source material from the encyclopedia.
The Hurwitz book [http://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=6T9Y1EhiwDUC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA8&amp;dq=Hurwitz+Lilith&amp;ots=Xc0tAxdn4E&amp;sig=N14llhXNzPVGguo8kYjKlsLU8d0#v=onepage&amp;q=lilith&amp;f=false p. 58] clearly states the ''That is why Lilitu is called the &quot;hand of Inanna.''.  Unless Hurwitz can be destroyed as a reliable source this section is properly sourced and will be returned to the article. [[User:Alatari|Alatari]] ([[User talk:Alatari|talk]]) 13:26, 22 May 2010 (UTC)


:Hurwitz references Langdon from his book Tammuz and Ishtar, Oxford 1914, pg. 74. You can view such references and more [http://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=6T9Y1EhiwDUC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA8&amp;dq=hand+of+inanna+lilith+langdon&amp;ots=Xc0tAAkm8E&amp;sig=vvsK56BiC2wKEK4zQR68xPjV4GE#v=onepage&amp;q=hand%20of%20inanna%20lilith%20langdon&amp;f=false here]. If I recall correctly Patai also cites this text in the Hebrew Goddess in his chapter on Lilith.

:A major reason that section was deleted btw is that it tended to try to use the revisionist historical account that is not academic consensus on the demonic spirit Lilitu. There is no evidence of historical Lilith worship until the modern era, at least as far back as 1899 in Aradia. It also repeated much of what is already part of the article and tended to switch focus to Inanna. The &quot;hand of Inanna&quot; part was in there before the add and deletion. It didn't need to be repeated. [[User:Xuchilbara|Xuchilbara]] ([[User talk:Xuchilbara|talk]]) 23:35, 22 May 2010 (UTC)


:I looked up Tammuz and Ishtar and found it [http://books.google.com/books?id=ZuhDAAAAIAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=langdon+ishtar&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=H6Hc9iKGqT&amp;sig=eUmA9Na77s6YRN9ve199HTpR18I&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=Y5X4S86cGY_LlAeTjtCfCg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CBgQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false here]. The citation provided by Hurwitz is correct. In Langdon's notes on the same page he notes that this demon he is describing is what the Semites call &quot;Lilitu&quot;. [[User:Xuchilbara|Xuchilbara]] ([[User talk:Xuchilbara|talk]]) 02:45, 23 May 2010 (UTC)

I'm not an expert but just a critical reader from my science backround.  As I edited the Mesopotamian sections I noticed a great deal of errors and did my best to correct.  Some of this debate and confusion seems to me to stem from referring to a single lilitu demon or ''the'' Lilitu demon Lilith.  Is a reference in the archaic literature properly translated?  How did the Sumerians refer to a class of items and to a proper individual?  Is '''Ki-sikil-lil-la-ke''' a reference to a specific demon or a class? How about Ardat-lil? [[User:Alatari|Alatari]] ([[User talk:Alatari|talk]]) 16:41, 24 May 2010 (UTC)

Another point was that Hurwitz even disagrees with the etymology of Lilith from the widely accepted Rabbinic opinions.  He admits his opinion is minority (see pg 50? of 1980 book).  I sense Lilith has some controversy even in the academic community.  Wikipedia has guidelines about giving equal time to non-equal opinions [[WP:UNDUE]]. [[User:Alatari|Alatari]] ([[User talk:Alatari|talk]]) 16:41, 24 May 2010 (UTC)

I have no idea how to judge how accepted the Mesopotamian section is as of 2010.  If I understand the hypothesis goes: Judaism descend as a subbranch from the Akkadian Semitic speakers.  Their concepts of religion descended from (or were reactionary to) the concepts of that time.  Attributes of Lilith existed attached to some of the 500+ deities of that period.  Lilith of Judaism is a distant memory evolved from those times. This is controversial because of the limited amount of information from that period and the lack of language (speaking, writing) usage of that period.  Both of those are limits to all archaeology.  [[User:Alatari|Alatari]] ([[User talk:Alatari|talk]]) 16:41, 24 May 2010 (UTC)

I'm gonna do my best here. The word &quot;lilitu&quot; is confusing. Its a word that can refer to owls, a entire class of spirits, or just Lilitu herself. I am presuming the Hebrews inherited the loan word of &quot;lilith&quot; from their days in Babylonian captivity, as this is when the word first appears in Isa. 34:14. In fact this is where it gets tricky. (Hebrew language is similar to Canaanite. Lilith comes from the Sumero-Babylonian side of myth.) It is hottly debated rather this passage actually really refers to the Lilith or not. According to the later Zohar it does. According to other people it doesn't. See, owls, lilitu demons, and Lilith herself were said to roam the desert with wild animals and haunt desolate places and graveyards. (Inanna: Queen of heaven and earth states that after Lilith left the garden when Gilgamesh cut down the try she fled into the wilderness (desert) where she dwells today.) Owls in Mesopotamia are associated with evil spirits and haunted desolate and wild places like lilitu demons.

A good portion of this debate with sources is found [http://jewishchristianlit.com/Topics/Lilith/isaiah_dsc.html here]. Part of Patai's [http://www.jstor.org/pss/537379 chapter on Lilith]. There is [http://gnosis.org/lilith.htm this] from Patai too.
&quot; 'Lilith' is usually derived from the Babylonian-Assyrian word lilitu, ,a female demon, or wind-spirit'-one of a triad mentioned in Babylonian spells. But she appears earlier as 'Lillake' on a 2000 B.G. Sumerian tablet from Ur containing the tale of Gilgamesh and the Willow Tree. There she is a demoness dwelling in the trunk of a willow-tree tended by the Goddess Inanna (Anath) on the banks of the Euphrates. Popular Hebrew etymology seems to have derived 'Lilith' from layil, 'night'; and she therefore often appears as a hairy night-monster, as she also does in Arabian folklore. Solomon suspected the Queen of Sheba of being Lilith, because she had hairy legs. His judgement on the two harlots is recorded in I Kings III. 16 ff. According to Isaiah xxxiv. I4-I5, Lilith dwells among the desolate ruins in the Edomite Desert where satyrs (se'ir), reems, pelicans, owls, jackals, ostriches, arrow-snakes and kites keep her company.&quot;

&quot;The Lamiae, who seduced sleeping men, sucked their blood and ate their flesh, as Lilith and her fellow-demonesses did,&quot;

As followed from the above the Babylonian/Persian incantation bowls speak of multiple &quot;liliths&quot;, [http://jewishchristianlit.com/Topics/Lilith/bowls.html here].
&quot;You are bound and sealed, 
     all you demons and devils and liliths,
by that hard and strong, 
     mighty and powerful bond with which are tied Sison and Sisin....
The evil Lilith, 
     who causes the hearts of men to go astray 
     and appears in the dream of the night &quot;
Another one:
&quot;In the name of the Lord of salvations.
Designated is this bowl 
     for the sealing of the house of this 
    Geyonai bar Mamai, 
that there flee from him the evil Lilith, 
     in the name of &quot;YHWH-El has scattered&quot;; 
     the Lilith, 
     the male lilin, 
    the female liliths, &quot;
If I recall Patai also mentioned &quot;liliths&quot; being exorcised in his part about the Babylonian incantation bowls.


Further adding to confusion Killi, seems to be an epithet of Inanna's and denotes the owls connections with prostitution, in which Lilitu is called a &quot;prostitute&quot;. Harris suggests in his thing about the Burney relief:
&quot;&quot;Relevant here is the new interpretation by Thorkild Jacobsen of the well-known Burney Relief. [referring to Jacobsen &quot;Pictures and Pictorial Language (The Burney Relief) from Figurative Language of the Ancient Near East 1987]. The winged goddess of the plaque with bird's claws, flanked by owls and standing on two lions couchant, he believes, is Inanna as &quot;Lady Owl&quot; who, when named Kilili, &quot;denotes the harlot who like the owl comes out at dusk.: He suggests that the Burney Relief may have &quot;served as a cult-relief at the house alter of an ancient bordello.&quot; If so, and Jacobsen makes a convincing case, then the very depiction of the goddess breaks down the boundary between species, between the divine and ornithic.&quot;&quot;

There's also a few passages talking about Lilitu hanging out windows as a prostitute, as well as Ishtar.

This is one of the many reasons that the Burney relief was once thought to depict Lilith, besides the seductive bird woman flanked by owls.

[[User:Xuchilbara|Xuchilbara]] ([[User talk:Xuchilbara|talk]]) 20:20, 25 May 2010 (UTC)

==Added ToDo template==
There are things that need to be done so check the ToDo list above and help out.  [[User:Alatari|Alatari]] ([[User talk:Alatari|talk]]) 16:33, 22 May 2010 (UTC)

== Popular Culture section ==

It's growing and I'm not sure how notable any of them are.  I think it needs shortening but cant find the Wikipedia guidelines on this section, ATM.  [[User:Alatari|Alatari]] ([[User talk:Alatari|talk]]) 17:31, 24 May 2010 (UTC)

I found a guideline: [[WP:POPCULTURE]] but haven't digested it yet.  Anyone adding new PopCulture content please read this first.  [[User:Alatari|Alatari]] ([[User talk:Alatari|talk]]) 17:37, 24 May 2010 (UTC)

== Greek version ==

the section titled Greek version needs cleaned up (because of ambiguity).  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/96.230.235.232|96.230.235.232]] ([[User talk:96.230.235.232|talk]]) 22:01, 3 July 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== The Sumerian Legend of Lilith ??? ==

If this is a real myth, not an artistic forgery (or just plain forgery) it should be the basis of a section, or at least mentioned: [http://www.lilithgallery.com/library/The_Legend_of_Lilith.html The Sumerian Legend of Lilith].  I for one am a bit skeptical, since... 
# I cann't find a non-internet reference on any page with this,
# it diverges so much from most other accounts,
# it incorporates &quot;[[Marilith]],&quot; which I've not seen anywhere else except in [[Dungeons &amp; Dragons|D&amp;D]], and
# it seems little too pretty, romanticized, poetic, and engineered for certain modern audiences...
...but can't find explicit debunking either.  Does anyone know if its real? --[[Special:Contributions/69.138.148.185|69.138.148.185]] ([[User talk:69.138.148.185|talk]]) 21:47, 11 July 2010 (UTC)

:The &quot;translator,&quot; Charles Alexander Moffat, also wrote novels for the Forgotten Realms series of books.  That, the mention of &quot;six-armed marilitus&quot;, the benevolent-goddess role given to Lilith, and his article on &quot;Atlantis Forgotten&quot; makes me think it's just flakey hippie hogwash. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 00:15, 12 July 2010 (UTC)

::I'm afraid this is a bit of an artisticly based forgery (not unlike the centaur skeleton displayed at our local university's library) -- though it was obviously done by someone who knows the field and is good at making the pieces fit.  The author had me going for a bit.
::What gives it away are the &quot;maraliths&quot; -- this is a creature from Dungeons &amp; Dragons, which game creator Gary Gygax has admitted to having just made up.  The creature was invented in the '70's with the name type V (5) demon, with [[marilith]] being suggested as a name for one.  Later, marilith became the name of the demon type.  Had Gygax been aware of such a legend, it would have been called marilith from the beginning, and probably not a demon.  The name is cross between &quot;Lilith&quot; and &quot;[[Mara]]&quot; (a demon who tempts Buddha, much as Satan does Jesus).  The &quot;maralith&quot; and &quot;marilith&quot; are too identical in both name and description to be coincidence -- the author had to have gotten this idea from the game.  Other than the lack of any direct reference to an original source and radical departure from other known sources, this is the one obvious give-away to its being a bit of modern fiction.
::Good bit of neo-romanticism though, poetic and well done, with a nice bit of ironic tragedy.  The author should add a &quot;this is fiction&quot; boiler plate, however, and this is not a source that should be reference into a serious article. --[[User:BlackJar72|Jared]] ([[User talk:BlackJar72|talk]]) 01:10, 12 July 2010 (UTC)

:: It has occurred to me that this might belong in the section on modern pop-culture, along with the other modern Lilith fiction.  The problem is without an admission from the author or referencable debunking, the ficticious nature falls into the realm of &quot;opinion and original research&quot;; since this doesn't belong else where it can't be used at all.  That's unfortunate, since many people reprint, quote, and reference this as fact, and having a place where this story is listed for what it really is would be helpful for many gullible people researching Lilith for neopagan and/or feminist purposes.  A debunking site for this would thus be useful, if there's one out there. --[[User:BlackJar72|Jared]] ([[User talk:BlackJar72|talk]]) 15:30, 12 July 2010 (UTC)

:::It doesn't belong in the article unless there are reliable, third-party sources establishing that it's notable enough to include in an article on [[Lilith]] in the first place. Without that we'd just be propagating something of dubious importance with coverage.--[[User:Cuchullain|Cúchullain]] [[User talk:Cuchullain|&lt;sup&gt;t&lt;/sup&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/Cuchullain|&lt;small&gt;c&lt;/small&gt;]] 15:38, 12 July 2010 (UTC)
==Suggest split Sumerian Lilitu / Talmudic-Kabbalah Lilith / Lilith literature, popular and occult?==
Handicapped here since my own knowledge pretty well ends where the Sumerian material ends. It still seems that the article is very overlong, filled with poorly sourced content (and sources that are just poor), and with Sumerian, Kabbalah and pre-Raphaelite content drifting in and out of each section. This is only a suggestion but would actually dividing the article help downsize and stabilize content? 

2. Alternatively someone who really understands what appear to be eight to ten different Talmudic, Midrashic and Kabbalah sources could try and go in and sift them out and put in chronological order so we can see some line of development in the traditions? [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 06:30, 20 November 2010 (UTC)

:perhaps it would be preferable to clean up the article instead of just splitting it. --[[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|(𒁳)]]&lt;/small&gt; 11:07, 20 November 2010 (UTC)
::agree - I ''really'' hate arbitrary splits about what is essentially the same entity. [[User:Casliber|Casliber]] ([[User talk:Casliber|talk]] '''·''' [[Special:Contributions/Casliber|contribs]]) 11:38, 20 November 2010 (UTC)
:::Cleanup, split not needed. [[User:TeraSuccubi|TeraS]] ([[User talk:TeraSuccubi|talk]]) 22:21, 20 November 2010 (UTC)
:Okay that seems unanimously against the first suggestion, fair enough it wasn't a brilliant suggestion. '''withdrawn'''. But don't see objection to the second, so at least clean up can put the Jewish texts in chronological order?[[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 00:41, 21 November 2010 (UTC)
::Go for it. [[User:Casliber|Casliber]] ([[User talk:Casliber|talk]] '''·''' [[Special:Contributions/Casliber|contribs]]) 11:58, 21 November 2010 (UTC)

==Section: Lilith in Western Art?==
Is there a source for identifying any of these pictures as anything to do with the Talmudic Lilith?[[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 05:40, 21 November 2010 (UTC)
:Following investigation... no... so deleted. Ref for Rosetti added. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 19:58, 15 December 2010 (UTC)
:Since this is part of a religious topic I believe the respectful option to change the image used should be taken. [[User:Alanlevin|Alanlevin]] ([[User talk:Alanlevin|talk]]) 19:06, 30 April 2011 (UTC)

==[[Siegmund Hurwitz]]==
Can someone academically minded please do a prune on all the [[Siegmund Hurwitz]] sourced content?[[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 19:58, 15 December 2010 (UTC)
*What do you mean by 'prune'?  Is his authority been destroyed by newer research or is there just too much verbiage dedicated to his research?  [[User:Alatari|Alatari]] ([[User talk:Alatari|talk]]) 08:37, 4 February 2011 (UTC)
::Hi. Well I'm not really sure anyone has ever given &quot;authority&quot; to the work or that Hurwitz ever did any actual (source) research of his own rather than - it looks more like a tertiary (and chronologically disordered) rehash of late19th/e.20thC sources on Mesopotamia with Kabbalah and Jungian psychology (his actual area) thrown in. Aside from that the verbiage is overweight, and seems to have been dumped wholesale into the article - perhaps because it's online as a Googlebook and most sources on Mesopotamia aren't? Some of his statements can actually be nailed down to early work by ANE scholars, but a lot can't. I got tired very quickly when I tried to do something with it, and was hoping someone else would have a try? Cheers [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 17:28, 5 February 2011 (UTC)

I was going through the article today some and all the references to this one rather poor work of scholarship was making my head hurt. We would require a pretty heavy overhaul of this article to bring things into the current century. [[User:DreamGuy|DreamGuy]] ([[User talk:DreamGuy|talk]]) 00:02, 7 February 2011 (UTC)

:I see Ian T is doing sterling work with new refs, and going hungry. 
:Dream Guy - agree with above, but a point on one of your deletions, [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Lilith&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=412432567&amp;oldid=412432280 here]. Under normal circumstances I'd fully agree with you, however here I think we have a special case since the key context of this section, the one Biblical use, is partly dependent on all the other animals/birds/creatures mentioned in the same chunk. In fact I'm 90% I inserted those links to [[Gesenius]] myself, if not then I would at least like to claim that I did. The context of that mid section (Bible, between ANE content and Talmudic content) is primarily a translation issue and a determining factor with hapax legomena is always surrounding text. It would be better to link to a more modern/complete lexicon than Gesenius, but I don't think there's one online. '''AND''' indeed link to modern scholarly commentaries on this section of Isaiah, which I suppose I could dig up. But before doing that can I request/suggest this one particular delete be restored. Then I'll try and supplement with academic refs in addition on each of the 7 or 8 Hebrew creatures mentioned. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 01:12, 7 February 2011 (UTC)
::Thanks, just finished dinner, and desert.  Thinking about second dinner, but have to go to bed soon anyway.  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 01:29, 7 February 2011 (UTC)

How reliable/well sourced is the basic supposition of any connection between ANE Lamashtu and Talmudic Lilith? 
:'[[Lamashtû]]'' or ''Labartu'' (in Sumerian ''Dimme'') was a very similar Mesopotamian demon to Lilitû, and Lilith seems to have inherited many of Lamashtû's myths. Hurwitz (1980) p.34-35
Hurwitz should be replaced with Manfred Hutter, “Lilith.” In Dictionary of Deities and Demons in the Bible, edited by Karel van der Toorn, Bob Becking, Pieter W. van der Horst. Leiden: 1995. But also Handy, Lowell K. &quot;Lilith&quot;. Anchor Bible Dictionary . New York: Doubleday, 1992. gives a different view. The Lamashtu section should reflect this in the header and then link to the main Lamashtu article.
[[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 00:10, 16 February 2011 (UTC)

== Dead Sea Scrolls ==

In the dead sea scrolls section, there is a sentence that just says &quot;Translation[76]&quot;. What is the meaning of this sentence? Perhaps it should be removed or elaborated on. [[User:Kaldari|Kaldari]] ([[User talk:Kaldari|talk]]) 22:45, 18 January 2011 (UTC)

== Comment on Islamic Sources ==

Since Lilith is not mentioned in [[Quran|the holy Quran]] or the [[Hadith]], it is not considered existing from an Islamic point of view. Arabs who mention it could have taken it from the Talmud or the Bible. {{unsigned|131.175.12.86}}
:Which is why there isn't a section about Islam in the Lilith article.  The section on Lilith in Arab mythology says they got it from Jewish sources (which does not always mean the Talmud or the Bible).  Arabs and Muslims are not the same thing. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 16:18, 18 March 2011 (UTC)

==Hebrew text links to online Gesenius dictionary removed ==
I removed several links to this outside website embedded within the body of the [[Lilith]] article, which you removed with the claim that I should see the talk page to see why. I did not see anything on the talk page showing a consensus for these links, which would appear to strongly violate multiple policies. We do not put external links in the bodies of articles, and we do not do so over and over, and we do not officially endorse outside sources of information with a specific POV to promote (the site in question promotes evangelical Christianity) as if they were some Wikimedia Foundation entity like Wiktionary or something. Please do not add such links again. [[User:DreamGuy|DreamGuy]] ([[User talk:DreamGuy|talk]]) 18:46, 19 March 2011 (UTC)
::Hello Dream Guy, Okay, this relates to the paragraph dealing with the Hebrew Bible use of Lilith and the surrounding birds/animals. Strange because I remember answering this and explaining (a) that links to a Hebrew dictionary were needed when the Hebrew meaning of the surrounding birds/animals was a major factor in how some translators translate the passage, and (b) that it was perhaps regrettable that the [[Gesenius]] dictionary was hosted on a site that (true) does promote Evangelical Christianity, but that I was not aware of a better online Hebrew dictionary (that doesn't mean there isn't one). As this user objects to the host (I don't know if it is against Wikipedia policy to link to a dictionary hosted on this site, again it may be?) '''does anyone know of an alternative online Hebrew dictionary that can be used in the refs?''' It would be a massive task to transcribe a dozen bird/animal entries from [[Brown–Driver–Briggs]]. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 04:56, 20 March 2011 (UTC)
Correction: The answer was there see above, 7 Feb.[[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 05:07, 20 March 2011 (UTC)
:I am responding to a notice at [[WP:ELN]] and have not studied the article, but so far I do not think that such links (seen in this {{diff|Lilith|prev|414157188|diff}}) are suitable for Wikipedia. First, there is the issue mentioned (we do not use external links in an article per [[WP:MOS#External links]]). Second, if all the links are needed for some reason, it appears the text is not very encyclopedic. Is any [[WP:OR|original research]] used, and is it satisfactory that the article is not relying on [[WP:SECONDARY|secondary sources]]? My initial thought is that the approach of using all those links is not satisfactory. [[User:Johnuniq|Johnuniq]] ([[User talk:Johnuniq|talk]]) 09:20, 20 March 2011 (UTC)
::That's fine, the links are removed from main text, and I'm only thinking of how to provide something similar in sources/footnotes. It's simply a question of how to make the point that when translators take a list of creatures: ''tannin... bath... tsiyyim... 'iyyim...  sayir... liylith... qippowz... dayah'' they don't take one term in isolation. A ref from a standard commentary like Delitzsch's ''Isaiah'', and then from a ''Animals of the Bible'' type dictionary will do that job. But it still would be nice if it was possible to link ''tannin... bath... tsiyyim... 'iyyim...  sayir... liylith... qippowz... dayah'' to an online Hebrew dictionary in the relevant footnotes. The alternative would be first general ref from Delitzsch's ''Isaiah'' etc., and then from a ''Animals of the Bible'', and then third copying out by hand with page number a Heb dicref which is a lot of work - probably for nothing.[[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 10:05, 20 March 2011 (UTC)
::Done. Re the helpful suggestion to link to Wiktionary. Good idea, but but Wiktionary's coverage of Hebrew is fairly limited: e.g. no entry for [http://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/Special:Search?search=%D7%A7%D7%A4%D7%95%D7%96&amp;go=Look+up owl] Another copy of Genesius is hosted here, but this is also hosted by Christians http://www.tyndalearchive.com/tabs/Gesenius/ (realistically is there likely to be a Biblical Hebrew dictionary on the Web that isn't put there either by Christians or Jews?) And is Wiktionary likely to substitute what is already there? Anyway: '''Resolution - remove links to lexicon''' [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 11:18, 20 March 2011 (UTC)

== Salamanca ==
What about ''Lilith'' by [[J. R. Salamanca]]? Cf. Gottlieb in ''The Paris Review Interviews'', Vol. 1. --[[User:13Peewit|13Peewit]] ([[User talk:13Peewit|talk]]) 21:13, 9 August 2011 (UTC)
:Patricia Monaghan ''Goddesses in World Culture'' 2010  Page 65 &quot;JR Salamanca's Lilith was made into a 1962 movie of the same title that has become a cult classic. A study of the Lilith archetype informed by Jungian psychology, the film's character of Lilith is the beautiful inmate in a sanitarium, &quot; -- isn't [[Lilith (film)]] already in the article? [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 06:04, 28 January 2012 (UTC)

==Anchor Bible Dictionary==

&gt;Lowell K. Handy (1997) notes, &quot;Very little information has been found relating to the Akkadian and Babylonian view of these demons. Two sources of information previously used to define Lilith are both suspect.&quot;

OK, I want to know if this is an academically accepted viewpoint because obviously if anyone ever read Kramer, or Patai, or even better Jacobsen there's extensive research on lilitu and the origins of Lilith. In fact if I recall this passage is quoted out of context and is in fact referring to the Burney relief, not Lilith over all. If anyone wants to try to challenge Kramer's translations and win I would like to see that because its peer reviewed and academically accepted.

[[Special:Contributions/98.197.26.77|98.197.26.77]] ([[User talk:98.197.26.77|talk]]) 05:41, 3 September 2011 (UTC)

:New stuff goes at the bottom.  [[WP:NPOV|Wikipedia doesn't decide what's &quot;right,&quot;]] it just presents what different [[WP:RS|reliable sources]] have to say on a subject.  Not all reliable sources agree.  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 16:46, 5 September 2011 (UTC)

== 500AD??? ==

How can she be mentioned in Isaiah and then the lead says she wasn't mentioned till 500AD?

    Hebrew: וּפָגְשׁוּ צִיִּים אֶת-אִיִּים, וְשָׂעִיר עַל-רֵעֵהוּ יִקְרָא; אַךְ-שָׁם הִרְגִּיעָה לִּילִית, וּמָצְאָה לָהּ מָנוֹח
    Hebrew (ISO 259): u-pagšu ṣiyyim et-ʾiyyim w-saʿir ʿal-rēʿēhu yiqra; ʾak-šam hirgiʿa lilit u-maṣʾa lah manoaḫ[74]
    34:14 &quot;And shall-meet desert creatures et (particle) jackals
    the goat he-calls his- fellow
    lilit (lilith) she-rests and she-finds rest[75]
    34:15 there she-shall-nest the great-owl, and she-lays-(eggs), and she-hatches, and she-gathers under her-shadow:
    hawks[kites, gledes ] also they-gather, every one with its mate.    [[Special:Contributions/71.86.157.30|71.86.157.30]] ([[User talk:71.86.157.30|talk]]) 16:02, 30 September 2011 (UTC)
:The word appears in Isaiah, but the character is not developed until the Talmud, and the word came to refer to the character from there. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 16:11, 30 September 2011 (UTC)

== Title Image ==

Lilith or Lilitu appears to be a Mesopotamian or Syriac tradition that was incorporated into Hebrew folk and mystical rabbinical thought over centuries of Jewish contact with foreigners. I don't know that Lilith has anything to do with a serpent in any tradition, especially because she would have become before the Fall if she were an actual character in Genesis, and might not have anything to do with the Serpent if she is just something incorporated later. Lilith is regarded as the first wife of Adam in some traditions and in others as an immortal demonic spirit that seduces men and murders children that exists beyond the garden of Eden, even until present times. 

With this background, which picture do you think is more appropriate to depict Lilith? The first is a Rossetti image of Lilith looking into a hand mirror while combing her hair in what appears to be a sort of pre-Victorian setting. The second is another 19th Century Romanticized image of Lilith, this time a nude with a snake wrapped around her body. User:Ian.thomson claimed that the latter was more appropriate because it was in line with the myth than the Rossetti image because of its association of the character with a snake and nudity in the Garden of Eden. I personally think the latter is gratuitous and potentially offensive, although I can respect Wikipedia's policy on censorship. Beyond this, I don't think the Collier painting is necessarily better than the Rossetti one.

If Lilith is an immortal demon or is regarded as such in myths, then why is there a problem portraying her in whatever her setting is there? Speaking strictly about the tradition about her in the Garden of Eden, it may be more appropriate than not to have her nude. But she isn't necessarily restricted to that setting, and even if she was, why would she have a serpent from a later act? How does one even determine which is better through consensus?[[User:Nanib|Nanib]] ([[User talk:Nanib|talk]]) 00:36, 26 January 2012 (UTC)


[[File:Rossetti lady lilith 1867.jpg|thumb|left|275px|''Lady Lilith'' (1867) by [[Dante Gabriel Rossetti]] at the [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]]]]

[[File:Lilith (John Collier painting).jpg|center|250px|''Lilith'' (1892) by [[John Collier (artist)|John Collier]] in [[Southport]] Atkinson Art Gallery]]

===Burney Relief===
[[File:Burney Relief Babylon -1800-1750.JPG|thumb|left|250px|Burney Relief Babylon -1800-1750 BCE]]
Also, what do you think of this one as a title image? A variant of it was removed from the title area of the article because it was regarded as not being accepted widely by experts as the character by the one who removed it. If the character is a non-Hebrew myth originally that was assimilated into certain mystical traditions in the first place, then would the depiction of a of a deity the concept of Lilith is believed to have descended from or may be at least related to be better or worse than any 19th Century Romantic image? Whatever happens with the title image, this should probably be added somewhere.
([[User:Nanib|Nanib]] ([[User talk:Nanib|talk]]) 00:35, 26 January 2012 (UTC))

===Discussion===
Long story short - I like all of these - but would prefer an ancient (or at least pre-1500) illustration that closely connects to the Lilith myth.  The Burney relief, especially the photo here, is great, but it seems to require too much explanation that it is, or is related to, Lilith.  FWIW, I wrote most of the ''[[Lady Lilith]]'' article and am absolutely in love with that painting, especially the later version, but it is a Victorian expression of an ancient idea.  Similarly I like the Collier version, but it's too slick and modern (not even Victorian in style!) to express the ancient idea.  BTW, I am a dirty old man and have no objection to including it further down in the article.  I seem to remember that the snake is associated at least indirectly with Lilith, but among these three, I guess the best is Burney.  Let's look for something else though.  [[User:Smallbones|Smallbones]] ([[User talk:Smallbones|talk]]) 00:07, 26 January 2012 (UTC)
:per [[Wikipedia:Relevance of content]] what ideally is needed is an illustration which relates to the article subject. For better or worse the article subject is a female demon which was credited in the Talmud with causing wet dreams, so does lend itself to semi-erotic depictions of dirty (probably young, manga-minded) men. Connection to the &quot;night bird&quot; in the list of egg-laying tree dwelling birds in Isaiah is in itself tendentious, the theories of the 1880s connecting the demoness of the Talmud to any earlier Mesopotamian goddess are highly speculative, connection to the Burney Relief is now rejected. The image by Rossetti despite the title has little more to do with the Talmudic legend than any of Rossetti's other paintings for Leyland.  So at this point, until someone provides a Jewish-Talmudic picture, the Collier 1892 is probably as near to the subject as any. And, note, a lot of Hurwitz' content in this article is based on the speculations of 1890s scholarship, so nearer to Collier than to Rossetti. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 02:33, 26 January 2012 (UTC)
* Rossetti to Leyland: &quot;The painting focuses on Lilith, but is meant to be a &quot;Modern Lilith&quot; rather than the mythological figure.&quot; [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 02:38, 26 January 2012 (UTC)
::Absolutely agree - but that shouldn't mean it couldn't be included lower down in the article.  Having done some very quick research - a google image search - there is some evidence that the snake in the garden was Lilith or at least part human female http://mv.vatican.va/3_EN/pages/x-Schede/CSNs/CSNs_V_StCentr_04.html (from the Sistine Chapel) and a similar one on a capital at Notre Dame de Paris.  There's also a huge amount of stuff suggesting that some stuff here might be fan-cruft for the new pop idol of the hour - Lilith.  e.g. vampire Lilith, lots of Collier type Lilith with snakes.  No reason not to explore the various re-emergences of Lilith as long as they are documented in (very) reliable sources.  But lets not concentrate on that or push somebody's fave new fantasy.  [[User:Smallbones|Smallbones]] ([[User talk:Smallbones|talk]]) 02:47, 26 January 2012 (UTC)
:::How about using this cropped image instead, at least temporarily?
[[File:CroppedLilith.png|thumb|275px|''Lilith'' (1892) by [[John Collier (artist)|John Collier]] in [[Southport]] Atkinson Art Gallery]]  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Nanib|Nanib]] ([[User talk:Nanib|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Nanib|contribs]]) 03:28, 26 January 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

I think we'd be best served by not swapping photos more than once a day.  Everybody agreed?  [[User:Smallbones|Smallbones]] ([[User talk:Smallbones|talk]]) 03:43, 26 January 2012 (UTC)

An article about so ancient a subject is ill-served by an image of an interpretation by either 19th century English painters (Rossetti or Collier). Lilith has influenced all sorts of literature and art (western and non-western) with supporting images. The article needed a section on Lilith in Western art to complement the Western literature section so I made one ([http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Lilith&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=473448959&amp;oldid=473276654 diff]). That is where relatively recent images from western art belong. Rossetti is more famous than Collier, so in a section on Lilith in Western Art, Rossetti's is the more relevant illustration, especially since more of the text is devoted to his work and his supported by Rossetti's poem. Therefore, I was [[Wp:BOLD]] and returned the Burney Relief to the top of the article, and used the Rossetti painting in the new 'Western Art' section  ([http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Lilith&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=473449728&amp;oldid=473448959 diff]). I hope this gives a better historical balance to the topic (and a more appropriate place to display the painting than as the lead image). [[User:whiteghost.ink|Whiteghost]].[[User talk:whiteghost.ink|ink]] 03:17, 27 January 2012 (UTC)
:Whiteghost
:See Smallbones comment. Bold is one thing. Unilaterally resolving a Talk topic is another. The article has been returned to status quo, see [[Wikipedia:Reverting]] &quot;If there is a dispute, the status quo reigns until a consensus is established...&quot; see also [[WP:NPOV]] in relation to Burney reflief, and [[WP:Undue]] in relation to Rossetti. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 04:58, 27 January 2012 (UTC)
NB, also please note the comment made to [[User_talk:Smallbones#Lilith]], but if there's going to be discussion of this article, it'd be helpful if it was here. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 05:05, 27 January 2012 (UTC)

:This article is not about a modern artwork, but rather about an ancient mythological entity. The lead image should reflect that.  The Burney Relief has been the consensus lead image for some time, you do not get to come in an override a long-standing consensus. [[User:Yworo|Yworo]] ([[User talk:Yworo|talk]]) 20:01, 29 January 2012 (UTC)
::But the Burney relief doesn't depict Lilith at all.  It depicts Ishtar.  If we couldn't find a public domain image for the Gilgamesh article, would it be acceptable to use a picture of Hercules? [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 20:08, 29 January 2012 (UTC)
:::According to who? The article says it is under debate, and has a whole section about it being identified with Lilith. There is disagreement, but no disproof. [[User:Yworo|Yworo]] ([[User talk:Yworo|talk]]) 20:10, 29 January 2012 (UTC)
::::The article here points out the problems with the Lilith identification, namely that it was based on assumptions and bad translation (or reading translations in ways the translators, such Gadd, said were incorrect), that this would be the only depiction of Lilith ever.  As the article here puts: ''That this initially misread single line of evidence was taken as virtual proof of the identification of the Burney relief with &quot;Lilith&quot; may have been motivated by the existence of a Hebrew demon &quot;Lilith&quot; which is given the epithet of a &quot;screech owl&quot; in the English Bible.''
::::In other words, the entire argument for Lilith is based on connecting one misread line with one possible translation and interpretation of a single Bible verse.
::::Because of this, it would be [[WP:OR]] or even inaccurate to use the image.
::::[[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 20:25, 29 January 2012 (UTC)
:::::Read further, under the subsection Ereshkigal. Even the British Museum acknowledges that the image may depict Lilith. Just add clarification to the caption, that is has been identified by some sources as possibly representing Lilith. [[User:Yworo|Yworo]] ([[User talk:Yworo|talk]]) 20:28, 29 January 2012 (UTC)
{{od}}That's hardly evidence in favor for identifying the relief with Lilith, or else they wouldn't prefer the identification with Ereshkigal.  Again, the identification is based on a misreading of an outdated translation to identify it with a possible reading of a possible translation of the Bible.  You have not addressed this.  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 20:36, 29 January 2012 (UTC)
:I don't have to address this, that would be original research. The article on the [[Burney Relief]] currently list several academic positions on the matter of identification with Lilith. The sources ''disagree'', but no source has been provided which states that all modern scholars now reject the identification. Until that's provided, it is you using ''original research'' to try to exclude the image. One scholar's opinion that is was a misidentification does not disprove the identification, it is simply one of several opinions that have varying weights and followings. [[User:Yworo|Yworo]] ([[User talk:Yworo|talk]]) 20:45, 29 January 2012 (UTC)
:It turns out that the sentence you quoted (''That this initially misread single line of evidence was taken as virtual proof of the identification of the Burney relief with &quot;Lilith&quot; may have been motivated by the existence of a Hebrew demon &quot;Lilith&quot; which is given the epithet of a &quot;screech owl&quot; in the English Bible.'') was itself original research, cited only to a translation of Isaiah and not to any source that stated there had been a misreading. In other words, it was an editorial opinion of some Wikipedia editor and I've removed it from [[Burney Relief]]. [[User:Yworo|Yworo]] ([[User talk:Yworo|talk]]) 20:55, 29 January 2012 (UTC)

::{{ec}}The identification with Lilith is traced back to one misreading of an outdated translation. It is not some later naysayer's claim. The misreading is the entire basis for the original identification with Lilith, which the later sources repeat. That is not OR.
::The identification with Lilith is inconclusive at best, an error otherwise. Nothing discredits the Ishtar or Ereshkigal interpretations, but plenty discredits the Lilith interpretation.
::Re new post, there's still the issue that &quot;Gadd, the original translator, writes: &quot;ardat lili (kisikil-lil) is never associated with owls in Babylonian mythology&quot; and &quot;the Jewish traditions concerning Lilith in this form seem to be late and of no great authority.&quot;  The translation they cited pointed out that their interpretation was faulty before they made it.  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 21:11, 29 January 2012 (UTC)
:::That's only got to do with the owl imagery, which is not the only basis for the identification. You yourself are engaging in original research here. If you want to say or imply that the identification was ''entirely'' based on a mistranslation, you will need a citation for that. That one of several reasons for an identification has been disproved does not invalidate the other reasons for the identification. Nowhere does the [[Burney Relief]] article say that the identification has been ''disproven'' or even that it has been ''rejected'' by most modern scholars. If you actually have some support for these more extreme claims, be sure to add them to [[Burney Relief]], along with citations. [[User:Yworo|Yworo]] ([[User talk:Yworo|talk]]) 21:18, 29 January 2012 (UTC)
Yworo, it's not an extreme claim to say that it has been rejected by most modern ANE scholars.
{{quotation|LILITH?In the 1930s, scholars identified the voluptuous woman on this terracotta plaque (called the Burney Relief) as the Babylonian demoness Lilith. Today, the figure is generally identified as the goddess of love and war |Bible Review Vol 17  Biblical Archaeology Society - 2001}} [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 02:03, 30 January 2012 (UTC)

==Off Talk-page discussion==
::''I've copied this from SusanStierch's Talk page to here''
'''[[Lilith]] picture edit war on the horizon'''
Well, maybe not yet, but it's aiming in that direction. And it has a bit of everything:
vampires, snakes, sex, murder, Rossetti, the Sistine Chapel, and modern fan-cruft.  What it seems to be missing is a modern woman's perspective and good judgement.  Send any such person you know who has a sense of humor. Note: not ''[[Lady Lilith]]'' - just plain [[Lilith]].  [[User:Smallbones|Smallbones]] ([[User talk:Smallbones|talk]]) 02:56, 26 January 2012 (UTC)
::I shared it with [[User:Whiteghost.ink]] - I think it might be something she'd be interested in. If it gets out of control I'd advise that you ask for a semi-protection (if they're ip's) or a dreaded request for comment? [[User:SarahStierch|SarahStierch]] ([[User talk:SarahStierch#top|talk]]) 21:47, 26 January 2012 (UTC)
:::I added a section on Western art - it seems to me that's where a 19th century painting should appear. Also, the topic is one of such ancient-ness that any 19th century image will throw it out of balance. The Pre-Raphaelites and other 19th century painters had, you might say, a &quot;quirky&quot; attitude to history - their purposes were artistic, not historical or representative. Their view of the topic is one of many. [[User:whiteghost.ink|Whiteghost]].[[User talk:whiteghost.ink|ink]] 03:26, 27 January 2012 (UTC)
''end of copy section''
* '''Comment''' - I believe wider participation would improve this article, and others that attract the same traffic (see edit history for last year). So the above communication in my view doesn't fall into the net of [[WP:Canvassing]], but all the same the subject of this article is '''not''' about art, the subject is either the [[Talmud]] or debatably the [[Talmud]] + [[ancient Assyria]]. Therefore I suggest a moratorium on any image edits, and even perhaps talk about images, for 2 or 3 days to give people who are not acquainted with the article subject area to read up on the Talmud and ancient Assyria before diving into what image might or might not be appropriate to the article content. Does that sound reasonable? If not then dive straight in :) [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 05:28, 27 January 2012 (UTC)
::I missed your comment before making a change.  Three pix are included - so that should keep everybody happy for at least 24 hours.  I'll also suggest that a couple of folks here are pretty touchy - we can work this out to everybody's satisfaction.  Certainly if we can get some better ancient illustration.  Please take your time, there is no deadline, but there are people who will help.  [[User:Smallbones|Smallbones]] ([[User talk:Smallbones|talk]]) 05:41, 27 January 2012 (UTC)
:::Thank you Smallbones, but WP guidelines are here for a purpose and [[WP:Revert]] says that it is the status quo of the article which should be maintained, not a disputed edit. Particularly since new editors with no history on this subject have been alerted, the article should hold its status quo so new editors can see how it looks under consensus. Can you please revert your last edit to restore the form of the article before recent swapping around of images. I'm concerned that the next thing we know someone will be adding some manga or anime images. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 09:09, 27 January 2012 (UTC)

::::I don't want to cause any problems with this great article. I was simply trying to help by adding the section on Western art and the links within it to show that these sorts of images come with their own freight and of course to help readers learn about that freight if they want to. These art works are not context-free. As I said, they are neither illustrations, nor history; they are art, created by artists for their own (often purely aesthetic) purposes. That is important if you are choosing something to illustrate a topic like this. The Burney image communicates the antiquity of the topic, so it seems a good one to have as a lead. The topic is nothing if not ancient. The 19th century paintings show that the story of Lilith still resonated in that century. That is the only relevance they have. So in my opinion, they belong under a heading &quot;Western art&quot;. You can see from the refs that Rossetti was interested in history (it was an important component of the PRB manifesto) and that he engaged with it, but he used it for his own poetic and artistic ends. As an artist, Collier was less interested in history than in the form of his subject. He has given his painting an historical title to increase its perceived merit and sales potential because the artistic arbiters of the day encouraged &quot;history painting&quot;, so such a setting would have had more cachet than if he had called it &quot;Woman with Snake&quot;. Both 19th century paintings are only loosely connected to the topic. I think you only need one 19th century painting in the Western art section, and that should be the one that is both the more tightly connected and the more famous - Rossetti's. This is even more the case if it is agreed that the topic is the Talmud or the Talmud + Assyria. Again, only trying to help by offering some thoughts about the best illustration. Sincerely, [[User:whiteghost.ink|Whiteghost]].[[User talk:whiteghost.ink|ink]] 09:32, 27 January 2012 (UTC)
:::::Whiteghost,
:::::Sorry but again '''this is not an art article''' any more than it is a computer games, cosplay, manga or anime article, we have to respect [[WP:Weight]].
:::::(i) can we please have some respect for WP policy. [[WP:Revert]] states:
:::{{quotation|&quot;If there is a dispute, the status quo reigns until a consensus is established...&quot;}}
:::::(ii) a 1800BCE statue with no relation to Judaism is no nearer a topic from a 800CE Jewish text ([[Alphabet of Sirach]]) than Rossetti's painting (2600 years on one side, 1000 on the other) no matter how famous it may be to art-buffs. With my visitor to the Louvre* hat on I am also well aware that [[Lady Lilith]] is a famous painting, but '''this is not an art article.''' 
:::::(iii) re. &quot;the best illustration&quot; - great but it is extremely difficult to a find a fully relevant and suitable Jewish woodcut or other illustration for material of this kind. To date the Collier one was the best, which is why it was the status quo. A truly suitable picture, which would really fit the article would be [http://books.google.fr/books?id=VfAX_wkMM4IC&amp;pg=PA134-IA32#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false either the Lilith incantation bowl in the University of Pennsylvania Museum, or the one at Harvard University] but neither of these exist in copyleft form to be uploaded to WP Commons. If someone wants to find a relevant image - there they are.
:::::[[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 10:15, 27 January 2012 (UTC)
::::::* I have never been to Delaware [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 10:24, 27 January 2012 (UTC)
Image reverted to status quo per [[WP:Revert]]. I got bored of waiting for someone else to revert. The fact that it's back to status quo doesn't mean it has to stay that way, please feel free to continue with discussion above. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 16:54, 27 January 2012 (UTC)
{{od}}
My view of the images:
*Rossetti's Lady Lilith bears nothing to identify her as Lilith other than the title.  It could just as easily be Mary Magdelene, a member of Rossetti's family, or some woman Rossetti fancied.  Rossetti did not use any of his interest in history in that painting at all.  The only connection is the title, and nothing else.  I actually had not seen the painting before seeing it in the Lilith article, so I don't get how it's &quot;more famous.&quot;
*The Burney relief is often identified with Lilith, but this identification has been discredited.  If it wasn't for that, I'd prefer this over the others.
*The Collier image is in line with the myth.  The first time I saw the painting, I knew it was Lilith before seeing the title.  &quot;Woman with Snake&quot; would be a possible title, but such a subject is more modern and so mythology would be a more appropriate subject.  The painting's age and the subject's white skin kinda prevents it from being an earth or maize goddess accompanying the [[Rainbow Serpent]] from [[Australian Aboriginal mythology]] or the [[Horned Serpent]] from the [[Southeastern Ceremonial Complex]].  It does not prevent the subject from being from Abrahamic mythology, as most of Europe saw it as a white mythology.  Anyone familiar with Abrahamic mythology would have to conclude it was Lilith or Eve, but such a sensual Eve is made less likely by the painting's age.  &quot;Gratuitous and potentially offensive&quot; has no bearing on Wikipedia's policies in any way, shape, or form; and the only real nudity are a pair of breasts (really, how are breasts offensive?  I'm not trying to be a twentysomething heterosexual male here, they just occupy space and occasionally provide nourishment and/or comfort).  I have seen this image in a number of works before reading this article.
*The Incantation bowls are the oldest depictions of Lilith available, so I wouldn't object to using those.  Perhaps we could contact someone at [http://penn.museum/departments-contacts.html the museum at Pennsylvania University] or [http://www.semiticmuseum.fas.harvard.edu/icb/icb.do?keyword=k66717&amp;tabgroupid=icb.tabgroup105586 the Semitic museum at Harvard] and asks for a public domain image, copyleft image, or an image that they could give us permission to use.  While the Harvard bowl appears to be a little clearer, its more abstract (I'm not sure if I'm looking at eyes or breasts), so I favor the Pennsylvania bowl.  It's a little harder to make out (but it could just be the photo), though the face is more skull-like, which works well.
A bit off-topic, but I do find the erroneous connection of manga with &quot;perverted young man&quot; to be a bit annoying, probably because my univerity's anime club is watching [[Princess Jellyfish|something not too different from Ugly Betty]] and [[Steins;Gate|something Philip K Dick could've written]]. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 18:17, 27 January 2012 (UTC)
:Interesting points about the images, although here the use of art is for illustration, so it remains an issue whether western or eastern illustrations are most appropriate. Be that as it may, why is it okay to have a section on Lilith in Western Literature and not one on Lilith in Western art and instead muddle the two? Why isn't it important to communicate the context of artistic and literary interpretations, especially the easy way via links from a quote? [[User:whiteghost.ink|Whiteghost]].[[User talk:whiteghost.ink|ink]] 23:49, 27 January 2012 (UTC)
:::Hi Ian, good comments
:::And sorry about the anti-mangaist jibe ;), it was based on an idle image search on &quot;Lilith&quot; and in reply to the &quot;dirty old man&quot; comment on the Collier painting's nipples. Note that [[User:Nanib]] also removed four nipples on the [[Bathsheba]] article at the same time.
:::Hi Whiteghost
:::&quot;Why isn't it important to communicate the context of artistic and literary interpretations&quot;? Because of [[WP:Weight]] mainly. It's inevitable that anything that becomes common cultural property across ages and religions will pick up both pop culture and high culture references. Particularly with Second Temple Judaism material transmission via Christianity into Western (then world) culture means that any Second Temple article such as [[Gehenna]], [[Beelzebub]], whatever will end up with a burgeoning video game section at the end of it which acts as a magnet for irrelevant IP traffic. I'm all in favour of high culture but there comes a point at which adding high art is no better than video games, the literature section here is already too fat, and could add [[Lilith (opera)]] by [[Deborah Drattell]] and novel by [[Naomi Gal]] and so on, but these need to be wikilinks if the authors/composers/artists are notable enough to have their own articles. [[Lady Lilith]] is notable '''but has its own article already''' - should we drop the image of Sassanid demon-protection bowl into the Rossetti bio because he sold a painting to Leyland as &quot;Lilith&quot; - as far as I can see that says more about Rossetti's marketing skills than anything relevant to occult beliefs among Jewish exiles in 6th Century Iraq. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 02:21, 28 January 2012 (UTC)

==Images of lilith(s) on 6th Century Jewish demon-protection bowls==
Whether or not the Harvard etc incantation bowls will ever make it to WP:Commons as img, they should be in the article as text - surprising omission since after Talmud and Dead Sea Scrolls they are the third oldest undisputed text source, and the oldest undisputed image source. Added paragraph and links and quotation box of one of Montgomery's 2011 translations from [[Nippur]]. Cheers [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 16:54, 27 January 2012 (UTC)
:Having spent more than enough time on this due to a user's squeamishness about nipples, etc., I suggest we leave the lede illustration-less until a genuine Jewish illustration of Lilith turns up in copyleft form. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 03:51, 30 January 2012 (UTC)

== A suggestion ==
Would it be a good idea to break all the material about the impact of the &quot;Lilith legend ... as source material in modern Western culture, literature, occultism, fantasy, and horror&quot; into a new article (that is, break out sections 8, 9,10)? Then this article could focus on the ancient Talmudic and Assyrian components. [[User:whiteghost.ink|Whiteghost]].[[User talk:whiteghost.ink|ink]] 11:53, 1 February 2012 (UTC)
:Hi Whiteghost, helpful suggestion, and I personally would be in favour, but unfortunately I suspect it's probably against [[WP:CONTENTFORK]]ING. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 12:20, 1 February 2012 (UTC)
::Wasn't intended as a suggestion to generate articles for/ against the topic or for giving different points of view about Lilith - that ''would'' be against the policy. The suggestion was rather to create an article about modern cultural impacts so those could be explored without compromising the original article's focus or purpose. [[User:whiteghost.ink|Whiteghost]].[[User talk:whiteghost.ink|ink]] 23:59, 1 February 2012 (UTC)

== Laylah ==
In the Talmud, [[Hanina bar Hama]] talks about the night [[Angel Laylah]] (female) in charge of pregnancy, conception, birth and death. 
:Rabbi Hanina bar Pappa expounded: The angel in charge of pregnancy is named &quot;Laylah.&quot; He takes a drop of semen and places it before the Holy One, blessed be He, saying: &quot;Lord of the Universe, what shall be with this drop?[http://books.google.com/books?id=xDN41LJY26kC&amp;pg=PA53&amp;lpg=PA53&amp;dq=niddah+16b+laylah&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=6LxUO8t2aE&amp;sig=3xR39tIUB7bu1LkvSi8VvKlb3YM&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=E8FwT_CSCoG4twe6zqHDBg&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=niddah16blaylah&amp;f=false] Talmud, Niddah 16b [http://halakhah.com/niddah/niddah_16.html#PARTb] [[User:USchick|USchick]] ([[User talk:USchick|talk]]) 20:27, 26 March 2012 (UTC)
::Yes the Talmud has [[Hanina bar Papa]] saying that, and it is in the [[Lailah]] article. But to connect with Lilith we need Secondary not Primary sources, per [[WP:PSTS]]. Rabbi Geoffrey W. Dennis seems to think they are distinct ''The encyclopedia of Jewish myth, magic and mysticism'' 2007 says &quot;Lailah: “Night.” Not to be confused with Lilith, this is the angel of conception (and sex). Lailah escorts new souls to their bodies and erases from their memories all the torah they knew in the guf ha-Briyot (Nid. 16b; Sanh.&quot;) [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 05:29, 28 March 2012 (UTC)

==Lilith with a serpent's tail==
[[Image:Hugo van der Goes 009.jpg|thumb|200px|Like this one c. 1468]]
According to some sources, Lilith is the one who tempted Eve in the Garden of Eden, that's why the snake is depicted as female with a serpent's tail. It is not a mistake, but simply an interpretation. From the dictionary of angels [http://books.google.com/books?id=kGXelGEMdWgC&amp;pg=PA172&amp;lpg=PA172&amp;dq=angel+of+conception+laylah+zohar&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=fx0jkDGfY3&amp;sig=jwy9DP4K1y-Z662PboiLaGz4InE&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=NIhyT4H1DMvbggfotYGQAQ&amp;ved=0CB0Q6AEwADgK#v=onepage&amp;q=angel%20of%20conception%20laylah%20zohar&amp;f=false] &quot;In the cabalah she is...represented as a naked woman whose body terminates in a serpent's tail.&quot; And this source talks about Lilith being &quot;the female of Samael called 'snake' and illustrated as a snake from the 1400s on.&quot; [http://books.google.com/books?id=U9ViAIrVur4C&amp;pg=PA114&amp;dq=Lilith+Zohar+garden+of+eden&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=Z5ZyT9uOL8Shtwfk9fiOBg&amp;ved=0CEUQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=Lilith%20Zohar%20garden%20of%20eden&amp;f=false] Later when Christians didn't know the story about Lilith (because she's not in the Christian Bible) and didn't know why the snake was female, they came up with the explanation about the snake being &quot;seductive&quot; and that's why it's female. [[User:USchick|USchick]] ([[User talk:USchick|talk]]) 04:58, 28 March 2012 (UTC)
:Hi USchick, yes it is very likely that [[Hugo van der Goes]], and other examples of Christian art with the tail, are indirectly influenced by medieval Jewish legends, but what ones? We've just discussed the problem with [[Gustav Davidson]]'s book before on [[Lailah]]; It's a book for entertainment not a serious [[WP:RS]], unlike Ginzberg which is the scholarly source he primarily used but rarely credits. Davidson's comment &quot;In the cabalah she is...represented as a naked woman whose body terminates in a serpent's tail.&quot; is pretty well useless, he doesn't tell us where &quot;in the cabalah&quot; and often when you track Davidson's comments back to Ginzberg you find he's misread them. So to go in the article we'd need a source saying &quot;painter X was influenced by Jewish tradition Y appearing in source text Z,&quot; or something concrete. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 05:21, 28 March 2012 (UTC)
::I'm not sure that quoting the Kaballah as a primary source would be very helpful in this case. Goddess in the Grass: Serpentine Mythology and the Great Goddess By Linda Foubister  is a secondary source that describes Lilith being represented in art in the 14th century with a serpents tail [http://books.google.com/books?id=U9ViAIrVur4C&amp;pg=PA114&amp;dq=Lilith+Zohar+garden+of+eden&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=Z5ZyT9uOL8Shtwfk9fiOBg&amp;ved=0CEUQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=Lilith%20Zohar%20garden%20of%20eden&amp;f=false] like the one by Hugo van der Goes. [[User:USchick|USchick]] ([[User talk:USchick|talk]]) 01:20, 16 April 2012 (UTC)

==Lead==
There was consensus on the lead and all of a sudden it changed to something ridiculous without any discussion. What happened? Lilith is a mythological figure, what makes her Jewish? Why is there commentary about her in the lead paragraph before she's even introduced? I'm reverting it. [[User:USchick|USchick]] ([[User talk:USchick|talk]]) 01:57, 24 April 2012 (UTC)
{{quotation|Lilith (Hebrew: לילית‎; lilit, or lilith) is a '''character in Jewish religion''', developed earliest in the Babylonian Talmud, who is generally thought to be related to a class of female demons Līlīṯu in Mesopotamian texts. '''However, Lowell K. Handy (1997) notes, &quot;Very little information has been found relating to the Akkadian and Babylonian view of these demons. Two sources of information previously used to define Lilith are both suspect.&quot;[1] The two problematic sources are the Gilgamesh appendix and the Arslan Tash amulets, which are discussed below.[2]'''

The term Lilith occurs in Isaiah 34:14, either singular or plural according to variations in the earliest manuscripts, though in a list of animals. In the Dead Sea Scrolls Songs of the Sage the term first occurs in a list of monsters. In Jewish magical inscriptions, on bowls and amulets from the 6th century CE onwards, Lilith is identified as a female demon and the first visual depictions appear.

In Jewish folklore, from the 8th–10th centuries Alphabet of Ben Sira onwards, Lilith becomes Adam's first wife, who was created at the same time and from the same earth as Adam. This contrasts with Eve, who was created from one of Adam's ribs. The legend was greatly developed during the Middle Ages, in the tradition of Aggadic midrashim, the Zohar and Jewish mysticism.[3] In the 13th Century writings of Rabbi Isaac ben Jacob ha-Cohen, for example, Lilith left Adam after she refused to become subservient to him and then would not return to the Garden of Eden after she mated with archangel Samael.[4] The resulting Lilith legend is still commonly used as source material in modern Western culture, literature, occultism, fantasy, and horror.}}
What specifically do you want to change? Could you underline? [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 02:10, 24 April 2012 (UTC)

Lilith is a [[legendary creature]] in many different cultures. She needs to be introduced before she is disputed. [[User:USchick|USchick]] ([[User talk:USchick|talk]]) 02:20, 24 April 2012 (UTC)
:Hi USchick, but Lilith is not a legendary creature in many different cultures. Lilith is primarily documented from Isaiah (possibly?), the prayer bowls, Talmud to the Alphabet of Sira as a Jewish legend. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 02:33, 24 April 2012 (UTC)
::The two bits you've bolded. (&lt; u &gt; &lt; / u &gt; can be used to underline). 
::1. [[legendary creature]], this might be better than &quot;character&quot; but &quot;in Jewish mythology&quot; should stay.
::2. I think a modern source in the lede &quot;However, Lowell K. Handy (1997) notes, &quot;Very little information has been found relating to the Akkadian and Babylonian view of these demons. Two sources of information previously used to define Lilith are both suspect.&quot;[1] The two problematic sources are the Gilgamesh appendix and the Arslan Tash amulets, which are discussed below.[2]&quot; is definitely required given this article's history of using out of date Victorian sources. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 02:38, 24 April 2012 (UTC)

1. Jewish mythology is not the same thing as Jewish religion. Currently, the article states &quot;Jewish religion.&quot; This is inaccurate.
2. The subject needs to be introduced in an article. You can't dispute something you haven't properly introduced.
3. Mesopotamia is a region. There were lots of people there. Some of them were Jewish. Most of them were aware of Lilith. Therefore, she was a [[legendary creature]] and not a character (person). She was mentioned in Jewish sources, but only casually, because she needed no introduction, lots of people knew who she was. Even non-Jewish people. [[User:USchick|USchick]] ([[User talk:USchick|talk]]) 02:48, 24 April 2012 (UTC)
:[[Moses]] is a character in Jewish religion. Lilith is a [[legendary creature]] in Mesopotamian mythology. [[User:USchick|USchick]] ([[User talk:USchick|talk]]) 02:55, 24 April 2012 (UTC)
::Hi again
::1. is correct, I agree. It should have said Jewish mythology
::2. is not correct. The current lede does introduce it.
::3. According to sources in the article there is no evidence of any non-Jewish belief in Lilith prior to the Christian Middle Ages. When you say &quot;Lots of people&quot; that suggests a source. What is it?
::Now you've added a dispute tag - which was unneeded. And a bad habit when discussion was underway, why do you want a dispute? I'm not interested now, sorry, we'll freeze this until other regular editors get here. Cheers. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 02:57, 24 April 2012 (UTC)
:::You are not the owner of this article. You can't just make stuff up and claim that you're not interested now. There was consensus about the lead and it was changed without discussion to something that is completely inaccurate. That's why I'm disputing it. [[User:USchick|USchick]] ([[User talk:USchick|talk]]) 03:01, 24 April 2012 (UTC)
::::I'm not the owner of this article, but I am one of three or more regular contributors who has it on the watchlist as an article which attracts an undo amount of WP:FRINGE and WP:OR. Your edit removed the Anchor Bible Dictionary, Lowell K. Handy and other sources and added unsourced opinion. Please present your source and other editors can look at it. Cheers. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 03:17, 24 April 2012 (UTC)
:::::According to ''Creation Myths of the World: An Encyclopedia, Volume 1'' Lilith was absorbed by the Hebrews while they were exiled in Babylon [http://books.google.com/books?id=9I62BcuPxfYC&amp;pg=PA254&amp;dq=lilith+mesopotamian+mythology&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=fxiWT4ztB4W69QSezq2eDg&amp;ved=0CGEQ6AEwCQ#v=onepage&amp;q=lilith%20mesopotamian%20mythology&amp;f=false] which means that other people knew about her, not just the Jewish people. The Biblical Archaeology Society agrees. [http://books.google.com/books?id=n5tAAQAAIAAJ&amp;q=lilith+mesopotamian+mythology&amp;dq=lilith+mesopotamian+mythology&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=1hqWT8XhE5Oa8gTe49WkDg&amp;ved=0CD0Q6AEwAjgK] Sumerian and Mesopotamian cultures were not all Jewish. North Syrian [[http://books.google.com/books?id=VfAX_wkMM4IC&amp;pg=PA223&amp;dq=lilith+mesopotamian+mythology&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=hxyWT6v9JIqs9AS664nODg&amp;ved=0CEIQ6AEwAzgU#v=onepage&amp;q=lilith%20mesopotamian%20mythology&amp;f=false]], and definitely mythological. Cheers. [[User:USchick|USchick]] ([[User talk:USchick|talk]]) 03:27, 24 April 2012 (UTC)
Hi thanks for these sources:
* 1. David Adams Leeming is a reliable WP:RS, although this isn't one of his more academic works. 
{{quotation|In the Talmudic Creation myth we find an extension of the original Genesis account, with more emphasis on the ... The presence of the figure of Lilith reflects a Mesopotamian tradition absorbed, presumably, by the Hebrews in exile in Babylon...}}
So evidently does not &quot;mean that other people knew about her, not just the Jewish people.&quot; It means what it says, ''&quot;The presence of the figure of Lilith [in the Talmudic Creation myth] reflects a Mesopotamian tradition absorbed, presumably, by the Hebrews in exile in Babylon.&quot;'' It does seem possible however that Leeming is unaware that the Lilith material in Mesopotamia is now discredited, since he makes no mention of recent research.
* 2. What does the BAR article say? 
* 3. Sorry, the third source [[Raphael Patai]] (1967, 1990) is not reliable. 
I can't see what this will prove. Modern research separates Lilith into a distinctly Jewish myth based on some Mesopotamiam antecedents, as Leeming does. But there is no evidence for a single female &quot;Lilitu&quot; demon pre the Jewish sources. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 03:34, 24 April 2012 (UTC)
:2. According to the article: Lilitû – the hand of Sumerian Innana, lilitû demons are Assyrian, Greco-Roman mythology, Arabic mythology. According to the article and all the sources cited, Lilith is a multicultural figure, not simply a Jewish one. 
:Lilith is a [[legendary creature]] and all the sources support that.
:I'm simply suggesting that in the lead paragraph, she needs to be introduced accurately. [[User:USchick|USchick]] ([[User talk:USchick|talk]]) 04:02, 24 April 2012 (UTC)
::Hi
::2. Please. What does the BAR article say? Please quote the sentence from the article.
::As regards the lede. In order to make the change you want to make, you need to first provide a modern source for a single female Lilitu demon prior to the Jewish sources that takes into account recent scholarship. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 04:12, 24 April 2012 (UTC)
:::Hi. I'm not disputing the source, I'm disputing the description. Just because she was mentioned in Jewish sources, this does not make her a Jewish character. Moses was a Jewish character. Jesus was a Jewish character. There is a big difference between a Jewish character and a demonic legendary creature of non-Jewish origin, and they had trouble naming the creature in Jewish texts and translations – owl, zu bird, etc. Lilith is associated with Inanna [http://books.google.com/books?id=JjoBs_u5rigC&amp;pg=PA236&amp;dq=Lilith+Inanna&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=3iaWT4f9LIm69QSH2-2nDg&amp;ved=0CFIQ6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=Lilith%20Inanna&amp;f=false][http://books.google.com/books?id=unQkpOpJYi0C&amp;pg=PA38&amp;dq=Lilith+Inanna&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=3iaWT4f9LIm69QSH2-2nDg&amp;ved=0CDYQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Lilith%20Inanna&amp;f=false][http://books.google.com/books?id=DF4pNpLmRBUC&amp;pg=PA142&amp;dq=Lilith+Inanna&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=3iaWT4f9LIm69QSH2-2nDg&amp;ved=0CF8Q6AEwCA#v=onepage&amp;q=Lilith%20Inanna&amp;f=false] which predates her Jewish heritage. She was mentioned in Jewish texts in reference to idol worshiping non Jewish people, which makes her '''not''' a Jewish character as stated in the lead. Biblical Archaeology Society: Lilith, or &quot;night demon,&quot; the demon wife of Adam. [http://books.google.com/books?id=QpwPAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA4&amp;dq=Biblical+Archaeology+Society+lilith&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=TC2WT-GbFIG29QTy3NDBDg&amp;ved=0CEUQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=Lilith&amp;f=false] (Search for Lilith) [[User:USchick|USchick]] ([[User talk:USchick|talk]]) 04:40, 24 April 2012 (UTC)
{{od}}
:Hi U Schick
:I located the BAR article, it's this which is already footnoted in the article. http://www.bib-arch.org/e-features/lilith.asp 
:The lede says &quot;a character in Jewish mythology,&quot; she's clearly a character in the Talmud per Leeming &quot;figure&quot;. 
:These are not reliable sources:
* Gillian M. E. Alban teaches Literature and English at Dogus University in Istanbul, ''Melusine The Serpent Goddess in A. S. Byatt's Possession and in Mythology'' 2003 doesn't cite recent research.
* Lynn Gottlieb She Who Dwells Within: A Feminist Vision of a Renewed Judaism 
* The third source you've cited is 1903.
As I said, in order to make the change you want to make, you need to first provide a modern source for a single female Lilitu demon ''prior'' to the Jewish sources that takes into account recent scholarship. These don't. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 05:08, 24 April 2012 (UTC)
::Please provide a source where she is &quot;a character in Jewish mythology,&quot; otherwise, according to all the sources you cited, she is a [[legendary creature]] of Mesopotamian origin. Thanks. [[User:USchick|USchick]] ([[User talk:USchick|talk]]) 05:19, 24 April 2012 (UTC)
:::Hi, I've already covered these in the above (1) &quot;character&quot; rather than &quot;creature&quot; in the Talmud is supported by Leeming above. (2) the modern sources do not say she is a creature, nor that Lilith is of Mesopotamian origin. Leeming says &quot;The presence of the figure of Lilith reflects a Mesopotamian tradition absorbed, presumably, by the Hebrews in exile in Babylon&quot; which accords with what is in the lede. I think it best that we wait for either IanT, Editor2020 or Dougweller to get here. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 07:44, 24 April 2012 (UTC)
::::According to your own introduction, she appears on lists of animals and demons. How is that not a creature? If the sources say that she was absorbed into Jewish mythology from Mesopotamia, why not just say that? The incantations and amulets are used as protection against an [[evil spirit]], not a character. Your own statements are not supported by the sources. [[User:USchick|USchick]] ([[User talk:USchick|talk]]) 14:32, 24 April 2012 (UTC)
:::::I invited comments from WikiProject Mythology. [[User:USchick|USchick]] ([[User talk:USchick|talk]]) 18:53, 24 April 2012 (UTC)
::::::Not everyone all at once, please. lol [[User:USchick|USchick]] ([[User talk:USchick|talk]]) 17:37, 26 April 2012 (UTC)

== Feminism should not be catorgized under Occult ==
With respect to the contributors of this article, In modern occultism: &quot;The depiction of Lilith in Romanticism continues to be popular among feminists, Wiccans, satanists, and in other modern occultism&quot; Feminism is not an occult and should not be referenced as such. Jessicaheiman 
:Jessica, agreed, not sure how secure Amy Scerba's webpage article is as a source in general, but that word in particular is now gone. Feel free to edit yourself.  [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 09:32, 19 June 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>pk2rqc5vv58wzvg5gzwb08emr2vwlqy</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
