<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Shofar</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>172388</id>
    <revision>
      <id>387850978</id>
      <parentid>315268065</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-09-30T03:51:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cwinterfield</username>
        <id>13164678</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7845">So exactly where did the support come regarding women sounding the shofar only for other women.  Having had the honor of sounding shofar for our congregation of 500+ for over 20 years, I find it amazing that the three Rabbis I worked with didn't know that detail.Cwinterfield[[User:Cwinterfield|Cwinterfield]] ([[User talk:Cwinterfield|talk]]) 03:51, 30 September 2010 (UTC)

{{WikiProject Judaism|importance=mid|class=start}}

{{WPMusInst |quality=|importance=}}

The following was removed on a previous edit:

:''The horn is flattened and given a turned up bell by applying heat to soften it. A hole is made from the tip of the horn to the natural hollow inside. Because this hollow is of irregular bore, the [[harmonic]]s obtained when playing the instrument can vary: rather than a pure perfect fifth, intervals as narrow as a fourth, or as wide as a sixth may be produced. ''

I assume it was removed by mistake, and put it back (slightly rearraged) in the &quot;construction&quot; section. If it's faulty in any way, I'd appreciate fixes, of course. --[[User:Camembert|Camembert]]

Re the portion of the article saying it's never used today outside of Yom Kippur and Rosh Hashanah services: I may be clueless about Jewish liturgy, but wasn't it used during the celebrations immediately after the capture of the Western Wall by the Israelis in 1967? Similarly, I've heard (apocryphally) of it being used as a signaling device by the Israelis in battle situations. -[[User:152.163.252.4|152.163.252.4]] 11:24, 7 Dec 2003 (UTC)

:I don't know about that, but what the article says is that it's ''almost'' never used outside of those times, which I think is accurate. --[[User:Camembert|Camembert]]

In the section on the performer, the article says &quot;Every Jew is eligigble for any sacred office, providing s/he is acceptable...&quot;, and then goes on to say &quot;If a potential choice will cause dissention, he should withdraw his candidacy...&quot;. Where would I find guidance on the use of &quot;s/he&quot; vs. &quot;he&quot; as a gender-neutral pronoun, particularly within a given paragraph? I'd expect them to at least be internally consistent. Shall I change the &quot;he&quot; to &quot;s/he&quot;, or is the initial &quot;s/he&quot; understood to set the referent for the following pronouns? --[[User:AnthonySorace|AnthonySorace]]

== didgeridoo style ==
Are there any players that play it [[didgeridoo]] style, i.e. with [[circular breathing]] and [[multiphonics]]?[[User:Myrtone (the strict Australian wikipedian)|Myrtone (the strict Australian wikipedian)]][[User_talk:Myrtone (the strict Australian wikipedian)|(talk)]]

I don't think so, a shofar requires a lot of air quantity, and a lot of pressure to sound, too much for circular (cheek) breathing. [[User:71.199.123.24|71.199.123.24]] 21:40, 31 August 2006 (UTC)

And regarding multiphonics: a shofar does not make any sound if you just blow into it (like a flute or recorder) you need to purse your lips and make a sort of bzzzzz sound. You can change the tone by changing the tone of the bzzzz, so I don't see any way of making multiple sounds. [[User:71.199.123.24|71.199.123.24]] 21:44, 31 August 2006 (UTC)

== Unique sound waves ==

:[http://www.geocities.com/shofar221/soundwaves_unique Click] on a computer representation of a &quot;tekiah&quot; . Note the second tkiya note is similar but not identical to the first. The second starts out the same, then the long note of the first note is more sustained (and perhaps more melodic). The second note below has a vibrating long note at nearly the same amplitude. The third part of the note trails off and is similar but not identical in the two examples.

I removed the section (above) from the article. While it is accurate to state that the Shofar has &quot;unique sound waves,&quot; this statement would hold for any instrument. &quot;Unique sound waves&quot; are what make a shofar sound like a shofar, a violin sound like a violin, or my voice sound like me, when I speak. The second assertion, that a &quot;computer representation&quot; is not the identical to the real thing, would likewise hold up for a recording or &quot;computer representation&quot; of anything. --[[User:Dbolton|Dbolton]] 01:50, 25 August 2006 (UTC)

== What type of horn may be used ==

This article goes around and around, and contradicts itself, on the subject of exactly which horns may be used, and in particular, whether the horns of non-kosher animals may be used.  It's clear that there are differences of opinion on this point, but that could be presented a lot better - at present, several different views are presented, each as if it's the only authoritative one, and they're scattered through different sections of the article.  I'd suggest creation of a new section for this issue, moving all the explanations into that one section, and summarizing the range of views that exist (with emphasis on the point that it depends which authority you follow) instead of giving them all in detail.[[User:129.97.79.144|129.97.79.144]] 16:22, 7 September 2007 (UTC)

== Silver trumpet vs. Shofar ==
''From the article'': &quot;The shofar is prescribed for the announcement of the New Moon and solemn feasts (Num. x. 10; Ps. lxxxi. 4)&quot;
:The ref to Num 10 v 10 needs to be checked, I think it refers to the Silver trumpets and not the more humble rams horn. -- Paul Carley, 05:45, 16 November 2007.

== Post-Biblical times ==
The first sentence under the &quot;Post-Biblical times&quot; section speaks of &quot;the ban on playing musical instruments as a sign of mourning for the destruciton of the temple.&quot; Where can I learn more about the ban as a sign of mounring? The reference ending the paragraph (Heritage of Music, pp 44-45) does not address that issue. [[User:4unity|4unity]] ([[User talk:4unity|talk]]) 02:05, 18 January 2009 (UTC)

==Bracha==
What's a bracha?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/161.184.48.121|161.184.48.121]] ([[User talk:161.184.48.121|talk]]) 02:22, 30 January 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Blessing. [[User:Ariel.|Ariel.]] ([[User talk:Ariel.|talk]]) 10:26, 21 September 2009 (UTC)

==Vandalism==
In the section on the usage of the shofar in the temple, the word &quot;instrument&quot; is interrupted by &quot;POOOP.&quot;  I'm not sure how to fix it, otherwise I would have.[[User:Messor|messor]] ([[User talk:Messor|talk]]) 22:25, 17 March 2009 (UTC)

==Golden calf==

It should be remarked that, according to my jewish history teacher (therefore, I dont have references) who is a Rabbi the shofar can´t be a cow horn because that would be a reminder of the [[golden calf]] episode. That info it is not on the article.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/186.80.61.183|186.80.61.183]] ([[User talk:186.80.61.183|talk]]) 00:31, 15 September 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:I've never heard that, but if you can find a reliable reference, go ahead and put it in the article. [[User:Tad Lincoln|Tad Lincoln]] ([[User talk:Tad Lincoln|talk]]) 16:26, 15 September 2009 (UTC)
::Actually, I noticed that it ''is'' in the article already. It just doesn't say that it's because of the golden calf incident. [[User:Tad Lincoln|Tad Lincoln]] ([[User talk:Tad Lincoln|talk]]) 16:29, 15 September 2009 (UTC)
:::&quot;[http://www.vbm-torah.org/roshandyk/rh67mt.htm The Impact of Shofar upon Prayer]&quot; by Rav Moshe Taragin discusses this. From its second paragraph: &quot;The Gemara in Rosh Ha-shana (26a) cites a debate whether the horn of a cow may be used for shofar.  One reason suggested by the Gemara for the stringent view argues that a cow's horn invokes memories of the Golden Calf...&quot; [[User:Jonathunder|Jonathunder]] ([[User talk:Jonathunder|talk]]) 17:30, 15 September 2009 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>e96coybscjveb0k7crwu01uiga0x6r0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
