<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Concordat</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>168423</id>
    <revision>
      <id>492650946</id>
      <parentid>492478301</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-05-15T06:22:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Nobody'sman</username>
        <id>16803415</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Criticism Section */ I pointed out the biased and unsubstantiated view of one author who added to the main page under Criticism of Concordats.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="31964">{{WikiProject Catholicism|class=Start|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Politics|class=Start|importance=Mid}}

==EB==
Seems rought cut and paste from the 1911. There's a concordat in Italy and maybe other countries.
[[User:Ericd]]

''Concordat'' is a term used for an agreement between the pope and a government or sovergein on religious matters. This page should be turned into a general page about the word or a disambiguation page, with links to various concordats. [[User:Maximus Rex|Maximus Rex]] 05:13, 12 Dec 2003 (UTC)

:Seconded.  --[[User:Daniel C. Boyer|Daniel C. Boyer]] 20:46, 13 Dec 2003 (UTC)

==Others==
What about the Concordat with Poland from 1993?

:I would strongly encourage someone who knows how to do so to create an article on the Conordat of Fontainebleu of 1813, which Napoleon negotiated with the pope to resolve their dispute (Napoleon had earlier annexed the papal states, been excommunicated, and then brought the pope to France!) and after the short-lived Council of 1811 that included French, Italian, and German churchmen.  Moreover, I would strongly encourage the creation of either one article or separate articles on France's revolutionary and Napoleonic church councils that occurred in 1797, 1801, and 1811, respectively.  Because there were three of them and the final one included Italians and at least one German and was (according to Napoleon) intended as a precursor to a General Council a la Constantine, such an artilce would be significant enough to merit inclusion in any reputable encyclopedia.  I'd be happy to contribute and help edit, but I'll leave it to someone with better Wiki knowledge to get something started.  Best, --[[User:164.107.92.120|164.107.92.120]] 22:18, 15 November 2006 (UTC)

==Refs==
References to concordatwatch and other non-concordat means of Church influence were stripped from the article. These should not have been removed being relevant to the subject and a prime source of reference material.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/217.43.194.217|217.43.194.217]] ([[User talk:217.43.194.217|talk]]) 12:38, 27 December 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

The main referenced source on this page and the internally linked pages is Concordatwatch, a group of anti-Catholic secularists.  This hardly qualifies as a disinterested qualified authority.  But then again, this is Wikipedia.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/173.46.241.80|173.46.241.80]] ([[User talk:173.46.241.80|talk]]) 22:37, 28 October 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

I completely agree.  Using Concordatwatch is totally inappropriate.  Any normal person reading that website would easily come to the conclusion that it is biased- therefore under Wikipedia's own standards we cannot take facts from it.  Furthermore, the entire website is filled with historical and legal inaccuracies.  Clearly, somebody, or more likely a group of somebodies have put some serious time and effort into Concordatwatch, but it's still not legitimate source to be using.  The website is clearly anti-catholic, secularist, and left leaning.  That's fine, but we can't use them as source.

Another issue with this page is the overall treatment concordats as some sort of special secret agreement that only the Holy See makes.  This is incorrect, a concordat is simply a treaty (just like a nuncio is the Holy See's term for ambassador).  Therefore, any criticism of the signing, legal process of signing, and supposed lack of democratic process is really a criticism of the Vienna Convention on the Law of Treaties, as it spells out very clearly the process of signing a treaty (which is what a concordat is).  

I will be removing all content from this page that are sourced to this website.  I have no problem with criticism to concordats, in fact, criticism is need to have a balanced article, but that criticism can't come from a clearly biased source, particularly one that is full of historic and legal inaccuracies.

--[[User:Fictio-cedit-veritati|Fictio-cedit-veritati]] ([[User talk:Fictio-cedit-veritati|talk]]) 21:50, 23 September 2011 (UTC) 

==Split==
The UK use should be split into another article.--&lt;sub&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus]]|[[User_talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt; talk &lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; 21:44, 4 August 2009 (UTC)

:Agreed and done. [[User:Jnestorius|jnestorius]]&lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Jnestorius|talk]])&lt;/sup&gt; 20:18, 9 October 2009 (UTC)

==Category==
I think we have enough articles on individual concordats that we should create a [[:Category:Concordats]]. Thoughts? --&lt;sub&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus]]|[[User_talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt; talk &lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; 21:44, 4 August 2009 (UTC)

==Removed paragraph==
This seems to be relevant to [[Foreign relations of the Holy See]] in general, rather than any specific concordat:
:The Vatican has been particularly vocal on issues of [[abortion]] in [[Ireland]] and [[Portugal]], and in attempting to ensure references to Christianity in the prospective [[EU constitution]]. Less high profile are agreements concerning taxation and partial state funding of Catholic owned institutions such as orphanages, homes for the elderly and hospices for those suffering from [[AIDS]].
[[User:Jnestorius|jnestorius]]&lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Jnestorius|talk]])&lt;/sup&gt; 20:18, 9 October 2009 (UTC)

== Concordats by country ==

There's a whole host of data at Concordat Watch that isn't touched and could be utilized. Working on it.
&lt;br /&gt;

Surely users do not search for &quot;Concordat of year xxxx&quot;, but, &quot;Concordats of ''country'' xxxx&quot;. A better format might look like:
&lt;br /&gt;


==== [Country] ==== 
(Signed) [Year][Month][Day], [Document title],  [Link to English translation]
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
For example,
&lt;br /&gt;

==== Concordats with Germany ====
(20 July 1933), [[Reichskonkordat]] &lt;ref name=&quot;English Translation&quot;&gt;[http://www.concordatwatch.eu/showkb.php?org_id=858&amp;kb_header_id=752&amp;order=kb_rank%20ASC&amp;kb_id=1211 Reichskonkordat English Translation] &lt;/ref&gt;

...

&lt;references /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Would it be OK to rearrange? Help appreciated.
--[[User:PeterBrietbart|PeterBrietbart]] ([[User talk:PeterBrietbart|talk]]) 17:42, 19 June 2010 (UTC)

I've begun rearranging - I'd appreciate any discussion. The plan is now to add to the content and begin sourcing. --[[User:PeterBrietbart|PeterBrietbart]] ([[User talk:PeterBrietbart|talk]]) 16:21, 21 June 2010 (UTC)

== Bavaria Deletion ==
I'm proposing we delete Bavaria as a category:&lt;/br&gt;
Bavaria is no longer an independent country (now a German state).&lt;/br&gt;
The 1817 Concordat link has no content.&lt;/br&gt;
I'm writing up a better article that will come under the &quot;Germany&quot; title. Once that's done (and nothing is lost), I'll go ahead. Thoughts? --[[User:PeterBrietbart|PeterBrietbart]] ([[User talk:PeterBrietbart|talk]]) 11:51, 29 June 2010 (UTC)
&lt;/br&gt;
I've written an article that is a work in progress for dealing with the [[Concordats with individual states of Germany]]&lt;/br&gt;
I'll get rid of the &quot;Bavaria&quot; title, since it is now defunct. --[[User:PeterBrietbart|PeterBrietbart]] ([[User talk:PeterBrietbart|talk]]) 22:56, 29 June 2010 (UTC)

== Article Neutrality Issues ==

The Criticism of Concordats section was edited on the 23rd of December to read

:is an anti-Catholic website supporting secularism, abortion and feminism which documents from their own point of view historical and contemporary concordats across the world.[ref]For example, Concordat Watch is cited as a source in Plichtová and Petrjánošová (2008, p.46, 50), DiMarco (2009, p.5), Baker (2010, p.38), and Hosack (2010). [/ref]

Previously:

:is a website supporting separation of church and state which documents historical and contemporary concordats across the world.[ref]For example, Concordat Watch is cited as a source in Plichtová and Petrjánošová (2008, p.46, 50), DiMarco (2009, p.5), Baker (2010, p.38), and Hosack (2010). [/ref]

&lt; &gt; to [ ] for clarity.

I have since reverted the changes, since I consider the use of inflammatory language unhelpful, and because the reference did not substantiate anything like those claims. I would appreciate the assistance of neutral Wikipedia editors to referee any potential edit-wars that ensue. 

I understand that these are delicate issues for Catholics, and as such I would appreciate a flourishing discussion here. 

[[User:PeterBrietbart|PeterBrietbart]] ([[User talk:PeterBrietbart|talk]]) 12:04, 29 December 2010 (UTC)

I don't see anyone trying to bring back the problematic formulation, so I removed the tag. --[[User:Jules.lt|Jules.LT]] ([[User talk:Jules.lt|talk]]) 10:02, 26 April 2011 (UTC)

===Criticism===
This section contains only criticism of the concordats without noticing noting the possible positive aspects nor the arguments in their favour, thus compromising the article's neutral point of view of the subject. [[User:BonifaciusVIII| &lt;font face=&quot;old english text mt&quot;&gt;Bonifacius&lt;/font&gt;]] 19:45, 2 August 2011 (UTC)

====Neutrality====
I've removed the neutrality flag for now, please see the [[Talk:Criticism of concordats|main article's talk page]] for detailed discussion.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:PeterBrietbart|PeterBrietbart]] ([[User talk:PeterBrietbart|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/PeterBrietbart|contribs]]) 11:37, 15 September 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Neutrality Tag ==

I will be adding the standard warning for a non neutral page.  This website relies heavily upon an anti catholic website to define a catholic topic.  That really says it all.  Furthermore, even linking to this website to show the text of a concordat is a bad practice because often the website adds in their own comments at the top before you get to read the actual text.  That would be like sending somebody to a website to read a copy of the constitution that has been prefaced by a biased anti American statement.  Also, see my comment below under the Ref heading.
--[[User:Fictio-cedit-veritati|Fictio-cedit-veritati]] ([[User talk:Fictio-cedit-veritati|talk]]) 22:27, 23 September 2011 (UTC)

:Fictio, the neutrality tag is not a &quot;Warning&quot;. It is intended to bring editors into an existing discussion on the talk page. Tagging the article when there is no active discussion is not what the tag is intended for. As I mentioned elsewhere, we don't typically deem sources unreliable simply because they are &quot;anti-religious&quot;, or &quot;anti-catholic&quot;. Indeed, when dealing with the criticism of a religious practice, many of the sources we find will contain such material, for obvious reasons. In your edit, you have added &quot;anti-catholic&quot; before a statement, which I'll note is unsourced, and can probably be seen as a bit pov on the other end. I'm going to remove that &quot;anti-catholic&quot; bit, per [[WP:BRD]]. We can still talk about it here, of course. I'd urge you to reconsider the POV tag, since there's no consensus regarding neutrality concerns, or an active discussion to draw in editors. All the best, &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User:Mann_jess|&lt;b&gt;Jess&lt;/b&gt;]]&lt;span style=&quot;margin:0 7px;font-variant:small-caps;font-size:0.9em&quot;&gt;&amp;middot; [[Special:Contributions/Mann_jess|&amp;Delta;]][[User_talk:Mann_jess|&amp;hearts;]]&lt;/span&gt; 04:39, 24 September 2011 (UTC)

::Jess, this page clearly has pov issues.  As to concordant leaks being anti-catholic, it's obviously anti-catholic.  Asking for a source on that is unreasonable, almost like asking for a source on calling Neo-Nazi website anti-Semitic.  Furthermore, this has been discussed on this page before.  I will revert back to fico's edit. --[[Special:Contributions/150.108.238.38|150.108.238.38]] ([[User talk:150.108.238.38|talk]]) 07:28, 24 September 2011 (UTC)

:::I'd ask that you please don't edit war. I see no other discussion of adding the &quot;anti-catholic&quot; prefix to the description, and consensus should be established for such an addition before it is reintroduced. Frankly, I think the &quot;separation of church and state&quot; descriptor is probably a bit much too, so it might be better to just remove the whole concordantwatch thing altogether. I see it picked up nowhere in secondary sources (correct me if I'm wrong). That said, whether it's left in or not, we can't describe it like that without sourcing. Perhaps you have a better source for some of this content? I'd certainly welcome it! &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User:Mann_jess|&lt;b&gt;Jess&lt;/b&gt;]]&lt;span style=&quot;margin:0 7px;font-variant:small-caps;font-size:0.9em&quot;&gt;&amp;middot; [[Special:Contributions/Mann_jess|&amp;Delta;]][[User_talk:Mann_jess|&amp;hearts;]]&lt;/span&gt; 20:00, 24 September 2011 (UTC

::::Nobody is edit-warring- there's just a consensus here that the site is anti-catholic.  Also, the website says that it is 'for the separation of church and state' (http://www.concordatwatch.eu/showtopic.php?org_id=843&amp;kb_header_id=29281) so there is nothing wrong with noting that here.  No source is really needed to call it anti-catholic, as that is self evident by reading it.  Here is a source though from a catholic source deeming the cite anti-catholic (http://forums.catholic.com/showthread.php?t=557779).  If a Jewish source was to term something anti-Semitic we'd note that, so we'll note that here too.  Also, the site relies heavily on news articles from atheistic and militant sensualist websites (with self-proclaimed agendas against religion).  Please cease removing the anti-catholic comment.  There is a consensus among editors and there is now evidence that the site has been termed anti-catholic by catholic sources. --[[Special:Contributions/150.108.232.75|150.108.232.75]] ([[User talk:150.108.232.75|talk]]) 21:42, 25 September 2011 (UTC)

:::::We can't add content to the article based on the opinions (even the majority opinions) of editors here. We need a reliable source for such a descriptor, and even if we had one, we'd have to attribute it. We can't simply state such a thing in wikipedia's voice. Please see [[WP:V]] - the threshold for inclusion on wikipedia is verifiability, not truth. You are, indeed, edit warring (see [[WP:EW]]), which is disruptive, and I'd kindly ask that you stop. The &quot;source&quot; you provided to forums.catholic.com is to a forum, which is not a [[WP:RS|reliable source]]. Do you have a reliable, secondary source which deems the site anti-catholic. That all said, I'd like to remove the entire thing, and I'm going to boldly do that now, hoping that it will be a reasonable compromise. If you find that compromise unacceptable, please discuss the matter further here, per guideline at [[WP:BRD]], and don't simply reintroduce the &quot;anti-catholic&quot; descriptor without discussion. Thank you. &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User:Mann_jess|&lt;b&gt;Jess&lt;/b&gt;]]&lt;span style=&quot;margin:0 7px;font-variant:small-caps;font-size:0.9em&quot;&gt;&amp;middot; [[Special:Contributions/Mann_jess|&amp;Delta;]][[User_talk:Mann_jess|&amp;hearts;]]&lt;/span&gt; 06:18, 26 September 2011 (UTC)

::::::Jess, thanks for removing that material.  While what stands right now is a lot better than what was there, it is currently not sourced and and when it was it came from concordatwatch.  What I'll do now is change the wording slightly so as to make the reader aware the concordats are literally just treaties under different names, and that any criticism of them being undiplomatic should be directed at the treaty signing process in general, not at specifically concordats.  I'll work to have this reflected on the criticism page as well.  --[[User:Fictio-cedit-veritati|Fictio-cedit-veritati]] ([[User talk:Fictio-cedit-veritati|talk]]) 19:50, 6 October 2011 (UTC)

:::::::Hi Fictio. I partially undid one sentence of your proposal, which I explained in my edit summary. If my reasoning there isn't clear, let me know here and we can discuss it further. Thanks! &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User:Mann_jess|&lt;b&gt;Jess&lt;/b&gt;]]&lt;span style=&quot;margin:0 7px;font-variant:small-caps;font-size:0.9em&quot;&gt;&amp;middot; [[Special:Contributions/Mann_jess|&amp;Delta;]][[User_talk:Mann_jess|&amp;hearts;]]&lt;/span&gt; 20:35, 6 October 2011 (UTC)

::::::::Hi Jess- the fact that concordats are what the Holy See calls treaties is what I would consider common knowledge; wikipedia mentions as much on other pages concerning concordats as well.  Any law textbook in International Law will explain the international personality of the Holy See and thus their power to create and enter into treaties.  The way in which the concordats are signed was sourced, the source being the Vienna Convention on the Law of Treaties.  You can read the convention if you want- it lays out how treaties are signed (and yes, some might call that undemocratic).  Given this, do you still take issue with my sentence?

::::::::You may find the following useful.  It will actually pose as an excellent source (the best I've seen so far) for the continued reworking of these pages.

::::::::http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/04196a.htm --[[User:Fictio-cedit-veritati|Fictio-cedit-veritati]] ([[User talk:Fictio-cedit-veritati|talk]]) 21:15, 6 October 2011 (UTC)

:::::::::Hmm. Maybe there was a misunderstanding here. I only reverted the portion which began &quot;Most criticisms against concordats, however, apply to all treaties&quot;. We don't have a source for that, as far as I can tell. We'd need a strong source, and then we'd likely have to attribute it to someone. Does that make sense? &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User:Mann_jess|&lt;b&gt;Jess&lt;/b&gt;]]&lt;span style=&quot;margin:0 7px;font-variant:small-caps;font-size:0.9em&quot;&gt;&amp;middot; [[Special:Contributions/Mann_jess|&amp;Delta;]][[User_talk:Mann_jess|&amp;hearts;]]&lt;/span&gt; 21:22, 6 October 2011 (UTC)
::::::::::BTW, can you indent your posts? I just went through and indented this section. It gets hard to read when posts are all jumbled together. Thanks. &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User:Mann_jess|&lt;b&gt;Jess&lt;/b&gt;]]&lt;span style=&quot;margin:0 7px;font-variant:small-caps;font-size:0.9em&quot;&gt;&amp;middot; [[Special:Contributions/Mann_jess|&amp;Delta;]][[User_talk:Mann_jess|&amp;hearts;]]&lt;/span&gt; 21:24, 6 October 2011 (UTC)

::::::::::: Hi Jess, maybe there has been a misunderstanding, but this conversation is about neutrality.  Until the matter of concordat watch is finished we'll leave it up.  If we decide not to trust it then we have to get rid of the criticism sentence because while it isn't sourced right now it's drawn entirely from concordatwatch.  As to my sentence that you deleted- I don't understand what you think needs a strong source.  The fact that concordats are the same as treaties? --[[User:Fictio-cedit-veritati|Fictio-cedit-veritati]] ([[User talk:Fictio-cedit-veritati|talk]]) 23:09, 7 October 2011 (UTC)

::::::::::::I just checked the criticism page, and right in the header it acknowledges that concordats are treaties with the Holy See.  I've also noticed this in other articles on here.  So right now wikipeida 'agrees' with me if you will.  I think you should accept this norm, or else you'd have to go to all of those articles and change them.  And again, this is really considered to be common knowledge- go to the UN's website and run a search on concordats, you'll soon get the picture.  I'll work on finding a formal statement, but I think for now it is really in our best interest to continue with the precedence set in various other wikipeida articles and other places on the web. --[[User:Fictio-cedit-veritati|Fictio-cedit-veritati]] ([[User talk:Fictio-cedit-veritati|talk]]) 23:19, 7 October 2011 (UTC)

:::::::::::::Hi Fictio. 1) I guess we're back to edit warring over the neutrality tag. That's not really all that productive. As I explained above, the tag is not intended to &quot;mark the article&quot;, as you're using it. It's intended to draw editors into an existing discussion. There isn't an existing discussion on the topic you believe is contentious, so the tag is inappropriate. It should not sit there forever because one editor believes the article needs improvement. 2) Thank you for indenting your posts. I appreciate it. I've fixed your signature, which was sitting on the next line. 3) I never said concordats are not treaties. I said we cannot write &quot;criticisms of concordats apply to other things too&quot; without sourcing. If other articles say the same thing without sourcing, then they need to be fixed. It's not my job to fix them in order to keep this article from repeating the same mistake. 4) Common sense is not a metric for including content. [[WP:V|Sources are]]. We need sourcing to include that content, both for verifiability, and so we can attribute the claim to someone. &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User:Mann_jess|&lt;b&gt;Jess&lt;/b&gt;]]&lt;span style=&quot;margin:0 7px;font-variant:small-caps;font-size:0.9em&quot;&gt;&amp;middot; [[Special:Contributions/Mann_jess|&amp;Delta;]][[User_talk:Mann_jess|&amp;hearts;]]&lt;/span&gt; 05:05, 8 October 2011 (UTC)
:::::::::::::: Hi Jess.  Rather unfortunately, I've been away from this for quite sometime.  Thanks for leaving everything intact.  1) I understand what you're saying about the neutrality tag, and you certainly have a better understanding of the workings of wikipedia than I do.  The reason I put the tag up is because I believe that biased sources have been used in the writing of the articles and that, as a result of this, readers ought to be forewarned until we can come to some form of understanding.  There is perhaps a better tag to communicate this, do you know of one?  2) Thank you.  3) I understand what you are saying here, though I have provided sources more carefully explaining the nature of concordats.  I will again include those in any future edits.  4) I think you misunderstood the sense in which I used 'common sense'.  I'm certainly not suggesting that we write factual statements and then not source them because they are 'common sense'.  I pointed you in the direction of where information supporting my position can be found, and will again work to include such links in future posts. --[[User:Fictio-cedit-veritati|Fictio-cedit-veritati]] ([[User talk:Fictio-cedit-veritati|talk]]) 23:23, 3 January 2012 (UTC)

== Criticism Section  ==

Currently, this section does not cite any sources.  Given this, I would like to remove it, leaving only the link to the actual criticism page, unless others can provide some links to credible websites to support some of the assertions made.  --[[User:Fictio-cedit-veritati|Fictio-cedit-veritati]] ([[User talk:Fictio-cedit-veritati|talk]]) 23:25, 3 January 2012 (UTC)

From a Church-State scholar's perspective, the contentions regarding Concordats seems reasonable to resolve.  ''From a Catholic perspective'', the Church has the moral and theological right to enter into diplomatic relations with states in order to reach agreements regarding the care of its members residing there.  This is the concept of ''libertas ecclesiastica'' (freedom of the Church).  However, from ''a non-Catholic perspective'' (NOT an anti-Catholic perspective), this poses certain concerns regarding religious freedom, such as: 1) Concordats give to the Church a privileged position that other religious groups are denied (European history in numerous books reveals this fact), 2) Concordats are not &quot;the same as treaties&quot; because they are entered into by an entity that is BOTH religious and political in nature, viz., the Catholic Church, whereas any other treaty is between two sovereign entities on a horizontal level, i.e., purely political in nature (see Robert A. Graham, “Introduction: Reflections on Vatican Diplomacy,” in Kent and Pollard, eds., ''Papal Diplomacy'', 1, 2), and 3) depending on the negotiations agreed upon in the Concordat, some religious groups face the threat of being marginalized (example: in Spain, although the Constitution guarantees religious freedom (theoretically), yet in practice, Protestant, Muslim, and Jewish groups are restricted from certain forms of proselytism).[[User:Nobody&amp;#39;sman|Nobody&amp;#39;sman]] ([[User talk:Nobody&amp;#39;sman|talk]]) 16:41, 11 May 2012 (UTC)

I hold a Ph.D. in Church-State Relations and had added the previous paragraph (above) to the main page under the section &quot;Criticism of Concordats,&quot; providing a balanced view of them.  However, someone else added footnotes 5-13 that are NOT balanced nor substantiated.  For example, the statement preceding footnote 7 implies that the shops, hotel resorts, etc. are owned by the Catholic Church and that the Church, in order to avoid payment of taxes for a commercial enterprise, had built small shrines to make it appear like a religious facility.  As the paragraph currently reads, this is the surmising of its author and cannot be substantiated.  The only other logical conclusions is that those businesses are not owned by the Church, but the proprietors have built small shrines in order to claim tax exemption status, in which case this is NOT the fault of the Church, but instead the proprietors who have hypocritically used the shrine to mask a commercial enterprise.  In America, many Pentecostal and mega-church organizations do the same thing -- they have small stores built onto the main sanctuary where they sell items purportedly under the name of their church and thus avoid taxes.  If the Catholic Church does something similar, they are not the only religious organization to do this.  From this perspective, mentioning only the Catholic Church in the Criticism section is NOT balanced and is full of BIAS.  This paragraph should be removed, or re-written to reflect a substantiated and balanced view of concordats in the country(ies) mentioned.  Tax-exempt status is not particular to the Catholic Church, at least not in America, where all religious organizations enjoy such a status because one of America's enlightened statesman, James Madison, realized that the power to tax is the power to destroy.  If churches had to pay taxes, and one year they could not gather the funds to pay property taxes, the government would have the power to close their doors.  Since religious organizations are beneficial to society, they are properly accorded a tax-exempt status.[[User:Nobody&amp;#39;sman|Nobody&amp;#39;sman]] ([[User talk:Nobody&amp;#39;sman|talk]]) 06:22, 15 May 2012 (UTC)

== Merger proposal ==
{{Discussion top|1=The result was to '''merge''' here. -- &lt;font face=&quot;Antiqua, serif&quot;&gt;''[[User:Hrafn|Hrafn]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Hrafn|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Hrafn|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;''('''[[M:Precisionism|P]]''')&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 06:41, 14 May 2012 (UTC)}}
I am proposing that [[Criticism of concordats]] be merged here as:
#It would seem to be undue [[WP:WEIGHT]] to have an article on ''criticism of'' a topic that is far, far larger than the ''discussion of'' the topic (i.e. excluding the ''simple listing'' of the concordats).
#That article appears to be largely based upon [[WP:Synthesis]] (mainly of the concordats themselves) and to sources of generally questionable quality.
I am therefore initially proposing that only the 'Financial privileges, tax exemption and secrecy' section (which includes citations to the like of ''The Guardian'', ''The Telegraph'' and ''Time'') be merged here. If other material is agreed to be based upon material found to be reliable, it can be included as well (assuming WP:WEIGHT issues do not intrude). &lt;font face=&quot;Antiqua, serif&quot;&gt;''[[User:Hrafn|Hrafn]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Hrafn|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Hrafn|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;''('''[[M:Precisionism|P]]''')&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 02:44, 11 January 2012 (UTC)
:As I just wrote on the other talk page, I think this is a good idea.  We can merge whatever seems fairly credible now, and then work further on refining the content once it has been merged.  --[[User:Fictio-cedit-veritati|Fictio-cedit-veritati]] ([[User talk:Fictio-cedit-veritati|talk]]) 03:41, 11 January 2012 (UTC)
:Saw this on the reliable sources notice board. If there's reliably sourced non-synthesized material it could be merged here; If ''criticism of condordats'' isn't an appropriate article title and if the material could be rewritten from sources, it might be better to take ''criticism of...'' to AfD. [[User:Tom harrison|Tom Harrison]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Tom harrison|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 13:58, 21 January 2012 (UTC)
::If somebody's willing to rewrite material from the few reliable sources at CofC, I'd happily support deletion of that article. As long as we preserve what few reliable third party sources we have on the topic of concordats, I'm happy. &lt;font face=&quot;Antiqua, serif&quot;&gt;''[[User:Hrafn|Hrafn]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Hrafn|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Hrafn|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;''('''[[M:Precisionism|P]]''')&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 15:53, 21 January 2012 (UTC)
{{Discussion bottom}}

== The List ==

Given that the Holy See must have entered into hundreds (thousands) of treaties with states over the last millenium or so, this list is at considerable risk of becoming [[WP:INDISCRIMINATE]]. Of particular concern are:
*Concordats lacking their own article -- likelihood of being non-notable, and therefore unsuitable for inclusion.
*Concordats lacking either their own article or a citation -- not [[WP:Verifiable]], and therefore &lt;u&gt;clearly&lt;/u&gt; unsuitable for inclusion.
&lt;font face=&quot;Antiqua, serif&quot;&gt;''[[User:Hrafn|Hrafn]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Hrafn|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Hrafn|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;''('''[[M:Precisionism|P]]''')&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 02:57, 11 January 2012 (UTC)
:I wasn't aware of [[WP:INDISCRIMINATE]], but having read it, it does seem like it is a valid concern for 'The List'.  I clicked on a fair number of the concordats that have pages, and the majority of those pages are stubs written from one source (usually a bad one).  So what do you propose?  Cut down the list, and/or the pages as well?  --[[User:Fictio-cedit-veritati|Fictio-cedit-veritati]] ([[User talk:Fictio-cedit-veritati|talk]]) 03:39, 11 January 2012 (UTC)
::(i) Cut them down. Then (ii) either rename the article to [[List of concordats]] (this is what the article currently is really) or add significant [[WP:SECONDARY]] ''discussion of'' the history, current usage, etc of concordats. &lt;font face=&quot;Antiqua, serif&quot;&gt;''[[User:Hrafn|Hrafn]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Hrafn|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Hrafn|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;''('''[[M:Precisionism|P]]''')&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 03:52, 11 January 2012 (UTC)
:::I could be amenable to a plan like that.  I don't know how much sense it would make to not have a general page about concordats and yet have a list page with criticism on it, so we'd definitely want to add some discussion of the history, current usage, etc., as you suggested.  For right now, would you agree that we should remove condordatwatch as the source referenced for several concordats?  --[[User:Fictio-cedit-veritati|Fictio-cedit-veritati]] ([[User talk:Fictio-cedit-veritati|talk]]) 04:04, 13 January 2012 (UTC)
::::I'd be happy with the removal of ''any'' apparently-[[WP:SPS]] that nobody has made a specific defence of (unless claim to reliability is self-evident -- e.g. some published religious historian's blog). But this means that any concordats cited only to such sources will also have to go. &lt;font face=&quot;Antiqua, serif&quot;&gt;''[[User:Hrafn|Hrafn]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Hrafn|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Hrafn|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;''('''[[M:Precisionism|P]]''')&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 04:21, 13 January 2012 (UTC)

== This is stupid! ==

GUYS, JUST '''''SHUT UP'''''SO THEY CAN FINISH THIS ARTICLE!
--Jon  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.250.208.49|24.250.208.49]] ([[User talk:24.250.208.49|talk]]) 23:57, 19 March 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;</text>
      <sha1>2n4h2lslclzuvt4eaqv8l1b3l510bqi</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
