<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Anglicanism</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>149123</id>
    <revision>
      <id>514889487</id>
      <parentid>514889289</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-27T21:51:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SineBot</username>
        <id>4936590</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Signing comment by [[Special:Contributions/71.167.69.46|71.167.69.46]] - &quot;/* American vs British English? */&quot;</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="138299">{{skiptotoctalk}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=4 January 2007
|action1result=not listed
|action1oldid=98250234

|action2=GAN
|action2date=4 August 2007
|action2result=not listed
|action2oldid=149031723

|currentstatus=FGAN
|topic=philrelig
}}
 
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WPReligion|class=C|importance=Top}}
{{ChristianityWikiProject|class=C|importance=top|anglicanism=yes|anglicanism-importance=Top|methodism-work-group=yes|methodism-importance=Top|calvinism=yes|calvinism-importance=Top|core-topics-work-group = yes|core-topics-work-group-importance=low}}
{{WikiProject England|class=C}}
}}
{{WP1.0|v0.5=pass|class=C|category=Philrelig|WPCD=yes}}
{{archive box collapsible|large=yes|box-width=100%|
# [[Talk:Anglicanism/Archive1|Jan 2003-Mar 2006]]
# [[Talk:Anglicanism/Archive 2|Apr-Dec 2006]]
# [[Talk:Anglicanism/Archive 3|Jan 2006-Sept 2007]]
# [[Talk:Anglicanism/Archive 4|Oct 2007-Dec 2007]]
# [[/Archive 5|February to June 2008]]}}


== Little mistake regarding Anglican church as third largest. ==

It would be the 4th largest, after Oriental Orthodox.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/142.108.125.222|142.108.125.222]] ([[User talk:142.108.125.222|talk]]) 20:14, 29 August 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:The sources I've seen all show it as the third largest.  If you have an alternative - please show us where the figures are derived from.  [[User:David Underdown|David Underdown]] ([[User talk:David Underdown|talk]]) 08:10, 1 September 2008 (UTC)
::Same with the sources I've seen. Still, I suspect those sources lump Eastern Orthodox and [[Oriental Orthodox]] together, which is misleading. —[[User:Angr|'''An''']][[User talk:Angr|''gr'']] 08:18, 1 September 2008 (UTC)
:::Not misleading, it is wrong. --[[User:Secisek|Secisek]] ([[User talk:Secisek|talk]]) 06:56, 19 December 2008 (UTC)

I would rephrase &quot;Anglicanism forms one of the principal traditions of Christianity, together with Protestantism, Roman Catholicism and Eastern Orthodoxy&quot; as Anglicanism should be within Protestantism (it might be the biggest/more important, still should be classified within Protestantism)  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/198.89.66.135|198.89.66.135]] ([[User talk:198.89.66.135|talk]]) 20:19, 3 February 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Anglicanism is generally portrayed as ''via media''; labeling it as Protestant is controversial.  [[User:Tb|Tb]] ([[User talk:Tb|talk]]) 01:48, 4 February 2010 (UTC)
::This is news to me. As a lifelong Episcopalian I have yet to meet anyone who does not believe Episcopalians are Protestants. The article is as a result very confusing, at least to uneducated American laity. The sheer amount of debate on this topic in the discussion forum shows that many readers do not find the article clarifying in that regard - it's actually *jarring* to read that I am apparently a member of some other sect. Most questionnaires including faith list 'protestant' as a category, and most people I know would classify Episcopalians under that rubric.[[Special:Contributions/151.204.140.143|151.204.140.143]] ([[User talk:151.204.140.143|talk]]) 21:38, 3 June 2010 (UTC)
:::What other sect does the article say you are &quot;apparently a member of&quot;?  Still, the job of the article is not to reinforce people's antecedent opinions: sometimes the full complexity of the world as it is can be jarring.  You write as if it is a criticism of the article that it does not reinforce what you already thought.  [[User:Tb|Tb]] ([[User talk:Tb|talk]]) 22:44, 7 June 2010 (UTC)

The Wiki pages for Charismatic Christianity and Pentacostalism both claim between 250 and 500 million followers. http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charismatic_Christianity, http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentecostal, Baptists are said to have close to 100 million: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baptists#Membership

==Hoax==

D. J. Rozday the Armenian theologian may very well not exist: a brief search today revealed a few other Rozdays only (Sept 29, 2008 revision not valid) [[User:Felix Folio Secundus|Felix Folio Secundus]] ([[User talk:Felix Folio Secundus|talk]]) 22:33, 30 September 2008 (UTC)

==Catholicism NPOV dispute==
Why is this page under the &quot;catholicism&quot; link when it is a protestant church? [[Special:Contributions/81.129.62.111|81.129.62.111]] ([[User talk:81.129.62.111|talk]]) 16:33, 14 October 2008 (UTC)
:I'm not sure what you mean. It's in [[:Category:Catholics not in communion with Rome]], which is an accurate description of the [[Anglo-Catholic]] end of the Anglican spectrum. —[[User:Angr|'''An''']][[User talk:Angr|''gr'']] 17:10, 14 October 2008 (UTC)

The Anglican churches are catholic, or at least consider themselves to be. Anglicans say the Nicene creed, which includes believing in the holy catholic church. My baptism certificate is prefixed, &quot;Membership of the One, Holy, Catholic and Apostolic Church&quot;. And I am an Anglican. [[User:Millbanks|Millbanks]] ([[User talk:Millbanks|talk]]) 12:31, 18 December 2008 (UTC)

:What ever you might say about Anglicans such as [[John Keble]], [[Edward Pusey]], [[William Laud]], or for that matter [[Henry VIII]], you could certainly not say they were &quot;protestant&quot;s. They would not have, either. --[[User:Secisek|Secisek]] ([[User talk:Secisek|talk]]) 19:35, 18 December 2008 (UTC)

Practice varies. The (Anglican) Church of Ireland states specifically that it &quot;is both Protestant and Catholic&quot;. But in Queensland, Australia, Anglicans would not be so forthcoming about being Protestant. [[User:Millbanks|Millbanks]] ([[User talk:Millbanks|talk]]) 15:12, 22 December 2008 (UTC)

:And [[Sydney Anglican|a few hundred miles to the south]], they wouldn't be so forthcoming about being Catholic. —[[User:Angr|'''An''']][[User talk:Angr|''gr'']] 15:37, 22 December 2008 (UTC)

You are so right! [[User:Millbanks|Millbanks]] ([[User talk:Millbanks|talk]]) 19:52, 22 December 2008 (UTC)

:Very true! -- [[User:Secisek|Secisek]] ([[User talk:Secisek|talk]]) 21:49, 22 December 2008 (UTC)

The act of settlement states it is a &quot;reformed religion&quot; - a religion of the ''reform''ation. It certainly IS protestant. When Henry VIII broke with with Rome they became Schismatic. With the introduction of the Book of Common Prayer they became heretical. And technically, protestantism isn't a religion.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/217.171.129.74|217.171.129.74]] ([[User talk:217.171.129.74|talk]]) 16:33, 23 December 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

I'm sorry you have to be anonymous, but, yes, the Anglican churches are Protestant (and catholic) and yes, there is no such thing as the protestant religion, nor the protestant church. My step son is Greek Orthodox, and we console each other that in the eyes of Rome, he is a schismatic and I am a heretic. Still, I sleep easy at night, with my heretic wife, who is the mother of a schismatic and married a heretic. [[User:Millbanks|Millbanks]] ([[User talk:Millbanks|talk]]) 23:18, 23 December 2008 (UTC)

lol (above). okay just to make peace (God willing). you either say both or neither. is 'Via Media' a doctorine? the Anglican orders and I think? sacrements are honoured in the Orthodox Churches, and also Catholic,.. almost, with orders, a one week fast track for preists on the left wing of the church. on the right wing we have Episcopalian to Methodisim...after that your in to Calvinism and saying that is included is maybe a bit like the converse that Anglicans are still in communion with Rome. Peace. [[User:dava4444|dava4444]]  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|undated]] comment added 02:29, 8 July 2009 (UTC).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!--Template:Undated--&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:We are in danger of tripping over terminology.  The article has fallen victim to it.  In Anglican terms &quot;catholic&quot; means &quot;universal&quot;, and refers to the whole body of believers.  Since the Church of Rome has arrogated the word &quot;catholic&quot; to itself, a reader can be misled by its use here.  A couple of times the article referes to Western Catholic tradition, meaning traditional closer to Roman practice, not &quot;catholic&quot; at all.

:Even the [[Church of Scotland]], as extreme it its Protestantism as can be, declares it is part of the catholic Church.  So does the Methodist Church.  Surely these should be included in the Category &quot;Catholics not in communion with Rome&quot;? It is not listed.  That category is a daft one; invented out of contradictory definitions and self-definitions.

:The idea that &quot;catholic&quot; and &quot;protestant&quot; are somehow a contradistinction is a mischievous idea.  Protestants are catholic.

:There is no doubt that the Anglican Churches are Protestant by any normal definition.  That they are catholic too is also undoubted by anyone but Romanists! Whether the Church of Rome is catholic as it claims is open to debate.

:[[User:Howard Alexander|Howard Alexander]] ([[User talk:Howard Alexander|talk]]) 22:33, 31 January 2010 (UTC)

::What you say expresses one point of view within Anglicanism.  Other Anglicans would recoil and insist they are not Protestant at all.  Some would also say that--despite their intentions--the Presbyterians and Congregationalists and Baptists are ''not'' catholic.  Some intend by &quot;catholic&quot; to mean specifically some assumptions about church order (episcopacy, succession) and sacramental theology.  What you say here certainly well expresses the opinions of one party within Anglicanism, but it is by no means agreed on all sides.  [[User:Tb|Tb]] ([[User talk:Tb|talk]]) 22:49, 31 January 2010 (UTC)

:::In that case we need clarity of terminology. [[User:Howard Alexander|Howard Alexander]] ([[User talk:Howard Alexander|talk]]) 07:18, 1 February 2010 (UTC)

::::I agree, and I think we have fairly good clarity.  The via media language says &quot;between Reformed Protestantism and Roman Catholicism&quot;, which avoids the ambiguities; we also say ''The degree of distinction between Reformed and western Catholic tendencies within the Anglican tradition is routinely a matter of debate both within specific Anglican churches and throughout the Anglican Communion.'' which expresses exactly the question you raise, and points out that there are simply different answers to that question given.  [[User:Tb|Tb]] ([[User talk:Tb|talk]]) 00:32, 2 February 2010 (UTC)

:::::This article shouldn't be in the category 'Catholics not in communion with Rome'. Catholic in this sense means 'Roman Catholic' and this clearly doesn't describe the Anglican Communion as a whole. The wikipedia page 'Anglo-Catholicism' is in this category and that is sufficient. [[User:Sbmackay|Sbmackay]] ([[User talk:Sbmackay|talk]]) 05:30, 19 June 2010 (UTC)
:::::::'Catholics not in communion with Rome' are by definition ''not'' &quot;Roman Catholic&quot; in any normal sense of the term!  'Roman Catholics not in communion with Rome' would be a contradiction in terms.  I don't have strong views of the category, which is essentially half-applicable, half-not, but overall it should probably stay. [[User:Johnbod|Johnbod]] ([[User talk:Johnbod|talk]]) 14:02, 19 June 2010 (UTC)
:::::::: Roman Catholic usually means Latin Rite Catholics in communion with Rome.  Lots of non-Latin Rite Catholics are also in communion with Rome (the Byzantine Rite Catholics in Communion with Rome, for example), but aren't thought of in normal conversation as 'Roman Catholic'.  The definition of Catholicism given in St. Athanasius' Creed is much larger than that claimed by the communion of the Bishop of Rome. The 'Catholic Faith' is trinatarian. Many in the Anglican communion are very much proud to be both Catholic and Reformed.  Let the article stay in the category. [[User:Bo|Bo]] ([[User talk:Bo|talk]]) 20:12, 19 June 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::::That may be so in &quot;normal conversation&quot; between people with degrees in theology, but the distinction is notoriously lost on the vast majority of the world's population, &amp; Eastern rite Catholics often find themselves ticking boxes reluctantly as RC, using the term, as most of the world does, for anyone in communion with Rome. [[User:Johnbod|Johnbod]] ([[User talk:Johnbod|talk]]) 02:20, 20 June 2010 (UTC) 
:::::::::::: Bet they have fun explaining the priest's wife and children to other 'RC's then... That is part of the point, the East has married priests (brought up in the faith, not converts), doesn't use the filogue, and some don't ascribe to the Immaculate Conception, all very much part of being 'Roman Catholic' (in the Latin Rite).  Roman Catholic to most folks (even those that reluctantly tick the RC box) is 'Latin Rite' (if it meant 'Catholic in communion with Rome', the reluctance wouldn't be their for Eastern Catholics). [[User:Bo|Bo]] ([[User talk:Bo|talk]]) 02:43, 20 June 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::::::I disagree. For most English-speaking people (who have ever thought about the matter at all) &quot;Roman&quot; is, not surprisingly, as opposed to &quot;Anglo&quot; (or in Holland or Germany &quot;Old&quot;) rather than as opposed to &quot;Maronite&quot;, &quot;Armenian&quot; or &quot;Uniate&quot;.  But of course both senses exist. And most Catholics of any sort dislike the &quot;Roman&quot; altogether, many rather strongly. You may be aware this issue was the subject of one of WP's longest and lamest article title disputes. [[User:Johnbod|Johnbod]] ([[User talk:Johnbod|talk]]) 04:20, 20 June 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::::::: Are you saying simply that everyone checks 'RC' reluctantly?  If so, so be it.   Catholic doesn't mean 'in communion with Rome', nor is it  'another name for 'Roman Catholic'...The glossary of the catechism uses 'in the West, the Roman and Ambrosian (Latin) rites', so anyone who even reads the CCC understands the distinction as I expressed it... If Joe Everyman doesn't get that distinction, perhaps the appropriate articles should be used to enlighten him...[[User:Bo|Bo]] ([[User talk:Bo|talk]]) 04:42, 20 June 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::That is not how the category is being used, it is being used for a much narrower definition of Catholic (look at the range of pages included. 'Catholic' in the broader sense includes Lutherans and Presbytarians, and many other Protestant groups, but they aren't in the category.[[User:Sbmackay|Sbmackay]] ([[User talk:Sbmackay|talk]]) 00:25, 20 June 2010 (UTC)
::::::::::The category seems to include almost anyone who claims catholicity via the Athanasian Creed and the Historic Episcopate.  Anglicans claim both. [[User:Bo|Bo]] ([[User talk:Bo|talk]]) 02:01, 20 June 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::::I'm not even convinced that all Anglicans do claim Catholicity via Apostolic succession. There's nothing referencing this claim in the article. Either way, it's likely to be misleading to the average reader.[[User:Sbmackay|Sbmackay]] ([[User talk:Sbmackay|talk]]) 02:11, 20 June 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::::: What? If you'll notice the first line of paragraph three in the article on Anglicanism, the claim to tradition, the historic episcopate, early church fathers, and scripture are all there..[[User:Bo|Bo]] ([[User talk:Bo|talk]]) 02:53, 20 June 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::::::The claim that apostolic succession is a foundation of Anglicanism is there, but it's referenced by a CoE website which mentions the 'historical episcopate'. This phrase is interpreted as apostolic succession only by the Anglo-Catholic stream of the Anglican Communion, and is stated this way in only some of the Provinces. The statement is not NPOV and needs to be altered. Unless somehow Anglo-Catholic Anglicanism is the only Anglicanism. [[User:Sbmackay|Sbmackay]] ([[User talk:Sbmackay|talk]]) 03:29, 20 June 2010 (UTC)
::::::::::::::Many more than the 'Anglo-Catholics' consider the historic episcopate to be apostolic succession -  Even Sydney Anglicans!  http://www.sydneyanglicans.net/news/communion/explaining_the_episcopate/ Our agreement with that assessment isn't what matters. [[User:Bo|Bo]] ([[User talk:Bo|talk]]) 05:10, 20 June 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::::::::That link is quoting the ACNA declaration, not Sydney Anglican opinion. See my comment below.[[User:Sbmackay|Sbmackay]] ([[User talk:Sbmackay|talk]]) 06:33, 20 June 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::::::Thats nonsense.  The Anglicans quite rightly claim to be the successors of all the medieval Roman Catholics in England.  It was then what built all those impressive 800 year old churches,  and wrote Bede's history,  and Thomas a Becket.  Unlike a lot of the other Protestants,  they claim direct succession from that period.  But Anglicans are not Roman Catholics now,  their Church was firstly split off by Henry's divorce and then spent more than 100 years in a series of partly reversed reformations.  They protested from the universal Western Catholic (Roman) church,  and thats what they are,  Protestants.[[User:Eregli bob|Eregli bob]] ([[User talk:Eregli bob|talk]]) 05:20, 20 June 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::::::: They protested, they reformed the church, and they continued the historic apostolic succession of the episcopate.  That is what they are, a protestant, reformed, catholic church.  Few in Anglicanism are more removed from the Anglo-Catholic branch within Anglicanism than Sydney, and even they hold to the historic apostolic succession of the Episcopate. Henry's divorce created a 'schism', but no heresies.  Elizabeth's restoration of the Church of England is where a protestant reformed catholic church took hold.  Again, it isn't our 'opinions' that matter, it is what do the Anglican Churches teach? [[User:Bo|Bo]] ([[User talk:Bo|talk]]) 05:32, 20 June 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::::::::Huh? Did you really read the SydAng article you linked to carefully? Glyn Davies is quoting the declarations of the [[Anglican Church in North America]], not the diocese of Sydney. He states his opinion as: ''&quot;I do not think that it can be proved from Scripture that what emerged in the medieval church in terms of the ‘historic episcopate’ satisfies Article VI of the 39 Articles&quot;'' He argues that 'historic episcopate' must refers to the NT office of bishop if it is to be consistent with the 39 articles teaching about the sufficiency of the Scriptures. There is no way the SydAng's would hold to Apostolic Sucession, and it's even less likely they would make it a foundational mark of Anglicanism.
:::::::::::::::As for Eregli's point - historic continuity is irrelevant. This discussion concerns the specific idea of Apostolic Succession, and whether that should be said to be foundational to Anglicanism.[[User:Sbmackay|Sbmackay]] ([[User talk:Sbmackay|talk]]) 06:31, 20 June 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::::::::See Glyn Davies [http://www.sydneyanglicans.net/news/communion/the_historic_episcopate_a_response/ second article on the topic]
:::::::::::::::Also a comment under the article: &quot;In the nineteenth century the Anglican Communion invented the expresion the historic episcopate in 1888 , ''so that the view that bishops were not the successors of the apostles could be maintained.'' Historic could mean an ancient but not a practice instituted by Our Lord. It could aso be inclusive of those who believed the opposite!&quot;[[User:Sbmackay|Sbmackay]] ([[User talk:Sbmackay|talk]]) 06:42, 20 June 2010 (UTC)
::::::::::::::: Most Anglicans claim lines of succession by laying of hands - the apostolic succession from New Testament Times (Even Sydney grants that it would have started in the NT, and they are mighty low-church).  Jos puts it much more simply &quot;It usually considered that the bishops of an Episcopal polity derive such authority from an unbroken, personal Apostolic Succession from the twelve apostles of Jesus. Bishops with such authority are known as the historic episcopate.&quot; http://www.anglicandioceseofjos.org/structure.html [[User:Bo|Bo]] ([[User talk:Bo|talk]]) 07:05, 21 June 2010 (UTC)
::::::::::::::::Where do you get this idea the SydAng's claim apostolic succession started in the NT? If it's from the article you linked to, I refer you to my above comments which you don't seem to have read. 
::::::::::::::::By the way, Jos?? Ironically, your source from the Anglican Diocese of Jos was written by ''Rev Sambo with helps from Wikipedia''!!! That is hilarious. Circular anyone? NPOV on this is actually quite important, as evidenced by the fact a Priest in Nigeria is depending on unreferenced claims in Wikipedia to teach ordinands about worldwide Anglican beliefs (and those claims in my opinion are misleading). See my response to the Apostolic Succession section below.[[User:Sbmackay|Sbmackay]] ([[User talk:Sbmackay|talk]]) 09:35, 21 June 2010 (UTC)

== Episcopalianism ==

In an edit summary, Angr wrote:
:''although the largest Anglican church in the US is the Episcopal Church, Anglicanism is still called Anglicanism there, and Episcopalianism now redirects more sensibly to Episcopal
True. Many other Americans, especially non-Christians, call it Episcopalianism (documented by several dictionaries.)  The term is also normal in Wales, Scotland and Ireland.  Before 'Anglicanism' was coined, the tradition was called Episcopalianism in England.

The use of [[episcopalianism]] (uncapitalised) to mean [[episcopal polity]] is very unusual, both in Wikipedia and in the world at large.

I propose including the phrase
:(sometimes known as '''Episcopalianism''')
in the lead section of the article.

--[[User:Hro%C3%B0ulf|Hroðulf]] (or Hrothulf) ([[User talk:Hro%C3%B0ulf|Talk]]) 06:51, 27 September 2008 (UTC)

:The thing is, I'm not convinced anyone calls Anglicanism ''in general'' &quot;Episcopalianism&quot;. At best, people in the U.S., Scotland, etc., may call their local brand of Anglicanism &quot;Episcopalianism&quot;, but I seriously doubt there are Americans or Scots who would say, for example, &quot;Episcopalianism is the state religion in England&quot;. —[[User:Angr|'''An''']][[User talk:Angr|''gr'']] 08:12, 27 September 2008 (UTC)

::I am not convinced about the general case either (though in the 17th and 18th centuries they did, so a mention makes piped links from historical articles like [[St. Bridget's Kirk]] work.)  
::However, in my opinion, as long as a significant minority calls its local brand ''Episcopalianism'', that is enough to be worthy of mention in the lead, since the local brands are identical to the English version, apart from the increased democracy.
::In particular, the provinces planted by overseas missions of ECUSA are certainly Episcopalian as much as they are Anglican.
::--[[User:Hro%C3%B0ulf|Hroðulf]] (or Hrothulf) ([[User talk:Hro%C3%B0ulf|Talk]]) 11:05, 27 September 2008 (UTC)

I am still struggling to make piped links like &lt;nowiki&gt;[[Anglicanism|Episcopalian]]&lt;/nowiki&gt; be unsurprising to the reader when they follow the link from a historical article such as [[St. Bridget's Kirk]].  

I looked up the Oxford English Dictionary today, and though it traces both Anglicanism and Episcopalianism to the 1800s, ''Anglican'' and ''Episcopalian'' both go back further, both meaning more or less the same thing as adjectives.

Therefore, I still think the phrase will be useful to readers:
:(sometimes known as '''Episcopalianism''')

--[[User:Hro%C3%B0ulf|Hroðulf]] (or Hrothulf) ([[User talk:Hro%C3%B0ulf|Talk]]) 08:57, 18 October 2008 (UTC)

I am an American who attends an Episcopal Church and I have never heard &quot;Episcopalianism&quot; in my life. If it is used, it is [[WP:NEO]]. -- [[User:Secisek|Secisek]] ([[User talk:Secisek|talk]]) 06:56, 19 December 2008 (UTC)

AHH! I see. I just went to St. Bridget's Kirk and it was not &quot;Episcopalianism&quot; (as in an Anglican denomination) that King Charles wanted to impose on the Scottish kirk, but rather [[Episcopal polity]]. Episcopalianism in that sense is not exactly the same as the Anglican Church of England. The link there should pipe to the polity, not to this page. -- [[User:Secisek|Secisek]] ([[User talk:Secisek|talk]]) 07:02, 19 December 2008 (UTC)

: Here in the US, I have certainly heard &quot;Episcopalianism&quot; as the &quot;ism&quot; term referring to the faith of the Episcopal Church, an Episcopalian (member of TEC) is sometimes referred to as a practitioner of Episcopalianism.  It's certainly not [[WP:NEO]]; if necessary, we need it restricted to the US.  I have '''never''' heard &quot;episcopalianism&quot; identified as simply &quot;episcopal polity&quot;, except in a context where &quot;episcopal&quot; in turn is referring specifically TEC or Anglicans in general.  I have never heard of a Roman Catholic referred to as an &quot;episcopalian&quot;, for example, whereas &quot;episcopalian&quot; is a more-or-less frequent term--'''especially''' in the days before such common knowledge of the Anglican Communion--and certainly should redirect either here or to a specifically American site, such as [[Episcopal Church (United States)]].  But here seems right. [[User:Tb|Tb]] ([[User talk:Tb|talk]]) 08:19, 19 December 2008 (UTC)
:: I agree that &quot;Episcopalianism&quot; can mean the practice of the Episcopal Church. I have doubtless used the word myself when saying, &quot;My parents both grew up Baptists, then after their marriage they converted to Roman Catholicism, and about ten years later they converted to Episcopalianism&quot;. I don't mean they converted to episcopal polity (which they already had in the RCC) but that they converted to the Episcopal Church; they became Episcopalians. (On a side note, I find it frustrating that there's no word for the practice of Baptists - Baptism means something else, as does Baptistry, and Baptistism just sounds dumb.) —[[User:Angr|'''An''']][[User talk:Angr|''gr'']] 08:38, 19 December 2008 (UTC)

The sample redirect cited above concerns the placement of Bishops in the non-Anglican Church of Scotland. It should NOT in the example given, redirect here, it should redirect to episcopal polity. -- [[User:Secisek|Secisek]] ([[User talk:Secisek|talk]]) 09:17, 19 December 2008 (UTC)

:Charles did also try to impose the BCP, he was trying to bring the two churches very much in line, James VI (and I) tried to impose only the Episcopal polit, Charles certainly got closer to imposing Anglicanism, it was only following the Glorious Revolution, and the non-juring bishops; support for Jacobitism that the Scottish Epsicopal Church became a completely separate body.  [[User:David Underdown|David Underdown]] ([[User talk:David Underdown|talk]]) 10:43, 19 December 2008 (UTC)

Now this touches on a difficult question, early Church of Scotland bishops retained their titles, but not their power as the kirk switched to a Presbryterian polity. What do we make of those bishops? I once suggested that they were in fact Anglican forerunners of the Scottish Episcopal Church and I was assured that was not so. How about this guy for example: [[Alexander Campbell of Carco]]. Protestant and Geneva trained, but a &quot;Church of Scotland&quot; bishop. What do we make of him? Could we call him an Anglican? He is clearly practicing &quot;Episcopalianism&quot; but is he Anglican as we understand the term? The Anglican Scottish Episcopal Church is often dated in it origins to the Restoration - with the non-jurors at the time of 1688/9 forming an Anglican breakaway Church off of the non-Anglican (but sometimes lead by  Episcopalianism) Church of Scotland. Thoughts? This IS complicated stuff. 

On the subject of our American church, I don't have to tell any of you that the notion of a denominational &quot;Episcopalianism&quot; is nearly dead here. &quot;Anglicanism&quot; will sadly be the only thing tying some churches together in any way in the very near future. -- [[User:Secisek|Secisek]] ([[User talk:Secisek|talk]]) 11:03, 19 December 2008 (UTC)

: I have no idea what Secisek is speaking of, except thatc it seems to be a veiled reference to the current schism.  [[User:Tb|Tb]] ([[User talk:Tb|talk]]) 15:41, 19 December 2008 (UTC)

::I'll calrify. The notion that we in the USA belong to a denominational &quot;Episcopalianism&quot; because of our membership in the Episcopal Church is corruption of the term. This will become more clear, as there are more and more self-proclaimed Anglicans who will leave the Episcopal Church. It would still be proper to refer to them as practicing &quot;Episcopalianism&quot; in their non-Anglican Communion churches. That is why the redirect of &quot;Episcopalianism&quot; should not point here. They may be governed by Episcopal polity - and therefore practice &quot;Episcopalianism&quot; - but if they wind up outside of the Anglican Communion, would it still be proper to call them Anglicans? This is hypothetical and we have no answer yet. This is also tangental to the issue I was raising which concerns the imposition of Episcopal polity on a non-Anglican Church as we saw in the Church of Scotland. -- [[User:Secisek|Secisek]] ([[User talk:Secisek|talk]]) 19:51, 19 December 2008 (UTC) 

I fear you are rather over-simplifying matters Secisek.  Anglicans of the 19th century certainly regarded the writings of Caroline divines as prefiguring many of their ideas.  But that should not be taken as implying that there was a continuity in those ideas in the Church of England throughout the intervening period, and certainly not that these ideas were regarded in the intervening period as characteristic of &quot;Anglicanism&quot;; if that term was used.

Effectively, the British Isles in the 18th century had four &quot;protestant episcopal&quot; churches; the established churches of England and Ireland, the Episcopalian church of Scotland, and the 24 &quot;Qualfied Congregations&quot; in Scotland, who recognised the Hanoverian Succession under the Toleration Act of 1712.  (The latter group, which had no bishops or diocesan structures, might plausibly be considered to be 24 congregational churches).  The Scots Episcopalian bishops cannot be considered Anglicans - as they denied the validity of the episcopal orders of the Church of England, and vice versa. But, asked to identify &quot;Anglicans&quot; within Scotland, 18th century English divines would have pointed to the qualified congregations, not to the Episcopalian bishops.

Hence it is probably only correct to conjoin &quot;Episcopalianism&quot; and &quot;Anglicanism&quot;, if referring to the period after the various churches carrying these labels came to mutual acceptance and recognition; i.e. after about 1850. [[User:TomHennell|TomHennell]] ([[User talk:TomHennell|talk]]) 17:54, 19 December 2008 (UTC)

:The Roman Catholic Church can be described as practicing &quot;Episcopalianism&quot; which is a theoretical system for organizing church goverment, not a subgroup within Christianity that operates under a common name, tradition and identity, which is the definition of a religious denomination, like &quot;Anglicanism&quot;. Use of the former as a synonym of the later is a corruption and should be avoided. 

:That aside, what do you make of the Scottish bishop I cited above? I took the Anglican project flag off of him, but was uncertain in doing so. Is he a non-Anglican practioner of &quot;Episcopalianism&quot; or an Bishop in the Church of Scotland when it happened to be Anglican for a time? -- [[User:Secisek|Secisek]] ([[User talk:Secisek|talk]]) 19:51, 19 December 2008 (UTC)

:: To be honest, I cannot see any respect in which he could be classed as Anglican - and certainly the Church of Scotland cannot at this time be so termed.  From the article, his career rather seems typical of the tulchan bishops of the latter half of the 16th century in Scotland.  Melville denounced episcopacy in principle from around 1574 onwards, but it is only in 1580 that this view was accepted by the General Assembly, and 1581 when it was incorporated into the second Book of Discipline.  After this date, even though the bishops had no effective authority, they remained a legally necessity for the Church to maintain access to its properties and income - as long as James remained adamantly oppposed to legislation abolishing their legal status. And. of course, their continued existence made it possible for James gradually to restore disciplinary jurisdiction to them from 1610 onwards  [[User:TomHennell|TomHennell]] ([[User talk:TomHennell|talk]]) 02:00, 20 December 2008 (UTC)

That was my feeling as well, which is I removed the Anglican tag that some well-meaning editor placed on it. On the other hand [[John Paterson (archbishop)]], as a Church of Scotland non-juror, clearly planted seeds that would lead to Anglicanism in Scotland. Agreed? -- [[User:Secisek|Secisek]] ([[User talk:Secisek|talk]]) 09:54, 21 December 2008 (UTC)

==Numbers of Adherents==

The main article says there are 77 million Anglicans, though the articles it refers to give  figures of 70 million and 73 million. But how are these figures arrived at? I've put a similar question about their numbers to the Roman Catholics (in the talk page of the article about the RC church), and have received some interesting answers, even though their discipline and public relations are greatly superior to those of the Anglican churches. [[User:Millbanks|Millbanks]] ([[User talk:Millbanks|talk]]) 23:24, 23 December 2008 (UTC)

== Tagging - via media ==

I have removed a whole series of tags relating to Anglicanism as a Via Media between Catholic and Protestant traditions.  There is a lot of material in this article that needs in-line citation, but the issue of the via media is fully discussed (and references cited) in the section on theories of Anglican identity.  [[User:TomHennell|TomHennell]] ([[User talk:TomHennell|talk]]) 17:23, 6 February 2009 (UTC)

I have a problem with via media being dated to the period of the Commonwealth (mid 17th c) shouldn't it date to the Oxford Movement (mid 19th c)? [[User:Nitpyck|Nitpyck]] ([[User talk:Nitpyck|talk]]) 08:20, 7 March 2009 (UTC)

:Well the first person to use the term was [[Richard Hooker]], to what extent it remained an active idea between then and the Oxford Movement might be debateable, but it was certainly in existence.  [[User:David Underdown|David Underdown]] ([[User talk:David Underdown|talk]]) 10:46, 7 March 2009 (UTC)

Yeah ok but (and notice I did choose the name nitpyck) The sentence reads -
&quot;By the mid 17th century the Church of England (and associated episcopal churches in Ireland and in England's American colonies) came to be seen as comprising a distinct Christian tradition with theologies, structures and forms of worship representing a middle ground, or via media...&quot; and through the 17th c COE was clearly considered Protestant since you had to be one to become king or queen, and the ruler was the head of the church. Also at that time the COE was the church in the American colonies and when that changed after the American Revolution (late 18th c)its new name included the word Protestant. Also I'm pretty sure in the 16th and 17th centuries the Spanish would still have lumped the COE in with the rest of the Protestants and had not yet come to see them as a distinct Christan tradition. [[User:Nitpyck|Nitpyck]] ([[User talk:Nitpyck|talk]]) 21:36, 7 March 2009 (UTC)

: good points nitpyck.  The idea of Anglicanism as a via media does go back to Hooker, and is explicit in George Herbert and Lancelot Andrewes.  But the Restoration changed matters, and from the late 17th century to the early 19th century, I doubt whether many Anglicans would have thought in these terms. Parliamentary legislation of the 18th century refers to the &quot;Protestant Episcopal Church&quot; (i.e. Church of England); and the &quot;Protestant Presbyterian Church&quot; (i.e. Church of Scotland) as counterparts; but this assumed equivalence itself would not have been acceptable to many Anglicans (and indeed Presbyterians). The section on Anglican identity does go into the various ways in which the term &quot;via media&quot; was understood in the 19th century.  Maybe the header paragraph should be adjusted to be more consistent (and to avoid the impression that Anglicanism had a consistent understanding on these matters from the mid 17th century onwards).  Perhaps:
:&quot;For a period in the mid 17th century the Church of England (and associated episcopal churches in Ireland and in England's American colonies) was presented by some Anglican divines as comprising a distinct Christian tradition with theologies, structures and forms of worship representing a middle ground, or via media, between Reformed Protestantism and Roman Catholicism; a perspective that came to be highly influential in later theories of Anglican identity&quot; [[User:TomHennell|TomHennell]] ([[User talk:TomHennell|talk]]) 01:20, 8 March 2009 (UTC)

:I like it- [[User:Nitpyck|Nitpyck]] ([[User talk:Nitpyck|talk]]) 06:43, 8 March 2009 (UTC)

== Focus of Unity ==

The article has identified the Archbishop of Canterbury as the &quot;focus of unity&quot; for some time, but a recent anonymous editor, and then a regular editor, think it shouldn't say that.  The &quot;focus of unity&quot; language is long-standing, and refers specifically to the Archbishop, as distinguished from the other &quot;instruments of unity&quot; (Lambeth Conference, ACC, and primates' meeting).  I would like to hear the reasons against repeating the normative use of these Angilcan organizations here before the text is changed. [[User:Tb|Tb]] ([[User talk:Tb|talk]]) 05:12, 11 April 2009 (UTC)
:The term Focus of Unity referring solely to the Archbishop of Canterbury is a completely new one to me. I have never heard it used in that specific sense. Now I am not a member of any inner circles and I am sure that it is used but for how long and in what context? Perhaps it should be referenced. [[User:Dabbler|Dabbler]] ([[User talk:Dabbler|talk]]) 10:12, 11 April 2009 (UTC)
::It is in the windsor report, certainly.  More to the point, I would suggest that it hasn't ever been used to refer to anything but the ABC--distinguish it carefully from &quot;intrument of unity&quot;, which has referred to the &quot;big four&quot;. [[User:Tb|Tb]] ([[User talk:Tb|talk]]) 21:39, 11 April 2009 (UTC)
The article is too focused on the Anglican Communion. Much of it should be merged there and this article should be completely rewritten to something more along the leaner lines of [[Catholicism]] [[Orthodox Christianity]]. Thoughts? -- [[User:Secisek|Secisek]] ([[User talk:Secisek|talk]]) 17:47, 13 April 2009 (UTC)
: Yeah, but then we get into the thorny &quot;how anglican can you be without the anglican communion&quot; question, and golly, '''that''' can of worms i'm not eager to open. [[User:Tb|Tb]] ([[User talk:Tb|talk]]) 18:14, 13 April 2009 (UTC)

== And what about King henry VIII? ==

I was taught in school that the Anglican church was essentially founded by King Henry VIII so that he could change the rules and be able to divorce his wife.  However, the article does not even mention this.  Was I taught wrong?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/64.35.207.238|64.35.207.238]] ([[User talk:64.35.207.238|talk]]) 12:08, 21 October 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:He's mor erelevant to the [[Church of England]] specifically than the wider concept of Anglicanism.  [[User:David Underdown|David Underdown]] ([[User talk:David Underdown|talk]]) 12:46, 21 October 2009 (UTC)

::I have reverted an edit making reference to Henry VIII, it seems that an editor had missed this discussion on the talk page.  There is a separate article on the [[History of the Church of England]].   This page relates primarily to the common identity and traditions, and range of diverse opinions and practices, in an association of autonomous churches that may once have had allegiance to the British Crown, but now mostly do not. [[User:TomHennell|TomHennell]] ([[User talk:TomHennell|talk]]) 23:48, 21 October 2009 (UTC)


== &quot;The earliest Anglican formularies corresponded closely to those of contemporary Reformed Protestantism;&quot; ==
Must be wrong, the earliest Anglican formularies were during the millenium when the Anglican church was in full communion with Rome, surely? It means the earliest post schism Anglican formularies doesn't it? --[[User:BozMo|BozMo]] [[user talk:BozMo|talk]] 18:15, 4 March 2010 (UTC)
:Even then it's not true; the schism occurred under Henry VIII; the earliest formularies written after that were the Litany, which did not correspond closely to Reformed ones; and the 1549 prayer book (the next thing) was far too conservative for those interested in greater Reformation.  [[User:Tb|Tb]] ([[User talk:Tb|talk]]) 22:45, 4 March 2010 (UTC)

::: perhaps &quot;formularies&quot; is wrong - the reference is to the Articles of Religion, Book of Common Prayer and Ordinal - specfically the 42 Articles of 1553 and 39 Articles of 1563/1571; and the 1559 and 1662 BCP with their ordinals. These are regarded as the 'historic formularies' of the Church of England for the purposes of Canon Law and the declarations required of English clergy at their induction.  Maybe it is too specifically an English term, and a better might be suggested. Henry offered the Bishop's book, the Ten Articles and the Six Articles - but these are clearly not yet distinctively Anglican in nature; and hence don't count as Anglican formularies, either in law, or for the purposes of Wikipedia (I would submit).  But that is my opinion, maybe you could offer a correction or clarification? [[User:TomHennell|TomHennell]] ([[User talk:TomHennell|talk]]) 02:33, 5 March 2010 (UTC)

:::: I've made a change that I think helps considerably.  What I think you're missing is that there were certainly formularies before 1550, they were just different.  And the idea that we should only look to what is &quot;distinctively Anglican&quot; would produce the odd result that the Nicene Creed or the list of canonical books are not Anglican formularies.  It was the ''new'' formularies which had Reformed influence, not the &quot;oldest&quot; formularies.  But even then, the 1549 prayer book is surely one of the &quot;earliest&quot;, well before the current &quot;historic&quot; books of 1559 and 1662, and 1549 belies the theory that the &quot;earliest&quot; had more Reformed influence than later ones.  [[User:Tb|Tb]] ([[User talk:Tb|talk]]) 18:15, 5 March 2010 (UTC)

:::::: Thanks; I have made a small further change.  The point being that formulations and liturgies that were securely acceptable within mainstream Reformed Protestantism in 1550, had come to become regarded as unacceptable to many godly protestants by 1600. Over the decades, the boundaries between what was ''adiaphora'' and what was ''essential'' shifted in Geneva; and the expectation was that the reformed churches elsewhere in Europe would follow the lead.  But Elizabeth refused to shift, so by the early 17th century (e.g. in Donne and Herbert) Anglicanism is clearly distinguishable from Calvinism; to a degree that had not been the case in 1550. [[User:TomHennell|TomHennell]] ([[User talk:TomHennell|talk]]) 01:46, 6 March 2010 (UTC)

::::::: Thank you both, much improved to my limited knowledge. --[[User:BozMo|BozMo]] [[user talk:BozMo|talk]] 20:47, 6 March 2010 (UTC)

== Percentages  ==

The article identifies: high church, broad church, low church, Continuing Anglicans, and Anglo-Catholics. How many belong to each group? Where are they most found? I mention this in part since the Anglo-Catholic end of the spectrum seem to dominate Anglican WP articles. How many Anglicans deny their Protestant roots? [[User:Nitpyck|Nitpyck]] ([[User talk:Nitpyck|talk]]) 03:12, 6 May 2010 (UTC)

: Perhaps 50 years ago, that might have been possible (or at least possible within England and Wales, and at the parish level).  If you went into an English parish church, you could commonly detect a 'party' affiliation; which hymn book did they use?, Church Times or Church of England Newspaper?, what services were on the notice-board (and at what times)?, how did the rector term himself?  (However even then, if you had asked the parishioners themselves whether they had a particular churchmanship, they would most likely have denied it, saying that the tradition of their particular parish was simply 'normal' for the Church of England.)  Now clear party affilitation  is no longer the case for the majority of parishes, partly as liturgical reform has jumbled-up the practices of various traditions who are consequently much more used to variation and experimentation; partly becuase previously rival parishes (and publications) have merged to save costs; but also because the sorts of issues that are currently divisive, most often cut across the old liturgy-based distictions. [[User:TomHennell|TomHennell]] ([[User talk:TomHennell|talk]]) 09:28, 6 May 2010 (UTC)

: Your question, Nitpyck, has rather a large thumb on the scale.  We might as well ask how many Anglicans deny their Catholic roots?  To think that Anglicanism was invented in the sixteenth century is already to prejudge such questions.  The strong number of Anglo-Catholics tends to be an American phenomenon, in my opinion.  [[User:Tb|Tb]] ([[User talk:Tb|talk]]) 17:34, 6 May 2010 (UTC)

::Thumb or not, to say it didn't start with Henry VIII seems Anglo-Catholic. But how is it spread in Africa which I believe (not know) is where most Anglicans now live? Are the African churches high or low or is that distinction no longer useful? This is all second hand to me since my family was last COE when Pennsylvania added a Test Act and banned prayers for the King.[[User:Nitpyck|Nitpyck]] ([[User talk:Nitpyck|talk]]) 06:44, 7 May 2010 (UTC)

:::There was much continuity with the earlier English church (Dioceses were reorganised, and new ones created, but much of the senior clergy remained the same, abbeys were dissolved, but some were raised to the status of cathedrals, at Peterborough for instance the last abbot became the first bishop), and under Henry the church retained a largely catholic identity.  It was under Edward that a more Protestant character appeared, due to those who dominated his governemtn (edward was under age).  Of course under Mary the pendulum swung (violently) back the other way, and Elizabeth's position attemoted to reach a compromise.  To some extent that broke down under Charles I, and of course under the Commonwealtha presbyterian polity was adopted, but with the Restoration returned the bishops.  High Church and Low Church had slightly different connotations then, and what we would now recognise as Anglo-Catholicism emerged in the 19th century (along with more evangelical groups such as the Clapham Set).

:::As to Africa, it often depends which missionary society was most active in a given region, and who set up the theological colleges and so on.  As can be seen from the make up of [[GAFCON]], Nigeria and Uganda have strong Evangelical leadership.  [[User:David Underdown|David Underdown]] ([[User talk:David Underdown|talk]]) 09:39, 7 May 2010 (UTC)

== Protestants? NPOV dispute==

There seems to be a peculiar anti-reality bias in the current form of this article. While many, many Anglicans (at least, Americans) consider themselves Protestant, this is not adequately addressed, but given only as an aside in the 'doctrinal issues' section.

Looking at the archives, this is *very* clearly a result of modern revisionism. As recently as Archive 2, under the heading &quot;Other Protestants&quot; we find lines like

:*But you are correct in that the line should be removed. &lt;i&gt;Other protestants&lt;/i&gt; do maintain the episcopate: Methodists, some Baptists, Pentacostals, for example.

going uncontended. Italics are mine. Then in Archive 3 we get a lengthy theological debate over the status of the church.

If in 2006 nobody found it the *least* bit odd that people should refer to Anglicans as Protestants, doesn't it deserve a clearer mention? Note that a section with a number of replies is &lt;i&gt;entitled&lt;/i&gt; &quot;Other Protestants&quot;, with nobody responding to the effect that 'Anglicans are not Protestants'.

If, in fact, it is truthful that the majority of Anglican churches consider themselves not to be Protestant churches, by all means that should be stated. But to utterly wipe out the actual history is totally anti-wikipedia.

Firstly, there ought to be some statement near the top about the fact that up until very recently (2006?) Anglicans were considered a Protestant church, at least by most humans aware of the church's existence.

Secondly, there ought to be a mention of Henry VIII. Even if his effect on the religion was not as great as thought (and taught) by many, it's misinformation not to include him. How can one educate if one doesn't clear up common misperceptions?

As it stands now, unlike the overwhelming majority of wikipedia articles, there's no clearly-delineated early section summarizing and explaining the history and origins of the movement. Note under Elizabeth I:

:*One of her first moves as queen was to support the establishment of an English &lt;i&gt;Protestant&lt;/i&gt; church, of which she became the Supreme Governor.

The Duke of Monmouth was supported for the throne for his Protestantism. William of Orange married into the family partly because they wanted a Protestant.

Under James II:

:*Charles II opposed the conversion, ordering that James's daughters, Mary and Anne, be raised as &lt;i&gt;Protestants&lt;/i&gt;.

There's lots of evidence that the majority of England, and the majority of English monarchs, at least at one point considered the Church of England a Protestant church. How is this not mentioned?

[[Special:Contributions/151.204.140.143|151.204.140.143]] ([[User talk:151.204.140.143|talk]]) 22:27, 3 June 2010 (UTC)

: I think most of these are already discussed in [[Church of England]] and [[History of the Church of England]] where they belong.  This is why I pointed out (below) that this is the page for Anglicanism, not for the Church of England.  [[User:Tb|Tb]] ([[User talk:Tb|talk]]) 22:53, 7 June 2010 (UTC)

: some good points there - though I think most of them could be met by a judicious expansion of the discussion of just this issue in the &quot;Doctrinal Issues&quot; section.  The article could also benefit from pruning of the some terminology - for instance in the opening where Protestantism is presented as a tradition distinct from Anglicanism.  

: However, I think your basic thesis is flawed.  In general, the awareness of the Church of England as &quot;Anglican&quot; from the mid 19th century onwards, superceded any understanding of itself as 'Protestant'.  It is certainly true that early 18th century parliamentarians adopted a device by which the faith of the country was identified as &quot;The Protestant Religion&quot; of which the Monarch must be a faithful adherent, adn which found concrete expression in the etablished &quot;Protestant Episcopal Church&quot; in England, and the &quot;Protestant Presbyterian Church&quot; in Scotland.  But however congenial this might be, it was always a fudge; contrived to allow the Church of England to acknowledge as King a man (George 1st) who was a Lutheran.  Scots Presbyterians never regarded members of the Church of England as their co-religionists, nor did they accept the authority of the King in Parliament in matters spiritual.  In effect the 18th century Church of England adopted a counterpart approach; they could not acknowledge the spiritual authority of a parliament that was partially Presbyterian, so the convocations of York and Canterbury ceased to meet: as they had no one to pass any resolutions to for statutory debate.  So the 18th century understanding of the Church of England as Protestant was a dead letter; in effect the modern such understanding dates only back to the Evangelical Movement of the early 19th century; and it is precisely this understanding that later 'Anglicans' saw themselves as replacing.  Perhaps I need to expand the &quot;Identity&quot; section, though it should not become a potted history of the C of E.  [[User:TomHennell|TomHennell]] ([[User talk:TomHennell|talk]]) 01:23, 5 June 2010 (UTC)
::That is slightly more realistic, but frankly not much. The Church of England was quite certain it was Protestant between the mid-Elizabethan period and the mid 19th century; what &quot;device&quot; parliamentarians are supposed to have &quot;adopted&quot; in the &quot;early 18th century&quot; I can't imagine - the [[Succession to the Crown Act 1707]] merely used concepts that had been standard for generations.  That Anglicans also knew they were not Presbyterians is no argument against this. [[User:Johnbod|Johnbod]] ([[User talk:Johnbod|talk]]) 01:45, 5 June 2010 (UTC)

::: What was new (and effectively a fudge) in this period, was the broad concept of a continuing Protestant religion; i.e. a common religious identity amongst (most of) the churches that derived from the 16th century Reformation - and which might therefore embrace a wide range of non-Catholic belief. The fudge arose out of the failure of &quot;Comprehension&quot;; the aspiration that the Church of England might redefine its formulae and liturgy in such a way as to allow non-Catholic non-Anglicans to participate in its worship.  But the aspiration proved impossible in practice; with the consequent creation in England of the distinct worshipping communities of Anglicanism and Dissent; the fudge allowed that both would continue legally.  In continental Europe such a fudge had already been adopted int the Netherlands; but otherwise almost all non-Catholic churches were celarly either Lutheran or Reformed, and as such, mutually rejected any suggestion that they shared a common religion.  A similar , and equally absolute, mutual rejection would separate Scots presbyterians from English Anglicans (although both churches were clearly 'Reformed' in origin and doctrine). So the Parliamentary concept of a &quot;Protestant Religion&quot; remained a legal fiction with no spiritual application at all. The modern concept of Protestantism as a continuing religious identity is essentially an American development; Diarmaid MacCulloch detects it first in mid-18th century Pennsylvania. What forced a change across the rest of the Anglican tradition was primarily the experience of Mission.  Church of England missionaries of the 18th century tried to maintain the principle that the converts of Dissenters should never be considered as Christians until they became Anglicans; but by the end of the century this ideal had broken down. So by the 19th century, we do find an awareness of a common Protestant identity in many places, but the contents of that identity were far from uniform; Anglicans, Methodists and Presbyterians probably, but the status of Baptists and Quakers in this supposed common tradition would remain far less clear. [[User:TomHennell|TomHennell]] ([[User talk:TomHennell|talk]]) 01:53, 6 June 2010 (UTC)

It should be noted that this article is not [[Church of England]] but [[Anglicanism]].  The development of &quot;Anglicanism&quot; as a specific thing even independent of the specifics of the Church of England is intimately tied with the increasing influence of Anglo-Catholic theology.  One might see this as &quot;modern revisionism&quot;, but only if one thinks the 16th century is the official &quot;starting point&quot; of Anglicanism.  That is itself already to prejudge the question; we can find as many theological (and English Constitutional!) points articulating strongly that the reformed Church of England was ''also'' continuous with the ancient Church of England and not any kind of new thing.  (Consider the official ordinal numbers on bishops, who controls the ancient Cathedrals even after official toleration of Roman Catholics, etc.)  Moreover, the word &quot;Protestant&quot; changes its meaning over time, and is often used by those who are ignorant of the details of Anglican history or theology.  [[User:Tb|Tb]] ([[User talk:Tb|talk]]) 17:14, 7 June 2010 (UTC)
::Oh dear. You'll be bringing [[Celtic Christianity]] in next.  This isn't so much revisionist as reviving 17th antiquarianism. [[User:Johnbod|Johnbod]] ([[User talk:Johnbod|talk]]) 19:17, 7 June 2010 (UTC)
:::I can't make out what on earth you're talking about now.  Perhaps you could address what I said rather than your incorrect predictions of what I might say in the future?  [[User:Tb|Tb]] ([[User talk:Tb|talk]]) 22:14, 7 June 2010 (UTC)
:::Also, if the 19th century branch theory, and 21st century via-media-ism is &quot;reviving 17th [century] antiquarianism&quot;, then the idea that Anglicans have always unproblematically called themselves &quot;protestant&quot; since 15xx (we never get much specificity on just when) must be false.  It can't simultaneously be true that it's revisionist, and 17th century, and unheard-of-before-now. As it is, the article seems to spend a fair about of time trying to explain the point; insisting that we must find a trivial answer, and put it first, in order to tell people what they expect to hear, is wrong.  We don't need to give the &quot;simplistic answer closest to the truth&quot;, we can just explain the truth in all its gory detail.  If we are speaking about contemporary Anglicanism, it is indeed controversial to say that it is simply protestant full-stop, but I am all in favor of fuller explanations of the complexity of the topic.  The article already has a pretty full explanation, but where it needs more, by all means let's add more.  At this point, it gets complaints that its discussion is too hard, as if the goal of the article is to simplify reality to be easy to understand.  [[User:Tb|Tb]] ([[User talk:Tb|talk]]) 22:51, 7 June 2010 (UTC)
::::You're tying yourself in knots here, but frankly I can't be bothered with more more of this. Just look at the page frankly, and ask yourself if it '''in any way''' explains why the vast majority of Anglicans for most of the periods since the Reformation, and a very considerable number today, thought or think of themselves as Protestant.  I and other visitors to this cosy corner clearly don't think it does. [[User:Johnbod|Johnbod]] ([[User talk:Johnbod|talk]]) 23:28, 7 June 2010 (UTC)
:::::Well, let's imagine someone who wonders why that's true, and so they start reading.  And they get to the third paragraph of the lead, which explains that the formularies ''corresponded closely to those of contemporary Reformed Protestantism'', identifies the first important difference, namely, that ''the retention in Anglicanism of many traditional liturgical forms and of the episcopate was already seen as unacceptable by those promoting the most developed Protestant principles'', and that by the 17th century, ''the Church of England and associated episcopal churches...were presented by some...as comprising a distinct Christian tradition, with theologies, structures and forms of worship representing a middle ground, or via media, between Reformed Protestantism and Roman Catholicism''.  The relevance of this time is of course that it is when Anglicanism (as an international phenomenon, distinct from the Church of England itself) began in earnest.  So, if they are wondering why so many Anglicans have considered themselves Protestant, there it is.  For the reader who goes on, we find interesting discussion of Newman, Maurice, and Sykes on ecclesiology.  And, we find the discussion of &quot;both Catholic and Reformed&quot; in the section on Doctrine, a large discussion on churchmanship, an explanation that the sacramental practice of the church can be traced to its identity as both Catholic and a church of the Reformation.  I think that if someone read the whole article wondering why &quot;the vast majority of Anglicans...thought or think of themselves as Protestant&quot;, they would have to have skipped over all those sections.  [[User:Tb|Tb]] ([[User talk:Tb|talk]]) 23:52, 7 June 2010 (UTC)
::::::These are exactly the problem sections, which carefully avoid ever actually stating the self-identification of Anglicanism as part of Protestantism (and carefully avoid mentioning Lutheranism for that matter).  The article falsely gives the impression that doctrinal &amp; organizational compromises and &quot;middle ways&quot; meant that Anglicanism thought of itself as outside Protestantism (here called &quot;Reformed&quot;). It didn't. [[User:Johnbod|Johnbod]] ([[User talk:Johnbod|talk]]) 00:00, 8 June 2010 (UTC)
:::::::I'm sorry, I thought the question was &quot;why do so many Anglicans consider themselves Protestant&quot;, for which you seem to allow only the answer, &quot;because Anglicans really are all Protestant&quot;.  What is interesting is whether ''actual Anglican churches'' might say that.  Here the story seems far less clear, no?  I mean, can you point us to the examples?  For example, it's really easy to find where the PCUSA identifies itself as Protestant.  It should be easy to find where the Church of England website says so.  Of course, what it ''says'' is both Catholic and Reformed, which is the language you find so objectionable.  ''My'' view is that the church is both to the extent that it draws from both, and neither to the extent that either is read to exclude the other, but this is only my view, and the article tries to stick with what is actually officially said. [[User:Tb|Tb]] ([[User talk:Tb|talk]]) 00:04, 8 June 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::I realize this is a long thread, but please recall this is concerned with Anglican self-identity mostly in the past. If they had had a website at any point between the reign of Elizabeth and - well that's an interesting question, but much much later anyway - the question would be beyond doubt I imagine.  Do we really need to go into the ''evidence'' for who was included in the term Protestant over that period?? [[User:Johnbod|Johnbod]] ([[User talk:Johnbod|talk]]) 01:45, 8 June 2010 (UTC)
::::::::::Cf. [[Baptist successionism]]. Anglo-Catholic accounts of Anglicanism are often similar (see [http://www.christchurchanglican.org/ang_topix/protestant.html here]). [[User:Srnec|Srnec]] ([[User talk:Srnec|talk]]) 04:15, 8 June 2010 (UTC)
::::::::::The article is actually not mostly about the past; it is about the present.  Its purpose is not the History of Anglicanism, but Anglicanism, focusing principally on the present, just as does [[Rome]], [[Japan]], or [[Boston]].  [[User:Tb|Tb]] ([[User talk:Tb|talk]]) 18:10, 8 June 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::::Another wiggle! The lead, and top half of the article, which is mostly what we are concerned with here, are actually rather more about the past, and most statements in the second part of the article have no time period attached to them. [[User:Johnbod|Johnbod]] ([[User talk:Johnbod|talk]]) 19:43, 8 June 2010 (UTC)
::::::::::::Please assume good faith, ok?  The original complaint was that the question of Protestantism is mentioned &quot;only as an aside in the 'doctrinal issues' section.&quot;  This isn't true.  The original complaint was not about &quot;the past&quot;, but argues that the ''present'' of the church is unquestionably Protestant, speaking ironically as if only in 2006 (when particular edits were made to this article) did objection to that label arise.  The original complaint was incorrect; the term &quot;Protestant&quot; has been objected to at various times for various reasons by various Anglicans, going back some time, considerably before 2006.  I can't tell which is your objection now: is it that there should be a plain statement &quot;Anglicanism is part of Protestantism&quot; somewhere in the lead, or is it that the complex question of Anglicanism's relation to Protestantism is not sufficiently discussed, or is it that it is discussed, but incorrectly?  [[User:Tb|Tb]] ([[User talk:Tb|talk]]) 20:36, 8 June 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::::::::The last of these, as already explained. [[User:Johnbod|Johnbod]] ([[User talk:Johnbod|talk]]) 20:40, 8 June 2010 (UTC)
You seem to be saying, if I understand it, that the article leads to a different conclusion than an honest look at the self-presentation of Anglican churches would suggest.  If we take a look at [http://www.cofe.anglican.org/faith/anglican/], we find almost no discussion of &quot;Protestant&quot;, not even &quot;Catholic and Reformed&quot; language, but instead, a discussion of the Lambeth quadrilateral, a historical survey which says, &quot;Anglicans trace their Christian roots back to the early Church, and their specifically Anglican identity to the post-Reformation expansion of the Church of England and other Episcopal or Anglican Churches.&quot;  That is the full discussion of the topic for the Church of England's public presentation of what Anglicanism is.  And the &quot;post-Reformation expansion&quot; is explicitly the 17th century spread to North America, Australia, New Zealand, and South Africa, and then the later spread by missionaries in Asia, Africa, and Latin America.  And then the Church of England's self-presentation moves on to the present-day Anglican Communion, theological method, sacraments, and connectionalism.  The Church of England does not think it notable.  The Episcopal Church's website is characteristically harder to navigate, but at [http://www.episcopalchurch.org/109399_13729_ENG_HTM.htm] we get a definition of &quot;Anglicanism&quot;, where the relevant bit says, &quot;Anglicanism reflects the balance and compromise of the via media of the Elizabethan settlement between Protestant and Catholic principles&quot;, but does not say at all that the church is Protestant.  At [http://www.episcopalchurch.org/109399_15131_ENG_HTM.htm], we read, &quot;Anglicans are categorized as Protestants by many Roman Catholics, Protestants, and some Anglicans,&quot; and, &quot;some Anglicans are ambivalent about being categorized as Protestants because of the importance of the catholic tradition in Anglicanism&quot;, followed with a brief discussion of the branch theory.  Perhaps you are looking at other present-day official documents; can you give some links to them?  [[User:Tb|Tb]] ([[User talk:Tb|talk]]) 20:59, 8 June 2010 (UTC)
::The wikipedia article on Protestantism itself is vastly different to the presentation here. ''&quot;The separation of the Church of England (then including the Church in Wales) and Church of Ireland from Rome under King Henry VIII did not take a Protestant form. However by the efforts of Thomas Cranmer Archbishop of Canterbury and Thomas Cromwell, both with Lutheran sympathies[18], the Churches assumed a Protestant character, and under King Edward VI the Churches became openly Protestant, adopting Calvinist doctrines in the Forty-Two Articles, restored under Queen Elizabeth I. Thereafter the defence of Protestantism in Britain and Ireland became a major political issue, culminating in the deposition of King James II &amp; VII and the settlement of the Crown in the line of Princess Sophia and &quot;the heirs of her body being Protestant&quot;. In the nineteenth century some of the Tractarians proposed that the Church of England and the other Anglican churches are not Protestant, but a middle path between Rome and Protestantism (via media). This assertion was attacked by, amongst others, the Church Association.[19]''
::If that is accurate, then the opening paragraph is struggling to achieve a NPOV when it seperates Anglicanism from Protestantism. The average, non-expert reader is very likely to be led astray. All these technical in-house discussion are really missing the point. The article should simply state that Anglicanism is an heir of the Protestant Reformation, and that subsequent interpretations of Anglicanism have defined themselves as via-media.[[User:Sbmackay|Sbmackay]] ([[User talk:Sbmackay|talk]]) 02:54, 19 June 2010 (UTC)
:::The other article covers the ground well, and that is what is missing here. I'm not sure you last sentence is sufficiently clear, though; we have enough of that sort of vagueness here already - what does a school student make of &quot;heir of the Protestant Reformation&quot;?  [[User:Johnbod|Johnbod]] ([[User talk:Johnbod|talk]]) 03:13, 19 June 2010 (UTC)
::::Agreed. I'm placed a NPOV tag on the article. This discussion more than warrants it.[[User:Sbmackay|Sbmackay]] ([[User talk:Sbmackay|talk]]) 03:20, 19 June 2010 (UTC)
:::::I don't care much about the tag but the article on Protestantism is about the protestant history not about the nature of the Anglican Communion though. For example it is all very well to say that &quot;Thomas Cranmer reformed the Church of England&quot; but Cranmer was executed by Mary I who completely reintegrated the Church of England with Rome, in which state it remained well after Cranmer was pushing up the daisies. So from the point of view of the article on the status of the Anglican Communion Cranmer has virtually no relevance. It is the [[Elizabethan settlement]] which is widely talked of as the start of the &quot;via media&quot;, which contained strong doctrinal element of both Catholic and Protestant traditions and one could certainly argue that the changes under Cranmer (through which bishops survived) are not terribly relevant to that question. And of course between 1559 when the Elizabethan settement took place and 1572 when the churches split, communion existed with Rome. --[[User:BozMo|BozMo]] [[user talk:BozMo|talk]] 20:26, 20 June 2010 (UTC)
:::::Looking around there are reasonable references to the origins of the via media generally being attributed to Elizabeth [[Elizabethan_Religious_Settlement#Legacy|here]], which could be brought into this article if there is a lack of adequate sourcing. --[[User:BozMo|BozMo]] [[user talk:BozMo|talk]] 22:43, 20 June 2010 (UTC)
::::::That article doesn't attribute via media to Elizabeth. It says 'At the time it was believed to have established a Protestant church', but that her preferences made it 'possible'. This article still has an Anglo-Catholic bias as far as I can see.[[User:Sbmackay|Sbmackay]] ([[User talk:Sbmackay|talk]]) 05:06, 21 June 2010 (UTC)
::::::: Your right, via media cann't  be attributed to Elizabeth, she was establishing a Protestant Episcopal Church.  Her reforms and 'settlement' kept it from becoming a puritan church (despite Cromwell) and made room for the more 'reformed' (nearly an English sub-rite of the Latin rite) churchmanhsip of Charles I &amp; II.  I don't see where you're getting an 'anglo-catholic' biase reading from though.... [[User:Bo|Bo]] ([[User talk:Bo|talk]]) 06:28, 21 June 2010 (UTC)
::::::The Elizabethan settlement was widely considered to be a protestant settlement at the time.  This was not particularly disputed until the Oxford Movement.  And, of course, the leading figures in the Oxford Movement for the most part concluded that the Church of England was, in fact, inalterably protestant, which is why they all defected to Rome.  This and other articles on Anglicanism has and has had an overwhelming Anglo-Catholic bias.  The second sentence in this article is already proclaiming that bias when it sets up Anglicanism as one of the four major branches of christianity, separate from &quot;protestantism&quot;.  The via media is also a red herring.  The original conception of the via media was that it was a middle way between Roman Catholicism and ''Calvinist Presbyterianism'', not between Roman Catholicism and &quot;Protestantism,&quot; seeing as everyone thought of the CoE as being protestant at the time.  This is why the characters in the Tale of the Tub are named Peter, Martin, and Jack - the Church of England there is being represented by Martin Luther (whose theology, it's worth noting, was actually ''more conservative'' than that of the Church of England).  The treatment of Anglicanism in wikipedia is embarrassingly biased towards Anglo-Catholic positions, and deeply ahistorical. [[User:John K|john k]] ([[User talk:John K|talk]]) 18:50, 26 August 2010 (UTC)

== Apostolic Succession ==

Editor Sbmackay has recently made a number of changes to the article, which are intended to correct an inaccurate summary of the Anglican practice of the Apostolic Succession. I feel these edits are not an improvement(and are not supported by the references cited).  In particular, it is indisputable (in my view ); that all Anglican churches practice the apostolic succession in the consecration of bishops and the ordination of priests; that this distinguishes Anglcan churches from most other denominations originating in the Protestant Reformation - to the extent that many such churches (e.g. the Church of Scotland) have in the past held that this invaldiates any claim of the Anglican communion to be Protestant at all; and that this universal practice is based on a distinctive doctrine of church authority that is particularly characteristic of Anglcanism.  The edits point out that the Anglican understanding of the apostolic succssion is not identical with that of Roman Catholcicism (but that is not a surprising point, as the Roman church has specifically ruled this to be the case).  All this proves is that the two traditions differ as to how the apostolic succession is to be understood, not that anglicanism does not regard tha apostlic succession as an essential element in church authority.  Nor does the undoubted fact that the Dioces of Sydney taks a rather different position on this from the rest of the Anglican communion, invaldiate the general point.  But what do other editors think? [[User:TomHennell|TomHennell]] ([[User talk:TomHennell|talk]]) 00:10, 21 June 2010 (UTC)
: Restored the article to condition before sbmackay's POV rampage.  

The Sydney position points out that even those most removed from anglo-catholicism still consider the episcopate to be historic and in the apostolic succession.  [[User:Bo|Bo]] ([[User talk:Bo|talk]]) 01:59, 21 June 2010 (UTC)

::Ok, maybe I was a little enthusiastic, sorry about that.
::Firstly, all of the 'unreferenced' tags added were valid and shouldn't be removed.
::Second, I agree that the reference to Richard Hookers view does not necessarily represent the English Reformers as a whole, although I believe that the statement was true. The distinction here is really important, and needs to be included in the discussion. In keeping with their views of the sufficiency of scripture (evident in the Articles), the English Reformers didn't retain succession because it is an essential part of Catholicity, but because the office of bishop is found in the New Testament. They didn't think succession was essential to true 'Catholic' ministry, but believed the successors of the apostles were those who held their doctrine. They recognised the ministry of those who didn't hold to succession. They, and many Anglicans today, interpret the 'historic episcopate' simply as the continuing order of Bishops/Priests/Deacons, rather than a strict view of tactarian succession. Even if it's practiced, you can't equate succession (which is a much narrower interpretation of this practice) with holding it as 'foundational' to Anglican identity. The fact is that many provinces don't hold that the 'historic episcopate' means apostolic sucession, and I haven't seen anything referenced to substantiate that claim (hence my alteration of the opening of the article). To achieve NPOV on this article the definition of 'historic episcopate' must be left open. 
::Thirdly, on SydAngs - I don't think Bo has read my comments above (under Catholicism) yet, where I pointed out the misunderstanding of the article linked to. I think the article basically proves my point that parts of the Anglican church interpret 'historic epicopate' in a way other than apostolic succession, along with English Reformers. [[User:Sbmackay|Sbmackay]] ([[User talk:Sbmackay|talk]]) 04:56, 21 June 2010 (UTC)

::: Some interesting points there Sbmackay; however: 
::: - it isn't good Wikpedia practice to place 'unreferenced' tags into an article without doing something further about it; if you feel that an interpretative statement requires a reference to support it, then you should supply one youself. It may be that the references you find support a different interpretation (or a rephrased interpretation), then you should raise the matter on this discussion page. Many editors regard multiple scattering of citation tags as hostile.
::: - the historic circumstances by which the apostolic succession came to be preserved in the Church of England at the Elizebethan settlement remain unclear (David Edwards discusses the point at some length). Most likely the queen and her reformed divines were originally primarily interested in maintaining undisputed legal succession - i.e. ensuring that the bishops and priests of the English church had undisputed title to the secular and spiritual rights and interests of their religioius corporations. But by the end of Elizabeth's reign the explicit issue of whether the consecration of Arhbishop Parker had validly transmitted the apostolic succession had become very much a live controversy between Anglican and Catholic apologists. Hooker has to be read in this context, but also Lancelot Andrewes and other proponents of a 'high' episcopal ecclesiology. What is undisputed, so far as I am aware, is that Anglican committment to the absolute neccessity of the apostolic succession in conferring valid orders has never and nowhere subsequently wavered; and consequently the foundation narrative of almost all Anglican churches can only be understood in these terms (the United States and Canada being the most obvious examples). I do not then see any objection to understnding apostolic succession as 'foundational' to Anglican churches (other than the the exceptional instance of C of E). 
::: - I am not equipped to enter into andy debate about the Diocese of Sydney. However, saying &quot;it is done in Sydney&quot; is not the same as &quot;It is done in parts of the Anglican church&quot;. [[User:TomHennell|TomHennell]] ([[User talk:TomHennell|talk]]) 09:50, 21 June 2010 (UTC)

::::In response:
::::- I have searched for references for some of the more disputable claims, but am yet to find anything. The fact is that many sections of the article have many disputable unreferenced claims. Many sections have no references at all. The verifiability policy is clear that any material that is challenged, or likely to be challenged should be referenced. The amount of debate on this page is evidence enough that at least some citation tags are warranted. And this needs to be assessed on the basis of the objective quality of the article, rather than the implied motivations of the person placing tags.
::::- &quot;committment to the absolute neccessity of the apostolic succession in conferring valid orders has never and nowhere subsequently wavered&quot;. This is the particular claim that I have yet to see any verification of. The reason it seems so unlikely to me is that it would make it impossible to be Protestant! And yet the Anglican church has historically been remarkably Protestant. I have a feeling there is quite a bit of Nth American bias in this article. For example, under 'specific Anglican beliefs': ''&quot;Following the passing of the 1604 Canons, all Anglican clergy had to formally subscribe to the Articles. Today, however, the articles are no longer binding, but are seen as a historical document that has played a significant role in the shaping of Anglican identity.'' Now, that is true of North America, but by no means the whole Communion. I come from NZ and all clergy there still promise to uphold the Articles. And that's just one little Antipodean tip of the iceberg! [[User:Sbmackay|Sbmackay]] ([[User talk:Sbmackay|talk]]) 10:39, 21 June 2010 (UTC)

::::: Sbmackay, I think you will find the proceedings of the Lambeth Conferences helpful on these matters - especially 1948 (in respect of the absolute necessity of the apostolic succession in conferring valid priestly orders); and 1968 (on the apostolic succession again, and on the 39 articles).  Much of the discussion in these occasions focussed around the [[Church of South India]], the [[Old Catholic]] church, and the status of Florence [[Li Tim-Oi]]. There is an very wide degree of variation in practice and doctrine across the Anglican communion, but no Anglican church accepts as valid, priestly orders that have not been episcopally conferred in accordance with the apostolic succession.  This is so exceptional a position amongst churches of the Reformation tradition, that it has to be stated unequivocally in the article. As you point out, many Anglican's consider themselves to be Protestant, but many (perhaps most) Protestants do not, for exactly this reason.  As to the matter of Nth American bias, I would agree with you - and would welcome clarification of matters that are stated as being more widely applicable than is actually the case. [[User:TomHennell|TomHennell]] ([[User talk:TomHennell|talk]]) 12:20, 21 June 2010 (UTC)

:::: I have managed to track down [[John Pearson (bishop)|Bishop John Pearson]]'s classic statement of Anglican belief with reference to the apostolic succession;

:::::&quot;Christ said to His Apostles, As My Father hath sent Me, even so send I you. As He had from the Father a command to teach the people, and to depute ministers who were needed for this duty and furnished with the necessary authority, so likewise the Apostles had the same office and command, with the same power of choosing ministers, and so on in a continuous succession to the end of the world. Accordingly, an Apostle is an extraordinary Bishop, and a Bishop an ordinary Apostle ; and thus the Episcopate was founded by Christ in the persons of the Apostles, and, as existing in the persons of their successors, it is derived from the Apostles.

:::: It is arguable that Pearson's statement was over-claiming even in the Restoration church; but his general position is the basis for most discussions at an official level over the past 100 years.  The basic elements of the doctrine comprise these three assertions; that valid priestly and episcopal orders cqn only be conferred through consecration by bishops themselves validly consecrated in line of succession from the apostolic chuch; that this consecration embodies Christ's final charge to his followers to go out into all the world and make disciples of the nations; and that the handing on of this charge from the apostles to the episcopate also involved a handing on of some aspects of apostolic authority. It is my contention that the first of Pearson's assertion is indeed universally characteristic of modern day Anglicanism in all its forms.  Pearson's second assertion is now probably only acccepted in a more indirect form.  The third is perhaps the most controversial, in that Pearson explicitly rejects the Catholic doctine of bishops as being successors to the full range of apostolic authority. But if episcopal authority is a substantially limited form of apostolic authority, then the qustion is begged; which apostolic authority is extraordinary and 'personal' and hence dies with them; and which is continued in the ordinary office of a bishop.  [[User:TomHennell|TomHennell]] ([[User talk:TomHennell|talk]]) 00:36, 22 June 2010 (UTC)     



{{od}} The Church of England itself no longer requires direct subscription to the 39 Atricles, clergy now swear to &quot;uphold the historic formularies of the Church of England&quot; or somethign along those lines.  [[User:David Underdown|David Underdown]] ([[User talk:David Underdown|talk]]) 12:53, 21 June 2010 (UTC)

:...which includes the 39 articles. Clearly. Indirect/direct, they're still required to swear to uphold them. Likewise Australia:
::&quot;The Anglican Church of Australia, being an Apostolic Church, receives and retains the Catholic Faith, which is grounded in Holy Scripture and expressed in the Creed, and within its own history, in the Thirty-nine Articles, in the Book of Common Prayer and in the Ordering of Bishops, Priests and Deacons.&quot; 

:I really don't have a stamina for these Lambeth-like conversations, but I may come back to this at some stage.[[User:Sbmackay|Sbmackay]] ([[User talk:Sbmackay|talk]]) 13:18, 21 June 2010 (UTC)

::Sure, but if you look at why the change was made, you'll see that the clear intent was to &quot;downgrade&quot; the importance of the articles.  [[User:David Underdown|David Underdown]] ([[User talk:David Underdown|talk]]) 13:48, 21 June 2010 (UTC)

:::Well maybe the article should say that then? Sure there may be subtleties to the oath, but as it stands the article is simply not accurate. 'In the CofE clergy must swear to uphold the historic formularies, which includes the 39 articles'.
:::Another example of dubious claims - &quot;it is a canonical requirement to use fermented wine for the Communion&quot;. That may be a Lambeth declaration, and it may be true of Nth America, but that's not equivalent to canonical law everywhere. [[User:Sbmackay|Sbmackay]] ([[User talk:Sbmackay|talk]]) 23:38, 21 June 2010 (UTC)

::::I've changed the wording.  If you can offer ''actual citations'' for your doubts, then the general pattern will have to do.  Likewise, if you can offer an example of a province where it is ''not'' a canonical requirement to use wine, complete with citation, then we can change it to something like &quot;in most provinces&quot; or some such.  [[User:Tb|Tb]] ([[User talk:Tb|talk]]) 23:55, 21 June 2010 (UTC)

{{od}} I've foudn the book I was thinking of (I think it was TomHennell who dug it out once before), [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=yIigL5EI260C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=anglican+identity&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=HJIgTN6TM8XuOfeE9EE&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CC8Q6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false ''Aspects of anglican Identity''] by Colin Podmore.  It's not completely availble in Google books but Chapter 4, which covers the position of the 39 Articles, and the declaration of assent which CofE clergy are now required to make is available in full.  As I recall from my mother's ordination as deacon a couple of year's ago, the [[Church in Wales]] position is similar.  [[User:David Underdown|David Underdown]] ([[User talk:David Underdown|talk]]) 10:50, 22 June 2010 (UTC)

== Use of this Article in a published book ==

A 2008 version of this article has been published as a book [http://books.google.com.au/books?id=gC93bLKtMqMC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Church+Schism+%26+Corruption&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=ViUfTOygC4ugkQXtrO2fCw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCcQ6AEwAA Church Schism &amp; Corruption] by Achim Nkosi Maseko, and is now available on Google Books and lulu publishers. The same author has a blog where the link to his published book is given as christianunitycampaign.blogspot.com. Also on the 'Causes' page of facebook the same author, Achim Nkosi Maseko has provided a link to the same book. Apparently, the book in question has been republished into six seperate books from Book 1 to Book 6. All these books are downloadable for free from internet

A 'Press Release' from the author himself ([http://www.prlog.org/10138100-church-schism-corruption-recently-published-book-downloadable-from-lulucomcontent3125198.html found here]) says:

:''Very astounding, original, factual and revealing. Great work with extensive research combined with profound outlay of facts. This book will surely change the Christian world landscape as it provides never-been-seen facts about the evil practices in the whole Christendom.''

[[User:Sbmackay|Sbmackay]] ([[User talk:Sbmackay|talk]]) 09:16, 21 June 2010 (UTC)

== Catholics not in communion with Rome ==

The [[:Category:Catholics not in communion with Rome|category]] defined itself as follows: &lt;blockquote&gt;A list of professed Catholic groups, or persons, who identify themselves with Roman Catholicism (at least as it was since the Council of Trent) and who were (or have been) officially censured as excommunicate by Rome.&lt;/blockquote&gt;  Anglicanism obviously does not fit within this definition, as it does not identify itself with post-Tridentine Catholicism. [[User:John K|john k]] ([[User talk:John K|talk]]) 05:01, 25 August 2010 (UTC)
 
:Although Anglicanism generally understands itself as a reformed Catholic tradition its Catholicism is generally ( but not always ) pre-Tridentine in character.  The category probably requires a different definition. [[User:Afterwriting|Afterwriting]] ([[User talk:Afterwriting|talk]]) 17:42, 26 August 2010 (UTC)
::Any definition that includes Anglicanism would also have to include a whole ton of churches that are not normally seen or described as Catholic - at the very least, the Eastern Orthodox and the Scandinavian Lutheran churches, but probably also all the other Lutheran and Reformed denominations, and maybe to all Nicene denominations.  The current definition is the one which was created five years ago when the category was created, and has never been disputed until now. Anglicanism doesn't belong. [[User:John K|john k]] ([[User talk:John K|talk]]) 18:32, 26 August 2010 (UTC)

== Catholic ==

There has been a long discussion at [[Catholic Church]] about the name of the article and the &quot;Roman&quot; has been removed.  Given that Catholic is also the common name the use of Roman in the lede is unnecessary.  I realise that the anglo-catholic group has a position here but I think it is enough that the &quot;half way&quot; concept is there (despite the 39 articles).  In general we need a lot more citations in the article to support some of the positions taken.   --[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  09:34, 16 September 2010 (UTC)

:the idea of the Catholic Church means something else within Anglicanism, and the (Roman) Catholic Church itself recognises this see [[Anglican Roman Catholic International Commission]].  We need to be absolutely clear which usage is intended at any given point in the article.  The mediation on the article name agreed that it was entirely about the name fo the article, and not usage elswhere, and that other articles should not have Roman added or removed without discussion.  [[User:David Underdown|David Underdown]] ([[User talk:David Underdown|talk]]) 09:39, 16 September 2010 (UTC)

::Firstly, the other article intentionally states that it is *also&quot; known as the &quot;Roman Catholic Church&quot; - so it has not been removed as a name of that church. Secondly, as mentioned above, the mediation on that article's name agreed that the use of the name of &quot;Catholic Church&quot; *only* applied to that particular article and was not to used as a reason for altering other articles.  This agreement, however, has been blatantly ignored by some editors involved in that mediation ( including, incredibly, the so-called &quot;mediator&quot; ). My own view is that in articles about other churches is that it is usually more appropriate to use &quot;Roman Catholic Church&quot; and that is generally already the case in such articles. [[User:Afterwriting|Afterwriting]] ([[User talk:Afterwriting|talk]]) 10:43, 16 September 2010 (UTC)

:::I realise that some people are unhappy with that mediation but thats life on wikipedia.  Also common name applies here,  People normally use &quot;Catholic&quot; unless they are making a religious point.  In the context of the sentence it is very clear what it means, there is no ambiguity so the common name, and the article name should be used.  Its Wiki-lawyering to say the name change does not extend, although any disputed change needs discussion.  --[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  10:57, 16 September 2010 (UTC)

::::Quite - there is a distinction here, Catholicism with regards to Anglicanism has a particular meaning, and it is not Roman Catholicism, and while it may appear clear to you in one place, it is confusing to use terms in different ways within the same article.  You have not addressed the fact that the official dialogue between the two Churches has always included Roman its name for these very reasons.  The issue of Anglicans regarding themselves as &quot;Catholic and Reformed&quot; (or sometimes &quot;Catholic, but Reformed&quot;), is an essential part of the Anglican identity as it is today, see http://www.cofe.anglican.org/about/history/ and http://www.ireland.anglican.org/index.php?do=about - that is thewhole point of the idea of the ''via media'', between Protestant and Roman Catholic, yes, and in this instance the difference between the Anglican understanding of Catholicity and that of the Roman Catholic Church is vital, take the &quot;Roman out and it destroys the meaning entirely.  [[User:David Underdown|David Underdown]] ([[User talk:David Underdown|talk]]) 11:23, 16 September 2010 (UTC)
:::::Well there is also a difference between the Orthodox understanding of Catholicism and that of Rome.  The argument that &quot;Roman&quot; has been used in official dialogue is more convincing, but would be better not in a primary source.  My understanding is that &quot;Catholic but Reformed&quot; is an important part of the identity of a part of the Anglican communion but not all of it, or lease not without the large &quot;C&quot; becoming a small &quot;c&quot;. --[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  11:37, 16 September 2010 (UTC)
::::::Then your understanding is incorrect. This is a mainstream definition of Anglicanism and is not just that of a a &quot;part&quot;. And arguments about &quot;C&quot; and &quot;c&quot; use are essentially meaningless except in the minds of those who want to falsely assert that &quot;Catholic&quot; only validly refers to Roman Catholicism. [[User:Afterwriting|Afterwriting]] ([[User talk:Afterwriting|talk]]) 11:59, 16 September 2010 (UTC)
:::::::If its a mainstream definition you should have no difficulty in finding a third party source (not a self-description) which confirms it.  You should also stop making assumptions about the motives of other editors and address the content issue as well as showing some respect for [[WP:BRD]] --[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  12:31, 16 September 2010 (UTC)

== &quot;Catholic and Reformed&quot; ==

The term &quot;Catholic and Reformed&quot; has long been used as a self-description within Anglicanism.  Just because one editor is not familiar with this is no excuse to simply remove it.  If you want a reference then add a citation required tag - but don't simply remove it at the first opportunity. [[User:Afterwriting|Afterwriting]] ([[User talk:Afterwriting|talk]]) 11:14, 16 September 2010 (UTC)
:I'm fully entitled to remove newly inserted material per [[WP:BRD]].  You also need a third party source, self=description is more problematic. --[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  11:33, 16 September 2010 (UTC)
::Then on this basis you won't object if I begin removing all references in articles about the Roman Catholic Church which come from official Roman Catholic sources as they aren't &quot;third party&quot; either.  The reason why the Roman Catholic Church is usually called the &quot;Catholic Church&quot; is on the basis of its &quot;self-definition&quot;.  Others don't accept this definition.  [[User:Afterwriting|Afterwriting]] ([[User talk:Afterwriting|talk]]) 12:04, 16 September 2010 (UTC)
:::If new text is inserted on any article then another editor can revert it and request discussion.  Your source has been challenged and you need to discuss it.   You also need to address the issue on this page.  The name of Catholic Church has been determined by wikipedia process, you may not like that and you can also challenge it as nothing is fixed.  In the meantime you need to come up with a third party reference to support a statement that Anglicanism is both Catholic &amp; Reformed, and you need to address the points I made above in response to another editor.  --[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  12:24, 16 September 2010 (UTC)
:::::::In case you haven't noticed - which you obviously haven't - I actually started this discussion.  So you can stop the crap about my &quot;need to discuss it&quot;.  Your arguments so far demonstrate your highly biased POV. If you do a Google search on &quot;Catholic and Reformed&quot; + &quot;Anglican&quot; you can find numerous articles which support this claim about Anglican self-definition.  So stop your disruptive edit warring and insisting on your prejudiced understanding of what &quot;Catholic&quot; means.  [[User:Afterwriting|Afterwriting]] ([[User talk:Afterwriting|talk]]) 13:39, 16 September 2010 (UTC)
::::::::A discussion means reaching agreement, not simply making a statement here and then reinserting your opinion before agreement is reached.  --[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  14:00, 16 September 2010 (UTC)

::::How &quot;third-party&quot; does something have to be? http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=eM8-AAAAIAAJ&amp;q=%22catholic+and+reformed%22&amp;dq=%22catholic+and+reformed%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=5RmSTLHYHpSmOKO3tMsH&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CDcQ6AEwAQ is published by SPCK, which is of course an Anglican Missionary society.  As Anglicanus says, hos much of the Catholic Church article depends on publications of the church, or of theologians who belong to it?  Try also [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=8Pdx3HQ96zsC&amp;pg=PA340&amp;dq=%22catholic+and+reformed%22+anglican&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=qxqSTI7vKISNOKC5pPwH&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CDIQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=%22catholic%20and%20reformed%22%20anglican&amp;f=false] [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=ihjfPxvqYJwC&amp;pg=PA279&amp;dq=%22catholic+and+reformed%22+anglican&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=qxqSTI7vKISNOKC5pPwH&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6&amp;ved=0CEQQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=%22catholic%20and%20reformed%22%20anglican&amp;f=false], [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=I2ABbvK_k_UC&amp;pg=PA13&amp;dq=%22catholic+and+reformed%22+anglican&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=qxqSTI7vKISNOKC5pPwH&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=7&amp;ved=0CEkQ6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=%22catholic%20and%20reformed%22%20anglican&amp;f=false], [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=sCY4sAjTGIYC&amp;pg=PA269&amp;dq=%22catholic+and+reformed%22+anglican&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=SRuSTOAczIE4spawxgc&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCoQ6AEwADgK], [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=dpjtH9MxW_8C&amp;pg=PA31&amp;dq=%22catholic+and+reformed%22+anglican&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=SRuSTOAczIE4spawxgc&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwATgK], [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=7cw9AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA96&amp;dq=%22catholic+and+reformed%22+anglican&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=SRuSTOAczIE4spawxgc&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CDwQ6AEwAzgK], [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=PhCh7ZgMOhAC&amp;pg=PA39&amp;dq=%22catholic+and+reformed%22+anglican&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=khuSTNmeJYGROLy-7JkI&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CC8Q6AEwATgU], [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=TxP5Ww_JO64C&amp;pg=PA106&amp;dq=%22catholic+and+reformed%22+anglican&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=khuSTNmeJYGROLy-7JkI&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CDQQ6AEwAjgU] or jsut browse these [http://www.google.co.uk/search?hl=en&amp;tbo=1&amp;tbs=bks%3A1&amp;q=%22catholic+and+reformed%22+anglican&amp;aq=f&amp;aqi=&amp;aql=&amp;oq=&amp;gs_rfai= Google book results] to see what a commonplace it is.  [[User:David Underdown|David Underdown]] ([[User talk:David Underdown|talk]]) 13:30, 16 September 2010 (UTC)
:::::And you seem to be missing the point that this is a matter of self-identity, it was Anglicanism understands itself to be, for which surely the most authoritative source are statements of the Church itself of its position, just as the Catechism etc are used to show how the (Roman) Catholic Church describes itself.  [[User:David Underdown|David Underdown]] ([[User talk:David Underdown|talk]]) 13:40, 16 September 2010 (UTC)
::::::I'm not challenging the phrase is in use, and is favored by some but the nature of the two words &quot;Catholic&quot; and &quot;Reformed&quot; is (as stated in the body of the article) not agreed between Churches within the communion or within groups within those Churches.  Something supported several of the references above support.  Its not just that phrase but a large part of the text which comes before it which leaves the wrong impression.  Reading the whole thing again (as relief from my &quot;abusive and bullying behaviour&quot;) it seems to me that a lot of material in the lede needs to be in the main body and the lede itself drastically shortened.  Such an action would allow the wider context of the phrase to be properly explained and the lede in turn to summarise the article rather than introduce new material.  Oh, and I am not missing the point on self-identity, the point is that third party sources are more reliable and would normally be found to support primary assertions  --[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  14:13, 16 September 2010 (UTC)
:::::::Different parts of Anglicanism may understand the precise meaning of the phrase differently, but I'd been interested to see any evidence of that aspect being rejected entirely (though if the Sydney Anglicans did I wouldn't be entirely surprised, they are certainly much keener on the Reformed aspect).  All I am asking is that the same standards be applied to this page as they have been to the catholic Church page, wehre the self-identity is larlgely expressed in terms of official documents and/or recognised theologians.  Sauce for the goose is sauce for the gander, and I'm afraid I odn't personally own a huge theological library.  I'd not dispute that this article is weak on sourcing overall, there's been no particualr push to tidy it up, and I don't feel I have the resources to embark on it.  But it is fundamental to an understanding of Anglicanism that its understanding of Catholicism is not co-terminus with Roman Catholicism, which is a term used by the Catholic Church as has been repeatedly demostrated, and in particular in its own dialogue with Anglicanism.  I think at this point we would all benefit from input from others if possible, rather than the three of us going round and round.  [[User:David Underdown|David Underdown]] ([[User talk:David Underdown|talk]]) 14:33, 16 September 2010 (UTC)
::::::::Well at the moment two of us are discussing and a third is throwing out insults; but it does need some more editors involved.  I'm not opposed to using authoritative Anglican sources, but that is not the same thing as a web site.  I have a reasonable theological library but not much on the history of the Church which is what is needed here.  I am pretty sure that there has been a previous debate elsewhere on Wikipedia which established that Anglicanism is a Protestant religion so this article is already at variance with agreed text elsewhere.  In effect we should be saying that the Anglican Church is a part of the Protestant tradition, but has maintained aspects of catholic belief and practice (as did the Lutherans) and then reference the Anglo-Catholic movement of the 19thC.   Its also clear that there are different claims from within the Anglo-catholic wing and increasingly more strident claims to contrary from the evangelical wings, although those are as much against liberals as they are against Anglo-Catholics.  At the moment the article is (as you say) very badly referenced and also (my opinion) orientated towards the Anglo-Catholic perspective.  That relates to the content and the lede.  --[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  14:45, 16 September 2010 (UTC)
::::::::::You are the one constantly &quot;throwing out insults&quot; and continuing to make blatantly hypocritical comments at every opportunity.  I have already asked you to cease this but you continue to persist in your uncivil behaviour.  It is an established principle for articles that an entity's own self-understanding should be respected - *not* the biased assessment of others.  In this case it is the mainstream view within Anglicanism that it is both Catholic and Reformed.  This is *not* just the view within Anglo-Catholicism and you and other editors persist in the nonsense that this is only an Anglo-Catholic view and assess what Anglicanism means by &quot;Catholicism&quot; by reference to Anglo-Catholic and Roman Catholic understandings of the term.  Whatever Roman Catholics or others may think of Anglicanism's &quot;Catholicism&quot; or &quot;Protestantism&quot; is essentially irrelevant.  The simple fact is that Anglicanism generally defines itself as being &quot;Catholic and Reformed&quot;. It also does *not* generally define itself as &quot;Protestant&quot; but if you want to find references that support that description then you can find them - as you can also find just as many  references which decsribe Anglicanism as a &quot;Catholic&quot; tradition. [[User:Afterwriting|Afterwriting]] ([[User talk:Afterwriting|talk]]) 15:37, 16 September 2010 (UTC)   
:::::::::::You must be using some new definition of &quot;insult&quot; which is unfamiliar to me, perhaps you would point me to the specific language which concerns you?  Your own is pretty self-evident. You might also want to spend some time reading the actual arguments rather than engaging in intemperate responses and edit summaries.  Your language and your edit warring without engagement place you on the verge of behaviour which would justify a formal complaint.  Please restrain yourself--[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  15:43, 16 September 2010 (UTC)
::::::::::::As I've already said on my talk page, your capacity for blatantly dishonest and hypocritical comments is quite amazing.  Your own persistent uncivil and bullying behaviour has already put you well over the verge of what justifies a formal complaint.  So - once again - please restrain yourself. [[User:Afterwriting|Afterwriting]] ([[User talk:Afterwriting|talk]]) 16:04, 16 September 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::::::You've said several things, but you have failed to give an example, parroting statements back may seem clever to you, but its not a way of avoiding a request to justify your comments.  --[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  16:10, 16 September 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::Well as the rest of the talk page shows, you are not the first to express the opinion that the presentation might favour Anglo-Catholic views.  At times it would have been uncontroversial to describe Anglicanism as being purely Protestant, but I'm not sure it's an accurate description of where it stands today, and you will probably find almost as many shades of opinion as there are Anglicans.  [[User:David Underdown|David Underdown]] ([[User talk:David Underdown|talk]]) 14:55, 16 September 2010 (UTC)
{{od}} Happy to agree that there are many shades of opinion.  I doubt by the way that anything is purely Protestant, any dissenting group will have various degrees of dissent.  The point is that they dissent/schism whatever.  The general debate on classification was [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Christianity/Archive_54#Denominations here] that that placed Anglicanism within the Protestant tradition based on sources so we probably need to go that way here.  That then makes it easier to point to the Anglo-Catholic tradition (for which I have much respect having been a part of it many years ago in The Church in Wales).  --[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  14:59, 16 September 2010 (UTC)
:Snowded's suggestions seem reasonable here, but of course I've always found the Anglo-Catholic bias of Anglicanism articles problematic.  In terms of use of &quot;Catholic&quot; by Anglicans, I would doubt that any Anglicans would explicitly reject that.  But low church Anglicans presumably view &quot;Catholic&quot; in the same sense that all other protestants do: &quot;one Holy Catholic Church&quot; - that the church is universal.  The particular Anglo-Catholic sense of the term - that it refers to the apostolic succession of bishops - is, so far as I know, wholly idiosyncratic.  &quot;Catholic&quot; should not be used in that sense in wikipedia without considerable explanation and context, and only when it can be explained that this is an Anglo-Catholic concept. [[User:John K|john k]] ([[User talk:John K|talk]]) 15:12, 16 September 2010 (UTC)
::It is *not* just an &quot;Anglo-Catholic&quot; concept at all - it has been Anglicanism's constant self-understanding since the English Reformation that it is both a &quot;Catholic&quot; and a &quot;Reformed&quot; church tradition.  The notion that this is somehow an Anglo-Catholic understanding is false - both historically and theologically. [[User:Afterwriting|Afterwriting]] ([[User talk:Afterwriting|talk]]) 15:52, 16 September 2010 (UTC)   
:::I'm not so sure of that.  I think the phrase doesn't really come into play until the 18thC (open to seeing a citation that says otherwise).  I don't think you would see it in Cranmer and his followers, look at his support of Melanchthon.  This needs some third party sources badly --[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  16:10, 16 September 2010 (UTC)
::::I seem to recall some of this conception going back to Laud.  But Laud is not a particular hero of low church Anglicans, as far as I know. Laud also was a failure - his vision of the CoE was defeated, latitudinarians owned the eighteenth century, and the Oxford Movement, while drawing on Laudian ideas, was a new beast that emerged in the nineteenth century.  At any rate, I did not say that the idea that the Church of England is &quot;Catholic&quot; is purely Anglo-Catholic.  I said that the meaning of Catholic as &quot;apostolic succession of bishops&quot; is purely Anglo-Catholic.  Cranmer and Parker would have viewed themselves as &quot;Catholic,&quot; but in the same sense that Luther and Calvin did - as believers in a single universal church of all believers, going back to the time of the early church fathers. [[User:John K|john k]] ([[User talk:John K|talk]]) 16:35, 16 September 2010 (UTC)
:::::Which makes the point that the main body of the article needs to provide a richer context to the evolving use of language here.  I need to hunt down some histories.  --[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  16:40, 16 September 2010 (UTC)

:Snowded, I don't actually see a huge use of sources in that discussion - and whether it's really fair to claim consensus on the small number of editors involved in that discussion.  [[User:David Underdown|David Underdown]] ([[User talk:David Underdown|talk]]) 15:23, 16 September 2010 (UTC)

::I'd have to go back over it in detail, but there was (and this from memory) a clear and authoritative history article that made the division.  --[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  15:33, 16 September 2010 (UTC)

:::From a preliminary reading of the above, plus the article and the source in question, I would say that this is something that needs additional sourcing. Clearly the C of E is a valuable source about itself and can be cited; but it would also be useful to have one or two additional &quot;views&quot; or &quot;ways of seeing&quot; this, with other quality sources. As a former C of E member, I also frequently heard the phrase &quot;both Catholic and Reformed&quot;, but equally I suspect there are many quality sources that will describe anglicanism as being essentially Protestant in nature and also distinct from Catholicism. So it needs to be approached with some care and a &quot;one source&quot; view isn't quite up to the mark. I don't think the cite tag was quite right there though, it's more a case of ensuring NPOV across the whole introduction including that statement. [[User:Jamesinderbyshire|Jamesinderbyshire]] ([[User talk:Jamesinderbyshire|talk]]) 16:58, 16 September 2010 (UTC)
::::The cite tag was an alternative to edit waring, I assumed other editors would respect [[WP:BRD]]  and didn't want to go past 2RR, not perfect but better than a revert battle.  In practice I think we need to tag the whole article or at least the lede then get to work on some properly sourced material.  As you say single sources, especially those which are &quot;internal&quot; are not really good enough.--[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  17:04, 16 September 2010 (UTC)

== Moving forwards ==

I added two tags to the article:  the need for a general clean up and also the complete lack of citations in many sections
There are some immediate issues that need to be resolved, for example the contradiction in the lede with [[Christianity]] over the major divisions of Christianity.  There are various ways of dealing with that, one of which is not to make any such claim but simply talk about its origins (at which point Catholic and Reformed makes sense with a 17C ref).  I pinged an old contact on the SCM Press (I was briefly a director back in the 70s/80s) and have a couple of books en route and when I get them will attempt some changes.  Best overall to discuss what needs to be done first however.  Comments?  --[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  08:46, 18 September 2010 (UTC)
:Just to note, that I plan to do some work on this over Christmas now I have the text books at home.  --[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  08:39, 14 December 2010 (UTC)

== Principal traditions ==

The lede phrase &quot;Anglicanism forms one of the principal traditions of Christianity&quot; is at odds with the much better sourced statements at [[Christianity]] which correctly (given the 39 articles) place it in the Protestant tradition all be it with some qualifications as nothing is neat and tidy in this area.   I suggest we change this to say something along the lines of Anglicanism is within the Protestant tradition, but had retained some beliefs and practices from Catholicism or something similar.  --[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  08:38, 14 December 2010 (UTC)

: I agree that the lede is unsatisfactory; but categorising Anglcanism as &quot;within the Protestant tradition&quot;, is (in my view) something that can only be done by robbing the term 'Protestant' of its positive character. Protestants (in a simplified catetgorisation) must believe in justifcation by faith, the priesthood of all believers, and the sole authority of scripture.  Anglicans may claim to hold all three doctrines; but most Protestants would consider the Anglican doctrines of the apostolic succession of episcopacy, the liberal interpretqtion of scripture, and of the authority of the ecumenical councils and creeds, to be incompatible with a strict applicaiton of these three doctrines. Anglicans often describe themselves as 'both Protestant and Catholic'; but it is plain that neither strict Catholics, nor strict Protestans would accept them as co-religionists without strong reservations.  In my view, it is much better to describe Anglicanism as &quot;originating within the traditon of Reformed Protestantism&quot;.  The idea that all Christianity could be divided into Protestant, Catholic and Orthodox camps, is fundamentally a construct of late 19th century Euro-centric [[Orientalism]], and should be abandoned as lacking any real content in the current context. [[User:TomHennell|TomHennell]] ([[User talk:TomHennell|talk]]) 10:51, 14 December 2010 (UTC)

::I agree its problematic and I understand the Protestant position here and the conflict in the Anglican Church between traditional and liberal, protestant and anglo-catholic further illustrates it.  Not so sure I agree with you on the &quot;construct&quot; argument.  We do have the two great schisms  although the Protestant one is messy and extended.  Whatever it is clear that they are not one of the major divisions.  I like your idea of originating within the traditon of Reformed Protestantism&quot; however.  If no one else contributes I'll try and edit along those lines--[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  11:13, 14 December 2010 (UTC)

:::  I assume you meant to say three great schisms:  Chalcedonian/Mononphysite; Greek/Latin; Catholic/Reformed.  Strictly, you might add a fourth; Trinitarian/non-Trinitarian.  My point is that the label 'Protestant' has no constant understanding in this schema; in the sixteenth century it broadly denoted Lutheranism, i.e. those Trinitarian reformed traditions that did not acknowledge the leadership of Geneva.  In the 17th century - in the context of the Thirty Years War - it came to mean something like 'Reformed and Lutheran together'.  In the early 18th century the UK parlaiment adopted a definition broadly equivalent to &quot;Established reformed non-Catholic Christianity&quot; (but this really was a construct, since neither of the two specificqally churches so designated would acknowledge the validity of the other).  In the nineteenth century it came to mean something like 'Western non-Catholic Christianity' - under the influence of the American Revolution, and of the missionary movement.  The problem with all of these lables is that they are essentially negative; protetants are varioiusly those who are not; Calvinists, Catholics, Anabaptists; as the designation of the 'other' changes, so the content of 'Protestantism' changes.  I think it is better to identify Anglicanism by how it is constituted now, rather than according to historical sub-divisions and schisms. [[User:TomHennell|TomHennell]] ([[User talk:TomHennell|talk]]) 13:07, 14 December 2010 (UTC)
::::Anglicanism does not generally identify itself as being a 'Protestant' tradition so it is therefore entirely incorrect for others to claim that it is.  Also, the Roman Catholic Church itself usually makes a clear distinction between Anglicanism and Protestantism.  Anglicanism's understanding of itself is expressed in the phrase 'Catholic and Reformed' which is already in the article.  This is also sometimes expressed as 'Catholic but not Roman, Reformed but not Protestant'.  The 39 Articles do not have anywhere near the kind of doctrinal authority within Anglicanism that many in other traditions imagine they do.  Regardless of how the articles are interpreted they have very limited authority are not definitive of what constitutes Anglican doctrine.  There is no valid reason, therefore, to define Anglicanism as 'Protestant' and doing so is ignorant. [[User:Anglicanus|Anglicanus]] ([[User talk:Anglicanus|talk]]) 14:32, 14 December 2010 (UTC)
:::::There is of course a difference between how Anglicanism chooses to define itself, and how it is defined by reliable third party sources.  Those on [[Christianity]] appear to place it as Protestant.  I've heard both sides of the 39 articles argument by the way and accept that you represent one perspective.  My real problem however is not to bracket Anglicanism into a Protestant group, but I do think it is not sustainable for it to be claimed as a 4th major tradition.  I am happy with Tom's suggestion that we just define it within its historical context and current constitution.  --[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  14:53, 14 December 2010 (UTC)
::::::Then that is your POV.  And you certainly seem determined from these and previous comments to insist that Anglicanism be defined as 'Protestant' despite the fact that Anglicanism generally understands itself to be distinct from that tradition.  As a distinct tradition it cannot be correctly classified as being within the 'Protestant' tradition.  Also, as the numbers of Anglicans worldwide, I believe, place its membership third after the Roman Catholic and Orthodox traditions - and before any Protestant traditions - this would make it a major tradition within Christianity as the article correctly states. [[User:Anglicanus|Anglicanus]] ([[User talk:Anglicanus|talk]]) 15:06, 14 December 2010 (UTC)
:::::::At the moment we have a weak source here (and I would like to see the actual text) to support your position.  The stronger sources on the Christianity article do not support a statement that it is a major tradition.  Maybe you could deal with that content issue rather attempting somewhat lamely to distract  with personal comments (your user name of course has no implied POV of any type).  Tom's suggestion is a neat way of avoiding any conflict here and you have failed to comment on that.  Maybe you would?  --[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  09:09, 16 December 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::I can live with the recent edits as a compromise even though I don't necessarily agree with the reasoning behind them.  My principal objection is with your insistence that Anglicanism should be defined as Protestant.  That is clearly a POV - which you are entitled to have but not to insist on - which is in conflict with how Anglicanism is usually described, at least in academic circles.  How it is understood or described on the 'popular' level may be another matter. I am an academic theologian and, in my world at least, most Roman Catholic Catholic and Protestant theologians I know would not describe the Anglican tradition as Protestant and clearly see it as a being a largely distinct tradition formed from aspects of both Western Catholic and Reformed theology and ecclesiology. In fact it is the Protestant theologians I know who are the most definite in saying that Anglicanism isn't a Protestant tradition. As long as you refrain from insisting on your point of view that is then we can avoid conflict on this issue. [[User:Anglicanus|Anglicanus]] ([[User talk:Anglicanus|talk]]) 11:25, 17 December 2010 (UTC)
::::::::::I'm not aware that I am insisting on anything, neither have I expressed a particular POV but rather referenced the sources on [[Christianity]] which classify it as protestant.  Also the Anglican references I have found don't see it as a distinct tradition, but rather as a collection of traditions.  Individual opinions, including professional status are not really what Wikipedia is about.  Its all about the reliable sources.  If I reference a classification on another article you should not assume a POV for myself, or for that matter any other editor.  --[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  13:01, 17 December 2010 (UTC)

::::::::::::I am not just 'assuming' a POV on your part. You certainly do have a very definite POV on this issue - as well as, it seems, an attitude that your POV is the only possibly acceptable one. This comes across very clearly in your previous comments on this issue and your intention to rewrite the article to reflect them. Your appeal to the references in the article on Christianity is especially weak and unconvincing. As you should be well aware, reliable sources can be found to support all sorts of positions and viewpoints on complex issues. When there is significant disagreement about the facts or interpretation of an issue these should be addressed in a balanced and NPOV manner. You, however, seem to want to dismiss any viewpoints or reliable sources that conflict with your apparently entrenched opinions. This seems evident from your attempts above to reject the numerous reliable sources which define Anglicanism as 'Catholic and Reformed'. So I do not consider your claims that you are not insisting on anything or have not expressed a particular POV to be credible. Your own comments contradict this and the appeal to selective sources that support particular opinions is not how Wikipedia articles are meant to be developed. [[User:Anglicanus|Anglicanus]] ([[User talk:Anglicanus|talk]]) 17:20, 17 December 2010 (UTC)   

:::::::::::::You don't like disagreement do you?  Maybe you confuse disagreement with dismissal?   Consistency between articles is a valid concern and the authorities used on the Christianity article are more substantial than those which were used here.  Calling  this&quot;weak and unconvincing&quot; may give you personal satisfaction but it does not deal with the content issue raised.  If you think they are selective sources then I suggest you go to that article and challenge them.  As to Catholic and Reformed, my point stands that this is an internal description not a third party one.  I've taken that off line to research it and will return to it at some stage in the future.  That is called responsible editing.  Name calling and broad brush accusations represents a failure to follow [[WP:AGF]] and are hardly worthy of your claimed profession.  --[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  21:39, 17 December 2010 (UTC)

::::::::::: In fairness to Anglicanus here, the [[Christianity]] article is not at all satisfactory in its general categorisation of the traditions of Christianity, and the references it contains are not to leading authorities in the subject.  Furthermore, the text of that article is not consistent with the illustrative tree diagrams that supplement it (allthough, if anything, the diagrams are even less satisfactory).  Wikipedia is not at its best in very general articles (few encyclopedias are).  More authoritative works of reference (such as the Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church) state explicitly that the degree to which Anglicanism may be considered Protestant continues to be strongly disputed. 

:::::::::::::I think the diagram is dire, if you want to propose its deletion you will have my full support.  I'm also happy to agree that many protestants dispute that the Anglican Church is Protestant, and ditto for Catholics.  Maybe its more accurate to say that it has facets of the major divisions.   The SCM study guide (to take one source) avoids the whole issue by simply describing each faction and makes no pretense to say that they are integrated in any way. --[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  21:44, 17 December 2010 (UTC)

:::::::: I tend to agree with Snowded here, that Anglacanism (notwithstanding the total headcount of its constituent churches) cannot be considered a distinct 'major' tradition within Christianity overall.  I think the section on Anglican identity within the article explains why.  Some Anglicans, especially those who are Evangelical in theological orientation, certainly do see themselves as within a common 'Protestantism'; other Anglicans see themselves as essentially 'Catholic' (but currently separated from Rome); others (perhaps a majority in England at least) would deny that there is any distinctive Anglican identity, over and above the underlying shared identity of all Christians. The most recent trends in Anglican ecclesiology (Booty and Sykes) reject these 'easy' reach-me-down identities, since they imply counterpart identities for Protestnatism and Catholicism that neither of these major traditions would accept.  These theorists would say that Anglicanism is indeed distinct - and would identify that distinction in terms of an understnading of prescribed liturgy, the systematic public reading of scripture, and an apostollic ministry; all within an explicit structure of canon law. This has certainly been found to be a way by which a wide variety of Christians have been able mutually to re-examine, develop and  share their stories of faith - though whether it capable of surviving some current challenges is still moot.  What it isn't is either Catholicism (as traditionally defined in terms of communion with Rome), or Protestantism (as it has developed since the 19th century).  Paradoxically perhaps,  it is close to an application of the principle:  '[[semper reformanda]]' as found in the reformed theologies of Luther and Calvin.  [[Alister Mcgrath]] proposes that this Protestanism of Reformed Method (as distinct from the standard understanding of Protestism as a defined Confession of Faith) should be seen as the true core of the Protestant Idea (but of course McGrath is an Anglican as well as a self-defined Protestant).  In my view, if you are going to categorise Anglicanism within a tradition , it is as Reformed, not as Protestant or Catholic; but certainly not as a distinct tradition in its own right. [[User:TomHennell|TomHennell]] ([[User talk:TomHennell|talk]]) 10:54, 16 December 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::Two of the sources I have don't talk of it as a distinct tradition, but have separate chapters on Protestant and Anglo-Catholic, i.e. seeing Anglicanism as an organisational form that accommodates different traditions. --[[User:Snowded|&lt;font color=&quot;#801818&quot; face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;'''Snowded'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Snowded#top|&lt;font color=&quot;#708090&quot; face=&quot;Baskerville&quot;&gt;TALK&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;  16:36, 16 December 2010 (UTC)

I'c like to add my voice to those who think we should not describe Anglicanism as a distinct branch of Christianity. [[User:John K|john k]] ([[User talk:John K|talk]]) 02:47, 17 December 2010 (UTC)

== Ordinariates ==

Okay, do we really need to put the bit about the ordinariates? I feel that should properly go in the article on the Roman Catholic Church, as it really has no bearing on Anglicanism outside of the very small group that will be taking Rome up on the offer.  [[User:Shadowmane|Shadowmane]] ([[User talk:Shadowmane|talk]]) 05:09, 31 March 2011 (UTC)
:Yes, I think that we absolutely need to mention the Ordinariates. They are clearly making some news and surfers are quite likely to come to Wikipedia to find out more about them.  It is the type of question that I turn to Wikipedia for. They are clearly within Anglicanism, broadly defined.  Narrowly defined, they are not, but that is the debate isn't it?  What is &quot;Anglicanism&quot;?  They call themselves Anglicans. Others call them Anglican. &quot;Anglican&quot; is in the title of the Papal documents setting them up.  Not to include them would be to shirk our responsibility to be an encyclopedia. Not to mention them would be to leave readers in the dark about the debate over the definition of &quot;Anglicanism&quot;. They should also be mentioned in the article about he Roman Catholic Church as well. It is not an either-or thing.--[[User:Bruce Hall|Bruce Hall]] ([[User talk:Bruce Hall|talk]]) 02:59, 13 June 2011 (UTC)

== American vs British English? ==

Is this article going to use American or British English? The only two instances of a variance I could find would be &quot;Civilisation&quot; vs &quot;Civilization&quot; or &quot;Organisation&quot; vs &quot;Organization.&quot;

My argument would be that for a large portion of the readership of these articles, the spelling with &quot;S&quot; instead of &quot;Z&quot; looks like a spelling mistake (And most English Spell Check programs will flag them as such). We should therefore use the standard American English Spellings with Z rather than S.[[User:ReformedArsenal|ReformedArsenal]] ([[User talk:ReformedArsenal|talk]]) 17:18, 17 May 2012 (UTC)

:Well, as these aren't spelling mistakes your &quot;argument&quot; is simply erroneous and nonsense. And Wikipedia articles are not written in &quot;Standard American Spellings&quot; for the benefit of spell check programs so this is also a totally irrelevant argument.  Articles are generally written in the form of English which is most appropriate for their subject - and last time I checked Anglicanism is predominantly found in Commonwealth nations where British English is more common.  So, to answer your question, this article will continue to use British English as there is no valid reason to change it to American English.  And, for your information, the [[Catholic Church]] article is also written in British English. [[User:Afterwriting|Afterwriting]] ([[User talk:Afterwriting|talk]]) 17:32, 17 May 2012 (UTC)
:: Articles should be written in the language that is most appropriate for those reading it... otherwise every article written about a French topic should be in French. I'll get right on changing that. My argument was that most of the readers of this article speak and read American English, and therefore it should be written in American English. According to your argument we should write this in Nigerian, since the highest population of Anglicans in any country is Nigeria. This is a community encyclopedia, you don't get to lord over an article just because you feel like it. Also, I'll get right on changing the article for the Catholic Church to Latin, since English isn't the official language of Vatican City.[[User:ReformedArsenal|ReformedArsenal]] ([[User talk:ReformedArsenal|talk]]) 18:15, 17 May 2012 (UTC)
:::You don't seem to have read [[WP:ENGVAR]], and by the way there is no [[Nigerian language]]!  Assuming the article already uses one of the 2 varieties of British English, it should continue to do so until there is a clear consensus here to change (and I wouldn't bother trying to get that). Your assumption that &quot;most of the readers of this article speak and read American English&quot; is unlikely to be correct, but is anyway beside the point. [[User:Johnbod|Johnbod]] ([[User talk:Johnbod|talk]]) 18:20, 17 May 2012 (UTC)
::::I feel like adding &lt;nowiki&gt;{{cn}}&lt;/nowiki&gt; the claim that the majority of readers of this article are American English readers and speakers. Even if it were true, that is not a good argument in favour of your opinion. This is the English Wikipedia not the American English Wikipedia, so all variants of English are to be treated equally, but not mixed in its articles. That also means no Latin or Ibo articles in the English Wikipedia please. [[User:Dabbler|Dabbler]] ([[User talk:Dabbler|talk]]) 17:17, 18 May 2012 (UTC)

From [[WP:ENGVAR]]:
&quot;Strong national ties to a topic: An article on a topic that has strong ties to a particular English-speaking nation should use the English of that nation.&quot; 

I therefore rest my case. [[User:Afterwriting|Afterwriting]] ([[User talk:Afterwriting|talk]]) 18:01, 18 May 2012 (UTC)

FWIW, Afterwriting has the better grasp of WP policy on this topic and I support his position. [[User:Carl.bunderson|carl bunderson]] [[User talk:Carl.bunderson|(talk)]] [[Special:Contributions/Carl.bunderson|(contributions)]] 17:16, 21 May 2012 (UTC)

==myth of the via media and use of the word 'anglican'==

i find dubious the claim in the opening paragraph that some english, irish and american &quot;anglicans&quot; of the 17th and 18th century emphasized the via media between protestantism and roman catholicism. if this is true, the view must have been confined to a small and not very vocal minority of churchmen of this early period. it was certainly not representative. the church of england at this stage overwhelmingly, uncompromisingly (and legally) identified as protestant full stop.  with perhaps the exception of some ultra high church non-jurors in the scottish highlands, churchmen--high, low, latitudinarian, etc--would have taken exception at the suggestion that they somehow stood in the middle between geneva and rome. apologists for episcopacy and the prayer book vis-a-vis dissenters at home and continental protestants justified these on the basis that they represented a truly protestant return to primitive christianity and the gospel, not a measure of affinity with roman catholicism or continuity with pre-reformation practice...not by any stretch. anglo-catholics have to stop projecting their own claims on the church back into pre-tractarian history, when such latter-day practices as swinging incense, invoking saints, using latin or even the word &quot;mass&quot; in worship, and belief in transubstantiation were anathema to english protestant national self-consciousness and in fact illegal. the emphasis on the apostolic succession doesn't even really come in until the 19th century. 

also, there should be a section on the genealogy of the word anglican and the history of its use. except for the latinate ecclesia anglicana, one never sees use of the term 'anglican' in the 17th and 18th century literature. this is a post-tractarian neologism as far as i can tell. over and over one sees, rather, &quot;churchmen&quot; or &quot;protestant church by law established&quot; etc to designate the church of england and its adherents. if this article is to be responsibly attentive to historical context it should emphasis that both the via media concept and the very term anglican, as referring to a distinctive branch of christianity, are products of the 19th century and later.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/71.167.69.46|71.167.69.46]] ([[User talk:71.167.69.46|talk]]) 21:50, 27 September 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;</text>
      <sha1>hn30o6qx6w1gwhpkbfr3kffv5h6pplw</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
