<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Liturgy</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1315729</id>
    <revision>
      <id>489233310</id>
      <parentid>488089630</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-04-25T23:25:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>John Carter</username>
        <id>3358555</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Top priority for Religion</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3659">{{WikiProject Christianity|class=Start|importance=Top|theology-work-group=yes|theology-importance=Top}}
{{WPReligion|class=Start|importance=Top}}

The Catholic Encyclopedia is in the public domain, and a ''lot'' of information should be imported from there. [[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|('''&amp;#5839;'''&lt;/small&gt;)]] 08:44, 23 Dec 2004 (UTC)

== Richly yet responsatorily dimensional? ==

I nuked this sentence:
:&quot;They are constructed upon the responsatory rhythms established by God's own speaking and doing as seen throughout the Bible, simple yet richly and dimensionally profound.&quot;
for POV.  There may be a NPOV way of phrasing it, but I'm having a hard time with that. [[User:75th Trombone|SFT]] | [[User Talk:75th Trombone|Talk]] 03:00, 16 February 2006 (UTC)

== Add external website? ==

I think the external links of this page can be improved. The Quaker link is to a '''''non-liturgical''''' site. The Jewish Encyclopedia is from over a century ago. The Catholic Encyclopedia link is also from 1908 and hence has no concept of the major liturgical changes that have taken place during the last century - including Vatican II and the significant changes within the Roman Catholic Church. I would, hence, submit the website [http://www.liturgy.co.nz Liturgy website] for consideration as an external link. It includes [http://www.liturgy.co.nz/html/book.html Celebrating Eucharist] which, to my knowledge, is the only contemporary online &quot;ceremonial guide&quot; - a liturgical guide and explanation to contemporary theory and practice in Anglican, Roman Catholic, Lutheran, and other liturgies. --[[User:Alcuinz|Alcuinz]] 05:41, 12 August 2006 (UTC)

:As there has been no disagreement with the above statement in over a week, I am adding the website in the article. --[[User:Alcuinz|Alcuinz]] 05:10, 22 August 2006 (UTC)

==Quaker Worship==

Even unprogrammed Quaker worship has some form and it is guided by the Elders, who usually indicate the close of the Meeting for Worship by shaking hands.  Meetings for worship for business, for marriage and funerals may have a pre-agreed form and are, hopefully carried out under God's guidance, becoming liturgy. 
The WP article:
[[Religious_Society_of_Friends#Programmed_worship| Religous Society of Friends/Programmed Worship]] indicates the diversity of Quaker Worship.  
Perhaps the Liturgy article could indicate that this diversity exists, as there are signficantly more Programmed Friends than Unprogrammed.
---Vernon White 18:12, 16 October 2006 (UTC)
{{-}}


==BC &amp; Jewish synagogues==

The abbreviation &quot;BC&quot; seems inappropriate, to some degree, here. BCE (Before common era) may be better, but I've changed it to &quot;pre-christian,&quot; since the topic is clearly about a Christian topic. Oops, should I capitalize it like this: &quot;pre-Christian&quot;? On another, related note, is there another type of synagogue besides the Jewish ones? &quot;Jewish synagogue&quot; just seems redundant to me, at least in common usage it would. Rather like &quot;Jewish rabbi&quot;...
[[User:Drkeithphd|Drkeithphd]] 17:54, 1 January 2007 (UTC)

==Missing the point==
This whole article is highly misleading and misses the point: liturgy means &quot;the work of the people&quot; and should be defined with reference to a particular form of worship. Just because people have a set way of doing things does not correspond to &quot;liturgy&quot;. In other words &quot;liturgy&quot; isn't the same as &quot;ritual.&quot; Its what the community believes is achieved by the rite it engages in that sets a liturgical community off against a non-liturgical ritual. This article needs a lot of help! [[User:Hyper3|Hyper3]] ([[User talk:Hyper3|talk]]) 20:29, 26 February 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>45gsg8vu8ytr72ixexg06uw7xwjsydd</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
