<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Báb</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>208686</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518944577</id>
      <parentid>489861543</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-21T00:03:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Adding/updating {{OnThisDay}} for 2012-10-20.  Errors? [[User:AnomieBOT/shutoff/OnThisDayTagger]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15698">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Bahá'í Faith|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WPReligion|class=B|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Iran|class=B|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Biography
|living=no
|class=B
|listas=Bab
}}
{{WP1.0|class=B|category=category}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2006-10-20|oldid1=82661331|date2=2007-10-20|oldid2=165766826|date3=2008-10-20|oldid3=246328908|date4=2009-10-20|oldid4=320618684|date5=2010-10-20|oldid5=391773573|date6=2011-03-21|oldid6=420017474|date7=2011-10-20|oldid7=456591682|date8=2012-10-20|oldid8=518903207}}

{| class=&quot;infobox&quot; width=&quot;290px&quot;
|-
!align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;|[[Image:Vista-file-manager.png|50px|Archive]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Wikipedia:How to archive a talk page|Archives]]
----
|-
|[[Talk:Báb/archive1|Archive 1]] &lt;small&gt;2005-01 &amp;mdash;2007-09&lt;/small&gt;
|
|-
|}&lt;!--Template:Archivebox--&gt;

{{User:MiszaBot/config
|algo = old(30d)
|archive = User Talk:Báb/archive%(counter)d
|counter = 2
|maxarchivesize = 125K
|minthreadsleft=2
}}


==Fair use rationale for Image:Selectionfromthebab.jpg==
[[Image:Nuvola apps important.svg|70px|left]]
'''[[:Image:Selectionfromthebab.jpg]]''' is being used on this article. I notice the image page specifies that the image is being used under [[Wikipedia:Fair use|fair use]] but there is no [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline|explanation or rationale]] as to why its use in '''this''' Wikipedia article constitutes fair use. In addition to the [[Wikipedia:Image copyright tags/Fair use|boilerplate fair use template]], you must also write out on the image description page a specific explanation or rationale for why using this image in each article is consistent with [[WP:FU|fair use]].

Please go to [[:Image:Selectionfromthebab.jpg|the image description page]] and edit it to include a [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline |fair use rationale]]. Using one of the templates at [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline]] is an easy way to insure that your image is in compliance with Wikipedia policy, but remember that you must complete the template. Do not simply insert a blank template on an image page.

If there is  other fair use media, consider checking that you have specified the fair use rationale on the other images used on this page.  Note that any fair use images lacking such an explanation can be deleted one week after being tagged, as described on [[Wikipedia:Criteria for speedy deletion#Images.2FMedia|criteria for speedy deletion]]. If you have any questions please ask them at the [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions|Media copyright questions page]]. Thank you.&lt;!-- Template:Missing rationale2 --&gt;

[[User:BetacommandBot|BetacommandBot]] ([[User talk:BetacommandBot|talk]]) 07:04, 15 January 2008 (UTC)

== People removing page from category &quot;Manifestations of God in the Baha'i Faith&quot; ==

Um, why? I would normally just revert the edits and not even ask but it's happened a couple times and has been changed by a couple different users so it would seem like someone has a reason for doing this, even if they aren't putting it in their edit summary (which you ruddy well should) [[User:Peter Deer|Peter Deer]] ([[User talk:Peter Deer|talk]]) 13:59, 28 February 2008 (UTC)

:See [[Wikipedia:Categories_for_discussion/Log/2007_January_4#Category:Manifestations_of_God|this discussion]]. [[User:Cuñado|&lt;font color=&quot;#AF7817&quot;&gt;'''Cuñado'''&lt;/font&gt;]] ☼ - [[User talk:Cuñado|&lt;font size=&quot;-3&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 14:51, 28 February 2008 (UTC)

:The discussion explains nothing. It was for a category called &quot;Manifestations of God&quot;. The current category has a different name and clearly explains that it applies only to Bahai. Either the category exists or it does not. If it exists then this article belongs in it. If you don't think there should be such a category you are free to propose its deletion, but there is no more reason to remove relevant content from it while it exists than there is to remove [[Saint Peter]] from the categories &quot;Eastern Orthodox saints&quot; and &quot;Papal saints&quot;. [[User:Paul Barlow|Paul B]] ([[User talk:Paul Barlow|talk]]) 15:44, 28 February 2008 (UTC)
::Agreed. [[User:Peter Deer|Peter Deer]] ([[User talk:Peter Deer|talk]]) 16:35, 28 February 2008 (UTC)

:::Nomination is [[Wikipedia:Categories_for_discussion/Log/2008_February_29#Category:Manifestations_of_God_in_the_Bah.C3.A1.27.C3.AD_Faith|here]].  [[User:Cuñado|&lt;font color=&quot;#AF7817&quot;&gt;'''Cuñado'''&lt;/font&gt;]] ☼ - [[User talk:Cuñado|&lt;font size=&quot;-3&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 06:23, 29 February 2008 (UTC)

== Removal of Dead Link ==
Hey guys, this article is super interesting. I was going through the references, and I noticed a link takes you to an error 404 from the BBC. So, I deleted the link and added a cite tag. I've been looking for another source, but I can't find it. If you've got some time, please look it up. Otherwise unreferenced material needs to be omitted. I'll continue to search for it as well. --[[Special:Contributions/24.129.105.240|24.129.105.240]] ([[User talk:24.129.105.240|talk]]) 09:30, 14 April 2008 (UTC)
:It's been fixed.  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 12:41, 14 April 2008 (UTC)

== family ==

how come nothing is written about His mother and father? 

Father was : Siyyid Muhammad Ridá
Mother was : Fátimih Bagum  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/79.66.127.119|79.66.127.119]] ([[User talk:79.66.127.119|talk]]) 14:43, 29 November 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== edit ==

i have added a small section about his mother and father, and also about his marriage.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/86.3.88.158|86.3.88.158]] ([[User talk:86.3.88.158|talk]]) 11:49, 24 December 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Early life==
In ''Early life'' it is written :'' ... and the boy was raised by his maternal uncle[[Hájí Mirzá Siyyid 'Ali|Ḥájí Mírzá Siyyid `Alí]]'', now Ḥájí Mírzá Siyyid `Alí is linked to ''Bab'': is this link correct  or wrong??? Bab and maternal uncle seems to be the same person??? --[[User:Giorces|giorces]] ([[User talk:Giorces|talk]]) 12:23, 7 February 2009 (UTC) [http://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/Discussioni_utente:Giorces mail]
:No, for example if Joe is only notable because of Frank the page on Joe redirects to the page on Frank where it's expected that one would be able to find out more about Joe.  The same situation here and I've unlinked the name.  [[User:T0lk|T0lk]] ([[User talk:T0lk|talk]]) 12:33, 7 February 2009 (UTC)
::Absolutely correct to delete what is effectively a self-link. Thanks, [[User:MARussellPESE|MARussellPESE]] ([[User talk:MARussellPESE|talk]]) 18:16, 7 February 2009 (UTC)

== age  ==

The article says ''between when he was 15 and 20, he joined his uncle in the family business'', however many sources say that he was about 14-15. --[[User:Melaniegreyton|Melaniegreyton]] ([[User talk:Melaniegreyton|talk]]) 13:22, 15 March 2009 (UTC)
:The [[WP:SOURCES|most-reliable academic sources]] are what are trying to be used in this article.  Remember Wikipedia is not written in the Baha'i view, and must be written in a [[WP:NPOV|neutral point of view]].  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 16:17, 15 March 2009 (UTC)

There are not very many non-Bahá'í sources written about the Báb. In addition, the Báb joined his buisness on attaining the ''age of maturity'' which for boys in Islam is about 14 or 15. --[[User:Melaniegreyton|Melaniegreyton]] ([[User talk:Melaniegreyton|talk]]) 17:57, 28 March 2009 (UTC)
:Interpreting ''age of maturity'' without a secondary source is [[WP:OR|original research]], and/or putting together information from multiple sources to reach a conclusion that is not stated explicitly by any of the sources is [[WP:SYNTH|synthesis]] and also considered original research and not allowed. There are quite a few non-Baha'i sources on the life of the Bab including Amanat's Resurrection and Renewal and extensive articles in Iranica and the Encyclopedia of Islam.  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 18:05, 28 March 2009 (UTC)
''Resurrection and Renewal'' is written by a Bahá'í author  --[[User:Melaniegreyton|Melaniegreyton]] ([[User talk:Melaniegreyton|talk]]) 12:40, 29 March 2009 (UTC)
::Nope, his family is Baha'i, but he himself has significant issues with the Baha'i administration, and the House of Justice has indicated that he should removed from the Baha'i membership lists.  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 14:19, 29 March 2009 (UTC)

The Bab writes in his own writings that he was 15 when he began to work in the family buisness. &quot;till I reached fifteen years of age I lived in the land which witnessed My birth [Shíráz]. Then Thou didst enable Me to go to the seaport [Búshihr] where for five years I was engaged in trading&quot;  ''Selections From the Writings of the Báb'' pp. 181  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Lizzie1988|Lizzie1988]] ([[User talk:Lizzie1988|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Lizzie1988|contribs]]) 11:14, 15 May 2009 (UTC) --[[User:Lizzie1988|Lizzie1988]] ([[User talk:Lizzie1988|talk]]) 12:07, 15 May 2009 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
:Using primary source material without a secondary source commenting on that primary source is [[WP:OR|original research]] and not allowed.  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 12:35, 15 May 2009 (UTC)
::It seems that interpreting something from a primary source that is not from a secondary source is now allowed.  However if a primary source made a statement requiring no interpretation it is acceptable. From [[Wikipedia:OR#Primary.2C_secondary_and_tertiary_sources|WP:OR]] ''Without a secondary source, a primary source may be used only to make descriptive claims, the accuracy of which is verifiable by a reasonable, educated person without specialist knowledge.''  Regards, [[User:T0lk|T0lk]] ([[User talk:T0lk|talk]]) 14:36, 16 May 2009 (UTC)
:::No, you can only say that the primary source states something, not that it is definitive fact.  For example, you can only state that the &quot;Bab stated he was 15 when he started working&quot; not that &quot;The Bab was 15 when he started working&quot;.  These statements are quite different, and only a secondary source can be used to state the second one. Also in this case the secondary source statement would still need to remain in the article as its different than the primary source.  Furthermore, it's always better to use secondary sources: &quot;''Wikipedia articles should rely mainly on published reliable secondary sources and, to a lesser extent, on tertiary sources.''&quot;  Instead of trying to find small exceptions to the rules, stick to the best practices; use non-Baha'i academic secondary sources.  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 14:56, 16 May 2009 (UTC)

I think that if the Bab himself writes he was 15, then that makes it reliable. I do not really understand these 'sources' etc. --[[User:Lizzie1988|Lizzie1988]] ([[User talk:Lizzie1988|talk]]) 18:03, 16 May 2009 (UTC)
::No, that's not how Wikipedia works.  Please read Wikipedia's policies on [[WP:V|verifiability]], [[WP:NOR|No original research]], and [[WP:NPOV|Neutral Point of View]] as well as the guideline on [[WP:RS|reliable sources]].  Reliable sources are those publishers that have a record of fact checking.  By definition primary sources do not have fact checking, and thus that why secondary sources are needed.  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 18:36, 16 May 2009 (UTC)

==  Proclamation  ==

This section, in particular, reads as if it were written to make and emphasize certain points of faith or doctrine.  Hoping someone with a good comfort level with the subject can clean  this up. [[User:Dans tes rêves|Dans tes rêves]] ([[User talk:Dans tes rêves|talk]]) 03:36, 20 October 2010 (UTC)
:The section is completely cited with the with recent academic research, published from academic presses which are considered to be the most [[WP:RS|reliable sources]], mostly from those critics of the Baha'is.  Do you have specific sources that present any views other the ones presented, or is it just your feelings.  You'll need sources to back up your assertion that the section is not neutral.  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 12:56, 20 October 2010 (UTC)
:: Also the current section does go over the variousviewpoints; that he wad claiming mahdihood right away, that he was claiming just being a the gate to the imam, and there was confusion among the public and his believers.-- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 13:19, 20 October 2010 (UTC)
:No issue with sources; it just seems that an undue amount of time is given to demonstrating such ideas as &quot;A number of his early followers had instantly recognized his station as a messenger from God with divine authority.&quot;  This section in particular seems to argue quite a bit that the Báb is the Twelfth Imam and not just the &quot;Gate&quot; -- which may be a valid point of doctrinal discussion for Bahá'ís, but seems to be beyond the point of an entry in an encyclopedia. [[User:Dans tes rêves|Dans tes rêves]] ([[User talk:Dans tes rêves|talk]]) 14:31, 20 October 2010 (UTC)
::I don't see it as one view versus another view.  Each paragraph deals with separate points.   Looking at the section, one main paragraph is on what he himself believed his station was, as the Qa'im, then the other large paragraph deals with how his claims to the public were understood and changed.  Then the final paragraph deals with how his message was understood within his followers itself, including both those that accepted his prophet-hood  directly (the statement you quoted above) and those that understood it otherwise.  If you read both Amanat and Saiedi you will see that both actually spend quite a bit of time on each of those things, including the confusion in the public regarding his station, and what he himself believed his station to be, and actually also MacEoin spends a significant time on the subject.  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]])

== The word &quot;báb&quot; ==

Should there be a link to {{Linktext|báb}}?--[[User:Mátyás|Mátyás]] ([[User talk:Mátyás|talk]]) 12:46, 20 October 2010 (UTC)
: No because that definition is from Bengali, not Persian. The meaning is very different. [[User:Smkolins|Smkolins]] ([[User talk:Smkolins|talk]]) 20:50, 15 November 2010 (UTC)

== Shrine of the Bab ==

Hello Friends,
I also made this mention on the page for the Shrine of the Bab, but with all the publicity in the last two days with the completion of the restoration, there seems to be an important fact omitted, that is, that there are the remains of three different people interred there: The Bab, Anis his companion, and 'Abdu'l-Baha.  Does Anis have his own page and if so, is it under that title . . .I don't see one, and if his remains are co-mingled with the dust of the Bab, he really should be mentioned.--I'm Nonpartisan 17:41, 13 April 2011 (UTC)  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:I'm nonpartisan|I'm nonpartisan]] ([[User talk:I'm nonpartisan|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/I'm nonpartisan|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;</text>
      <sha1>f0qjjfq7bpqo8oyx7pxzzwbi4xs4xs0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
