<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Hellenistic religion</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>11503595</id>
    <revision>
      <id>509215365</id>
      <parentid>504308847</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-08-26T08:49:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Magioladitis</username>
        <id>1862829</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>clean up using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8309)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3953">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Greece|class=Start|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Classical Greece and Rome|class=Start|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Christianity|class=Start|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=Start|importance=Top}}
}}

== Merge ==

I am suggesting a merge of this article with [[Hellenistic civilization]]. --[[Special:Contributions/151.201.147.161|151.201.147.161]] ([[User talk:151.201.147.161|talk]]) 14:54, 8 September 2008 (UTC)

:Disagree. This subject is potentially very large--[[User:Editor2020|Editor2020]] ([[User talk:Editor2020|talk]]) 15:43, 17 November 2008 (UTC)

: Also disagree.

== Theurgy? ==

This statement seems to be absolutely false, and a simple check of other wikipedia articles shows that.

:''Theurgy was practiced widely, and these too, were a continuation from earlier times.''

Theurgy entered into the Hellenistic religion rather late, and seems to have been limited only to those within Neoplatonism. Even then, additional research shows that is was highly debated and controversial among Neoplatonic philosophers. (see Neoplatonism by R.T. Wallis) The statement really should be removed. --[[Special:Contributions/151.201.146.212|151.201.146.212]] ([[User talk:151.201.146.212|talk]]) 16:57, 30 July 2010 (UTC)
:Thanks for the heads-up. The word &quot;theurgy&quot; was added by [[Special:Contributions/62.25.109.197|User:62.25.109.197]] on the 15 July. He/she replaced the much more reasonable &quot;superstition and magic.&quot; [[User:Singinglemon|Singinglemon]] ([[User talk:Singinglemon|talk]]) 17:40, 30 July 2010 (UTC)
::I was also wondering, the article seems to want to imply there was a (almost universal) Hellenistic religion, rather than a variety of distinct religions that were Hellenistic, and pretty much independent of the Hellenic religion. The Roman religion became Hellenistic, but was very different than the actual Hellenic religion. Greco-Buddhism was a merging of the Hellenic and Buddhist religions, and even more different than the Roman was to the Hellenic religion. The article starts out with the line that there are &quot;various systems of beliefs and practices&quot;, but then goes on to talk about those individual religions monolithically. --[[Special:Contributions/151.201.146.212|151.201.146.212]] ([[User talk:151.201.146.212|talk]]) 16:40, 3 August 2010 (UTC)
:::You're quite right, this page is limited in scope as it currently stands - the textbooks cited tend to describe what was going on in Greece itself rather than further afield - and they only cover the pre-Roman era. If you want to added in some more referenced sections on the topics you mentioned, then you're more than welcome, this article needs it. [[User:Singinglemon|Singinglemon]] ([[User talk:Singinglemon|talk]]) 19:14, 3 August 2010 (UTC)
::::I'm glad you agree. Unfortunately, I have walked down the road of putting a lot of time and effort into editing a poorly written article before. After taking the time to verifying sources, making corrections, deletions, rewrites, and attempting to create an encyclopedic article with a NPOV, I then had the whole article reverted to the original and article guarded by a group who believed in protecting the romanticized notions and false representations. I'm glad the theurgy statement was corrected, but I'm sure once certain groups find out the correction was made it will become a turf battle. I'm impressed there are people who take Wikipedia seriously. I just don't have the patience, fortitude, or time to fight. --[[Special:Contributions/151.201.146.212|151.201.146.212]] ([[User talk:151.201.146.212|talk]]) 11:49, 5 August 2010 (UTC)
:&quot;Superstition and magic&quot; has its own problems, as the pair is largely a value judgment, not just a description.  I think the page on Superstition is an example of the problems in imagining these words to be neutral descriptors. [[User:ABShippee|ABS]] ([[User talk:ABShippee|talk]]) 18:52, 26 July 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>aadwkavd05nf2wvaqjp49cavcnbgaq7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
