<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Brigham Young</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>373242</id>
    <revision>
      <id>495551534</id>
      <parentid>495550350</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-02T01:51:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mormography</username>
        <id>8652668</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Succession Crisis */ Mention Of Alleged Transformation Not Removed</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16449">{{Talk header|noarchive=yes}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
 {{WikiProject Biography|living=no|class=c|listas=Young, Brigham|politician-priority=High|politician-work-group=yes}}
 {{WikiProject Brigham Young University|importance=high|class=c}}
 {{WikiProject Christianity|class=C|importance=Top}}
 {{LDSproject|class=C|importance=Top}}
 {{WikiProject Religion|class=C|importance=Top}}
 {{WikiProject United States
  |class=C|importance=Top|listas=Young, Brigham
  |UT=yes|UT-importance=Top
  |USgovernors=yes|USgovernors-importance=low
  |USOldwest=Yes|USOldwest-importance=Mid
 }}
}}
{{Not a forum|personal beliefs, nor for engaging in [[Apologetics]]/[[Polemic]]s}}
{{On this day|date1=2005-07-24|oldid1=19468211|date2=2006-07-24|oldid2=65544971|date3=2007-07-24|oldid3=146680405|date4=2008-07-24|oldid4=227635279|date5=2011-07-24|oldid5=441213479}}
{{Backwardscopy
|author = Surhone, L. M., Timpledon, M. T., &amp; Marseken, S. F.
|year = 2010
|title = Nauvoo Legion: Militia, the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, Joseph Smith, Jr., Brigham Young, Native Americans in the United States, Nauvoo, Illinois, Mormon
|org = Betascript Publishing
|comments = {{OCLC|591328904}}, ISBN 9786130358006.
|bot=LivingBot
}}
{{Archive box|search=yes|
*[[Talk:Brigham Young/Archive 1|Archive 1]]}}

== Grave ==

The location of Brigham Young's grave is wrong on this article: he's not in the [[Salt Lake City Cemetery]], he's in the Mormon Pioneer Memorial Monument (park), &lt;s&gt;aka the Brigham Young Historic Park,&lt;/s&gt; aka the Brigham Young Family (Memorial) Cemetery. 
* {{citation |url= http://www.deseretnews.com/article/705380444/Significant-sites-artifacts-often-go-unnoticed.html |title= Significant sites, artifacts, often go unnoticed |first= Aaron |last= Shill |date= 4 April 2009 |newspaper= [[Deseret News]] }}
* {{citation |url= http://archive.sltrib.com/article.php?id=10795958&amp;itype=NGPSID |title= Markers of the past |first= Janine S. |last= Creager |date= 23 October 2008 |newspaper= [[The Salt Lake Tribune]] }}
* {{citation |url= http://www.ldschurchnews.com/articles/37413/Spotlight-on-historic-sites-Brigham-Young-Cemetery-Memorial.html |title= Spotlight on historic sites: Brigham Young Cemetery, Memorial |newspaper= [[Church News]] |date= 1 April 2000}}
The address is 140 East First Avenue, SLC, which places this on First Avenue (between North Temple and South Temple), just east of State Street; the location is essentially a [[pocket park]]. [[Eliza R. Snow]] is also buried there. -- [[Special:Contributions/208.81.184.4|208.81.184.4]] ([[User talk:208.81.184.4|talk]]) 22:37, 10 October 2011 (UTC)

:For images of the park/monument/cemetery, please see [[:commons:Category:Mormon Pioneer Memorial Monument]]. -- [[Special:Contributions/208.81.184.4|208.81.184.4]] ([[User talk:208.81.184.4|talk]]) 15:22, 12 October 2011 (UTC)
::Thank you, added link here to [[Mormon Pioneer Memorial Monument]]. —'''''[[User:Eustress|Eustress]]''''' &lt;sup&gt;''[[User talk:Eustress|talk]]''&lt;/sup&gt; 19:45, 17 October 2011 (UTC)
:::Great new article! However one minor thing still needs to be fixed in the text of ''this'' semi-protected article: the text in the last sentence of the &quot;Death&quot; section still says &quot;He was buried at Salt Lake City Cemetery.&quot; -- [[Special:Contributions/208.81.184.4|208.81.184.4]] ([[User talk:208.81.184.4|talk]]) 00:07, 18 October 2011 (UTC)
::::Perhaps you should [[Wikipedia:Why create an account?|create an account]]? In the meantime, I fixed the error and added a citation. —'''''[[User:Eustress|Eustress]]''''' &lt;sup&gt;''[[User talk:Eustress|talk]]''&lt;/sup&gt; 00:56, 18 October 2011 (UTC)
:::::Some users are unable to edit via an account for various reasons, usually involving the computer they access WP on. [[User:Good Olfactory|Good Ol’factory]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Good Olfactory|(talk)]]&lt;/sup&gt; 00:56, 20 October 2011 (UTC)

== Edit request from , 21 October 2011 ==

{{tn|edit semi-protected|answered=no}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;
In the second paragraph under the section of Controversial Teachings there is a discussion of an incident between William Appleby and Brigham Young regarding Blacks in the LDS Church.  The sixth sentence is an introduction to a quote by Brigham Young from the Journal of Discourses.  The introduction to this quote indicates that in 1863 Brigham Young was recounting what he told Appleby back in 1847 at Winter Quarters.  However that is not the case; the talk given in 1863 is not related to the encounter with Appleby in the least.  And neither are any of the other twelve references Brigham Young makes regarding Blacks in the Journal of Discourses.  The quote should be deleted because it is not relevant to the incident.  However, if you insist on using it then the introduction to the quote should simply read, “In 1863 Young said this regarding Blacks…” and add one or two of the other eleven quotes that shed a clearer light on the subject.  Thank you!

&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[User:R3miguy|R3miguy]] ([[User talk:R3miguy|talk]]) 23:59, 21 October 2011 (UTC)R3miguy
:Thank you for your input. I re-evaluated the text and removed extraneous information. However, the quote in question still appears insightful. Can you propose a more complete passage that would help readers interpret the quote in the proper context? —'''''[[User:Eustress|Eustress]]''''' &lt;sup&gt;''[[User talk:Eustress|talk]]''&lt;/sup&gt; 00:39, 22 October 2011 (UTC)
::&lt;small&gt;I've removed the {{tn|edit semi-protected|answered=no}} template, for now - as it's partially done, and up for discussion. If another specific request is required, please add a new {{tn|edit semi-protected|answered=no}}. Thanks, &lt;small&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid;background:#00008B&quot;&gt;[[User:Chzz|'''&lt;span style=&quot;background:#00008B;color:white&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;Chzz&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;''']][[User talk:Chzz|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00008B;background-color:yellow;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;►&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 07:50, 22 October 2011 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;

I’m sorry; I fail to see how the quote is insightful, just inflammatory and offensive, especially in the 21st Century (though quite common for the 19th Century, when it was made). But regarding your stated point – Brigham Young – Controversial Teachings – Blacks in the Priesthood, I think there are better representative quotes of Brigham Young’s teachings in Journal of Discourse. For example, in 1866 Young said, “Why are so many of the inhabitants of the earth cursed with a sin of blackness? It comes in consequence of their fathers rejecting the power of the Holy Priesthood, and the law of God. They will go down to death. And when all the rest of the children have received their blessings in the Holy Priesthood, then that curse will be removed from the seed of Cain, and they will then come up and possess the priesthood, and receive all the blessings which we now are entitled to. The volition of the creature is free; this is a law of their existence, and the Lord cannot violate his own law; were he to do that, he would cease to be God. He has placed life and death before his children, and it is for them to choose. If they choose life, they receive the blessings of life; if they chose death, they must abide the penalty. This is a law which has always existed from all eternity, and will continue to exist throughout all the eternities to come. Every intelligent being must have the power of choice, and God brings forth the results of the acts of his creatures to promote his kingdom and subserve his purposes in the salvation and exaltation of his children. If the Lord could have his own way, he would have all the human family to enter into his church and kingdom, receive the Holy Priesthood and come into the celestial kingdom of our Father and God, by the power of their own choice.” (Journal of Discourses, 11:272). Or this one: in 1855 Young said, “The conduct of the whites towards the slaves will, in many cases, send both slave and master to hell. This statement comprises much in a few words. The blacks should be used like servants, and not like brutes, but they must serve. It is their privilege to live so as to enjoy many of the blessings which attend obedience to the first principles of the Gospel, though they are not entitled to the Priesthood.” (Journal of Discourse 2:184)
 
However, if I misunderstand you and your point is in fact to find inflammatory and offensive statements by Brigham Young then you have succeeded in finding one of many if not hundreds and keep it as it is. There is no justifying it or finding a better way to interpret such a statement.
 
And given that you recognized the change made in 1978 I am sure you are familiar with what the LDS Church leaders have said about earlier justifications and explanations about this subject: they don’t matter. We have a living Prophet to teach us what Heavenly Father would have us know and do at this time, regardless of what He may have told them to do 150 years ago.
 
Thank you for your time in considering my input for your entry  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:R3miguy|R3miguy]] ([[User talk:R3miguy|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/R3miguy|contribs]]) 12:05, 25 October 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:I think we should avoid trying to decide what we as individuals think would be an appropriate reflection of Young's speeches and teachings. A better approach for an encyclopedia to take is to consider what ''other'' sources report on in this regard. It just so happens that the quote that is included is one that is very commonly quoted in works about Young. This may indeed be because authors have searched out the most &quot;inflammatory&quot; statement they can find, but when authors have done this time and time again, it's fair for an encyclopedia to reflect that, I think. The other quotes you have included are legitimate and are interesting, but they are seldom referred to by other sources. [[User:Good Olfactory|Good Ol’factory]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Good Olfactory|(talk)]]&lt;/sup&gt; 20:59, 25 October 2011 (UTC)

== Did you know Brigham Young lived in Auburn, NY as well?  This is known fact and documented  ==

Brigham Young, worked in Auburn , NY as a Carpenter ,glazier, and painter apprentice for John C. Jeffries Woodworking shop when he turned 16. Owners of several old houses in Auburn today claim the distinction of having a “Brigham Young mantelpiece.”  Before that (1816) he worked as a &quot;chore boy&quot; for Reed and Wadsworth Farms on W. Genesee St., and worked in what was claimed &quot;the oldest asparagus bed in the county&quot; on the corner of Grover St.

Dr. Sylvester Willard wrote an extensive paragraph in his diary, expressing unrestrained jubilation on the report of the death of that &quot;libertine&quot; Brigham Young. Dr. Willard utterly despised Young.  According to Prof. Walter Long, one of the mantles in what is now the Cayuga Museum was crafted by Young.  Perhaps in the course of his work, he made an advance on one of the Willard daughters..,(my speculation) which might explain Willard's wrath.  Willard regarded himself as a &quot;humble Christian man,&quot; (as long as not too much strain was manifest on his funds) and was often forgiving of most human failings.  He further regarded his daughters a perfect examples of the fair sex.  Neither of them ever married.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/155.52.208.80|155.52.208.80]] ([[User talk:155.52.208.80|talk]]) 19:14, 23 October 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Where are the references that support this claim? Without them, there isn't much that can be done with this material. -- [[Special:Contributions/208.81.184.4|208.81.184.4]] ([[User talk:208.81.184.4|talk]]) 18:26, 24 October 2011 (UTC)

The answer is simple - You can contact the Cayuga County Museum, Auburn, NY.  Hope that helps.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/207.38.112.242|207.38.112.242]] ([[User talk:207.38.112.242|talk]]) 09:18, 27 November 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:That would not be considered a [[Wikipedia:Identifying reliable sources|reliable source]]; since information gathered this way is by definition not published, it is not considered [[Wikipedia:Verifiability|verifiable]] to Wikipedia's standards. -- [[Special:Contributions/208.81.184.4|208.81.184.4]] ([[User talk:208.81.184.4|talk]]) 01:24, 29 November 2011 (UTC)

== SHORT DESCRIPTION value ==

A recent contrib to this article ([http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Brigham_Young&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=460361180&amp;oldid=458044585 dif]) butchers the name of the LDS Church. Can someone fix this? I can't because this article is semi-protected. -- [[Special:Contributions/208.81.184.4|208.81.184.4]] ([[User talk:208.81.184.4|talk]]) 18:20, 14 November 2011 (UTC)
:Done--[[User:ARTEST4ECHO|ARTEST4ECHO]] ([[User talk:ARTEST4ECHO|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/ARTEST4ECHO|&lt;sub&gt;contribs&lt;/sub&gt;]]) 18:24, 14 November 2011 (UTC)

== Succession Crisis ==

This statement &quot;These recollections indicate an experience of some kind that persuaded them that the Quorum of the Twelve Apostles was to lead the church with Young as the Quorum's President&quot; is POV.  Whether or not the Young's election inspired the recollections or the recollections inspired Young's election is matter of considerable historical debate.  The statement can be easily neutralized by swapping it with the preceding sentence and removing the allusion to the recollections:  &quot;The majority in attendance were persuaded that the Quorum of the Twelve Apostles was to lead the church with Young as the Quorum's President&quot;[[User:Mormography|Mormography]] ([[User talk:Mormography|talk]]) 12:55, 28 May 2012 (UTC)
:For this article to be objective, we must allow accounts of Young's alleged transformation of voice and appearance to that of Joseph Smith. To leave it out would be a violation of WP's policy on verifiable sources. An explanation of ''what'' persuaded a majority of the people in attendance to vote for Young as the new Church leader is both appropriate and necessary for this article. I for one vehemently object to the change you propose. Unless the consensus decides to omit the material and implement this change, I say, why don't you leave well enough alone? --[[User:Jgstokes|Jgstokes-We can disagree without being disagreeable]] ([[User talk:Jgstokes|talk]]) 01:38, 29 May 2012 (UTC)
::I think perhaps what could be done to satisfy both sides is that we do not delete mentioning such accounts, but rather that we rephrase it to allow for the possibility that Young's election inspired the recollections rather than vice versa. This is an issue that has been debated by various historians (including believing Mormon researchers such as [[Richard S. Van Wagoner]]) and I don't think there is a consensus view on the issue among historians. But what is not in dispute is that there were dozens of these types of recollections years after the fact, but none in the immediate years following 1847. [[User:Good Olfactory|Good Ol’factory]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Good Olfactory|(talk)]]&lt;/sup&gt; 01:55, 29 May 2012 (UTC)
:Jgstokes, it is not a matter of leaving well enough alone as it is a matter that has been contested for sometime.  It is not clear from your response if you genuinely do not understand or are just pretending.  The ''what'' has describe by Good Olfactory, in the article footnotes, and here http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Succession_crisis_(Latter_Day_Saints)#Conference_of_August_8.2C_1844 is what you have not addressed.  The POV in the article now will need to be removed according to wikipedia policy until you figure out how to eloquently included the discussion in the article. [[User:Mormography|Mormography]] ([[User talk:Mormography|talk]]) 01:36, 2 June 2012 (UTC)
:Jgstokes, also please note that your argument that &quot;we must allow accounts of Young's alleged transformation&quot; was never disputed in the proposed or implement changes.  The proposed and implemented changes do not remove mention of these accounts, just the POV spin.[[User:Mormography|Mormography]] ([[User talk:Mormography|talk]]) 01:50, 2 June 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>cvygm4haa8ecd9ouelbdogx11wft5w9</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
