<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Catechism</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>663294</id>
    <revision>
      <id>483299973</id>
      <parentid>466682701</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-03-22T02:46:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>71.219.214.16</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8927">{{ChristianityWikiProject|importance=Low|class=B|anglicanism=yes|anglicanism-importance=Mid|catholicism=yes|catholicism-importance=Mid|calvinism=yes|lutheranism=yes|lutheranism-importance=Mid|calvinism-importance=Mid}}


The &quot;improved definition&quot; says the same thing as the old definition, in denser language. It is not an improvement.  I've merged the two versions, to stop the competing reverts.  I should point out to the anonymous editor, however, that ''Catechetics'' is not actually the act of instruction itself, but the science of instruction.  [[User:Mkmcconn|Mkmcconn]][[User Talk:Mkmcconn| &amp;mdash;]] 16:27, 18 May 2004 (UTC)

== Unverified claims about Catholic teaching ==

The Catechism of the Catholic Church (see below) is the catechism that is most widespread use among Catholics today. It is the official Catechism of the Church. (No sources, but it's true!)

For Catholics obedient to the Pope of Rome (are you a catholic otherwise?), all the canonical books of the Bible (including the six books which do not appear in the Hebrew canon), plus the current Catechism of the Catholic Church or an approved compendium, constitute the complete and best resource for fully attaining to God's revelation to mankind. (This is clearly NOT roman catholic teaching; when the CC only accepts three on each other depending sources for understanding of the revelation: The Holy Scripture, The Sacred Tradition and the Magisterum (which is defined in the catechism as: &quot;Bishops, with priests as co-workers... are authentic teachers, of the apostolic faith, endowed with the authority of Christ.&quot; pagph. 888) (So this is not the same thing as a catechism!)

Catholics believe that Sacred Scripture and Sacred Tradition are expressed by the Catechism (Not the catechism! &quot;The Magisterium&quot;: the communion of the bishops togheter with the people) of the Catholic Church are both necessary for attaining to the fullest understanding of all of God's revelation. &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[Special:Contributions/213.67.174.43|213.67.174.43]] ([[User talk:213.67.174.43|talk]]) 22:00, 23 December 2006 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;

== NPOV, unencyclopedic, where do I begin? ==

The section on the Catechism of the Catholic Church is overlong, filled with non-neutral POV and purple prose, and overall is unencyclopedic.  Just a ''few'' excerpts that I find somewhere on the scale of &quot;questionable&quot; to &quot;ridiculous&quot;:

*&quot;a work of remarkable organization and breadth, containing articles of elegant reasoning and historical insight&quot;
*&quot;may construct any lesson needed for the time-tested Socratic Method of posing and answering questions, or for other methods, with complete confidence in the fidelity of the answers&quot;
*&quot;It also functions admirably for individual study as well&quot;
*&quot;avoiding any mistaken comparisons to simplified Q&amp;A teaching aids&quot;
*&quot;the serious catechist quickly realizes that this teaching tool accomplishes its ideal suitability to task through its definitive subject index, intelligent frontmatter tables, strict absence of redundancy, exhaustive footnoting&quot;
*&quot;writing style that fulfills a seemingly impossible balance between concise definition and transparently readable clarity&quot;
*&quot;Catechists find that it functions admirably both for individual or group reference and as an on-the-spot teaching aid&quot;
*&quot;Such an excellently made map to its subject is it, that facility with its contents easily constitutes facility with definitive Catholic teaching&quot;
*&quot;Its excellence of execution can stand as a best practices model for the 21st century scholar's art&quot;
*&quot;its' excellent subject index elegantly provides the functionality of a Question and Answer format but with a far greater degree of flexibility&quot;
*&quot;Because of the excellent index, teachers can easily reference The Catechism of the Catholic Church for answering questions 'on the fly' with the highest confidence in its fidelity to the subject matter&quot;

Let's set aside the sheer frequency of the word &quot;excellent&quot; in a passage that praises &quot;strict absence of redundancy&quot; for now...  I've got no problem if the author is a fan of the Catechism, but this does not fit &quot;a best practices model for the 21st century scholar's art.&quot; --[[User:Kuronekoyama|Kuronekoyama]] 04:14, 18 December 2006 (UTC)


I agree with you whole-heartedly on this matter and made the appropriate edits along with adding a bit of content.  When I have more time I will try to enrich this section.  -- [[User:A.Augustinus|A.Augustinus]] 


:Seconded, and added {{tl|POV-section}} before ever seeing the debate here. --[[User:Neurophyre|Neurophyre]]&lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Neurophyre|talk]])&lt;/sup&gt; 08:14, 6 January 2007 (UTC)

:I took a stab at cleaning up the section, but left the POV tag as a pointer to this discussion. --[[User:Neurophyre|Neurophyre]]&lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Neurophyre|talk]])&lt;/sup&gt; 08:27, 6 January 2007 (UTC)

== Catechism of the Catholic Church is addressed to the laity ==

[[Fidei depositum]] does not say that the Catechism is not for the laity. The Apostolic constitution is addressed to all the People of God. It says that the Catechism is presented to the whole Church. This Apostolic constitution appears at the front of the Catechism ([[User:Runwiththewind|Runwiththewind]] 22:19, 17 July 2007 (UTC))

==The Evangelical Free Church Catechism==

Can anyone expand/add information about this this entry? I believe this took place in 1898 and was the 'bringing' together of the non-conformist faiths with representations from the Congregationalists, Baptists, Wesleyan Methodists, Primitive Methodists, the Methodist New Connexion, United Methodist Free Church, Presbyterians, and Bible Christians. [[User:MBorrill|MBorrill]] ([[User talk:MBorrill|talk]]) 06:45, 6 December 2008 (UTC)

==Doctrinal Catechism==
I noticed an older 19th century catechism called the ''[[Doctrinal Catechism]]'', which was commonly quoted in Catholic-Protestant polemics in times past, and which is still quoted by a few contemporary authors. It is perhaps notable and would maybe deserve to be included in this page or in a related stub article. [http://biblelight.net/keenan.htm] [[User:ADM|ADM]] ([[User talk:ADM|talk]]) 07:46, 1 April 2009 (UTC)

== Citation needed for revision of the Westminster Shorter Catechism ==

I don't have a problem with the use of the &quot;revision of the Westminster Shorter Catechism&quot; as an illustration of the catechetical format of question &amp; answer, but I believe a citation is needed -- especially since the answer to Question #2 is in direct contradiction to the original answer, which is:

&quot;The Word of God, which is contained in the Scriptures of the Old and New Testaments, is the only rule to direct us how we may glorify and enjoy Him.&quot;

[[User:Edonovan|Evan Donovan]] ([[User talk:Edonovan|talk]]) 19:39, 20 February 2010 (UTC)

== &quot;Penny Catechism&quot; typo? ==

Should ''issued through the century'' read ''the centuries''?[[User:Autarch|Autarch]] ([[User talk:Autarch|talk]]) 20:42, 22 July 2010 (UTC)

==Popular catechisms were Luther's idea==
It doesn't come across in the article that the 1566 Roman Catholic catechism for everyone was one of the suggestions for church reform made by Luther in his early years, and was a part of the [[counter-reformation]]. Probably the one that affected the man in the street most, as he intended.[[Special:Contributions/86.42.215.188|86.42.215.188]] ([[User talk:86.42.215.188|talk]]) 20:59, 14 May 2011 (UTC)

== i.e. to indoctrinate ==

much I agree with the statement, even an atheist heathen like myself might consider the leap from &quot;sound down&quot; to &quot;indoctrinate&quot; a little POV.

Also, looking back to see when it was added (i.e. whether is was a recent perhaps vandalistic addition) I saw it's been there since... http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Catechism&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=281047915

April 1.  2009.  I think we've been had guys...   [[Special:Contributions/88.109.52.217|88.109.52.217]] ([[User talk:88.109.52.217|talk]]) 23:06, 31 August 2011 (UTC)

== Merger proposal ==

I propose that [[Ignorantia sacerdotum]] be merged into [[Catechism]], under [[Catechism#Catholic_catechisms | Catholic catechisms]]. I think that the content in the Ignorantia sacerdotum article can easily be explained in the context of catechisms, and the catechisms article is of a reasonable size in which the merging of Ignorantia sacerdotum will not cause any problems as far as article size or undue weight is concerned. [[User:JanetteDoe|JanetteDoe]] ([[User talk:JanetteDoe|talk]]) 20:42, 13 December 2011 (UTC)
:I agree... that sounds like a reasonable idea. The alternative might be to merge the Ignorantia sacerdotum article into the John Peckham article, intead. I'll leave it for others, more expert than I, to decide :-)  [[User:TheAMmollusc|TheAMmollusc]] ([[User talk:TheAMmollusc|talk]]) 13:15, 19 December 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>ikuz63bc8ih01lz1wjkqicn7iso8k2q</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
