<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Goddess worship</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>60929</id>
    <revision>
      <id>260213345</id>
      <parentid>236292862</parentid>
      <timestamp>2008-12-26T19:50:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TAnthony</username>
        <id>1808194</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Add Project banner  using [[Project:AutoWikiBrowser|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3216">{{DisambigProject}}
&quot; Monarchs such as [[Elizabeth I]] of England consciously drew on the iconic powers of a living goddess.&quot;

What the heck is this? 
-----

Pulled from the text for being POV. I am not a practicing Catholic (or really of any denomination of Christianity), but if the following is true, it needs to be developed in the article, not tacked on at the end in a fit of condescension -- [[User:Llywrch|llywrch]] 21:53 18 Jun 2003 (UTC)

::Elizabeth the First was not Catholic. Her father, Henry the Eighth seperated England from the Church, and thus created the Church of England,  which, as far as I'm led to believe, is Protestant. Hence another bunch of religious problems which include Elizabeth against her older half-sister Mary, who was a Catholic whose mother, Catherine, who was divorced from Henry (thus the Church thing), who was from Spain, and very closely linked to the Church. Okay, aside from the history lesson, and I just re-read what you wrote so the above is pointless, but Elizabeth I used the idea as a virgin because she didn't want to marry. I mean, her father beheaded two of his wives, and many more problems arose from married people that were involved in her life. So she chose to remain unmarried (whether or not she was still a virgin, is probably still up for debate). So she was kind of.. a technical virgin. In a way, it solved alot of the problems of the monarchy, but after her, the Tudor dynasty ended, and it went to her.. nephew or cousin or something. [[User:Disinclination|Disinclination]] 00:55, 27 September 2006 (UTC)

&lt;b&gt;Note that the author of the preceding article exaggerated greatly the situation of the Virgin Mary on all counts. She was never, and has never, been worshipped by the Catholic, Orthodox, Anglican, and Protestant churches, nor has she ever been seriously considered for any type of elevation to the status of Godhead.&lt;/b&gt;

Don't know about the latter three denominations, but in the Catholic religion Mary is a goddess in everything but name... With this, the trinity and an army of saints I never understood why they try to keep up the appearance of monotheism. [[User:Alensha|Alensha]] 17:35, 14 Apr 2005 (UTC)

== Mayan Religion ==

Perhaps some historical mention should be made of [[Ix Chel]] and her worship on [[Isla Mujeres]] and [[Cozumel]]. --[[User:Viriditas|Viriditas]] 09:42, 28 Oct 2004 (UTC)

== Merge? ==

Should this be merged with [[Goddess]]? &amp;mdash;[[User:Ashley Y|Ashley Y]] 03:09, 2004 Nov 18 (UTC)

:I think so.  If this were to exist as a distinct article, it would need to be expanded in a way to contrast it from [[goddess]]] by, for example, focusing on belief systems that worshipped goddesses primarily or exclusively, rather than the generality currently shared by both articles.  -[[User:Gtrmp|Sean Curtin]] 05:02, Nov 18, 2004 (UTC)

==Religioustolerance.org==

This article uses the religioustolerance.org website as either a reference or a link. Please see the discussion on [[Wikipedia talk:Verifiability/Religioustolerance.org]] and [[Wikipedia:Verifiability/Religioustolerance.org]] as to whether Wikipedia should cite the religioustolerance.org website, [[User:Jguk|jguk]] 14:07, 17 December 2005 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>ox1iw95vzrkrjc9pp29wbfrgk33i2fx</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
