<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:List of popes</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>77844</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520891117</id>
      <parentid>520529799</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-01T12:59:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marauder40</username>
        <id>7651504</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Pope Benedict XVI */ reply</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16794">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=FLC
|action1date=18:00, 1 Jun 2005
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured list candidates/List of popes/archive1
|action1result=promoted
|action1oldid=14538525

|action2=FLR
|action2date=03:43, 21 October 2008
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured list removal candidates/List of popes/archive1
|action2result=removed
|action2oldid=246375260

|currentstatus=FFL
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|blp=yes|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=yes|class=list|listas=Popes, List Of}}
{{WikiProject European Microstates|class=List|importance=High|Vatican City=yes|Vatican City-importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Christianity|class=List|importance=High|catholicism=yes|catholicism-importance=High}}
}}
{{WP1.0|v0.5=pass|category=Philrelig}}
{{archivebox|auto=yes}}

==Numbering of Popes==
If Pope-Elect Stephen is not officially counted as a pope, then shouldn't the numbering skip him?  As is, Zachary is numbered 90, and Pope-Elect Stephen as 91, and Stephen II as 92.  Shouldn't Pope-Elect Stephen be skipped in the counting and Stephen II be counted as 91, with all subsequent popes numbered accordingly? [[User:XinaNicole|XinaNicole]] ([[User talk:XinaNicole|talk]]) 14:05, 7 February 2011 (UTC)
:Recently an IP editor went through and added the numbering.  I am not real sure what they are numbering.  No matter what the numbering is wrong for the reason you list.  The question is what should the numbering be?  Should it be the number of Popes or the number of Pontificates?  Since due to Benedict IX the number is off by two between each.  This is the reason that the numbers weren't included until that editor added them.  I am also not sure the importance of the numbering as related to the numbering in each century.  I am not sure what that &quot;buys&quot; us.[[User:Marauder40|Marauder40]] ([[User talk:Marauder40|talk]]) 18:16, 7 February 2011 (UTC)
::Yeah, the century numbering seemed weird to me.  Is there a general precedence for other offices where a person holds non-consecutive terms?  I know with the US Presidents, Cleveland is counted as 22nd and 24th.  But I don't know if that's an American idiosyncrasy or if others do the same.
::Okay, I've been looking around at other lists, and it looks like it's common to count non-consecutive periods of rule with different numbers.  So, I'll edit it to count Pontificates and skipping Pope-Elect Stephen [[User:XinaNicole|XinaNicole]] ([[User talk:XinaNicole|talk]]) 20:40, 7 February 2011 (UTC)
:::&lt;s&gt;Okay, something is strange. This page lists Benedict as the 265th, but the Catholic Encylopedia online lists him as 266th [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/12272b.htm] Something strange is going on ... [[User:XinaNicole|XinaNicole]] ([[User talk:XinaNicole|talk]]) 20:47, 7 February 2011 (UTC)&lt;/s&gt; Found it! And error in numbering with 89 repeated [[User:XinaNicole|XinaNicole]] ([[User talk:XinaNicole|talk]]) 20:53, 7 February 2011 (UTC)
::::That list has Benedict IX listed 3 times and it has Stephen II listed and counted, which he shouldn't be.[[User:Marauder40|Marauder40]] ([[User talk:Marauder40|talk]]) 20:51, 7 February 2011 (UTC)
:::::According to the intro, Benedict XVI is officially 265th, so that indicates that Benedict IX's repeat counting is correct. I was confused because taking out Stephen would've reduced Benedict's number to 264, but now I see where the error was [[User:XinaNicole|XinaNicole]] ([[User talk:XinaNicole|talk]]) 20:58, 7 February 2011 (UTC)
::::::Yes it can be confusing.  I know the line that says &quot;That list is the one given here; it lists 263 men serving 265 pontificates (periods of Papal office), if Pope-elect Stephen is excluded (see below).&quot; Was accurate because I was the one that put a different version of the same line in with the same numbers.  When I originally put it in, it was sourced to a good source and I remember looking things up on the Vatican site to verify it.  I guess in all the updates someone removed the source.  The source was based on an article talking about the fact that the Vatican had just updated its latest listing of the Popes.  The source was right before Pope JPII died and Benedict was elected and placed the numbering at 262 and 264 at the time.  Good luck on updating all the tables, if you are going to do that.  I did it once and was pretty cross-eyed at the end. [[User:Marauder40|Marauder40]] ([[User talk:Marauder40|talk]]) 21:10, 7 February 2011 (UTC)
::::::Well, teh numbering was mostly correct.  The only errors were the repetition of 89 and counting Stephen, which two errors canceled out, so I only had to change a few numbers.  I thought of removing the century numbers, too, but that was too much [[User:XinaNicole|XinaNicole]] ([[User talk:XinaNicole|talk]]) 22:28, 7 February 2011 (UTC)

== Pope Joan ==

An IP editor keeps trying to add Pope Joan to the list.  First off the [[Pope Joan]] page itself lists her as a legend.  Second, the page lists those people that have been officially called a Pope by the Catholic church.  She isn't one.  Please refrain from readding without consensus.[[User:Marauder40|Marauder40]] ([[User talk:Marauder40|talk]]) 17:58, 21 April 2011 (UTC)

:The Ip probably confused her with [[Joan Baez|this claimed pope]]. In any case, not right. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 18:30, 21 April 2011 (UTC)
::Funny.  Thanks for the help.[[User:Marauder40|Marauder40]] ([[User talk:Marauder40|talk]]) 18:48, 21 April 2011 (UTC)

==Sub-numbers==

What's with the sub-numbering, which I've worked out shows the number within each century? E.g. John Paul II is 264/8, being the 264th pope overall, but the 8th whose papacy started in the the 20th century.  This is unnecessary, confusing, unorthodox, inappropriate, and is never explained anywhere.  Readers will have to work it out for themselves, as I did, but it shouldn't be there at all, imo.  --  [[User:JackofOz|&lt;font face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;Jack of Oz&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:JackofOz#top|&lt;font face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[your turn]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 23:15, 6 September 2011 (UTC)
:I agree.  Numbering popes as &quot;The ''n''th pope of his century&quot; is irrelevant, confusing, and, to my knowledge, not done by anybody else.  This was done by the IP editor who added all the numberings last January.  I'll probably go ahead and remove them, if nobody speaks up. [[User:Glenfarclas|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#3B6AA0;color:#EDEDED&quot; vlink=&quot;color:#EDEDED&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;'''Glenfarclas'''&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Glenfarclas|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#003F87&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]]) 21:45, 4 October 2011 (UTC)
::I don't think numbering by century adds anything. While it is a bit off the subject, I'd like to raise the issue of organizing by centuries. Would it be better to employ more organic groupings that would break the list into manageably sized logical series (e.g. Roman Empire, Western Empire, Great Schism, Avignon Papacy, etc.)?[[User:Novangelis|Novangelis]] ([[User talk:Novangelis|talk]]) 22:02, 4 October 2011 (UTC)
::: I'd suppport that idea.  Are those periods well defined?  --  [[User:JackofOz|&lt;font face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;Jack of Oz&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:JackofOz#top|&lt;font face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[your turn]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 10:57, 5 October 2011 (UTC)
:::: Such a division exists in [[History of the papacy]]. A preliminary scan shows adequate sources, often in the articles on the periods, but I haven't done a close inspection. I know I can't get around to it until at least next week.[[User:Novangelis|Novangelis]] ([[User talk:Novangelis|talk]]) 15:55, 5 October 2011 (UTC)
::::: I've gone ahead and removed the sub-numbering.  I have no real objection to dividing the list by era instead of century, except that I hate to perpetuate the notion that, you know, the middle ages just came to an end right in 1417, and they all had an inauguration party for the next era. [[User:Glenfarclas|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#3B6AA0;color:#EDEDED&quot; vlink=&quot;color:#EDEDED&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;'''Glenfarclas'''&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Glenfarclas|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#003F87&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]]) 06:45, 1 November 2011 (UTC)

==Many Missing References==

In the note section there is a huge lack of references. Please find sources for the various claims, well known or not. [[User:Repllyturns|Repllyturns]] ([[User talk:Repllyturns|talk]])
:While a good idea, they have to be [[WP:RS|reliable sources]] and the references have to say what is contained in the source. Reliability does not get transferred by proximity. Although one newspaper article about a controversial documentary might be a reliable source if it actually said what was in the edit, stringing it together with a highly dubious blog and some random websites to reach a global conclusion is [[WP:SYNTH|synthesis]].[[User:Novangelis|Novangelis]] ([[User talk:Novangelis|talk]]) 13:09, 7 September 2011 (UTC)

::Please explain how the websites are &quot;random&quot; and what would not qualify as &quot;random&quot;. Does Wikipedia have a policy which points out what is considered &quot;random&quot; stringing together of websites? And concerning a &quot;highly dubious&quot; blog, in what way? The blog owner cites himself as a Calvinist or Calvinistic Christian, therefore a protestant, and gives his rebuttal to Catholics who give their reasons as to why they consider Peter the first Pope. As such his replies qualify as a perspective from a Protestant who is debating their claims. It's also a commonly known fact (note the &quot;known for&quot; comment in this article without a reference to back that comment up) that all Protestants, not talking about nominal ones, deny that Peter was the first Pope. The websites give perspectives from various Protestants, their reasonings as to why.[[User:Repllyturns|Repllyturns]] ([[User talk:Repllyturns|talk]])  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|undated]] comment added 18:00, 7 September 2011 (UTC).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!--Template:Undated--&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:::Stringing together reliable sources and reaching a conclusion that is not found in any of the sources would be [[WP:SYNTH|synthesis]]. Collecting a few websites, probably based on Google ranking (probably not truly random, but far more haphazard than systematic, thus random) that support a general idea, then using the collection as evidence of a consensus is obvious [[WP:OR|original research]]. Someone, just as easily, could collect multiple websites expressing a minority position. Of course, this begs the question of the sources qualifying as reliable. Justifying the laughable blog because &quot;[t]he blog owner cites himself as a...&quot; is the antithesis of reliable; see [[WP:Verifiability]].

:::Doctrinal and scholarly minutia do not belong on this page; the notes are a synopsis. Appropriate qualifiers (''e.g.'' &quot;Recognized...by the Catholic Church&quot;) are present. Arguing details in an overview instead of the main page is a form of [[WP:COATRACK|&quot;coatracking&quot;]], using a page to advance a position that is not in the scope of the page ([[WP:TOPIC|off-topic]] or [[WP:UNDUE|undue weight]]). Details of the scholarly and doctrinal debates should be focused on [[Saint Peter#Connection to Rome]] without bloating the section relative to the article. Speaking of off-topic, regarding the issue of &quot;missing&quot; references, the article seems adequately sourced, but more sources and inline citations would both be useful and appropriate. [[User:Novangelis|Novangelis]] ([[User talk:Novangelis|talk]]) 16:58, 8 September 2011 (UTC)

== This page has been semi-protected for a week ==



[[File:Padlock-silver-slash.svg|75px|right]]
{{Policy shortcut|WP:SEMI|WP:SILVERLOCK}}
This page has been semi-protected for a week. Semi-protection prevents edits from [[Wikipedia:User access levels#Unregistered users|unregistered users]] (IP addresses), as well as edits from any account that is not [[Wikipedia:User access levels#Autoconfirmed users|autoconfirmed]] (is at least four days old and has ten or more edits to Wikipedia) or [[Wikipedia:User access levels#Confirmed users|confirmed]]. 

Such users can request edits to a semi-protected page by proposing them on its talk page, using the {{Tlx|Edit semi-protected}} template if necessary to gain attention. If the page in question and its talk page are ''both'' protected please make your edit request at [[Wikipedia:Request for edit]] instead. New users may also request the &lt;tt&gt;confirmed&lt;/tt&gt; user right by visiting [[Wikipedia:Requests_for_permissions/Confirmed|Requests for permissions]]. In case you wish clarifications, kindly contact me directly on my talk page. Thanks.[[User:Wifione|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color: red;&quot;&gt;Wifione&lt;/span&gt;''']] [[User talk:Wifione|'''&lt;sup&gt;Message&lt;/sup&gt;''']] 13:46, 11 September 2011 (UTC)

==Was Jesus Pope==

[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=List_of_popes&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=468379760 This edit] raises a fascinating and imaginative question, ''Was [[Jesus]] the first [[Pope]]?'', but the answer is most certainly ''No''. Jesus was the first head of the Church, but is considered by the Church to still be its head. His position is unchanged, and the Pope has always been his deputy at best. [[User:Andrewa|Andrewa]] ([[User talk:Andrewa|talk]]) 12:05, 1 January 2012 (UTC)

== On Leo IX and the Great Schism ==

In the section, dedicated to Pope Leo IX, it says that 'In 1054, Leo IX and Patriarch of Constantinople Michael I Cerularius excommunicated each other, beginning the still-existing East–West Schism'. This is incorrect. It was Leo IX's legate - cardinal Humbert, who excommunicated Cerularios and was, in turn, subject to a counter-excommunication by the Patriarch. This actually happened in June 1054, two months after the death of Leo IX.

I propose changing the quoted phrase to something like 'In June 1054 (two months after the pope's death) Leo IX's legate - cardinal Humbert and the Patriarch of Constantinople Michael I Cerularius excommunicated each other, beginning the still-existing East–West Schism'.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/178.176.10.109|178.176.10.109]] ([[User talk:178.176.10.109|talk]]) 11:20, 27 January 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Sourcing/citing ==

I don't know how the list was initially constructed, but would it be appropriate to place a catch-all footnote on the table (probably at the top of the &quot;Notes&quot; column) to the effect that &quot;unless otherwise specified, details are from the entry for the named Pope in Catholic Encyclopedia (1913)&quot;? If this is actually the source, it should solve citation without footnote bloat, the idea being to make it easy to [[WP:V|verify]] the source of claims. Anything controversial should have a detailed footnote.[[User:Novangelis|Novangelis]] ([[User talk:Novangelis|talk]]) 01:16, 23 March 2012 (UTC)
==File:Sixtuspope3.jpg Nominated for Deletion==
{|
|-
| [[File:Image-x-generic.svg|100px]] 
| An image used in this article, [[commons:File:Sixtuspope3.jpg|File:Sixtuspope3.jpg]], has been nominated for deletion at [[Wikimedia Commons]] in the following category: ''Media without a source as of 24 March 2012'' 
;What should I do?
''Don't panic''; a discussion will now take place over on Commons about whether to remove the file. This gives you an opportunity to contest the deletion, although please review Commons guidelines before doing so.
* If the image is [[WP:NFCC|non-free]] then you may need to upload it to Wikipedia (Commons does not allow fair use)
* If the image isn't freely licensed and there is no [[WP:FUR|fair use rationale]] then it cannot be uploaded or used.
To take part in any discussion, or to review a more detailed deletion rationale please visit the relevant [[commons:File:Sixtuspope3.jpg|image page (File:Sixtuspope3.jpg)]]

''This is Bot placed notification, another user has nominated/tagged the image'' --[[User:CommonsNotificationBot|CommonsNotificationBot]] ([[User talk:CommonsNotificationBot|talk]]) 02:02, 27 March 2012 (UTC)
|}

== Pope Benedict XVI ==

Under 'notes' it now reads: &quot;First Pope to have been conscripted into the Hitler Youth&quot;, and this is relevant ''because''....?

Unless somebody can justify this, I'm removing it. -- [[User:Hazhk|Peter]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Hazhk|Talk to me]]&lt;/sup&gt; 02:29, 30 October 2012 (UTC)
:The person that added originally, added it back again (and I have reverted it.)  I agree this is not relevant to this list.  It is a small fact about the early history of the person, long before they became Pope.  In the history of the Papacy, it is a extremely minor fact. It doesn't really show how he is any different from previous Popes.  It is the type of fact that only belongs in the article about the Pope. [[User:Marauder40|Marauder40]] ([[User talk:Marauder40|talk]]) 12:59, 1 November 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>dzqeuk3fa80vbtm15mirom43pey7fx6</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
