<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Azazel</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2472750</id>
    <revision>
      <id>493264420</id>
      <parentid>493264305</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-05-18T22:51:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SineBot</username>
        <id>4936590</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Signing comment by [[Special:Contributions/88.189.28.190|88.189.28.190]] - &quot;/* Azazel In Islam */&quot;</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="37236">{{WikiProject Judaism|class=B|importance=low}}
{{WPOccult|class=B|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=|importance=}}

== Azazel In Islam ==
I am leaving a brief note, seeking to draw attention to the fact that there are several grammatical and syntactical errors in this section. Also, the author deviates from the subject at hand, since he/she begins to discuss angels in Islam, as though that is relevant.  Please rewrite this section.  It needs to be more relevant, to not go off topic and to be grammatically correct. Thank you.

== Azazel as a Non-Word ==
I would like to suggest a greater elucidation of the idea that the link between Azazel and the &quot;scapegoat&quot; is a false construct because scapegoat is the result of an inaccurate handling of the translation of Azazel.  Anyone?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/88.189.28.190|88.189.28.190]] ([[User talk:88.189.28.190|talk]]) 22:50, 18 May 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Original Languages ==

I think much of this would be clarified by using the original languages involved instead of relying on various inconsistant transliterations. This isn't difficult in the age of Unicode.--[[User:Blackjack@jolly-roger.com|Blackjack@jolly-roger.com]] 22:25, 5 January 2006 (UTC)
:What specifically are you referring to? I can't figure out what you mean. Please clarify. [[User:Makaristos|Makaristos]] 02:34, 6 January 2006 (UTC)

== Dumb Ass Newbie to wiki:talk ==

I don't know how to comment without editing someone else's comment.

Look, I heard one person say that this is also being confused with Azarel from the Batman comic.  

I don't mean to be one of the faithful... but what are your sources? This is complete allegory compared to the KING James Auth. Version.  It doesn't use Azazel as a proper or active noun, instead it speaks directly of the Scape-Goat.  You can't claim to have better personal or educational wisdom than the translators of the KJV nor the editions leading up to that.  If it was interesting myth worthy of association, it would be in the &quot;Shakespeare Team&quot; version.  Shakespeare was able to rewrite the great tragedies because he researched and found a gold mine.  He found myth and applied modern truth. If there was value here, it would be the KJV.

I can over turn this proganda based on Enoch not being canon for a reason from great minds.  Look if you are going to use the Bible, understand the story and seek out the truth.  If you weight the facts that Azazel is the scape-coat in line with considering that 'Azazel' means 'strength of the lord'... you'll find the complete story of god's love for man according to the traditional canon.  God's strength is to save or forgive.  You can forgive the Man and save the Goat at the same time.  You might call it a demon, if you don't consider something natural.  God saves the goat and forgives the man for making it a slave.  At least the goat is grateful to god for the world we live in.

Blah-gaia-blah-goddess-blah... I write fiction too.  

You should remove the bible verses if you can't find a reason not to include Jesus as the scape-goat.  That's the story the bible tells... goat, lamb, strength of freedom, aryan promise to Abraham, pyramids, sahara desert... this entire entry in subjective and the bible connection with Leviticus should be limited due to the editorial liberties.  Does the Volgate include Enoch and use Azazel in Leviticus?  Sacrifice the subjective associations to Western Civilization's God and stop using it as your scapegoat and strength.  Hail Satan!  I am his prosecutor of fools! &lt;small&gt;(The above was written by [[User:FinLives|FinLives]] ([[User talk:FinLives|Talk]])&lt;/small&gt;

:Please explain this better. What exactly are you trying to say? (Also, see [[User talk:FinLives|your talk page]].) [[User:Makaristos|Makaristos]] 06:11, 29 June 2006 (UTC)

== The actual identity of Azazel: Unknown ==

I took the liberty of rewriting the &quot;Azazel in Leviticus&quot; section to make it more accurate by reporting that we ''don't'' in fact know what Azazel's identity was. It could have been a person, place, or thing; the text ''just doesn't say''. Later mythology, like the Book of Enoch, created a whole literary tradition out of Azazel, and I am not qualified to write about that. However, there are some things that I have corrected:
*The Leviticus text, though comparatively late compared to the rest of the Pentateuch, is much earlier than the Book of Enoch and the subsequent literary tradition about Azazel. I replaced the Leviticus section above the other sections to reflect this and show more clearly where the tradition grew out of.
*The scapegoat designated &quot;for Azazel&quot; was not called &quot;Azazel&quot;—Azazel is clearly something else. Why would the scapegoat and the place (or demon, or whatever) it was destined for have the same name?
*The word &quot;Azazel&quot; does not mean &quot;the goat of removal&quot;. The derivation is unclear at best, possibly incorporating ''-el'' (&quot;God&quot;, often used as a suffix in Hebrew to mean &quot;of God&quot;). The idea that the ''az'' part means &quot;goat&quot; is dubious because of the spelling in Hebrew; the ''az'' is not reduplicated (the actual spelling is ayin-zayin-aleph-zayin-aleph-lamed), so this leaves a part of the word unaccounted for.
Thanks for considering all this. Let's discuss. [[User:Makaristos|Makaristos]] 07:00, 17 August 2005 (UTC)



:as far as I'm concerned, you made perfectly good edits and have improved the article. [[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|('''&amp;#5839;''')]]&lt;/small&gt; 07:40, 17 August 2005 (UTC)

::Why, thank you. [[User:Makaristos|Makaristos]] 07:58, 17 August 2005 (UTC)

:[[Azhi Dahaka]] (meaning &quot;The Big Snake&quot;) from [[Avestan]] lore may have influenced the development of [[Azazel]] in Semitic lore. ---[[User:Decius|Decius]] 08:54, 17 August 2005 (UTC)

::Interesting. I didn't know about that. Avestan is, however, an Indo-Iranian language, whereas Hebrew is Semitic, and these families aren't related. It is possible it's some kind of loanword, but the absence of other loanwords from Iranian languages as early as the Book of Leviticus is fairly telling in my opinion. On the other hand, it would be interesting to note this. Maybe I'll add a section about possible etymologies, and consolidate all the information we have come up with so far. [[User:Makaristos|Makaristos]] 15:37, 17 August 2005 (UTC)
:::no, come on, ''azhi'' is completely unrelated. If anything, compare Avestan ''*aza'' (Sanskrit ''aja'') &quot;goat&quot;! Or rather look for a Semitic root. '' 'zz'' &quot;&quot;buzz? ''`zz'' &quot;be strong&quot;? ''wzz'' &quot;repay&quot;? [[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|('''&amp;#5839;''')]]&lt;/small&gt; 16:18, 17 August 2005 (UTC)
::::or maybe, since the spelling is '' 'z'z'l'', '' 'wz'' &quot;to mock&quot;? (as you see, my Semitic etymologizing skills are restricted to &quot;ignore all weak radicals, and look for a root that looks vaguely similar&quot; :) [[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|('''&amp;#5839;''')]]&lt;/small&gt; 16:21, 17 Au

:::::Hey, I've got it! I'll look on JSTOR when I get a second and come up with some actual scholarship on this, with names and articles we can cite! (-: [[User:Makaristos|Makaristos]] 16:59, 17 August 2005 (UTC)

:[[Azazel]] is not etymologically related to the ''Azhi'' element (which is from [[Proto-Indo-European language|PIE]] ''*angwhi-'', 'snake') in Azhi Dahaka. Etymologically, I would guess that ''Azaz-'' meant 'strong' or 'lusty', with 'lusty' resonating with 'goat'. ---[[User:Decius|Decius]] 17:02, 17 August 2005 (UTC)

::Could you clarify what you believe the connection to be, or why attention should be drawn to Azhi Dahaka? I don't see the connection. Thanks. [[User:Makaristos|Makaristos]] 17:08, 17 August 2005 (UTC)

:[[Uzza]] links these threads together: power, lust (she's connected with [[Aphrodite]], etc.), goats (the goat being a symbol of lust and associated with Aphrodite, etc.). But this is symbolism, not necessarily identical roots for the words. ---[[User:Decius|Decius]] 17:43, 17 August 2005 (UTC)
::Decius, I find it slightly confusing to have you change your signatures in the middle of a conversation :) ---[[User:Dbachmann|Azazel]] 18:42 , 17 August 2005 (UTC)

:If goats were associated with [[Uzza]] (as they were with her Roman and Greek counterpart), that might be relevant to the lore surrounding Azazel. ---[[User:Decius|Decius]] 18:47, 17 August 2005 (UTC)

I was at Yom Kippur services this year and could not help but notice that there is absolutely nothing to suggest that Azazel is evil. He is simply whatever it is that takes the goat that bears the sins of the people. There is no other reference to him anywhere in the Torah, I spent weeks looking for it while I was at shul. I'm a little confused as to the demonizing of Azazel both by the Talmudic scholars and the media. I just thought that that should be mentioned. Oh, and El does not mean &quot;of God.&quot; It's meaning is one of the mysteries of the Torah, but it proceeds the names of most of the important biblical figures. Very good information you've got there, and I have a deep respect for your skills in etymology.gust 2005 (UTC)

==Roll-call==

I'm going to list some Semitic demonic figures here with similar names (by the way, Decius used to study demonology but he's rusty at it now) and where they occur.

*Auza---Alternate form of ''Azza'' (see below).
*Aza---Alternate form of ''Azza'' (see below).
*Azza---Mentioned in Rabbinic lore, Solomonic lore. In the Talmud, Azza and Azael are said to have fathered the ''Sedim'' upon Naamah, before the Flood.
*Azael---&quot;In ''Midrash Petirat Mosheh'', ''Azael'' is mentioned as one of two angels (the other being ''Ouza'') who came down from heaven and was corrupted.&quot;---Gustav Davidson, ''A Dictionary of Angels including the Fallen Angels''.
*Azazel
*Aziel
*Azzael
*Azzazel
*Oza 
*Ouza
*Uzza

All these forms are ''Shem'' ('name') compounded to Aza (Yaza, Iaza, etc.):

*Semiaza 
*Semjaza
*Semyaza
*Shemhazai
*Shem-Yaza


---There's too much stuff to quote from my references now, but Davidson regularly states that Uzza (in these sources depicted as male not female) and Aza were interchangeable in the literature, so they may have the same etymology. It's pretty clear from this list (they are almost all interchangeable and may refer to the same or similar figure) that it is useless to just isolate Azazel and examine the etymology on its own. ---[[User:Decius|Decius]] 19:33, 17 August 2005 (UTC)
::well, I cannot rule out that popular etymologies between Azazel and Uzza, Azazel and serpents etc. were at play, but we have to clearly separate this from the actual ''etymology''. Azazel appears in ''Exodus'', in a goat-connection. Even if you think that Exodus was written in the sixth century, it is highly unlikely that Azazel is a hybrid Persian-Hebrew compound. Connection with Uzza is also impossible (where is the `ayin?). But sure, demonology is basically free association, I agree that such parallels have almost certainly been drawn before. [[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|('''&amp;#5839;''')]]&lt;/small&gt; 08:19, 18 August 2005 (UTC)

:I made clear above that I don't connect the Leviticus ''Azazel'' to PIE ''*angwhi-'', 'snake' (from which comes Persian ''azhi''). But I doubt that Semitic Azza and Azael have a different etymology from the duplicated Azazel. I maintain that one should be aware of the forms Azael, Azza, etc., when considering the etymology of Azazel. None of those forms I listed above are Persian, they are all from a Semitic source. It may be popular etymology (as I indicated when I said ''may'' have the same etymology) that developed a progression from ''Auza'', ''Ouza'', ''Azza'', ''Uzza'', but I haven't seen evidence that they are definitely not sharing the same etymology. The phonetics involved make Uzza and Azza unlikely, but I see nothing preventing Azazel and Azza (unduplicated) from being connected. Azael in my reference is said to be a compound of strength (aza) and god (el); Semyaza means &quot;He who is named Aza (strength)&quot;. ''Azza'' on its own is said to mean 'strong', etc. So it's not just Azazel on his own here. ---[[User:Decius|Decius]] 08:36, 18 August 2005 (UTC)

:I dropped in on you guys (Makristos and Dab) discussing the etymology of ''Azazel'', and noticed no mention of Azael (Semitic), Azza (Semitic), Aza (Semitic), Azzael (Semitic), and all the other forms known, that may have the same [[etymology]]. I admit I threw in [[Azhi Dahaka]] because I felt like &quot;fucking around&quot; with you guys while at the same pointing to a mythological parallel. ---[[User:Decius|Master Killer]] 09:26, 18 August 2005 (UTC)

== Azarel ==

Azarel redirects here, but as far as I know these names have nothing to do with one another. Anyone know better?
[[User:BeavisSanchez|BeavisSanchez]] 10:00, 31 January 2006 (UTC)

== Forty days and nights ==

The bottom of the third paragraph in the main article includes the phrase &quot;escaped destruction by living for forty days and forty nights on an ark&quot;.  The forty days and forty nights was only how long it rained (Gen. 7:12).  The occupants of the ark lived in it for one year and ten days (compare Gen. 7:11 with 8:13 ff.)  The text should be corrected accordingly.  [[User:65.135.87.11|65.135.87.11]] 05:47, 9 August 2006 (UTC)GRR

== Reorganization==
Rewrote in a way that separates out what the original sources stated from what (some) scholars interpreting those sources said later. Also distinguished literal meaning of original from interpretations. --[[User:Shirahadasha|Shirahadasha]] 04:44, 3 October 2006 (UTC)

== Unsourced Statements ==
Right now virtually all the interpretave material is unsourced. Where did this material come from? Right now large portions of the article are out of compliance with [[WP:Verifiability]] and [[WP:RS]] and this material will need to be deleted if sources can't be found. --[[User:Shirahadasha|Shirahadasha]] 01:57, 9 October 2006 (UTC)

:Renewing call for sources, will delete unsourced material in a week or so. --[[User:Shirahadasha|Shirahadasha]] 09:54, 29 November 2006 (UTC)

== &quot;Jewish legend&quot; Edit ==

Removed this edit to the &quot;In the Hebrew Bible&quot; section here:

:Jewish legend speaks of Azazel as the angel who refused to bow down before Adam.

Issues:
a. Content is in the wrong place, this doesn't appear in the Hebrew Bible.
b. Need to source [[Aggadah]] and [[Midrash]] as other edits. What book is it in?
c. [[Aggadah]] and [[Midrash]] should be referred to as such (with a link), not by a POV term like &quot;legend&quot; or &quot;myth&quot;. Many [[Haredi Judaism|Haredi]] Jews believe all or some of this material and do not regard it, or some of it, as legend. Best, --[[User:Shirahadasha|Shirahadasha]] 09:52, 29 November 2006 (UTC)

== &quot;Hebrew Bible/Rabbinic Literature&quot; Content ==

Removed the following material to talk:

:Traditionally the word &quot;Azazel&quot; has been translated as &quot;scapegoat&quot; because the [[Masoretic]] texts read ''‘ēz’ōzēl'' (rather than ''‘ăzā’zēl''), &quot;goat which removes [sins]&quot;. However, more recent findings of older Hebrew texts (see [[Dead Sea scrolls]]) read ''‘ăzā’zēl'' and ''‘ăzaz’ēl'', &quot;Azazel&quot;. The confusion of the word is due to the Hebrew [[niqqud|niqqudoth]], vowels represented separately from consonants (''‘ăzā’zēl'' and ''‘ēz’ōzēl'' share the consonantal base ''‘z’zl'').&lt;ref&gt;''The American Heritage dictionary of the English language.–4th ed.'', Houghton Mifflin Company, 2000 ISBN 0-395-82517-2&lt;/ref&gt;

:The &quot;scapegoat&quot; referred to in many translations of Leviticus (here translated as Azazel) most likely does not refer to either of the two goats mentioned in the chapter (&quot;the goat for a scapegoat&quot; is often changed to &quot;the goat as a scapegoat&quot;), but more probably refers to someone or something (see cliff theory below) that is a scapegoat — therefore, possibly a demon Azazel.

:The first goat (for Yahweh) was to be used as a sacrifice, while &quot;the goat chosen by lot for Azazel must be presented alive before Yahweh to be used for making atonement by sending it into the desert for Azazel&quot; (Lev. 16:10, &lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;niv&lt;/span&gt;).

:This is not to say that the goat being sent to &quot;Azazel&quot; is a sacrifice to the demon (if Azazel is, indeed, a demon) — the [[Torah]] itself explicitly says not to worship anyone but Yahweh (Exodus 20:3-6). The goat (instead of the Israelites) is being sent to be forsaken by God, a point made clearer in Leviticus 16:21-22, when Aaron was to &quot;lay both hands on the head of the live goat and confess over it all the wickedness and rebellion of the Israelites — all their sins — and put them on the goat's head.&quot; He would then &quot;send the goat away into the desert in the care of a man appointed for the task.&quot; The goat would &quot;carry on itself all their sins to a solitary place; and the man must release it in the desert&quot; (&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;niv&lt;/span&gt;). Leviticus also says that &quot;the man who releases the goat for Azazel must wash his clothes and bathe himself with water; afterward he may come into the camp&quot; (16:26, &lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;niv&lt;/span&gt;)

THis material clearly does not come from either the Hebrew Bible or Rabbinic literature as claimed. Wikipedia should not misrepresent or misattribute the contents of the Hebrew Bible or Rabbinic literature. If some of this material is commentary from one or more contemporary sources, these sources must be attributed. Unattributed claims that a particular interpretation is &quot;most probable&quot; or similar are particularly problematic, as they violate [[WP:SOAP]]. --[[User:Shirahadasha|Shirahadasha]] 12:53, 10 January 2007 (UTC)

::Good that you removed those parts, I thought they were a bit problematic. I think the last part of the section ''[[Azazel#In First Enoch|In First Enoch]]'' actually takes care of the confusion there. It seems the person who wrote it finds the article in confliction with their inherent dogma. -- [[User:Kerowren|Kerowren]]&amp;nbsp;([[User talk:Kerowren|talk]] &lt;small&gt;•&lt;/small&gt; [[Special:Contributions/Kerowren|contribs]] &lt;small&gt;•&lt;/small&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;plainlinks&quot; style=&quot;color:#002bb8&quot;&gt;[http://tools.wikimedia.de/~interiot/cgi-bin/Tool1/wannabe_kate?username={{urlencode:Kerowren}}&amp;site=en.wikipedia.org count]&lt;/span&gt;) 17:13, 10 January 2007 (UTC)

::I suspect much of this is likely perfectly legitimate material from modern commentators, and the difficulty is most likely attribution and sourcing. Perhaps sources will surface and this material can be put in an appropriate section. It's fine to present e.g. [[Nancy Pelosi]]'s opinion of [[George Bush]], but there's a problem if someone tries to present it unsourced in a section entitled &quot;In George Bush's writings&quot;. --[[User:Shirahadasha|Shirahadasha]] 23:06, 10 January 2007 (UTC)

== scapegoat ==

Why is William Tyndale's translation of &quot;scapegoat&quot; definitely incorrect?  It seems like it could be true to me. [[User:68.239.71.45|68.239.71.45]] 18:43, 25 March 2007 (UTC)

:I agree, especially based on the Masoretic Text, which spells it `Z'Z'L (I'm using ' to indicate ''alef,'' and ` for ''ayin''). How does the &quot;correct&quot; etymology (&quot;strong of god,&quot; &quot;impudent to god&quot; etc.) account for the first ''alef?'' It's an unusual matris lexionis. [[User:69.203.64.233|69.203.64.233]] 05:09, 30 April 2007 (UTC)
==Fair use rationale for Image:Azazel3.jpg==
[[Image:Nuvola apps important.svg|70px|left]]
'''[[:Image:Azazel3.jpg]]''' is being used on this article. I notice the image page specifies that the image is being used under [[Wikipedia:Fair use|fair use]] but there is no [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline|explanation or rationale]] as to why its use in Wikipedia articles constitutes fair use. In addition to the [[Wikipedia:Image copyright tags/Fair use|boilerplate fair use template]], you must also write out on the image description page a specific explanation or rationale for why using this image in each article is consistent with [[WP:FU|fair use]].

Please go to [[:Image:Azazel3.jpg|the image description page]] and edit it to include a [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline |fair use rationale]].

If there is other other fair use media, consider checking that you have specified the fair use rationale on the other images used on this page.  Note that any fair use images uploaded after 4 May, 2006, and lacking such an explanation will be deleted one week after they have been uploaded, as described on [[Wikipedia:Criteria for speedy deletion#Images.2FMedia|criteria for speedy deletion]]. If you have any questions please ask them at the [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions|Media copyright questions page]]. Thank you.&lt;!-- Template:Missing rationale2 --&gt;[[User:BetacommandBot|BetacommandBot]] 21:43, 31 May 2007 (UTC)

== In Islam? ==

Hey there. I was recently cleaning up the previously disastrous [[Iblis]] article, and in this process I came upon [http://www.pantheon.org/articles/a/azazel.html a source] which stated that Azazel was the original name possessed by the Islamic version of the devil, Iblis, before his disobedience to God earned him condemnation and his new name (which etymologically relates to &quot;despair&quot;). I'm wondering if this information can (or even should) be worked into the article; I don't see enough information to start a solitary section, and the given sections don't seem like welcome homes, either.--[[User:C.Logan|C.Logan]] 20:34, 2 December 2007 (UTC)
:And at my school, my religion teacher said that before it names is [[Iblis]], they name were [[Azazel]] [[User Talk:Azmi1995|Muhammad]] [[User:Azmi1995|Azmi]] 01:35, 15 June 2008 (UTC)

== Tekken 6 ==

The main antagonist of the video game ''Tekken 6'' is a demon named '''Azazel'''. I'll make a note of it in the Popular Culture part. [[User:Jienum|Jienum]] ([[User talk:Jienum|talk]]) 19:22, 7 December 2007 (UTC)

== In Music == 

Hello, just wanted to add a note about bands that use the name Azazel.  Morbid Angel used in the lyrics of Brainstorm on their second album, Blessed Are The Sick.  &quot;Azazel, lend to me your wings of twelve, I shall fly into the storm&quot;.  There is also a band from New Zealand that goes by the name Dawn of Azazel.

== Popular culture section ==

I added a popular culture section, and reference to a book that is based specifically on the Azazel story. This reference is important here because it would otherwise be lost to English speakers. The reason for this is that the book title was translated as 'devil' instead of 'Azazel'. I am not sure if I formatted the popular culture section correctly. I will make sure and fix it if I need to. [[User:Yeshuahasochek|Yeshuahasochek]] ([[User talk:Yeshuahasochek|talk]]) 14:20, 19 March 2008 (UTC)


== &quot;Old Pagan religions&quot; ? ==

The first paragraph of the &quot;In Pagan Religions&quot; section is vague as to the specific religions in question referring.  The number of ancient religions in question that predate Christianity is pretty extensive.  Also the paragraph doesn't cite any sources.

Anyone know which religions are being referred to in particular?  Or where this information came from?  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Peter K.|Peter K.]] ([[User talk:Peter K.|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Peter K.|contribs]]) 11:51, 10 July 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

The section appears to be original research making many unlikely claims, for example, implying that Satan was worshiped by pre-Christian pagans. Unless somebody can step forth with a reliable source, I'd recommend just deleting it. - [[User:Augustgrahl|Augustgrahl]] ([[User talk:Augustgrahl|talk]]) 23:14, 13 July 2008 (UTC)



== Any writings on where Azazel was/is buried? ==

If we accept the info given by the Book of Enoch, then Michael bound Azazel and threw him into an unbreakable tomb grave. Now if thats the case, then where is the location of the grave? Has there been any study into where Michael buried Azazel? Where did the Grigori/Watchers reside before the war?

== Azrael is not Azazel ==

The reference to [[Azrael]] (the Angel of Death) mentioned in the Discworld is not Azazel.  Recommend removal.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/68.150.173.245|68.150.173.245]] ([[User talk:68.150.173.245|talk]]) 05:07, 7 October 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
i would like to know if there are any egyptian references to azazel.[[User:Theycallmethebreeze|Theycallmethebreeze]] ([[User talk:Theycallmethebreeze|talk]]) 06:50, 1 August 2011 (UTC)
I thought the article said he was buried at the site of the azazel mountains[[User:Theycallmethebreeze|Theycallmethebreeze]] ([[User talk:Theycallmethebreeze|talk]]) 06:56, 1 August 2011 (UTC)

== Merge [[Azazel in rabbinic literature]] back into this article? ==

I do not think that the [[Azazel in rabbinic literature]] article is noteworthy or interesting enough to support itself as a separate article; besides, it seems to be riddled with information that duplicates information on this page. Merging the page would also provide a good opportunity to clean up the problems with the subordinate article, which has been tagged for several months now as needing fact-checking. Thoughts? --[[User:Makaristos|Makaristos]] ([[User talk:Makaristos|talk]]) 15:33, 8 October 2008 (UTC)

==movia fanatic==

hi there, I was looking up Azazel due to the mention of him in the movie Fallen, and I know movies arent correct at all, but nothing in there mentions all this here. although one of the comments says it was Lucifers first name?

maybe we can add in there that he is mentioned in Fallen.

and are we totally sure that this is him and his role? as it seems to be in dispute &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:194.32.190.4|194.32.190.4]] ([[User talk:194.32.190.4|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/194.32.190.4|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

== Merge [[Azazel in popular culture]] back into the article. ==

As [[User:Makaristos|Makaristos]], I believe ''Azazel in popular culture'' is not worthy or interesting enough to support itself as a separate article; If nobody objects, I'll be moving back the above-mentioned page into [[Azazel]] in a week. EOZyo ([[User Talk:EOZyo|мѕğ]]) 03:38, 22 January 2009 (UTC)
:I object strongly. If you don't think it's a worthy article, delete it. Don't stuff it back in here. The popular culture section has little to do with the original mythological analyzed here, and is considerably more at home with all the other articles in [[:Category: In popular culture]] (the types of references, how they're made). If you look at a couple of the demon IPC articles, you'll see patterns repeated quite obviously. [[User:Mintrick|Mintrick]] ([[User talk:Mintrick|talk]]) 04:17, 22 January 2009 (UTC)

:Do it. I don't know why it's separate to begin with. That's absurd. Mintrick clearly has an ulterior motive. It has to be moved back. It's unsustainable as a separate article. It's just a list of references in popular culture. Why wouldn't that belong with the main article like every other list of references for something in popular culture. I'm confounded. Just do it. [[User:Jiminezwaldorf|Jiminezwaldorf]] ([[User talk:Jiminezwaldorf|talk]]) 16:05, 21 March 2009 (UTC)
::And what sort of ulterior motive might that be? Perhaps my chain of popular culture-related stores will flourish if I can advertise that Wikipedia has hundreds of different in Popular culture articles? Doubtless that is it.
::The material from the pop culture doesn't belong here because it's just a long laundry list of simple allusions to a common mythological figure, while this article has a serious discussion of founding and cultural significance.[[User:Mintrick|Mintrick]] ([[User talk:Mintrick|talk]]) 19:07, 22 March 2009 (UTC)

:::A concise summary is needed and are ''clearly'' related as all are about some diabolic creature. Yes to the merge. [[User:Casliber|Casliber]] ([[User talk:Casliber|talk]] '''·''' [[Special:Contributions/Casliber|contribs]]) 21:30, 16 April 2009 (UTC)
::::A fallacy. If Abraham Lincoln is deeply significant to my life, does that affect encyclopedic coverage of him? No, of course not. It affects me. And would belong at my article. Just like none of these things have been shown to be essential to an understanding of the mythological aspects of the entity in question. As for a &quot;concise summary&quot;: What exactly would that contain? Is there any evidence that any of these allusions has particular significance, and should be included? Because if there's one, the rest will creep in over time, I assure you, and you soon have no summarization going on at all. Or did you imagine some useless fluff like &quot;Azazel has appeared many times in works of popular media&quot;.? Because I can assure you that 90% of Wikipedia mythology articles could carry the exact same, utterly uninformative statement. 
::::No, the Pop culture material has the most in common with its category brethren as an article. And that is where it should remain. [[User:Mintrick|Mintrick]] ([[User talk:Mintrick|talk]]) 22:28, 16 April 2009 (UTC)

== Azazel in the Septuagint ==

καὶ ἐπιθήσει Ααρων ἐπὶ τοὺς δύο χιμάρους κλῆρον ἕνα τῷ κυρίῳ καὶ κλῆρον ἕνα τῷ ἀποπομπαίῳ.  καὶ προσάξει Ααρων τὸν χίμαρον ἐφ᾽ ὃν ἐπῆλθεν ἐπ᾽ αὐτὸν ὁ κλῆρος τῷ κυρίῳ καὶ προσοίσει περὶ ἁμαρτίας.   καὶ τὸν χίμαρον ἐφ᾽ ὃν ἐπῆλθεν ἐπ᾽ αὐτὸν ὁ κλῆρος τοῦ ἀποπομπαίου στήσει αὐτὸν ζῶντα ἔναντι κυρίου τοῦ ἐξιλάσασθαι ἐπ᾽ αὐτοῦ ὥστε ἀποστεῖλαι αὐτὸν εἰς τὴν ἀποπομπήν ἀφήσει αὐτὸν εἰς τὴν ἔρημον (LXX Lev 16:8-10)


The ancient writers of the Septugint (1st century BC), both in Israel and in the Diaspora apparently understood Azazel to be the &quot;the goat that is sent away.&quot;  As they were native speakers of the language, I should think that they are to be trusted more than Nachmanides or other much later commentators.  Nachmanides, though a scholar was not a native speaker.  By his lifetime (ca. 1200 AD) Hebrew was long a dead language existing in scholarly use only.  It is reminiscent of the debate over whether or not Isaiah prophesied that a virgin would give birth.  Many claim that &quot;almah&quot; simply meant &quot;young girl&quot; but the LXX witers translated it as &quot;parthenos&quot; clearly meaning virgin in Greek.  It is imperative not to try to guess at meanings of ancient words, but, whenever possible, to find out how the speakers themselves understood them.  

Furthermore, it makes no sense that a jealous God who tolerated no rivals would command sacrifice to a rival demon named Azazel.  It would have been such a glaring inconsistancy that it surely would have caused the Israelites much concern and would have generated much debate.  There is no evidence of any such debate.&lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Danwaggoner|Danwaggoner]] ([[User talk:Danwaggoner|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Danwaggoner|contribs]]) 03:58, 5 May 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:It would be great if there was some scholarly discussion supporting these points. I have little knowledge in the subject area but hwat you say seems to make sense. Just making sure we follow policy of no original research. [[User:Casliber|Casliber]] ([[User talk:Casliber|talk]] '''·''' [[Special:Contributions/Casliber|contribs]]) 06:13, 5 May 2009 (UTC)

:: It's not new research.  In addition to the LXX writers, Josephus described it in his &quot;Jewish Antiquities&quot; in which he described the azazel as &quot;a goat that was sent in the wilderness as as Averter of evil.&quot;  The idea of azazel being a demon or other being is the new idea.  Origen understood it that way, as well, and it was translated as &quot;caprus emissarius&quot; in the Vulgate by Jerome.[[User:Danwaggoner|Danwaggoner]] ([[User talk:Danwaggoner|talk]]) 02:26, 9 May 2009 (UTC)

::: Hebrew is not a dead language and is still in use today.  Biblical Hebrew is somewhat different from modern Hebrew; however, it is very much alive in Rabbinic work.  The Septuagint and other translations deviate from the Hebrew meaning, if for no other reason than words do not have the exact same meaning and inferences when translated to different languages.  In Judaism, the Hebrew text always defines cannon. No exceptions.  To classify the Septuagint as Jewish cannon is flat out incorrect, it is merely a translation of the true text (regardless of what a legend might say about how it was translated.)  You reference scholarly discussion as the only place Hebrew is alive.  I assume you are referring to Biblical Hebrew in Rabbinic work.  Since Rabbis are and have been the spiritual leaders of Judaism since the destruction of the Temple, classifying their work as scholarly is misleading.  Their work may be scholarly, but it is also the only spiritual/religious work.  Separating the scholarly work from the religious work of Rabbis cannot be done and, when done, demonstrates a lack of understanding on how Judaism functions.  I know I'm making some assumptions here, but the tone of the Hebrew Bible section of this article relates to Jewish thoughts/observance.

::: All that being said, I agree with the point of Danwaggoner's comments.  Creating a demon is inconsistent with Judaism and not found in the Jewish texts.  It is found in the book of Enoch, which is not included in Jewish scripture for a variety of reasons.  Most importantly for this section, the Book of Enoch is not a Hebrew text nor is it in the Hebrew Bible.

::: I recommend removing the comment &quot;Most scholars accept the indication of some kind of demon or deity.&quot;  Most Jewish scholars do not accept this, and it is a statement in the Hebrew Bible section.  Further, I can't verify the source for this comment (maybe it's incorrectly sourced?), but the Anchor Bible Dictionary is not a Jewish source, it's a compilation of various religions.  I recommend moving the discussion of the Septuagint out of the Jewish section, as it implies that the Septuagint is a Jewish source work, which it is not.  Also, the King James bible is certainly not an authority on the Hebrew Bible.  Further, the general term Septuagint can often be associated with the broader work than the original 5 Books of Moses, many of which were translated by individuals, with varying degrees of quality, and by authors who were not, themselves, Jewish. --[[User:Lamber111|Lamber111]] ([[User talk:Lamber111|talk]]) 14:59, 19 April 2011 (UTC)

== Previous merge from another work==
Most of what's now in this article is a copy and paste from the [[Jewish Encyclopedia]], which although its WP article says it's now a public domain work, still has a copyright notice at the bottom: [http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?letter=A&amp;artid=2203].  This seems to have been done in this edit [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Azazel&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=252750233], and good previous work seems to have been pasted over in the process. [[User:Per Ardua|Per Ardua]] ([[User talk:Per Ardua|talk]]) 10:09, 18 May 2009 (UTC)

Actually, nothing in the previous version of the article was eliminated, just moved around. As for the copyright notice, http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/terms.jsp says that &quot;2.1 You will use the Service and any content, material, or information found on the Service solely for lawful, non-commercial purposes.&quot; Wikipedia is lawful and non-commercial, most of the copyright stuff is meant to prevent folks from wholesale printing the site and claiming it is their publication. Plus, the Jewish Encyclopedia is public domain, so this means that we can use the actual text. JewishEncyclopedia.com can only copyright the presentation of this information, so we can't just have a bot copy the stuff from their site to ours like Indopedia, Experiance festival, and other websites do to Wikipedia. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 12:52, 18 May 2009 (UTC)

== Proposed merger ==

Shouldn't this page be merged with [[Azazel in popular culture]]? I don't see how [[Azazel in popular culture]] should stand on it's own as a separate article since there isn't enough content for that. [[User:Swollenfish|Swollenfish]] ([[User talk:Swollenfish|talk]]) 11:25, 31 December 2009 (UTC)

== Concurs, not confers. ==

 &quot;Gesenius in his Hebrew lexicon confers with this.&quot;  No he doesn't.  He concurs. 

[[User:Hypercallipygian|Hypercallipygian]] ([[User talk:Hypercallipygian|talk]]) 06:17, 6 April 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>aj7904870fowbny5tfmk84f228nujtz</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
