<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Book of Exodus</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>317135</id>
    <revision>
      <id>499373266</id>
      <parentid>499283780</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-26T00:58:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MiszaBot I</username>
        <id>3797869</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot: Archiving 2 threads (older than 60d) to [[Talk:Book of Exodus/Archive 4]].</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3029">{{WikiProject Religious texts|class=B| importance= high}}
{{WikiProject Bible|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Judaism | class= B | importance= high }}

{{archive box|
*[[Talk:Book of Exodus/archive1|Archive 1]]
*[[Talk:Book of Exodus/archive2|Archive 2]]}}  


{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 150K
|counter = 4
|minthreadsleft = 4
|algo = old(60d)
|archive = Talk:Book of Exodus/Archive %(counter)d
}}

== What are we doing with this: Mass Exodus. Redirect, merge or seperate article? ==

The instance in which a large group of people, animals, or objects attempt to leave, evacutate or move to a different location.

*Some famous exodus include the jewish exodus from Egypt to the promised lands.

*Refugees ussally partake in exodus from troubled lands.



It’s not an exodus unless it’s a mass exodus.

Redirect, merdge or seperate article?

[[Image:superche.jpg|thumb||Che!]]

== Book of Exodus ==

Is there a reason why the name of this article does not start with &quot;Book of&quot;?  All the other articles in the Old Testament category start that way, except for four of the five books of the Torah.  If there are no objections, I'll have it changed.

== Leave as is ==

Because of its controversy there is a lot of scope for expanding it, so I believe it should not be merged.

== Wikipedia pushing polemical, biased POV hypothesis as if undisputed fact ==

From article: &quot;the story of the infant Moses's salvation from the Nile has its basis in an earlier legend of king Sargon&quot;

The last I heard, this was only a rather flimsy hypothesis that was proposed within certain schools of thought, but was criticized by other theologians, who have pointed out far too many differences in the two accounts, and far too few similarities.  It is even disputed which was written first, since the view that Exodus was written in the 500s BC does not truly enjoy the monopoly that this POV pushing article pretends, whereas the Sargon birth legend is only known from very late Babylonian copies.  And yet, wikipedia POV pushing editors here want to take this biased, weak hypothesis and un-neutrally weigh in on one side of the controversy, endorsing the sources that agree with their own POV and they present it as it had suddenly been &quot;proven&quot; and accepted by all, and the question were now suddenly &quot;settled&quot;, or as if all those who are skeptical of this hypothesis suddenly disappeared or don't count any more. In all other cases of literature, a ''very high standard'' is required to show direct borrowing or plagiarism from one work to another, but here, the standard is much lower; the barest of faint similarities is being pushed forward as sufficient &quot;proof&quot; of borrowing, yet to my knowledge nothing new has actually turned up in the last several decades that would settle this controversy. 

There  are thus serious neutrality issues and POV pushing issues with this article.   [[User:Til Eulenspiegel|Til Eulenspiegel]] ([[User talk:Til Eulenspiegel|talk]]) 13:41, 25 June 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>sa5042nyfoy8kims2yt1hc7sz5uvjkt</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
