<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Mass (liturgy)</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>35666101</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519728966</id>
      <parentid>508826557</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-25T09:39:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yobot</username>
        <id>7328338</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Removed wilbot tag, removed: {{User:WildBot/m01|dabs={{User:WildBot/m03|1|Holy Matrimony}}|m01}} using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8463)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8994">{{Copied |from=Mass (liturgy) |from_oldid=482237169‎  |to=Mass (Catholic Church) |diff=http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Mass_%28Catholic_Church%29&amp;oldid=484639668 }}
{{WikiProject Christianity|class=C|importance=High|theology-work-group=yes|theology-importance=High|lutheranism=yes|lutheranism-importance=High|catholicism=yes|catholicism-importance=Top|anglicanism=yes|anglicanism-importance=High}}
{{User:WildBot/m04|sect={{User:WildBot/m03|1|Anglican Missal#The American Missal|American Missal}}|m04}}
{{Archive box| [[/Archive01]] }}

== Merger/Name Change ==
{{rfc top|'''No consensus''' to merge. - &lt;b&gt;[[User:Jc37|jc37]]&lt;/b&gt; 00:27, 17 August 2012 (UTC)}}

Only the Holy Sacrifice of the Mass, that is to say the Catholic Mass, is a Mass. Could the name or content of the article be updated to reflect that fact?  I propose merging Mass (liturgy) and Mass (Catholic Church) to: The Holy Sacrifice of the Mass. Protestant &quot;masses&quot; are actually services. They are not Masses. [[User:Andrewrp|Andrewrp]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Andrewrp|Tally-ho!]]&lt;/sup&gt; 15:39, 17 June 2012 (UTC)
:Hello User:Andrewrp, I do not agree with the proposal. In several Lutheran churches, the term ''Mass'' is the regular term used to describe the celebration of the Eucharist in these Churches. ''Ecclesia Lutherana: a brief survey of the Evangelical Lutheran Church'' states: {{quotation|Melancthon, the author of the Augsburg Confession, states, that he uses the words Mass and the Lord's Supper as convertible terms: &quot;The Mass, as they call it, or, with the Apostle Paul, to speak more accurately, the celebration of the Lord's Supper,&quot; &amp;c. The Evangelical Princes, in their protest at the Diet of Spires, April 19th, 1529, say, &quot;Our preachers and teachers have attacked and utterly confuted the popish Mass, with holy, invincivle, sure Scripture, and in its place raised up again the precious, priceless SUPPER OF OUR DEAR LORD AND SAVIOUR JESUS CHRIST, which is called THE EVANGELICAL MASS. This is the only Mass founded in the Scriptures of God, in accordance with the plain and incontestable institution of the Saviour.}}
:Stating that 'Protestant &quot;masses&quot; are actually services' might reflect your point of view; however Wikipedia must report the term if it is used by other denominations. This article correctly gives three sections on masses in the Catholic, Anglican, and Lutheran traditions. The separate article on [[Mass (Catholic Church)]] exists to discuss the concept in that Church specifically. Thanks, [[User:Anupam|Anupam]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Anupam|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 19:41, 17 June 2012 (UTC)

:I agree with Anupam: although a minority usage within Anglicanism, the term is used today by a significant group of parishes &amp; authors and I have heard it used by Lutherans. [[User:Jpacobb|Jpacobb]] ([[User talk:Jpacobb|talk]]) 22:36, 17 June 2012 (UTC)
:This discussion has been silent for two months now and I am asking for administrative closure.  In any case, a merger here would have to be to bring the Catholic article under the wing of the more general title.  People looking for information on non-catholic masses are not going to look at &quot;Mass (Catholic Church)&quot; whereas Mass (liturgy is a stepping stone in the right direction for the reverse search. [[User:Jpacobb|Jpacobb]] ([[User talk:Jpacobb|talk]]) 00:34, 15 August 2012 (UTC)
{{rfc bottom}}

== Changes to lead section ==

Apparently I have made a wide-ranging edit.  In fact, it has two objectives: (i) I considered that the vague phrase &quot;traditional (=highchurch) christian denominations&quot; was potentially misleading, and so have pulled the specific denominations forward from later in the article; and (ii) I have removed the main contents of the short &quot;For more information&quot; paragraphs to a hatnote and omitted the more specific Catholic ones since they are covered in the [[Mass (catholic church)]] where they logically belong.&lt;br /&gt;

The note&lt;br /&gt;

:&quot;{{cite book|title=Sound of Worship|author=Douglas R. Jones|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=LG8Ynbazk5AC&amp;pg=PA38&amp;dq=The+Anglican+use+the+term+Mass+to+describe+the+worship+service&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=QkzdT5DQD4Os9AT7ldXsCg&amp;ved=0CDkQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=The%20Anglican%20use%20the%20term%20Mass%20to%20describe%20the%20worship%20service&amp;f=false|publisher=[[Focal Press]]|date=9 September 2010|quote=The Anglican use the term Mass to describe the worship service, but is should be very clear that although again to the outsider there is very little discernible difference between an Anglican Mass and a Roman Catholic Mass, to the faithful in these two churches there are very important differences that must be respected.}}
puzzles me since it does not state what the important differences are.  I propose to replace it with a quotation from ´´Unitatis Redintegratio&quot; which states that the western churches and ecclesiastical communities lack the sacrament of orders and &quot;have not preserved the genuine and total reality of the Eucharistic Ministry&quot;. (sect. 22) but will do this as a second edit. [[User:Jpacobb|Jpacobb]] ([[User talk:Jpacobb|talk]]) 00:42, 18 June 2012 (UTC)
:Thanks for your comments and edits User:Jpacobb. In my opinion, [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Mass_%28liturgy%29&amp;diff=498104540&amp;oldid=498099523 this addition] is not really needed because it only portrays the Catholic perspective on the term. If you wish to keep that paragraph, however, you might want to balance it with the Lutheran view on the Catholic use of the term, as delineated in [[Mass_(liturgy)#cite_note-1|this citation]]. The reference that you cited above, by Douglas R. Jones, was only added to demonstrate that some Anglicans retain the use of the term ''Mass''. I hope this helps. With regards, [[User:Anupam|Anupam]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Anupam|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 02:45, 18 June 2012 (UTC)
::Thank you very much for your comments and explanations, they are much appreciated.  I incline to keep the final paragraph I have just added even though I included it in the lead section on the basis of a misunderstanding.  I sense it is a relevant point in its own right as a statement about current views.  For the moment I am not going to add a reference to Lutheran attitudes.  The quotation you suggest refers to 16th century attitudes and can be paralleled by quotes from Anglican sources from the same time.  While you can certainly find individual Lutherans and Anglicans today who would sympathise with these opinions, I suspect that the Church authorities would be far more cautious.  [[User:Jpacobb|Jpacobb]] ([[User talk:Jpacobb|talk]]) 15:12, 18 June 2012 (UTC)
:::You're welcome User:Jpacobb, my pleasure! I understand your line of reasoning. However, per [[WP:NPOV]], I still find it necessary to balance the final paragraph of the introduction with Lutheran and Anglican attitudes. To address the issue you presented, I will preface the statement with the word &quot;historically.&quot; After all, issues such as these were the reason for the Reformation and led to the formation of the Lutheran Church in the first place. In addition, I added a modern reference from the Lutheran Church that addresses the Catholic Mass from their point of view; this official statement is meant to corroborate the historical reference. I hope this helps. With regards, [[User:Anupam|Anupam]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Anupam|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 19:00, 18 June 2012 (UTC)

== Mass = entire church service? ==

While the statement in the lead section to the effect that &quot;In these denominations, the term Mass often colloquially refers to the entire church service in general.&quot; may well be true  (&quot;misa&quot; is frequently widened in this way in Chile); I am not sure that the reference given says this.  It seems to me to be saying that &quot;routine&quot; RC eucharists are termed &quot;masses&quot; as well as the more special ones. Furthermore, my impression is among Anglicans who use the term &quot;mass&quot; a clear distinction is preserved and non-eucharistic offices are referred to by their correct names.  While agreeing that many Protestants avoid the term &quot;mass&quot; they don't as far as I know use &quot;service of worship&quot; to refer to the sacrament of the Lord's Supper.  I'd appreciate someone with better knowledge and sources than mine, having a look at these two sentences. [[User:Jpacobb|Jpacobb]] ([[User talk:Jpacobb|talk]]) 17:29, 2 July 2012 (UTC)
:The sentence you question should be removed.  The cited source does not support it.  And its meaning is obscure.
:I myself know of no Protestant use of &quot;service of worship&quot; in English, but the existence of a Wikipedia article with that title suggests that the phrase is in use.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 20:15, 2 July 2012 (UTC)
::I have heard the term &quot;Service of Worship&quot; (and &quot;Worship Service&quot;) and seen it on church noticeboards but it is never used as far as I know for a Eucharist. On the other hand &quot;[[Eucharist#&quot;Eucharist&quot; and other names for the rite|Divine Service]]&quot; is.(  [[User:Jpacobb|Jpacobb]] ([[User talk:Jpacobb|talk]]) 21:31, 2 July 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>1t1s7j0cbci19vhazv5s97vkp1z4h61</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
