<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Tosefta</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2642569</id>
    <revision>
      <id>340120670</id>
      <parentid>250911261</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-01-26T12:13:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Magioladitis</username>
        <id>1862829</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>expanding WikiProject Religious texts to make it reabale, replaced: WPRT2 → WikiProject Religious texts using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2774">{{WikiProject Religious texts|class=B}}
{{WikiProject Judaism | class=B | importance= high }}
I would think that Shaul Leiberman's &quot;Tosefta ki-Feshutah&quot; is the definitive commentary on tosefta, (instead of Rabbi Abramsky's work) although I'm not sure how one goes about proving that. Would you look at citations?, sales? conduct a poll of scholars?
20:19, 8 September 2005 (UTC)

:No argument there. Most of the citations of Tosefta study I have come across cite [[Saul Lieberman|Shaul (Saul)Lieberman's]] work as the definative study of the Tosefta.  His work is widely used in Orthodox circles as well as non-Orthodox works.  (JTS Press has been selling his work to Orthodox rabbis for years. Apparently its one of Orthodoxy's little secrets, like the way that some Orthodox rabbis order copies of CJLS teshuvot from the Rabbinical Assembly.  Not that they need to do so anymore, since the RA published most of their teshuvot, and then put many of them online.) [[User:RK|RK]] 03:11, 29 November 2005 (UTC)

::If we can't find a source verifying which edition is considered authoritative and by whom, we should take that piece out. Additionally, unless there is a reason not to, I'd like to remove the distinction between Orthodox and Non-Orthodox editions because it doesn't seem to add any real informational content. --[[User:Yonkeltron|yonkeltron]] ([[User talk:Yonkeltron|talk]]) 16:31, 10 November 2008 (UTC)

:Tosefta Kifshuta is '''the''' authoritative &quot;critical&quot; edition.  Period.  There are other commentaries, of course, but as for critical editions Lieberman's is it.  I cited [[Jacob Neusner]] to prove the point, although almost any other scholarly work on Mishnah and Tosefta could have been used.  I specifically chose Neusner because Liebrman strongly criticized Neusner's scholarship in an article published posthumously.  Neusner, has ever since been embroiled in an academic battle over his methodology and scholarship, and, subsequently has been severely critical of Lieberman.  However, even Neusner calls Lieberman's Tosefta Kifsutha &quot;masterful&quot; and uses it extensively in his works.  I beleive that Lieberman's work was not completed and only encompasses 3 or 4 of the six Sedarim.  However, I am not certain of this.
: As for Orthodox use of Lieberman: Anectodtaly, I know Orthodox Rabbis who use Tosefta kifshuta and Yerushalmi kifshuta.  I also know that even the editors of Artscroll's Yerushalmi edition consult Lieberman's work regularly - Although that doesn't mean that they ascribe to it's explanations. It does indicate that his works are respected by most everyone as having enormous scholarly value.[[User:Guedalia D&amp;#39;Montenegro|Guedalia D&amp;#39;Montenegro]] ([[User talk:Guedalia D&amp;#39;Montenegro|talk]]) 17:39, 10 November 2008 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>66h4lj1l87t75lwrdcbmzek9elvvvuw</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
