<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Religious cosmology</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>3612716</id>
    <revision>
      <id>497799204</id>
      <parentid>497799075</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-16T00:40:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Vblanton</username>
        <id>710269</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>added signature and timestamp to what i wrote</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5498">{{WPReligion|class=|importance=|Interfaith=yes|InterfaithImp=}} 
I added Zoroastrian Cosmology, realizing it will probably be me who ends up writing it. If there is a wish for me to complete it sooner than later, or I've completely forgotten about it (which is likely), please remind me, I'd be happy to receive the impetus/reminder. If someone wishes to tackle it, use [http://www.avesta.org/pahlavi/bundahis.html The Bundahishn] as your source. [[User:Khirad|Khirad]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Khirad|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 03:09, 4 January 2006 (UTC)

== neutrality/accuracy ==

The opening of this article is incredibly misleading.  Religious cosmologies, while they may be accepted by religious individuals, are in no way &quot;epistemologically valid.&quot;  

The claim that science rests on religious foundations is truly a tired, old, and frankly ridiculous argument.  One of the greatest virtues of science is that it allows us to ''overcome'' our religious mythologies by evaluating claims in terms of empirically verifiable facts.  If its basis were religious in nature, it would have no greater claim to objectivity than religious cosmologies.  This is not the case.  Science relies on hard facts, not mythological tradition.  

The claim that religious cosmologies constitute valid epistemology is not simply biased, it is flat-out false.  [[User:Hewn|Hewn]] 11:30, 21 February 2006 (UTC)

----
I have changed this description to be more objective. [[User:Mikecap|Mikecap]] 19:31, 1 April 2006 (UTC)

== Islam Section.... ==

Needs some rewriting. Someone happily vandalized the islamic section. Leafy 15:46, 23 October 2006 (UTC)

I think there is a mistake in the translation of the verse number 51:47. The correct translation reads as 'With power and skill did We construct the Firmament: for it is We Who '''create the vastness of space''',' instead of '''Steadily Expanding it''' '. I hope a trained scholar of Arabic language will realize it. (Ali Khan)

I have checked some old tafsirs as follows. They says Allah created the universe and do the expansion thereof. So please try to put it as it is.
1) With Hands We constructed the heaven. Verily, We are able to expand the vastness of space thereof. - Ibn Kathīr (1301-1373 CE)
2) (We have built) created (the heaven with might, and We it is who make the vast extent (thereof)) as We will; it is also said that this means: we expand the provision thereof. - Tafsir Ibn Abbas (618–619 CE)
(Fazil)  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/122.172.244.152|122.172.244.152]] ([[User talk:122.172.244.152|talk]]) 19:06, 20 September 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== WERK ==
Hey, I just created this account becasue I read something on this article that disturbed me. I know that no one agrees on how to interpret the word &quot;day&quot; in Genesis, but the line, &quot;Note that a 'Genesis day' is most probably to signify a prolonged period of time&quot; is a personal bias. I wanted to change it, but I am not a Wikipedian. So I wanted to put it out there, that maybe one of you could edit it into a block that tells about the two different interpratations or something like that. Cause when I went to that other article that was said to cover it extensively, I could find nowhere that it did -that phrase I mean. I might be over reacting, but, as a Christ Follower, I do not want people who are looking for Genesis related material to think that this is what it is most likely to mean. 1:19, 4 December 2006

Well... I don't know how to put up a nuetrality bulliten thing so... I am going to change it... If you don't like it you can change it back... Thanks?? 12:36 16 December 2006

== Jain Cosmology ==

The calculation of the Rajjus into light years looks incorrect as per the definition of Rajju.

== Hebrew Bible ==

Where does the Hebrew Bible talk of &quot;a flat, circular Earth floating like a bubble in an apparently infinite ocean of water&quot;?  There is nothing to that effect in Genesis, nor in [[Rashi]]'s commentary.  Is there any such thing in the [[Midrash]] on [[Bereshit Rabba|Bereshit]]?  [[User:Marshall46|Marshall46]] ([[User talk:Marshall46|talk]]) 18:31, 29 August 2010 (UTC)

== Hinduism ==

This section needs to be looked at for both neutrality, impartiality and supportive citations. The opening statement that Hinduism is the closest religion to the big bang theory (and other findings of &quot;Science&quot;) smacks of being written by a religious supporter of Hinduism. Seeking to legitimize their religions, one can find similar statements amongst adherents to other religions. For example, the many books on scientific alignment of the Bible and the Old Testament. Also, statements contradictorily switch between defining Hindu cosmology as one overarching system and as a multitude of systems that all fall under the category/umbrella of &quot;Hindu&quot; religions. --[[User:Vblanton|Vblanton]] ([[User talk:Vblanton|talk]]) 00:40, 16 June 2012 (UTC)

== Mayan ==

Would a section explaining why 2012 is important to the Mayan cosmology and a whole paragraph on their view of the cosmos and calendar be acceptable here?  It's a dead religion but seems relevant because people keep making movies and news about the end of the world based on their 2012 end of an epoch (not the world).  [[Special:Contributions/97.85.163.245|97.85.163.245]] ([[User talk:97.85.163.245|talk]]) 21:06, 24 January 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>bdbaaofwqgnz1x7wcyzthfg6k6mwc83</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
