<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Christmas</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>7334</id>
    <revision>
      <id>512226048</id>
      <parentid>512225833</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-13T18:39:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Moxy</username>
        <id>8729451</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Help:Reverting|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/205.250.77.215|205.250.77.215]] ([[User talk:205.250.77.215|talk]]) to last version by Carl.bunderson</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27468">{{User:MiszaBot/config
|maxarchivesize = 200K
|counter = 7
|minthreadsleft = 4
|algo = old(59d)
|archive = Talk:Christmas/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=/Archive index
|mask=/Archive &lt;#&gt;
|leading_zeros=0
|indexhere=yes}}
{{Talk header|search=yes}}
{{Auto archiving notice|bot=MiszaBot I|age=59|dounreplied=yes}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=PR
|action1date=21:06, 24 Aug 2004
|action1link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Christmas/archive1
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=5429354
|action2=FAC
|action2date=14:11, 23 Dec 2004
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Christmas/archive1
|action2result=promoted
|action2oldid=8749989
|action3=FAR
|action3date=07:14, 1 January 2006
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article removal candidates/Christmas/archive1
|action3result=demoted
|action3oldid=8777491
|action4=FAC
|action4date=21:48, 8 August 2006
|action4link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Christmas/archive2
|action4result=not promoted
|action4oldid=68299441
|action5=PR
|action5date=20:11, 1 January 2007
|action5link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Christmas/archive2
|action5result=reviewed
|action5oldid=97780556
|action6=GAN
|action6date=December 9, 2007
|action6link=Talk:Christmas/Archive 5#GA review
|action6result=Failed
|action6oldid=176587872
|action7=FAC
|action7date=17:23, 15 December 2008
|action7link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Christmas/archive3
|action7result=not promoted
|action7oldid=258065303
|action8=GAN
|action8date=05:45, 24 November 2010
|action8link=Talk:Christmas/GA1
|action8result=not listed
|action8oldid=398566937
|currentstatus=FFA
|topic=Philosophy and religion
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Christianity|class=B|importance=Top|portal=yes}}
{{WikiProject Holidays|class=B|importance=Top|Christmas=yes|Christmas-importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Festivals| class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject United States|class=B|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=B|importance=Top}}
}}
{{To do}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2005-01-07|oldid1=16335093|date2=2005-12-25|oldid2=31086283|date3=2006-01-07|oldid3=34190575|date4=2006-12-25|oldid4=96457352|date5=2007-01-07|oldid5=99005316|date6=2007-12-25|oldid6=179699601|date7=2008-01-07|oldid7=182270557|date8=2008-12-25|oldid8=260068680|date9=2009-01-07|oldid9=262524144|date10=2009-12-25|oldid10=333976906|date11=2010-01-07|oldid11=336361895|date12=2010-12-25|oldid12=404191049|date13=2011-01-07|oldid13=406027089|date14=2011-12-25|oldid14=467657919|date15=2012-01-07|oldid15=470145231}}

== Dates of celebration ==

There was never any issue of celebrating Christmas on May 28, April 18 or the other dates given. Some early writer suggested that Jesus was born on one of these dates. Christmas is by definition on December 25. If John Chrysostom said Jesus was born on some other date, why is that relevant? No modern scholar thinks that the date of Christmas has anything to do with the actual date Jesus was born on. Including this material just confuses the issue. [[User:Kauffner|Kauffner]] ([[User talk:Kauffner|talk]]) 04:00, 8 April 2012 (UTC)
:Christmas is the celebration of the birth of Christ, and thus a section discussing the &quot;Date of Celebration&quot; should include relevant information in full. Although this feast is now celebrated by the Western Church on December 25, we must also include the dates of previous celebrations. In addition, Christmas is celebrated by the Eastern Orthodox Church on January 7. Stating that &quot;For centuries, Christian writers accepted that Christmas was the actual date on which Jesus was born&quot; makes it seem like these writers were incorrect; in actuality, the date was not an issue. It is also important to retain mention of the reason of the celebration for the modern Church. These things are all relevant to a section discussing the &quot;Date of celebration.&quot; On the other hand, I think that the current section &quot;In 1743, German Protestant Paul Ernst Jablonski argued Christmas was placed on December 25 to correspond with the Roman solar holiday Dies Natalis Solis Invicti and was therefore a 'paganization' that debased the true church&quot; is a tangential assertion that is irrelevant to the section. I hope this helps. With regards, [[User:Anupam|Anupam]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Anupam|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 04:56, 8 April 2012 (UTC)
::There was never any celebration on most of these dates. Chrysostom and the rest were just speculating about this issue. You can calculate the birth for whatever day of the year you want. Is every date &quot;Christmas&quot;? We have have a separate [[nativity]] article for this stuff. The theory that Christmas is derived from some pagan Roman holiday is an extremely common one. I don't think there is anything to this theory myself, but the article needs to explain why someone might think this. You think Jesus was actually born on Dec. 25? That doesn't even sound like modern times. You need to base your arguments on modern reliable sources. [[User:Kauffner|Kauffner]] ([[User talk:Kauffner|talk]]) 06:04, 8 April 2012 (UTC)
:::No, I do not think that Jesus was born on December 25. I do, however, think that an article on &quot;Christmas&quot; should discuss, in brief, the various dates chosen for the birth of Christ under a section titled &quot;Date of celebration.&quot; I do find John Chrysostom's comment to be relevant, even if he was speculating, because as a [[Church Father]], he was very influential in choosing the date. Although I would prefer to leave it in, as a [[WP:COMPROMISE|compromise]], I will not object if you remove the section which states  &quot;That shepherds watched the flocks by night in the fields in the winter time is supported by the phrase &quot;frost by night&quot; in Genesis 31:38-40. A special group known as the shepherds of Migdal Eder (Gen. 35:19-21, Micah 4:8) watched the flocks by night year round pastured for Temple Sacrifice near Bethlehem&quot; if you still would like to trim the section. I hope this helps. With regards, [[User:Anupam|Anupam]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Anupam|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 06:15, 8 April 2012 (UTC)
::::The section would still be taking Chrysostom's theory way too seriously. I note that ''[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/03724b.htm The Catholic Encyclopedia]'' refers to this theory as Chysostom's &quot;unwarranted assumptions about Zachary.&quot; Chrysostom's sermon was delivered after Christmas was already an established feast. So it is a ''post facto'' justification, not a explanation of why the Dec. 25 date was selected. [[User:Kauffner|Kauffner]] ([[User talk:Kauffner|talk]]) 06:27, 9 April 2012 (UTC)
:::::It was a ''post factum'' justification for adopting for celebration also in Chrysostom's area the date of 25 December (as already established in the west) instead of 6 January.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 09:17, 9 April 2012 (UTC)
::::::I know what you mean, but I still feel the need to nitpick: Christmas was never on any date other than December 25. January 6 is Epiphany. The holiday already had this name in Chrysostom's time. Anyway, I think it is clear that the Zacharias material is getting undue emphasis. [[User:Kauffner|Kauffner]] ([[User talk:Kauffner|talk]]) 01:12, 10 April 2012 (UTC)
Changing &quot;In the earliest centuries of Christianity, no particular day of the year was associated with a celebration of the birth of Jesus.&quot; to &quot;For centuries, [[Christian]] writers accepted that Christmas was the actual date on which Jesus was born.&quot; seems substantial to me. Why removing the fact that no particular day was associated with the ''celebration''? Was it wrong? This was now done twice [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Christmas&amp;diff=486180179&amp;oldid=486178254] [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Christmas&amp;diff=486558591&amp;oldid=486482391] by the same [[User:Kauffner|user]]. [[User:HTML2011|HTML2011]] ([[User talk:HTML2011|talk]]) 04:31, 10 April 2012 (UTC)
:The section is entitled &quot;Dates of Celebration&quot;. There was a list of dates: &quot;May 28, April 18 or 19, March 25, January 2 or 6, November 17 or 20.&quot; But these dates are not dates anyone ever celebrated on, except in the sense that Epiphany is Jan. 6, Annunciation March 25, and whatnot. The version I wrote was stable for a long time. [[User:Kauffner|Kauffner]] ([[User talk:Kauffner|talk]]) 05:10, 10 April 2012 (UTC)
::Sorry, Kauffner, but I find that your change must simply be reverted.  Beginning the section about the date of celebration with &quot;For centuries Christian writers accepted that Christmas was the actual date on which Jesus was born&quot; leaves the reader with the impression that, until recently, Christian writers always accepted 25 December as the actual date.  This statement of yours is clearly false, as the information that you deleted clearly indicates that the earliest Christian writers proposed, on the contrary, quite a variety of dates.  And as well as being contradicted by sourced information that you deleted without explanation, your statement is unsourced: citing the fact that ''one'' 18th-century writer argued for the authenticity of the 25 December date is no proof that for centuries (which?) Christian writers (without exception?) accepted the 25 December date.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 06:00, 10 April 2012 (UTC)
:::&quot;When speculation began, Christians proposed many different dates: May 28, April 18 or 19, March 25, January 2, November 17 or 20. &quot; This is a totally unsourced statement. No reference. Nothing. What is the point of a list of dates anyway? As for Jan. 6, in ancient times Epiphany was primarily about the baptism of Jesus -- it was not Christmas on another day. [[User:Kauffner|Kauffner]] ([[User talk:Kauffner|talk]]) 06:42, 10 April 2012 (UTC)
::::I tend to agree with User:Esoglou and User:HTML2011 here. By the way, the reference is located after the consequent sentence. It just needs to be appropriately formatted. Cheers, [[User:Anupam|Anupam]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Anupam|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 07:08, 10 April 2012 (UTC)
:::::You mean ''Mercer''`s? No, it doesn't give any of these dates. The problem seems to be....that I am causing offense by implying that scholarship has advanced since the Middle Ages? Susan Roll, the source I cited, has a couple of pages documenting the early historiography of this subject. [[User:Kauffner|Kauffner]] ([[User talk:Kauffner|talk]]) 07:54, 10 April 2012 (UTC)
::::::I hope I have solved your puzzlement by using &quot;ref name=&quot;  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 08:48, 10 April 2012 (UTC)
A common question readers have is, &quot;Why is Christmas on December 25?&quot; I created this section some years ago so that there would be a place in the article were the various views and theories on this subject could be summarized and this question answered concisely. But now the section has a lengthy first paragraph in IMO sidetracks the reader and presents a fringe view of the issue. Chrysostom's views may be significant historically, but no modern writer thinks they are at all plausible. There is no basis to say what day of the year Jesus was really born, and no mainstream reference will tell you anything else. [[User:Kauffner|Kauffner]] ([[User talk:Kauffner|talk]]) 16:58, 10 April 2012 (UTC)
:An important part of the answer to that common question is to make clear from the outset that Christians have not always celebrated Christmas on 25 December, that this date has been chosen from among several candidate dates, and indeed that there are still Christians who have not accepted the 25 December date and have preferred to maintain a date that was in earlier use for the celebration.  Other more modern sources could be cited for Chrysostom's view, but citing Chryostom serves to indicate in what period the change to the 25 December date occurred in his area, and to indicate an argument that was in fact used at that time, whether valid or not does not really concern us at this point (I think it is baseless), in favour of making the change.  All this is in full accord with your statement that &quot;there is no basis to say on what day of the year Jesus was in fact born&quot;.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 18:40, 10 April 2012 (UTC)
Christmas is by definition on December 25. January 6 is [[Epiphany (holiday)|Epiphany]]. It was celebrated as Epiphany in Chryostom's time, and it is still celebrated as Epiphany in modern times. No, it is not older than Christmas. The earliest reference for it is dated 361. January 6 was the winter solstice on the Egyptian calendar. So when Rome placed Christmas on the Roman calendar solstice, Eastern Christians created a feast on a corresponding date according to their local calendar. [[User:Kauffner|Kauffner]] ([[User talk:Kauffner|talk]]) 23:46, 20 April 2012 (UTC)
:Not everyone would agree with your opening statement.  I think the majority would agree instead with the statement, &quot;Christmas is (by definition) an annual celebration of the birth of Jesus Christ celebrated generally on December 25 as a religious and cultural holiday by billions of people around the world&quot;.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 06:46, 21 April 2012 (UTC)
::Christmas is &quot;a Christian feast on December 25 or among some Eastern Orthodox Christians on January 7 that commemorates the birth of Christ&quot;, or so says [http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/christmas Merriam Webster]. I should point out that the Orthodox also celebrate on Dec. 25. They just calculate the date by a different calendar. We don't have define &quot;Christmas&quot; here. My point is just that Christmas is not the same as Epiphany, Annunciation, or any of the other extraneous dates given in this section. [[User:Kauffner|Kauffner]] ([[User talk:Kauffner|talk]]) 08:05, 21 April 2012 (UTC)
:::[http://www.armeniapedia.org/index.php?title=Armenian_Christmas Armenians celebrate Christmas on 6 January.] They don't fit into the &quot;general&quot; practice of celebrating Christmas on (Gregorian or Julian) 25 December. Even ignoring its survival to this day among the Armenians, 6 January was the date of the celebration of the birth of Jesus generally in eastern Christianity, persisting long in Egypt and even to the mid-6th century in Jerusalem (see [http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;tbo=1&amp;q=hastings+%22of+his+birth+in+the+flesh%22&amp;btnG= Hastings, ''A Dictionary of Christ and the Gospels'', vol. 1,] [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/03724b.htm Cyril Charles Martindale, &quot;Christmas&quot; in ''Catholic Encyclopedia'').]  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 08:37, 21 April 2012 (UTC)
::::The Armenian church celebrates Epiphany on January 6, just like every other Christian church. I'm sure you can find some source somewhere that says everyday is Christmas. [[User:Kauffner|Kauffner]] ([[User talk:Kauffner|talk]]) 00:51, 12 May 2012 (UTC)
:::::The cited source does say that &quot;Armenians celebrate Christmas on 6 January&quot;, doesn't it?  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 08:09, 12 May 2012 (UTC)
::::::In ''[http://books.google.com.vn/books?id=TW1hvJAOUiEC&amp;dq= Rituale Armenorum]'', the rites book for the Armenian church, the section on the rites for January 6 is entitled, &quot;Of the holy feast of the Epiphany of our Lord&quot;. The calendar for the Armenian church is given on pages 529-532. January 6 is given as &quot;''Epiphany'' of our Lord&quot;. There is no mention of Christmas. [[User:Kauffner|Kauffner]] ([[User talk:Kauffner|talk]]) 14:14, 12 May 2012 (UTC)
:::::::No contradiction: &quot;In the Armenian Church, we celebrate the birth ''and'' the Theophany&quot; (emphasis added),[http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;hl=en&amp;q=Manoogian+%22birth+and+the+Theophany%22] as was once done throughout the East (cf. sources cited above).  6 January (19 January if Julian 6 January is translated into Gregorian) ''is'' Armenian Christmas.[http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;hl=en&amp;q=Scott+%22original+January+6+date%22][http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;hl=en&amp;q=Mandel+%22Armenian+Christmas%22][http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;hl=en&amp;q=Tourian+%22choice+of+January+6%22][http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;hl=en&amp;q=Fedorova+%22had+their+Christmas%22][http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;hl=en&amp;q=Hajinian+%22Armenian+Christmas%22][http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;hl=en&amp;q=Kirakosi%EF%B8%A0a%EF%B8%A1n++%22Armenian+Christmas%22][http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;hl=en&amp;q=Kerr+%22Armenian+Christmas%22]  Many other reliable sources could be added for that statement.  Now how about citing some reliable source that would back up your assertion that Armenians do ''not'' celebrate Christmas on 6/19 January or that would say they celebrate it on some other date, such as 25 December?  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 15:47, 12 May 2012 (UTC)
::::::::Traditionally, this feast was &quot;Epiphany.&quot; &quot;Armenian Christmas&quot; is a modern idiom, like calling [[Hanukkah]] &quot;Jewish Christmas.&quot; Idioms like &quot;Christmas in August&quot; or &quot;Christmas every day&quot; are common too, but they don't tell you anything about the actual date of Christmas. On the modern [http://66.208.37.78/index.jsp?sid=1&amp;id=15830&amp;pid=33&amp;lng=en Armenian liturical calendar], January 6 is &quot;Holy Nativity and Theophany of our Lord Jesus Christ&quot;. This doesn't specify Christmas or Epiphany, but that's just a translation issue. I don't see any basis to say that the Armenian Church recognizes Christmas as January 6, or as any other date for that matter. Numerous references define Christmas as a feast held on December 25.[http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/christmas][http://www.thefreedictionary.com/Christmas] No matter how you define a word, there will somebody, somewhere who defines it differently. [[User:Kauffner|Kauffner]] ([[User talk:Kauffner|talk]]) 05:06, 13 May 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::Modern idiom or not, Armenians do call 6 January Christmas.  Thank you for presenting a source that confirms that even the Church calls 6 January &quot;Holy ''Nativity'' (= Christmas) and Theophany of our Lord Jesus Christ&quot;, celebrating in the same feast the birth and the baptism of Christ,[http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;hl=en&amp;q=Bullard+%22both+the+birth%20of%20Jesus%22][http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;hl=en&amp;q=Deirdre+Holding+%22both+the+birth+of+Jesus%22] as the Latin Church celebrates in its Epiphany feast the visit of the Magi, the baptism of Christ and the wedding feast at Cana. Reliable sources ''explicitly'' state that the Armenian Apostolic Church &quot;observes Christmas&quot; on 6/19 January.[http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;hl=en&amp;q=Kurian+%22observes+Christmas%22][http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;hl=en&amp;q=%22Bella+Waters%22++%22observe+Christmas%22][http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;hl=en&amp;q=MobileReference+%22observes+Christmas%22][http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;hl=en&amp;q=Sharan+%22observes+Christmas%22][http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;hl=en&amp;q=Lennox+%22Armenian+church+puts%22]  That is surely enough.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 08:12, 13 May 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::I guess I should have known that Merriam Webster and ''Rituale Armenorum'' aren't in the same league as an illustrious recipe book like ''All About Christmas''. This used to a nice article before it got rewritten by people who don't know the difference between Christmas and Epiphany, and, it seems, Annunciation and other holidays as well. [[User:Kauffner|Kauffner]] ([[User talk:Kauffner|talk]]) 09:56, 13 May 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::::[[WP:OR]]: neither Merriam-Webster nor Conybeare's ''Rituale Armenorum'' denies that 6/19 January is the date on which the Armenian Apostolic Church or Armenians in general celebrate Christmas.  Abundant sources say that 6/19 January is their Christmas.  Merriam-Webster's Encyclopedia of World Religions says the Armenians refused to abandon, as other eastern Christians did, having a festival on 6 January that commemorated both the birth and the baptism of Jesus,[http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;hl=en&amp;q=Doniger+%22both+the+birth%22] with the result that, for the Armenian Church, as you know, 6 January is the &quot;Holy ''Nativity'' and Theophany of our Lord Jesus Christ&quot;.  Conybeare is in reality a positive witness to Armenian celebration of Christmas on 6 January: he writes of &quot;two systems of calendar, one of which placed ''Christmas'' on December 25, the other on January 6 ... the Armenians oscillated from one ''Christmas'' date to the other&quot; and in the early eighth century &quot;returned to January 6 as the date of ''the birth-feast''&quot;.[http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;hl=en&amp;q=Conybeare+%22oscillated+from+one+Christmas%22] [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 16:42, 13 May 2012 (UTC)

The fact that Christmas is not mentioned on the Armenian liturgical calendar, either the traditional or the modern version, should be more than enough right there. I shouldn't have to prove that something doesn't happen. But here are references for Armenian non-celebration of Christmas:
*&quot;To this day, the Armenian church — still the major form of Christianity in Iran — observes Nativity on January sixth and does not observe Christmas at all.&quot; ''[http://books.google.com.vn/books?id=lwLf22iB5QUC&amp;pg=PA75&amp;dq=#v=onepage&amp;q=Armenian%20%22not%20observe%20Christmas%22&amp;f=false Journey of the Magi]'' (2006)
*&quot;The Armenians do not observe Christmas&quot; ''[http://books.google.com.vn/books?id=9koNAQAAMAAJ&amp;q=%22The+Armenians+do+not+observe+Christmas%22#search_anchor Encyclopaedia of religion and ethics]'' (1961)
*The Armenians &quot;still do not observe Christmas as a separate feast&quot;. ''[http://books.google.com.vn/books?id=1ALZAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=%22not+observe+Christmas%22#search_anchor The Christian churches of the East]'' (1961)
There are certainly many references to Epiphany as &quot;Armenian Christmas&quot;, but not nearly as many as there are to Hanukkah as &quot;Jewish Christmas&quot;.[http://books.google.com.vn/books?id=9BxHqlTZ3jIC&amp;pg=PA7&amp;dq=#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Jewish%20Christmas%22&amp;f=false][http://books.google.com.vn/books?id=cRgBkBWk_B4C&amp;pg=PA324&amp;dq=#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Jewish%20Christmas%22&amp;f=false][http://books.google.com.vn/books?id=0Yq_z5LaCjsC&amp;pg=PA148&amp;dq=#v=snippet&amp;q=%22Jewish%20Christmas%22&amp;f=false] This sort of loose usage is not evidence as to the literal date of the Christmas feast. [[User:Kauffner|Kauffner]] ([[User talk:Kauffner|talk]]) 03:52, 14 May 2012 (UTC)
:May we agree that, if Christmas is understood as the annual Christian celebration of the birth of Jesus (understood thus by the vast majority of sources), the Armenian Church and people do observe it (on 6/19 January), but if Christmas is understood as 25 December (understood thus by the first two sources you cite, and by some others that you do not cite), the Armenian Church and people do not observe that date at all?
:(Your third citation agrees with the many sources that say Armenians celebrate Christmas (birth of Jesus) in combination with Epiphany (baptism of Jesus), not as a separate feast, thus keeping to what was once the general practice in the east apart from Jerusalem, where 6 January was observed as a celebration of the birth alone.)  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 06:34, 14 May 2012 (UTC)

== Images in celebration section ==

[[File:NativitySceneCharlesPoerson.JPG|thumb|upright|left|''The Nativity'' by [[Charles-François Poerson]], 1667.]]
What does this image in the middle of the /intro/ of the celebration section tell the reader? [[User:HTML2011|HTML2011]] ([[User talk:HTML2011|talk]]) 11:35, 8 April 2012 (UTC)
===Date of celebration===
[[File:Advent Wreath (Broadway United Methodist Church).jpg|thumb|left|On Christmas Day, the Christ Candle in the center of the [[Advent wreath]] is traditionally lit in many [[church service]]s.]] What does this image at the start of the section &quot;Date of celebration&quot; tell about the date??? There is [[Christmas decoration]] for such things. I move it there. [[User:HTML2011|HTML2011]] ([[User talk:HTML2011|talk]]) 18:40, 9 April 2012 (UTC)

== Bad Reference in&quot;History&quot; section? ==

I have accessed the online copy of the document referenced (reference #38) for the quotation which begins this section :  &quot;It is cosmic symbolism...&quot; and I have been _unable to locate the quoted material_ anywhere in this document.  Here is the link:

http://www.scribd.com/doc/33490806/Hijmans-Sol-The-Sun-in-the-Art-and-Religions-of-Rome+Sol,+the+sun+in+the+art+and+religions+of+Rome&amp;ct=clnk

As this article appears to be locked against editing (why??), perhaps one of the Wikipedia powers-that-be would either:  1) Provide the correct source for the quote; or, if none can be found, 2) delete the bogus quote and replace it with something else.

I would also mention that it was anything but easy to locate this source.  Given Wikipedia's recent widely publicized committment to /verifiability/, perhaps something quoted from a more available source -- perhaps something which could be obtained through the average public library -- would be more appropriate.

Thanks for looking into this.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/74.92.174.105|74.92.174.105]] ([[User talk:74.92.174.105|talk]]) 22:35, 20 April 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

::::I fixed the reference. Yes, it really is in the book. There is now a link to the online version. I don't think it can be any easier to verify than that. [[User:Kauffner|Kauffner]] ([[User talk:Kauffner|talk]]) 23:11, 20 April 2012 (UTC)

:::::OK, the new link takes me to a very long, very slow-loading, very BLANK web page.  I thought perhaps one needed a Scribd account to view the document, so I opened one, but although the page has the -title- shown in the link, is is still blank other than a few generic links at the top (e.g., to Twitter), and some advertising at the very bottom.  No article; no text.  Alleged &quot;links&quot; to download or print the article are inactive (clicking on them does nothing).  Then I thought perhaps this might be a browser issue, so I retried using IE, FireFox and Opera.  Same result -- nada.
:::::I see that the ISBN links to a list of libraries having the printed document, so I'll try to find one of those eventually.  But the &quot;on-line&quot; document doesn't seem to be available.
::::::Curiouser and curiouser:  I just searched for the ISBN using ten different online book search engines (all listed by Wiki), and according to all of them this book does not exist.  Yet &quot;OttoBib&quot; produces bibliographic information for the source.
::::::Mind mentioning where you actually -saw- this quote?  Thanks.
:::::::I don't have any problem reading Scribd myself. [http://www.mulinodiamleto.it/mulino-di-amleto/concetti-di-base/steven-hijmans-sol-invictus-the-winter-solstice-and-the-origins-of-christmas Here] is an HTML version of the book. It used to be a scanned Google Book, but was it was apparently removed at some point. [[User:Kauffner|Kauffner]] ([[User talk:Kauffner|talk]]) 02:36, 1 May 2012 (UTC)

== Complete list of celebration day ==

Theres is missing a list o clebration day

As for my countries , Denmark is celebrat on the on 24 December,, i alsosheard som countries celbration on 6 of janury and diffrent dates. [[Special:Contributions/85.83.42.75|85.83.42.75]] ([[User talk:85.83.42.75|talk]])  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|undated]] comment added 00:23, 29 July 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!--Template:Undated--&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;</text>
      <sha1>7rs2ipz103wd0hpmedacdpepbgugj0o</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
