<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Massacre of the Innocents</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>20883994</id>
    <revision>
      <id>513438417</id>
      <parentid>513381004</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-18T21:34:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Springnuts</username>
        <id>724914</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Massacre or Slaughter? */ checking?</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20655">{{Talk header}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Christianity|class=B|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject Saints|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Bible|class=B}}
{{WikiProject Death|class=b|importance=mid}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2004-12-28|oldid1=10140039|date2=2005-12-28|oldid2=33001813|date3=2006-12-28|oldid3=96139521|date4=2007-12-28|oldid4=180564072|date5=2008-12-28|oldid5=260493234|date6=2009-12-28|oldid6=334538557|date7=2010-12-28|oldid7=404659498|date8=2011-12-28|oldid8=468172618}}

== historical and textual context ==

I added it, as it had been missing. Properly, the massacre is understood in the context of the historical Herod and Matthew's narrative and agenda. Did some reorg, too. [[User:Leadwind|Leadwind]] ([[User talk:Leadwind|talk]]) 17:56, 16 March 2009 (UTC)

== Non-neutral, sided to the &quot;fiction&quot;/atheist view. ==

This is HEAVILLY weighted and one-sided toward the atheist/&quot;this is fiction&quot; side, as they claim it as Biblical depictions of Holy Men, how it is excluded from biographies of Harod the Great, even saying the Nativity is Biblical fiction.


How is that neutral? Wikipedia is unbiased, and is to show us both sides. Other then reference of &quot;Ambrosius Theodosius Macrobius, Saturnalia, book II, chapter IV:11&quot;, that's about the only &quot;evidence&quot; that the genocide happened. The article actually dismisses it, over and over again.


How do you call this neutral? &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Most recent biographers of Herod therefore do not regard the massacre as an actual historical event,[3] but rather, like the other nativity stories, as creative hagiography.&quot;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Weasel words! Who claims this?



&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;The gospel of Matthew was written c 80 - 85 by an anonymous Christian appealing to a Jewish audience.&quot;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


First off, the Gospel of Matthew was written ''by'' Matthew, not an &quot;annonymous Christian&quot;, according to theology. You failed to bring it up. That is not neutral.


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;The story was patterned on the Exodus story of the killing of the Hebrew firstborn by Pharaoh and the birth of Moses.&quot;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

This is biased toward atheism and &quot;fiction&quot;. Not only is it [[blasphemy]], it also contradicts the Bible itself, and though you have the right to type it, this is WAY too one sided. Again, this not a ''parody'' of Exodous to Christians! It's history to them! As an un-biased, neutral website devoted to telling ALL sides of the story, I believe you should add some more SUPPORT fro this instead of saying &quot;it's fiction, it's fiction, it's fiction, here's a secular reference. it's fiction, it;'s fiction&quot;.....


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;The story is not mentioned by the contemporary Jewish historian Josephus, nor in the other gospels, nor in the early apocrypha.&quot;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


Again, you are dismissing it as FICTION, and provide little backup on evidence that is real!


'''''WIKIPEDIA IS NEUTRAL'''''! What ever happened to neutrral1 ''This is the most one-sided article I've laid eyes on''!


Someone, please fix it! &lt;br /&gt;
--[[Special:Contributions/74.184.65.160|74.184.65.160]] ([[User talk:74.184.65.160|talk]]) 12:29, 27 March 2009 (UTC) &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;

:———————————

:Actually, virtually no scholars today believe the Gospel of Matthew was written by the Apostle Matthew, so saying it was written by an anonymous Christian is both accurate and neutral. —[[User:Angr|'''An''']][[User talk:Angr|''gr'']] 12:56, 27 March 2009 (UTC)

:———————————

:Please correct me if I am wrong.  Neutrality in an encyclopedia is not the politically correct or diplomatic treatment of a topic.  It is the unbiased treatment of facts.  Unbiased in the language and unbiased in the display of available facts.  In other words, no facts are left out.  These facts may be supported by the opinions of professionals and scholars.  Their opinions must always be qualified by &quot;So-and-so believes...&quot;.  These become judgment calls and must be weighed as such.  However, their judgment holds much more weight than the layman's.  Think of it as a fair trial with all of the available evidence and top professionals and scholars.  Without the lawyers.  Sometimes lawyers bring in biased language and intentional skewing of the facts.  Out with them.  The judge and jury?  The readers of the articles.  However, their verdict is not the ultimate say in the truth of the matter.  They may draw the wrong verdict.  Ever see &quot;The Shawshank Redemption&quot;?

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
:'The story is not mentioned by the contemporary Jewish historian Josephus, nor in the other gospels, nor in the early apocrypha.'
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

:Again, you are dismissing it as FICTION, and provide little backup on evidence that is real!&quot;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

:The quote from the article is highlighting the scant &quot;evidence that it is real.&quot;  It is not being dismissed.  Rather, the Biblical claim is not being verified.  To create an accurate history, historians seek verification through multiple sources, the more the better.  In this case, verifying sources have not been found.  The account in Matthew is the only one.  Historians are very reluctant to put all their cookies in one jar, especially for high profile events.  [[User:MangyMaestro|MangyMaestro]] ([[User talk:MangyMaestro|talk]]) 10:30, 29 March 2009 (UTC)
::I agree that the article is one-sided, however, I might need to point out that wikipedia is written by many contributors and that you cannot cast out any blame at any author, just say that the article is biased.
::Concerning the article itself and its claims, I have read in &quot;[[The Case for Christ]]&quot; the interviews, done by [[Lee Strobel]], with thirteen leading evangelical apologists: [[Craig Blomberg]], [[Bruce Metzger]], [[Edwin Yamauchi]], [[John McRay]], [[Gregory Boyd]], [[Ben Witherington III]], [[Gary Collins]], [[D.A. Carson]], [[Louis Lapides]], [[Alexander Metherell]], [[William Lane Craig]], [[Gary Habermas]], and [[J. P. Moreland]].  Then the view that the massacre never took place is countered with the fact that it probably &quot;only&quot; was 25-30 boys that were killed by Herod, which would seem totally irrelevant to the historic scribes (or whatever their proper English names might be) of the day.  It also note that the deed was totally in agreement with what is known about Herod's character and I heard at a TV-program during Christmas that virtually all historians considers it to be in his character, even though they doubt it.
::Since the interviewees are wellknown scholars (or at least some), their view might be included. --[[User:KMA &amp;quot;HF&amp;quot; N|KMA &amp;quot;HF&amp;quot; N]] ([[User talk:KMA &amp;quot;HF&amp;quot; N|talk]]) 10:00, 30 March 2009 (UTC)

&quot;This is HEAVILLY weighted and one-sided toward the atheist/&quot;this is fiction&quot; side... How is that neutral?&quot; Editors are just reporting what historians say. That's neutral. When WP discusses evolution, it reports what scientists say because that's neutral, even if some people have supernatural reasons to disagree with it, just like some people have supernatural reasons to disagree with what historians say. [[User:Leadwind|Leadwind]] ([[User talk:Leadwind|talk]]) 22:40, 29 December 2009 (UTC)

:Wikipedia attempts to offer concise reports of the scholarly mainstream. It does not guarantee authenticity of episodes narrated in texts, but describes and reports. This is not Sunday-school: there is no special reverence for &quot;Scripture&quot; afforded in Wikipedia: these are historical texts, with cultural contexts and manuscript traditions to be reported, just the same as [[Sophocles]] . Claims that Wikipedia violates NPOV do invariably turn out to be cries of &quot;not ''my'' point-of-view&quot;.--[[User:Wetman|Wetman]] ([[User talk:Wetman|talk]]) 01:13, 30 December 2009 (UTC)
::I do not oppose the sentence itself, I only oppose to the repeating of it in the article.  It was in the lead AND the section I removed, which is totally unnecessary.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|signed]] comment added by&lt;/small&gt; [[User:Mythsearcher|MythSearcher]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Mythsearcher|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;  06:58, 13 January 2010 (UTC)

== Roman Syria ==

[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Massacre_of_the_Innocents&amp;curid=67762&amp;diff=286355985&amp;oldid=285688745 This deletion] of sourced material, with an edit summary contradicting what appears to be a [[WP:RS|reliable source]], needs explaining. If Judea was not in [[Roman Syria]] at that time, was Herod ordering assassination of infants outside his own jurisdiction? - [[User:Fayenatic london|Fayenatic]] [[User talk:Fayenatic london|(talk)]] 12:31, 27 April 2009 (UTC)
:According to [[Iudaea Province]], the province of Iudaea was not created until AD 6 (i.e. after the Massacre of the Innocents), and it implies that the region was part of the province of Syria until then. —[[User:Angr|'''An''']][[User talk:Angr|''gr'']] 12:52, 27 April 2009 (UTC)
::Herod was an independent king (however qualified his independence was in practical terms). Bethlehem was part of his kingdom, but his kingdom was not part of any Roman province. [[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 03:05, 30 April 2009 (UTC)
Also since Herod the Great died in 4 BC how could he order the &quot;Massacre of the Innocents&quot; in 1 AD?!
Why has no one added this bit of info so far? [[Special:Contributions/89.210.189.119|89.210.189.119]] ([[User talk:89.210.189.119|talk]]) 15:21, 23 October 2009 (UTC)
:Historians don't credit this as a historical event, so the gospel contradictions are sort of beside the point. [[User:Leadwind|Leadwind]] ([[User talk:Leadwind|talk]]) 22:35, 29 December 2009 (UTC)

== Nativity story in the Gospel of Matthew ==

POV tag added - as this is a non representative and unduly sceptical view.  [[User:Springnuts|Springnuts]] ([[User talk:Springnuts|talk]]) 20:59, 15 January 2010 (UTC)
:I have therefore had a [[WP:BOLD|go]] at simplifying and improving, and rm'd the tag.  [[User:Springnuts|Springnuts]] ([[User talk:Springnuts|talk]]) 21:09, 15 January 2010 (UTC)

I made a small change re Matthew's account of the magi. Original said: &quot;magi from the east follow a star to Judea&quot;. But the text doesn't say that the magi **followed** a star to Judea, only that the magi **saw** a star (actually, the &quot;King of the Jews' star&quot;) in the east, so went to Jerusalem. [[User:GDon|GDon]] ([[User talk:GDon|talk]]) 18:39, 24 November 2010 (UTC)GDon.

== Historicity ==

Multiple issues in this reversion [[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Massacre_of_the_Innocents&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=340584712&amp;oldid=340541612]]
- &quot;Most&quot; recent biographers.  On its own this is a bit of a [[WP:WEASEL|weasel]] word.  Why not &quot;It has been claimed that most ...&quot; - which is a sourced statement and unexceptional.
- &quot;recent&quot; ... again, bit weaselly.  Is it implied that being recent makes them more likely to be accurate?  
- &quot;biographers&quot; ... but actually the views of historians in general might give a fairer sample.
I don't want to do edit warring: might a third party have a go at a non POV revision?
[[User:Springnuts|Springnuts]] ([[User talk:Springnuts|talk]]) 16:47, 29 January 2010 (UTC)
:I removed the section today, since the issues above are not addressed.  As currently written it has balance (Some historians ...  whilst others ...).  I would have no objection to the sceptical historian being restored, if examples of the others are added, and will do that when I have time ! -  [[User:Springnuts|Springnuts]] ([[User talk:Springnuts|talk]]) 18:07, 11 February 2010 (UTC)

::It was reinstated by anon editor(s), and I rearranged it again. The historian is now quoted, and the sceptical views are justifiable encyclopedic content; I do not think it is right to remove them while looking for balancing views. It would of course be appropriate to add sourced examples of credible scholars who reach other conclusions. - [[User:Fayenatic london|Fayenatic]] [[User talk:Fayenatic london|(talk)]] 21:35, 11 February 2010 (UTC)

:::Thanks - happy with your edit and will try to add sourced stuff idc.  [[User:Springnuts|Springnuts]] ([[User talk:Springnuts|talk]]) 23:14, 11 February 2010 (UTC)

Link to news report saying infanticide in the Roman world of the time was not so shocking as infants below the age of two was not regarded as a person:
http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/10384460  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/86.162.138.204|86.162.138.204]] ([[User talk:86.162.138.204|talk]]) 02:20, 17 August 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== historicity doubts - body and heading, or body only? ==

Hi, there is a bit of [[WP:EDIT WAR|ping pong]] on the horizon re this topic, see this diff [[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Massacre_of_the_Innocents&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=347873722&amp;oldid=347815290]] and check history for others. It would be good to head it off at the pass. We are dealing with a contested [[argument from silence]].

The lead section should 'summarize the most important points—including any notable controversies'.  I would suggest two things follow: 

1)  The ref to numbers is removed - since there seems little controversy that the 'tens of thousands' figure is not believed, see eg the Catholic Encyclopedia: [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/07419a.htm].  Given that the lead already calls Bethlehem a village, there is no need to spell out the now generally accepted estimates of numbers, though it could be added in if wished.

2) The section of the lead re historicity is rewritten: &quot;Many modern writers treat the story as fiction.&quot; is one sided.  Would an editor not involved so far have a go at a non POV summary of this notable controversy please?

Hope this may provide a better way ahead.  [[User:Springnuts|Springnuts]] ([[User talk:Springnuts|talk]]) 09:19, 5 March 2010 (UTC)

:Have had a go at a non POV summary, changing &quot;Many modern writers&quot; to &quot;Some historians&quot;.  [[User:Springnuts|Springnuts]] ([[User talk:Springnuts|talk]]) 11:01, 6 March 2010 (UTC)

::Fair enough. Biographers of Herod are not necessarily representative of all historians writing on the subject. - [[User:Fayenatic london|Fayenatic]] [[User talk:Fayenatic london|(talk)]] 12:57, 6 March 2010 (UTC)

::No reason to drop the quote out of the text. The Historicity section has lost well-supported text, which I've restored.--[[User:Wetman|Wetman]] ([[User talk:Wetman|talk]]) 17:01, 14 March 2010 (UTC)

:::Please read [[WP:NPOV]]. The way to write a neutral article is not to treat both sides equally. The way to write a neutral article is to portray both sides the way they're portrayed in mainstream sources. If there is a majority viewpoint (with most historians favoring one view or the other), then it's biased to treat the two views as if they are equal. In this case, we should treat the majority viewpoint as the majority viewpoint and the minority viewpoint as the minority viewpoint. Violating NPOV is not really an option. Please humbly stick with what our best sources say rather than changing the article to suit your personal viewpoint. [[User:Leadwind|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;Leadwind&lt;/font&gt;]] ([[User_talk:Leadwind|talk]]) 14:19, 15 March 2011 (UTC)

:::Here's one section on WP:NPOV that's relevant to the majority/minority viewpoint: &quot;Accurately indicate the relative prominence of opposing views. Ensure that the reporting of different views on a subject adequately reflects the relative levels of support for those views, and that it does not give a false impression of parity, or give undue weight to a particular view.&quot; Historians mostly don't think the massacre really happened because there's no corroborating evidence (such as it being mentioned anywhere else in the Bible). I know it can hurt people's feelings to be in the minority, but on WP it's important to distinguish between majority and minority viewpoints. It's also the honest thing to do. If you can find a source that says most Christians think it's true, then we can talk about that, too, as long as it's separate from what most historians think is true. [[User:Leadwind|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;Leadwind&lt;/font&gt;]] ([[User_talk:Leadwind|talk]]) 14:30, 15 March 2011 (UTC)

::::I think the difficulty here arises from Maier's quote about &quot;most modern biographers ...&quot;.  It is quite possible that Maier is overstating the case &lt;u&gt;against&lt;/u&gt; historicity in order to justify his journal article, which argues &lt;u&gt;for&lt;/u&gt; historicity (and from my reading of Maier's article most of the &quot;biographers of Herod&quot; he speaks of are dependent on secondary rather than primary sources).  It is certainly an act of academic rigour to ensure you give full justice to opposing views, which Maier (imo) does.  The other part of the trouble is that many of those who comment in the literature have a pre-sharpened axe to grind.  Fortunately whether the incident really happened or not is of no interest to Wikipedia - only reflecting what is written by scholars.  My conclusion: find more verifiable stuff to balance the Maier's quote.  Hope this helps - and suggests positive ways forward!  [[User:Springnuts|Springnuts]] ([[User talk:Springnuts|talk]]) 17:48, 15 December 2011 (UTC)

The lead currently states that &quot;There are historians who view the event as non-historical.&quot; This seems to imply that such a view is not the majority view, and that would seem to be false. Are there ''any'' sources that claim that 'many' or 'most' scholars accept the story as real? If not, the lead should more accurately present the majority viewpoint.--[[User:Jeffro77|&lt;span style='color:#365F91'&gt;'''Jeffro'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style='color:#FFC000'&gt;''77''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Jeffro77|talk]]) 08:44, 29 December 2011 (UTC)

== Lead ==

&quot;historicizing&quot;??? [[User:Mannanan51|Mannanan51]] ([[User talk:Mannanan51|talk]]) 19:29, 30 May 2011 (UTC)mannanan51

:the verb &quot;to historicize&quot; is derived from &quot;history&quot; and means: &quot;to prove that something has actually happened like it's written in history books&quot;. [[Special:Contributions/93.219.169.49|93.219.169.49]] ([[User talk:93.219.169.49|talk]]) 18:10, 7 June 2011 (UTC)

::Actually, &quot;historicize&quot; means &quot;To make or make appear historical&quot; or &quot;To use historical details or materials.&quot;  The Oxford online dictionary defines it as &quot;treat or represent as historical&quot;--[[User:BruceGrubb|BruceGrubb]] ([[User talk:BruceGrubb|talk]]) 18:44, 27 August 2011 (UTC)
:::“When I use a word,&quot; Humpty Dumpty said in rather a scornful tone, &quot;it means just what I choose it to mean - neither more nor less.” [[User:Springnuts|Springnuts]] ([[User talk:Springnuts|talk]]) 17:31, 15 December 2011 (UTC)

== Reversion of heading section. ==

I have (here: [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Massacre_of_the_Innocents&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=468606661&amp;oldid=468336808]) changed the article back for four reasons:

1.  &quot;Some accounts&quot; suggests that there are a number of accounts of the massacre, varying in their count of the dead.  In fact there is one account, Matthew's, which does not give an estimate. 
 
2. &quot;... number them at more than 10,000&quot; - The number in the high thousands (I believe in an orthodox liturgy) is (I understand) of 144,000 - ie it is a symbolic numbering (cf the martrys in the Revelation to John) rather than a mathematical  estimate as such. 

3. &quot;Most modern historians&quot; - One source (Maier) says &quot;most modern biographers of Herod&quot;.    This is very different to a consensus of sources that &quot;most modern historians ....&quot;

4. The open-ness of the historicity question should be reflected in the summary.

[[User:Springnuts|Springnuts]] ([[User talk:Springnuts|talk]]) 15:14, 30 December 2011 (UTC)
:Do ''any'' historians state that it happened, or that it is likely to have happened?? Do ''any'' offer any ''evidence''?--[[User:Jeffro77|&lt;span style='color:#365F91'&gt;'''Jeffro'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style='color:#FFC000'&gt;''77''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Jeffro77|talk]]) 15:16, 30 December 2011 (UTC)

== Massacre or Slaughter? ==

It's a very minor point, but is 'Massacre of the Innocents' the standard terminology for this event?  In England, at least, I think 'Slaughter of the Innocents' is more common.[[Special:Contributions/109.158.131.253|109.158.131.253]] ([[User talk:109.158.131.253|talk]]) 12:33, 18 September 2012 (UTC)
:Slaughter is the term with which I too am familiar. [[User:Daniel the Monk|Daniel the Monk]] ([[User talk:Daniel the Monk|talk]]) 14:53, 18 September 2012 (UTC)
::Might be worth checking in some older standard textbooks.  [[User:Springnuts|Springnuts]] ([[User talk:Springnuts|talk]]) 21:34, 18 September 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>7fmlmgwfdoepd11t241to9niga4ikqm</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
