<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Rosh Hashanah</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>19596435</id>
    <revision>
      <id>513287982</id>
      <parentid>513010595</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-18T00:03:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Adding/updating {{OnThisDay}} for 2012-09-17.  Errors? [[User:AnomieBOT/shutoff/OnThisDayTagger]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24093">{{WikiProject Judaism | class= B | importance= high }}
{{WikiProject Holidays|class=B}} 
{{OnThisDay|date1=2004-09-15|oldid1=6183565|date2=2005-10-03|oldid2=24604640|date3=2006-09-22|oldid3=76980934|date4=2007-09-12|oldid4=157468809|date5=2007-09-13|oldid5=157312006|date6=2008-09-29|oldid6=241684738|date7=2008-09-30|oldid7=242039474|date8=2009-09-18|oldid8=314730557|date9=2009-09-19|oldid9=314731381|date10=2010-09-08|oldid10=383552132|date11=2010-09-09|oldid11=383568924|date12=2011-09-28|oldid12=452844508|date13=2011-09-29|oldid13=453072822|date14=2012-09-16|oldid14=512779957|date15=2012-09-17|oldid15=513188464}}
{{WP Israel|class=B|importance=high}}
{{merged-from|Feast of Trumpets (Christian holiday)|6 March 2010}}

==Date==
Gregorian dates for Jon Chungs asianness 2003 to 2007 from http://www.jewfaq.org/holiday2.htm#Dates as of 2004-12-17t14:44z.[[User:Jeandré| &amp;mdash; Jeandré]]
:I'd prefer to switch the language from &quot;sunset&quot;, and replace it with &quot;evening&quot;. By using the ambiguous word &quot;evening&quot; in all locations, we would be very NPOV, inclusive both of the common view that Jewish holidays start at sunset but don't end until nightfall, and also inclusive of the views (if any) that they really do end at sunset. What do others think? --[[User:Keeves|Keeves]] 12:49, 17 September 2006 (UTC)
::I feel that simply &quot;sunset&quot; should be NPOV enough. It is more clear than &quot;evening,&quot; and twilight/evening is really an extension of sunset, both in halakha and semantically. --[[user:Eliyak|Eliyak]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Eliyak|T]]&lt;/small&gt;·&lt;small&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Eliyak|C]]&lt;/small&gt; 03:09, 18 September 2006 (UTC)
:::Semantically, no: [[Sunset]] is when the sun goes below the horizon, and is an entirely different event than [[dusk]], which occurs later, when a certain degree of darkness arrives. They are different halachic events as well, and the halacha is uncertain as to whther the day ends when the ''sun'' is no longer visible, or when ''its light'' is no longer visible. To say that the holiday ends '''at''' sunset is simply wrong, and I will continue to fight it. A detailed discussion of this point is not appropriate for this article (it belongs in &quot;Hebrew Calendar&quot; or &quot;Jewish Holidays&quot; or something like that), and this article should keep it simple. My preference remains for either &quot;begins at sunset&quot; and &quot;ends at nightfall&quot; (or dusk), or to use &quot;evening&quot; at both ends. I hope more people will add their comments to this discussion. --[[User:Keeves|Keeves]] 12:09, 18 September 2006 (UTC)
::::Okay, there have been no other comments or suggestions, so I am now changing it to &quot;evening&quot;. --[[User:Keeves|Keeves]] 12:05, 22 September 2006 (UTC)
:::The proper word should be &quot;sundown.&quot; All Jewish days properly begin at &quot;sundown&quot; and end at sunset, as the article states. All the refernces in the article should be changed accordingly, I believe. I changed one, but I don't have the time to do more. [[User:66.108.106.230|66.108.106.230]] 13:31, 22 September 2006 (UTC) Allen Roth
::::Before I get into a dispute, I want to make sure we have defined our terms. My understanding is that &quot;sundown&quot; and &quot;sunset&quot; mean the same thing, namely, the moment when the sun passes below the horizon and is no longer visible, even though the sky is still bright. Further, my understanding is that although there are varying views in the Talmud and other authorities, in actual practice, all Jews agree that we must begin observing a holiday (however you want to define observance) no later than when the sun goes below the horizon, and that (when the holiday draws to its end) one must continue that observance '''past''' that point, and can end the holiday only when a certain degree of darkness has arrived. Is that how you understand these things? Thanks! --[[User:Keeves|Keeves]] 17:17, 22 September 2006 (UTC)

So, say that it begins on erev yontif at sunset, and then when it ends --- by nightfall?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/68.13.156.249|68.13.156.249]] ([[User talk:68.13.156.249|talk]]) 05:35, 28 August 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
: Indeed. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 06:28, 28 August 2011 (UTC)

==Traditions and customs==
==In the Hebrew Bible==
==In rabbinic literature==
==External link==

----
'''''Discussion:'''''

==Table.==
&lt;table border=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;2&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; width=&quot;300&quot;&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td colspan=&quot;3&quot; bgcolor=&quot;chocolate&quot;&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;font size=&quot;+1&quot;&gt;'''Rosh Hashanah'''&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&quot;orange&quot;&gt;Observed by:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td bgcolor=&quot;#ffde80&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;[[Judaism|Jews]]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&quot;orange&quot;&gt;Name&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td bgcolor=&quot;#ffde80&quot;&gt;[[Hebrew language|Hebrew]]: '''&amp;#1512;&amp;#1488;&amp;#1513; &amp;#1492;&amp;#1513;&amp;#1504;&amp;#1492;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&quot;orange&quot;&gt;Meaning:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td bgcolor=&quot;#ffde80&quot;&gt; &quot;Beginning of the year&quot;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&quot;orange&quot;&gt;Begins:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td bgcolor=&quot;#ffde80&quot;&gt;29th day of Elul
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&quot;orange&quot;&gt;Ends:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td bgcolor=&quot;#ffde80&quot;&gt;2nd day Tishri 
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&quot;orange&quot;&gt;Occasion&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&quot;#ffde80&quot;&gt;Jewish spiritual new year&lt;/br&gt;
Beginning of the Days of Awe&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&quot;orange&quot;&gt;Symbols:&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&quot;#ffde80&quot;&gt;Challah bread and [[honey]]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&quot;orange&quot;&gt;Related to:&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=&quot;#ffde80&quot;&gt;
[[Yom Kippur]]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

To the one who made this table,
That was excellent idea, and nicely done! Shana Tova! [[User:MathKnight|MathKnight]] 13:19, 15 Sep 2004 (UTC)

: However, it would be better if it was correct.  It starts when Elul 29 ''finishes'', i.e. at sunset, not ''on'' Elul 29.  I'll fix that.  You might want to explain the phrase &quot;spiritual new year&quot; which will confuse many people (what other new year is there?). --[[User:Zero0000|Zero]] 14:38, 15 Sep 2004 (UTC)

:The idea and table was by [[User:Neutrality|Neutrality]] however I'm not sure who put it in. &amp;mdash; [[User:Ilyanep|&lt;span style=&quot;color:gray;&quot;&gt;Il&amp;gamma;&amp;alpha;&amp;eta;&amp;epsilon;&amp;rho;&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Ilyanep|&lt;span style=&quot;color: #333333;&quot;&gt;(T&amp;alpha;l&amp;kappa;)&lt;/span&gt;'']] 21:11, 21 August 2005 (UTC)

==How many days?==
This article says &quot;''Rosh Hashanah occurs 162 days after the first day of Pesach''&quot; but [[New Year]] says 163 days.  I added an external link to this article that has a formula for determining the exact dates, but the formula is so convoluted I can't figure out if 162 is correct, 163 is correct, or sometimes one or the other.  Anyone?  [[User:SWAdair|SWAdair]] | [[User talk:SWAdair|Talk ]] 05:34, 1 Nov 2004 (UTC)
In modern times, 162 is definitely wrong.  I know R.H. has come on Saturday, because I remember Yom Kippur being on the day Columbus Day was observed in the U.S., and R.H. is always 1 week and 2 days before Yom Kippur.  Since 162 days is 23 weeks and 1 day, the day that is 162 days before a Saturday is always a Friday, but Passover never starts on a Friday using the current calendar, which is odd because it did on the day of the Crucifixion.  

From the first of Nisan (14 days before Passover) to Rosh Hashanah or from the first day of Passover to the first day of Succot (14 days after RH) is 30+29+30+29+30+29 = 177 days.  From the first day of Passover to RH is 14 days less, or 163 days.

However, when the lengths of the months were determined by sighting the moon visually, and not by a fixed cycle, there could be variation in the amount of time from Passover to RH.[[Special:Contributions/71.109.149.60|71.109.149.60]] ([[User talk:71.109.149.60|talk]]) 04:47, 26 November 2010 (UTC)

==Quartanzans?==

Do these exist? The poster has a track record of nonsense/suspect edits. [[User:Charles Matthews|Charles Matthews]] 11:43, 20 Feb 2005 (UTC)
:See [[Talk:Matzo]]. [[User:68.81.231.127|68.81.231.127]] 23:55, 20 Feb 2005 (UTC)

==Rosh hashanah on a Wednesday==
The article says that Rosh Hashanah is never on a Wednesday, but then it shows that 9/12/07 is Rosh Hashanah, which is a Wednesday!
:It must be an error, unless it says that it begins at sunset... which if you look at that table, it does say that.  My calendar says Rosh Hashanah on Thursday, 9/13/2007, which on a common calendar is still a Wednesday, 9/12/2007. [[User:CJLippert|CJLippert]] 03:56, 22 September 2006 (UTC)

== WikiProject Holidays ==

'''You may be interested in the WikiProject, [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Holidays|WikiProject Holidays]], a WikiProject that will focus on standardizing articles about Holidays. It has been around for quite some time, but I'm starting it up again, and would like to see some more members (and our original members) around the help out. Cheers.''' &amp;mdash; [[User:Ilyanep|&lt;span style=&quot;color:gray;&quot;&gt;Il&amp;gamma;&amp;alpha;&amp;eta;&amp;epsilon;&amp;rho;&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Ilyanep|&lt;span style=&quot;color: #333333;&quot;&gt;(T&amp;alpha;l&amp;kappa;)&lt;/span&gt;'']] 21:11, 21 August 2005 (UTC)

== Rapture ==

Shouldn't there be a section explaining the Christian belief that the rapture will fall during Rosh Hashanah.

:If you could first explain what &quot;rapture&quot; means and what proportion of Christians attach any significance to Rosh Hashanah... [[User:Jfdwolff|JFW]]&amp;nbsp;|&amp;nbsp;[[User_talk:Jfdwolff|&lt;small&gt;T@lk&lt;/small&gt;]] 13:45, 22 September 2006 (UTC)

== Rosh Hashana is not the Jewish new year ==
The Jewish new year is in Nissan as stated in Exodus 12:2 &quot;This month shall be for you the beginning of all months, it shall be for you the first of the months of the year.&quot; It is a biblical commandment that Nissan be thought of as the first month, not Tishrei. Rosh Hashana is the day that the Jews believe the world was created, it is therefore the earth's new year, not the Jewish new year. [[User:DeFender1031|DeFender1031]] 20:31, 21 September 2006 (UTC)
:Good point, but as I see it, it is just semantics. Yes, Nisan is most definitely the first of the months. But there are other ways to look at years also. I compare it to the concept of a fiscal year or a school year. Is it wrong for schoolchildren to end their vacation with the comment that &quot;The new year is starting soon&quot;? I think not. --[[User:Keeves|Keeves]] 23:52, 21 September 2006 (UTC)
::I understand, my father (he's a rabbi) often uses the idea of fiscal year and school year to explain the concept of Judaism having multiple new years. However, I still say that it is a biblical commandment that nissan be the Jewish new year. The point you make about semantics is the reason I didn't edit the article directly. Because I DO hear the argument for it to be allowed to be called the Jewish new year (also given that the year number changes at this point) . Furthermore, it is widely referred to as such. I just find it interesting that that description came about. [[User:DeFender1031|DeFender1031]] 01:49, 22 September 2006 (UTC)

:&quot;Rosh Hashanah&quot; means &quot;head of the year&quot;. I agree with the metaphor of the fiscal year, and I stand behind the article's present intro that states that RH is only one of the Jewish new years. But it is translated widely as &quot;Jewish New Year&quot; and see no reason to disclaim this further. [[User:Jfdwolff|JFW]]&amp;nbsp;|&amp;nbsp;[[User_talk:Jfdwolff|&lt;small&gt;T@lk&lt;/small&gt;]] 13:45, 22 September 2006 (UTC)

::Yes, &quot;Rosh Hashana&quot; does mean &quot;head of the year&quot;, however the term is not used biblically. Biblically it is referred to as &quot;yom hazikaron&quot; meaning &quot;day of rememberance&quot;. Furthermore, it is not referred to as &quot;Rosh Hashana&quot; in the prayers either. The earliest mention of &quot;Rosh Hashana&quot; to my knowledge is mishnaic. [[User:DeFender1031|DeFender1031]] 17:11, 24 September 2006 (UTC)
:::''Not to be confused with [[Yom Hazikaron]] on the 4th of Iyar.[[User:Aleph4|Aleph4]] 12:58, 27 September 2006 (UTC)

Rosh Ha Shanah is the Seventh Month, not the First Month, so it is not the Jewish &quot;new year&quot;. --- Leviticus 23:24 --- &quot;[...]On the '''first day of the SEVENTH month''' you are to have a day of rest, a sacred assembly commemorated with trumpet blasts&quot; --- It is unncessary to add &quot;the Jewish New Year&quot; to your title, since it is misleading as well as incorrect. [[User:84.101.119.9]] 02:41, September 24, 2006

The [[Talmud]] section on [[Rosh Hashanah]] begins with a statement that 

:There are four New Years. The first of Nissan is the new year for kings and for festivals. The first of Elul is the new year for the tithe of animals...The first of Tishrei is the new year for years...

Since Rosh Hashana is a festival, it is dated from the new year for festivals. But since it is the new year for years, the calendar changes on Rosh Hashanah. Judaism of course follows the Talmud on this one, As is often the case, the [[Hebrew Bible]] alone won't explain Jewish practice. (FYI the 4th new year is the new year for trees, on the 15th of Shevat). --[[User:Shirahadasha|Shirahadasha]] 01:52, 27 September 2006 (UTC)
:::See [[Tu Bishvat]].[[User:Aleph4|Aleph4]] 12:58, 27 September 2006 (UTC)

It is the new year in that it is when a year starts, for example, when 5770 ends and 5771 begins.  The terms &quot;1st month&quot;, &quot;2nd month&quot;, etc., mean the 1st month God created, the 2nd months God created, etc., and do not mean the 1st month of the year, the 2nd month of the year, etc.  R.H. is the first day (or two days) of the 7th month, and of the year.  The year starts with the first day of the 7th month and ends with the last day of the 6th month.  [[Special:Contributions/71.109.149.60|71.109.149.60]] ([[User talk:71.109.149.60|talk]]) 04:31, 26 November 2010 (UTC)

Which new year crossing does G-d use to calculate the prophecies, sabbaths and feast days? Since we are clearly not using TORAH to determine the new year(s) here and clearly something derived of man such as the Mishnah, then I believe to have the proper understanding we must go back to the writings of Mosheh. We can believe him as it is accounted twice that he ascended the mountain to speak with G-d and brought back to us the marriage covenant not to mention the starting of our TORAH. How can we as men debate this, saying this and that about something? All we are doing is confirming a prophecy in Dani'el about the moving of ordained times. [[User:Lambroger|Alan]] ([[User talk:Lambroger|talk]]) 13:50, 29 September 2011 (UTC)

== Tashlich ==
=== Pebbles/stones ===
Does anyone really use pebbles or stones for tashlich? I'd like to delete it, but figured I'd ask first. --[[User:Keeves|Keeves]] 01:57, 25 September 2006 (UTC)

I'm sure SOMEONE out there does.  Ask 10 Jews for an opinion, get 11 answers.  Shalom, y'all!--[[User:Greenbomb101|Greenbomb101]] 21:25, 20 January 2007 (UTC)
:The practce of throwing ANYTHING into the water is actually problematic halakhically, as it is transferring said object from one reshus to another, there is an added prohibition with stones, as stones are muktzah on sabbath and festivals. The whole custom is fundamentally flawed, and should therefore not be on the page at all, or be discouraged. &amp;mdash;&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash;&amp;nbsp;'''''[[User:DeFender1031|DeFender1031]]''''' 01:38, 28 November 2007 (UTC)

::A number of authorities object to the practice of Tashlich on grounds like those listed above. The existence of a dispute and these objections can certainly be included if sourced. However, the practice is widespread, included in standard Orthodox prayerbooks, and supported by many authorities. I would stress the importance of relying on [[WP:RS|sources]] rather than editors' own views. Best, --[[User:Shirahadasha|Shirahadasha]] ([[User talk:Shirahadasha|talk]]) 03:15, 28 November 2007 (UTC)
:::Take a look in any halakha sefer out there, they will all tell you that A) stones are muktzah B) throwing something from land into water is a transferring of reshus C) (for the case of using bread) feeding wild animals on sabbath and yom tov is also assur. If you want a source, look in any halakha sefer that deals with the prohibitions of shabbos and moed. These are NOT my own views, these are straight halakha. It's not my fault if those who print prayer books or the &quot;authorities&quot; are ignorant, and it is my hope that in the future, only those who actually deserve their authority obtain it. &amp;mdash;&amp;nbsp;'''''[[User:DeFender1031|DeFender1031]]''''' 19:35, 1 December 2007 (UTC)
Wikipedia is an encyclopedia, not a siddur.  Its purpose is to inform with a NPOV, not to encourage or discourage.  The article is supposed to be about what IS done, not what should be done.[[Special:Contributions/71.109.149.60|71.109.149.60]] ([[User talk:71.109.149.60|talk]]) 04:36, 26 November 2010 (UTC)

=== Delaying until non-Yom Tov day because of need to drive to water ===
The article is incorrect in its statement that Tashlich is not always done on the first or second day.  I know of a Chabad-Lubavitcher Rabbi in a place with no suitable body of water within walking distance, so he waits until the 3rd day of the month (or the 4th if the 3rd is Shabbos), and then drives to the ocean.  However, I know this only from original research and not from verifiable sources.  Someone with a verifiable source, please fix the article.  [[Special:Contributions/71.109.149.60|71.109.149.60]] ([[User talk:71.109.149.60|talk]]) 04:59, 26 November 2010 (UTC)

== lo be-adu rosh ==

I've never heard of this one before - as far as I know the classical saying is:

lo adu rosh, ve' lo bedu pesach

i.e. Rosh HaShana is not on 146 and Pesach can not be on 246. The extra &quot;be&quot; in the first part is confusing! Any confirmations?

[[User:Nachmore|Nachmore]] 05:50, 6 September 2007 (UTC)

== References ==

This whole article needs more in-line citations.  Anyone know a good NPOV source that we could cite for the information. [[User:Remember|Remember]] 17:52, 13 September 2007 (UTC)

:I don't know if there's such a thing as an NPOV source, but more references and better sourcing is certainly welcome. Best, --[[User:Shirahadasha|Shirahadasha]] ([[User talk:Shirahadasha|talk]]) 03:17, 28 November 2007 (UTC)

== Greetings ==

The traditional greeting is actually &quot;L'shana Tova&quot;, &quot;To/for a good year&quot;, not just &quot;Shana Tova&quot;, and the pronunication given is for the Anglicized version, not the Hebrew.  In Hebrew the stresses go on the final syllables of each of these words.  I didn't correct this because I didn't know how to enter the phonetic transcription into the wiki. [[User:Jaysonfire|Jaysonfire]] ([[User talk:Jaysonfire|talk]]) 19:29, 25 September 2008 (UTC)

== More on Yom HaZikaron? ==

As discussed above under &quot;Rosh Hashana is not the Jewish new year&quot;, the ur-traditional name is not Rosh Hashana. I've previously dealt with the extent to which some Wikipedians are upset when traditional or correct names are used for articles instead of popular ones, but is there any disagreement that the article's text, at the lest, should include more focus on this distinction and on the significance of the Yom HaZikaron-aspect of this, to wit, the rememberance vs. the &quot;New Year&quot; bit which, as others have said, tends to confuse those more familiar with traditions in which the New Year is a purely celebratory event? [[User:Czrisher|Czrisher]] ([[User talk:Czrisher|talk]]) 21:53, 1 October 2008 (UTC)

==Feast of Trumpets==

Update: Feast of Trumpets now redirects to [[Christian_observances_of_Jewish_holidays#Feast_of_Trumpets]], not to this article [[Special:Contributions/71.109.149.60|71.109.149.60]] ([[User talk:71.109.149.60|talk]]) 05:05, 26 November 2010 (UTC)

== OTD ==

Per the rules at [[WP:OTD]], this article is going to be excluded from [[Wikipedia:Selected anniversaries/September 28]] this year because it has serious maintenance issues. There are 8 weeks to go before this date, so please be sure to have those resolved by then. Thanks. &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Verdana; &quot;&gt;'''[[User:Howcheng|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#33C;&quot;&gt;howcheng&lt;/span&gt;]]'''  &lt;small&gt;{[[User talk:Howcheng|chat]]}&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 18:50, 1 August 2011 (UTC)
: Fixed. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 19:36, 2 August 2011 (UTC)

== Spelling ==
Where did the extra h come from at the end of Rosh Hashana?  --[[User:Redaktor|Redaktor]] ([[User talk:Redaktor|talk]]) 17:12, 14 September 2011 (UTC)

--I believe that it came from the fact that the word &quot;Shana&quot; (year) in Hebrew ends in the [[He (letter)|letter Hei]], which is the equivalent to the English [[H|letter H]], so really the question should be why did people stop transliterating the name of the holiday into English without the extra H at the end?  Also, technically, You should capitalize the S, to read: Rosh HaShana, and possibly even Rosh haShana, to signify that &quot;ha&quot; only serves as the definite article, and that Shanah is the second word in the phrase &quot;Head of the Year&quot; - i.e. Rosh haShannah.{{Unsigned|129.98.156.205}}

: According to [[Wikipedia:HEBREW#Formative_letters|WP:HEBREW]] the first &quot;H&quot; of HaShanah&quot; should be capitalised. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 13:55, 28 September 2011 (UTC)
: Also ,if you do a search for &quot;Rosh Hashana&quot; Google will automatically give you the results for the more correct and widespread &quot;Rosh HashannaH&quot; with an &quot;h&quot;. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 13:58, 28 September 2011 (UTC)

===Requested move===
&lt;div class=&quot;boilerplate&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #efe; margin: 2em 0 0 0; padding: 0 10px 0 10px; border: 1px dotted #aaa;&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Template:polltop --&gt;
:''The following discussion is an archived discussion of the proposal. &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on the talk page. No further edits should be made to this section. ''

'''No consensus''' to move. [[User:Vegaswikian|Vegaswikian]] ([[User talk:Vegaswikian|talk]]) 21:33, 8 October 2011 (UTC)

[[Rosh Hashanah]] → {{no redirect|1=Rosh HaShanah}} – Per [[WP:HEBREW]], which says &quot;In all capitalized words, he hayedi'a (ha, he) will be capitalized, '''as well as the word after it'''&quot; (stress is mine). Should be uncontroversial. I'd have done this myself, but apparently this page is move-protected. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 17:29, 1 October 2011 (UTC)

*&quot;Rosh Hashanah&quot; has WideSpread EngLish USage WithOut [[CamelCase]] so the CurRent TiTle is fine per [[WP:UE]]/[[WP:MOSCAPS]].  — [[User talk:AjaxSmack|&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid #000073;background:#4D4DA6;padding:2px;color:#F9FFFF;text-shadow:black 0.2em 0.2em 0.3em&quot;&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Georgia&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;'''AjaxSmack'''&amp;nbsp;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 05:54, 2 October 2011 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''' [[WP:UCN]] per AjaxSmack. [[Special:Contributions/76.65.128.90|76.65.128.90]] ([[User talk:76.65.128.90|talk]]) 08:35, 2 October 2011 (UTC)
*'''Oppose'''.  [[WP:HEBREW]] is intended for cases where there is no established English usage.  This is obviously not such a case.  [[User:LtPowers|Powers]] &lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:LtPowers|T]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 23:17, 3 October 2011 (UTC)
*'''Oppose'''. Common name. [[User:Glrx|Glrx]] ([[User talk:Glrx|talk]]) 22:45, 7 October 2011 (UTC)
:''The above discussion is preserved as an archive of the proposal.  &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on this talk page. No further edits should be made to this section.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- Template:pollbottom --&gt;

==Table of Dates==


~It would be good if this article included a table of dates on which this event falls in different years. I heard on [[Thought for the Day]] this morning that it is today (September 28) in 2011! [[User:ACEOREVIVED|ACEOREVIVED]] ([[User talk:ACEOREVIVED|talk]]) 16:04, 28 September 2011 (UTC)

== Sunday ==

The rules says Rosh HaShana does not start on a Sunday (and Wednesday  and Friday). Fine. But given that this year (2012) starts exactly on a Sunday,  isn’t it better to explain that if it says ''not on Sunday'' what it means it cannot start on the evening ''before'', ie Saturday? BTW, the reference used talks about Yom Kippur, not Rosh HaShana.--[[User:Sandribus|Sandribus]] ([[User talk:Sandribus|talk]]) 08:01, 15 September 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>ifdghb6fjsl3aigt8q48egmfoayvf9x</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
