<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Metrical psalter</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>3000081</id>
    <revision>
      <id>438798875</id>
      <parentid>351701843</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-07-10T20:33:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Richard M. Waugaman, M.D.</username>
        <id>11799583</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>I ask if anyone can provide an active link to the Sternhold and Hopkins translation, since the one listed is inactive.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3215">{{WikiProject Songs|class=B|auto=inherit|importance=}}
{{WPCalvinism/Article Scope|class=B|importance=mid}}


==Untitled==
The links I've added are good sources for expanding parts of this entry and for images as well. 

There seems to be some possible controversy and uncertainty over the music for the french psalters--whether they ever used popular, secular tunes and to what extent Calvin opposed or approved 4-part harmony. [[User:Dpknauss|Dan Knauss]] 03:29, 26 October 2005 (UTC)

== metrical psalms ==

About half an hour ago I typed in &quot;metrical psalms&quot; into the seach box which came up with nothing. I've just come accross this page from a Google search - could a redirect page be added so the term 'metrical psalm/s' comes here too?

 
== Psalters in German ==
Re: ''Neither of these musicians influenced Britain or America much, most likely because they used longer metres'' ... (e.g. 9.8.9.8. no citation, sorry, can someone help?). C.Winkworth complained famously of the difficulties of matching German metre, especially for the feminine or  stressed+unstressed line ending. 

Comments: For the chosen title, metrical psalters, German is less important - A psalter would be secondary, perhaps a present. The place of the psalms themselves from Luther on is unequivocably high, and the ups and downs of their musical accompaniment is similar over Europe. So I've tried to capture the essentials in a suitably short paragraph.
# It is possible that a world tour of psalms is a major undertaking - this piece has no direct equivalent in wikipedia.de, the nearest being &quot;Geschichte des geistlichen Liedes auf dem europäischen Kontinent&quot;. I am presuming it is not usual to cross-refer to other languages; Lobwasser also has his own article there.
[[User:83.228.206.97|83.228.206.97]]

== Ballad metre ==

This article contains an arguably non-NPOV viewpoint on the prevalence of common metre (ballad metre).  There are very good reasons for this.  
1) Family worship - universal common metre allows members of the family to sing right through the psalms, gradually adding to a limited stock of tunes
2) Small congregations without musicians.  My personal experience is of small Scottish psalm-singing Presbyterian congregations (in some of which a pretty good standard of congregational singing is achieved, incidentally without instruments, as is usually the case unless there is a continental e.g. Dutch background); and of contacts with several Church of Scotland congregations where the difficulty of obtaining an organist, perhaps from outside the congregation (for Lord's Day worship), or getting the tune without instruments (at midweek meetings) means a lot of unnecessary difficulty.  IMHO hymnbooks and songbooks are designed around city congregations - of course the older nonconformist hymnbooks had very many more common metre hymns and tunes. [[User:PeterR|PeterR]] ([[User talk:PeterR|talk]]) 21:14, 17 November 2009 (UTC)

==link to Sternhold and Hopkins==

The link no longer works. Can anyone provide an active link to the full text of this translation?
[[User:Richard M. Waugaman, M.D.|Richard M. Waugaman, M.D.]] ([[User talk:Richard M. Waugaman, M.D.|talk]]) 20:32, 10 July 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>9vrgltz2g5bd7ri0kc4aqrnc8hotg85</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
