<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Anatta</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>290386</id>
    <revision>
      <id>474324598</id>
      <parentid>474324456</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-02-01T02:15:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SineBot</username>
        <id>4936590</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Signing comment by [[Special:Contributions/90.202.174.43|90.202.174.43]] - &quot;&quot;</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21551">{{talk header}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Buddhism|class=C|importance=high
}}
{{philosophy|importance=|class= Start|auto=yes|eastern=yes|religion=yes}}
}}

{{archivebox|[[/Archive1]][[/Archive2]]}}

== Controversial ==

&quot;The concept of anatta has, from early times, been controversial amongst [[Buddhism|Buddhists]] and non-Buddhists alike and remains so to this day.&lt;ref&gt;see, e.g., Perez-Remon, ''Self and Non-Self in Early Buddhism'', Mouton, 1980&lt;/ref&gt;&quot;

According to [http://books.google.com/books?id=rcNdDilzilMC&amp;pg=PA19&amp;dq=Perez-Remon,+Self+and+Non-Self+in+Early+Buddhism&amp;sig=ACfU3U0ANuJpxn0xUGcewtEpqDHfJljRPA#PPA19,M1 Harvey], Perez-Ramon's personal interpretation is problematic. Now does the quote mean to convey the controversy among first and second generation Buddhologists as Harvey does in the linked page? If so that doesn't warrant presence in the intro. If &quot;controversial&quot; means that some Mahayanists use the word &quot;atman&quot; in a different way, then that should be stated a different way. What is it? What is the full quote from the source? [[User:Mitsube|Mitsube]] ([[User talk:Mitsube|talk]]) 04:13, 21 September 2008 (UTC)

::I can't see what the problem is -- the statement seems quite clear and self-explanatory.  Perhaps you need to read it again.  Re Harvey: you are misquoting him as he does not exactly say that &quot;Perez-Ramon's personal interpretation is problematic&quot; -- have another look at the link your provided. Anyway, that is just Harvey's opinion -- who is to say that he is right in that respect ?  You also say &quot;some Mahayanists use the word &quot;atman&quot; in a different way&quot;.  The quote makes no mention of Mahayana, does it ?  What about the Pudgalavadins ? --[[User:Anam Gumnam|Anam Gumnam]] ([[User talk:Anam Gumnam|talk]]) 23:02, 22 September 2008 (UTC)

:::Having read it again, I still believe that &quot;It still fails to avoid the problem of coherently relating craving to the 'Self.'&quot; =&gt; &quot;problematic.&quot;
:::Pudgalavadins had a different concept labeled with a different word, did they not? Certainly &quot;pudgala&quot; was likely controversial if it was an essence. It seems to have been a minor sect details of which are quite obscure and I don't have much material about them. I have just read something that tells me they labeled the conventional &quot;self&quot; a &quot;pudgala.&quot; So it's a sort of mindstream doctrine? Not actually that controversial. Some good sources on this would help.
:::There is nothing about a &quot;controversy&quot; in this article so a peacock sentence like that with no explanation does not belong in the lead paragraph by any means. I don't believe the concept is at all controversial. Even people like Dolpopa would surely still say that it is true. The Buddha used the word to mean that our grasping at self is a miscognition of the reality of the skandhas. I.e. &quot;I am this&quot; is always wrong and distracting. Some Mahayanists then went down metaphysical roads that aren't actually that closely related to this idea, which was phenomenological, not metaphysical. So they ended up saying, &quot;Those statements are true, but these other statements are a higher teaching about an ultimate reality beyond the range of thought except for enlightened people.&quot; So this is not the controversy here. In fact the shentong/rangtong controversy is not closely related to this either. [[User:Mitsube|Mitsube]] ([[User talk:Mitsube|talk]]) 23:21, 22 September 2008 (UTC)
::::I second Mitsube, the statement on controversy is not really needed. In fact it only confuses the audience about the topic. Instead, the introduction paragraph must stress on the fact that Anatta is not a metaphysical assertion, but rather a technique of viewing things to know their real nature. It in fact forms part of &quot;right view&quot; in the eightfold path. The concept of &quot;right view&quot; in the eightfold path clearly talks of viewing all experience in three main ways: that every experience in this universe is impermanent, that every experience is in some way leading to suffering and finally that no phenomenon in this universe has anything to do with the notion of a I, me, mine or myself (i.e. every phenomenon is 'not-self') It is critical to point out that Buddhism does not make a blanket statement that everything is not-self to confuse one of the natural notion of ego and self, but that the view of not-self is to be developed by training in right view (samma ditthi). It is important to understand that while when one understands that all experience is impermanent, it applies to everything but the experience of nirvana/nibbana. But when one understands that nothing is worthy of being deemed as a self or anything to do with it, it applies even to nirvana/nibbana. So nibbana is not a higher self.

:::::Dear friend, this is not what the Buddha taught! Of course the exact meaning of 'in this universe' and 'experience' has to be defined, but as such the statements that &quot;every experience in this universe is impermanent, that every experience is in some way leading to suffering and finally that no phenomenon in this universe has anything to do with the notion of a I, me, mine or myself&quot; is not correct! Buddha said very clearly that there is Nirvana, the unborn, without what there could be no liberation. So, there is a permanent phenomenon that is utter peace and which is *beyond* any notion of self or not-self! So, one cannot even state that it has nothing to do with a notion of 'I'! No-self is not just the simple negation of a self, which would be just another philosophical tenet, no-self goes completely beyond any concept of self or not-self (both and neither - see Tetralemma)! That is why the Tathagata refused to say anything about his existence or non-existence after death. - Bhikshu Trinley

::::Since the opening paragraph does not make the effort to make these points clear, it anyway needs a lot of improvements. To top it off, it befuddles the reader about the real meaning of the word by saying that it is controversial. On the one hand, I completely agree that different schools of Buddhism have different interpretations of the term, but I think it is scholastically incomplete to make an open-ended statement like that, saying that the concept is controversial, without exactly pin-pointing the origin of the controversy if any.[[User:BalajiRamasubramanian|AutoInquiry]] ([[User talk:BalajiRamasubramanian|talk]]) 15:43, 26 August 2009 (UTC)

:The sentence would be fine if it read: &quot;The question of how to interpret the concept of anatta has, from early times, been controversial amongst [[Buddhism|Buddhists]] and non-Buddhists alike and remains so to this day.&lt;ref&gt;see, e.g., Perez-Remon, ''Self and Non-Self in Early Buddhism'', Mouton, 1980&lt;/ref&gt;&quot; The Sammityas were Pudgalavadins, and they were one of the largest sects throughout the history of Buddhism in India. But we don't know much about them now, it is true.[[User:Sylvain1972|Sylvain1972]] ([[User talk:Sylvain1972|talk]]) 18:46, 26 August 2009 (UTC)

== Reformed brahmanism ==

Please provide the full context of the quote beyond what can be found at a certain polemical website. This is an extreme minority view in the Buddhist studies community. [[User:Mitsube|Mitsube]] ([[User talk:Mitsube|talk]]) 06:05, 4 October 2008 (UTC)

== Some Mahayana scriptures declare the existence of &quot;atman,&quot; which in these scriptures is equated with buddha-nature. ==

Not. Sabbe sankhara anicca dukkha and anatta are recognized by every single one of the Buddhists schools, no exceptions. So it's not a recognization of &quot;some kind of...&quot;; it is just very hard to understand/explain. It's easier to just ommit that part in this article and try to ask different Lamas and Ngakpas of the visions of this problematic... and western philosophers. See: Mhulamadhyamikakarikas by Nagarjuna, that's the philosophical basis for all Mahayana, how could it be then Atman or whatsoever?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/201.246.107.238|201.246.107.238]] ([[User talk:201.246.107.238|talk]]) 01:18, 16 April 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:It is used as a metaphor. Is this not clear from the article? Please let me know how you understand the article. [[User:Mitsube|Mitsube]] ([[User talk:Mitsube|talk]]) 03:00, 16 April 2009 (UTC)

:Other recognized Mahayana scriptures like the ''Lankavatara Sutra'' treat those who deny the Self as heretics. Here is an example:
 
::&quot;Those who propound the doctrine of non-Self are to be shunned in the religous rites of the monks, and not to be spoken to, for they are offenders of the Buddhist doctrines, having embraced the dual views of Being and non-Being [existence and non-existence]&quot; (F.G. Sutton, ''Existence and Enlightenment in the Lankavatara-sutra'', 98).[[User:Songhill|Songhill]] ([[User talk:Songhill|talk]]) 05:23, 7 November 2009 (UTC)

== Quote from Bhikku Bodhi ==
I would like it if someone could include any or all of this quote from bhikku bodhi in his book, 'In the Buddha's Words'. It is about dependent origination, but it pertains to this same self vs. not-self argument:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
'Several suttas hold up dependent origination as a &quot;teaching by the middle&quot;. It is a &quot;teaching by the middle&quot; because it transcends two extreme views that polarize philosophical reflection on the human condition. One extreme, the meta-physical thesis of eternalism, asserts that the core of human identity is an indestructible and eternal self, whether individual or universal. It also asserts that the world is created and maintained by a permanent entity, a God or some other metaphysical reality. The other extreme, annihilationism, holds that at death the person is utterly annihilated. There is no spiritual dimension to human existence and thus no personal survival of any sort. For the Buddha, both extremes pose insuperable problems. Eternalism encourages an obstinate clinging to the five aggregates(skhandas), which are really impermanent and devoid of a substantial self; annihilationism threatens to undermine ethics and to make suffering the product of chance.

Dependent origination offers a radically different perspective that transcends the two extremes. It shows that individual existence is constituted by a current of conditioned phenomena devoid of a metaphysical self yet continuing on from birth to birth as long as the causes that sustain it remain effective. Dependent origination thereby offers a cogent explanation of the problem of suffering that on the one hand avoids the philosophical dilemmas posed by the hypothesis of a permanent self, and on the other avoids the dangers of ethical anarchy to which annihilationism eventually leads.'
--Bhikku Bodhi
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

If someone could include some or all of this, if they feel it is pertinent, that would be a great help, as i do not feel yet comfortable editing articles.
--[[Special:Contributions/24.12.229.163|24.12.229.163]] ([[User talk:24.12.229.163|talk]]) 20:21, 27 April 2009 (UTC)

== Paragraph duplicity ==

The paragraph starting: At the time of the Buddha some philosophers and meditators posited a &quot;root&quot;.... is just copied and pasted. I was unsure what to do about it.

Thomas B.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Duckbeach|Duckbeach]] ([[User talk:Duckbeach|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Duckbeach|contribs]]) 01:11, 22 October 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Mixing Pali and Sanskrit words. ==

Word Sutta and Sutra(Pali and Sanskrit word for same thing) are both used in the article in different places. This might cause confusion and there should only be one or the other word used consistently. Somekind of compromise is also possible, e.g. ''Sutta(Sutra)''. Also, if someone should choose to use, let's say Sutta(which is Pali), then all the similar cases in article should use the pali word and not mix the languages. This is not problem only in this article, but also in other articles concerning Buddhism in Wikipedia.

In my experience, Sanskrit words are more common in western literature, but many Buddhist texts seem to use Pali.

[[User:Aperculum|Aperculum]] ([[User talk:Aperculum|talk]]) 18:17, 26 May 2010 (UTC)

::The Theravadans use Pali, most of the rest of the Indian Buddhist literature used Sanskrit. I think the best general policy is to use the English word where possible and then give both the Pali and Sanskrit in parens.[[User:Sylvain1972|Sylvain1972]] ([[User talk:Sylvain1972|talk]]) 15:10, 27 May 2010 (UTC)

Suttas and Sutras are ''not'' the same thing, so it would be a step backwards to use just one word throughout the article.  When referring to a Pali sutta or suttas, the word should be 'sutta' or 'suttas'.  When referring to Sanskrit Sutra or Sutras, the word should be 'Sutra' or 'Sutras'.  In an article which covers the ground of both suttas and sutras, this distinction actually helps to clarify rather than cause confusion because the reader will know &quot;the suttas say&quot; might be contradicted in what certain &quot;sutras say&quot; owing to legitimate doctrinal differences between, for example, Mahayana Sutras and the Pali suttas.  Another look could be taken to be sure this is being followed correctly in the article, but a quick skim indicated to me that it was (it didn't appear to me they were being used interchangeably: 'sutta' references tied back to the Pali Nikayas, especially via Paul Harvey, and 'Sutra' references went to sutras), although there is some ambiguity in how freely the Pali version of the term anatta is used in context where it should be anatman.  This is somewhat less of a problem than between sutta/sutra, but still an issue.--[[User:Vacchagotta|Vacchagotta]] ([[User talk:Vacchagotta|talk]]) 21:20, 28 May 2010 (UTC)

:They are two words for the same thing, and the distinction is not as clear as you say. In fact, they are two versions of the same word. Other early schools (particularly the Sarvastivadins) used Sanskrit, and so they have versions of most of the Suttas that they called Sutras. These have been inherited by later Mahayana traditions. So it is not just &quot;Suttas&quot; that say such-and-such, there are also &quot;Sutras&quot; that also say so.[[User:Sylvain1972|Sylvain1972]] ([[User talk:Sylvain1972|talk]]) 18:43, 29 May 2010 (UTC)

::I can agree with you in part; however when two languages are involved, there is a distinction, whatever you say.  The word in the two languages refer to the same concept but not in effect the same object. No matter how parallel, a Sanskrit sutra is ''not'' the same as a Pali sutta.  It is simply not the same text, and even in parallel discourses there are some noted differences in the content, though admittedly minor.  Also, there are Pali suttas which simply do not exist in any Sanskrit form and vice versa.  Peter Harvey, for example, who is the source for most all of the references to suttas in this article, was writing in reference to the Pali suttas, not necessarily to Sanskrit sources.  It is simply better all things considered, when the citation is to a Pali text or a source discussing Pali texts, to use the Pali 'sutta' and equally when Sanskrit (or Tibetan or Chinese versions of Sanskrit originals), use 'sutra'.  This of course, is just my opinion that I offer without editing the article proper.  When both, I propose 'suttas and sutras'.  If you are proposing the English word only, then I suppose 'discourses' would be the most ready option.[[User:Vacchagotta|Vacchagotta]] ([[User talk:Vacchagotta|talk]]) 20:21, 7 June 2010 (UTC)

:::I agree that Pali Suttas should be referred to as Suttas, and non-Pali scriptures should be referred to as Sutras. Perhaps I misunderstood, but based on your initial comments I was under the impression that you objected to this solution.[[User:Sylvain1972|Sylvain1972]] ([[User talk:Sylvain1972|talk]]) 15:41, 9 June 2010 (UTC)

== Removed improperly referenced material... ==

On 05:55, 23 August 2010 Tengu800  removed the entire Madhyamaka section claiming that it was &quot;improperly referenced material from ancient primary sources. Instead brought in modern Mahayana commentary on the main matter of interpreting Anatta.&quot;

Actually, the material is well referenced from modern translations; it belongs to a large and living tradition which relies upon a long commentarial tradition (not that such a thing makes it a requirement for WP). None of the material that was referenced is from primary sources - the material is (admittedly old) academic commentarial work from Nalanda University, with further commentaries made by Tsongkhapa who was another famous academic commentator. There are plenty of far more modern academic works that talk about these things - see the texts written by Sprung, Garfield, Williams, Inada, Streng, Napper, etc. etc.  In fact Napper (ISBN 0861710576, pp67-142) summarises and distinguishes an entire host of modern academic commentators and their views on anatta and the middle way philosophy.

The commentary that replaced it concerns the views of just one person, which certainly does not adequately typify the views of Anatta from the Mahayana perspective.

There are many different views of Anatta within various Mahayana schools. It is easy enough to find references to demonstrate that.
I have restored the Madhyamaka text and contextualised the Chán text..  ([[User:20040302|20040302]] ([[User talk:20040302|talk]]) 08:03, 5 May 2011 (UTC))

== Anatta in the Nikāyas ==

“One uses 'not-Self', then, as a reason to let go of things, not to 'prove' that there is no Self.” This quote of Peter Harvey is indicative of the problem of specious scholarship which opines that the Buddha used ''anatta'' as a mere ‘strategy’ for release, and never denied the Brahman Absolute. This entire section on ‘Anatta in the Nikāyas’ should be reworked.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.250.187.46|76.250.187.46]] ([[User talk:76.250.187.46|talk]]) 13:55, 12 September 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Anatta, Anatman, Advaita Vedanta, 5 senses and the concept of Tat Tvam Asi ==
I disagree with the start of the article, that is certainly not how I read the texts. However, linking that concept concerning the 5 senses with the concept of Anatman in Advaita Vedanta is incorrect because it fails to acknowledge the positioning of Tat Tvam Asi - 'you are that'. Instead, I read anatta and anatman from both advaita vedanta and through buddhism as being an acknowledgement that all we sense (hear and see etc.) is constructed through ourselves but the concept of self is also constructed. The world only exists because of how we interpret our senses through our mind - hence everything is an illusion - as demonstrated by Shankara's example of the rope and snake (so the old saying about a tree falling - it makes no sound because nobody is there to hear it because sound is a construct of how the mind interprets vibrations via the ear drum, but even if someone was there to interpret the vibrations as sound, that person is not really there because there is no essence that can be pinpointed as being - as in the old story about where is the cart?) . The key to anatman can be found most clearly when Ramakrishna came out of his trance and acknowledged that if the world is an illusion of our senses then we ourselves are part of that same illusion. The key to anatta and anatman is realising that yes, the world is an illusion of the senses but there can be no self because we too are part of the world and hence part of the illusion. The mind is a construct of the mind and therefore does not truly exist.
In Buddhism the self does not exist through several demonstrations - Nagarjuna's demonstration that mirrors the older Greek demonstration of a river and time. There can be no-self because the second it comes into being it ceases to be. The 'me' of today is not the same as the 'me' when I was a baby, and similarly, the 'me' of this exact moment, is different to a mili-second ago. There is therefore no tangible self beyond that which the mind constructs - but the mind itself changes constantly and the mind of now is not the same as before I started writing this blurb. This has nothing to do with the senses at all.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/86.27.37.82|86.27.37.82]] ([[User talk:86.27.37.82|talk]]) 22:36, 30 November 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Two interpretations?==
High, the only difference that has been noted in these two quite long paragraphs is that some interpret no self to mean it should be neither affirmed or denied, and others say that it just doesn't exist. Who is the first group - it's not something I've encountered before? I can think of the pudgalavadins who say that the self exists and is neither the same nor different to the aggregates, but that's not what was said.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/90.202.174.43|90.202.174.43]] ([[User talk:90.202.174.43|talk]]) 02:14, 1 February 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;</text>
      <sha1>cjw7lppc87sywdt6xsuc3issgf9y1tl</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
