<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Atheism</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>5157721</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521918382</id>
      <parentid>520597736</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T00:50:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>WotherspoonSmith</username>
        <id>2279519</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Religiosity/ intelligence/ Bell/ Dawkins' quote */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18900">{| style=&quot;background: #EE2244;&quot;
|-
|{{notice|The '''definition of atheism''' has been repeatedly argued on this talk page. Before suggesting substantial changes, please make sure that your view is entirely supported by [[WP:RS|reliable sources]] and has a [[wp:npov|neutral point of view]].}}
|-
|{{Round in circles|topic=the '''definition in the first paragraph'''}}
|}
{{Talk header|noarchive=yes}}
&lt;!----- // ADD NEW DISCUSSIONS TO THE *BOTTOM* OF THE PAGE // -----&gt;
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=FAC
|action1date=31 May 2006
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Atheism/archive1
|action1result=failed
|action1oldid=56164932

|action2=GAN
|action2date=29 December 2006
|action2link=Talk:Atheism/Archive 29#GA on hold
|action2result=failed
|action2oldid=97254190

|action3=FAC
|action3date=21:24, 28 April 2007
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Atheism
|action3result=promoted
|action3oldid=126689566

|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=2007-06-08
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Religion|class=FA|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Atheism|class=FA|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Philosophy|class=FA|importance=High|religion=yes}}
{{WikiProject Theology|class=FA|importance=Top}}
{{WP1.0|v0.7=pass|class=FA|category=Philrelig|VA=yes|WPCD=yes|small=yes}} 
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Atheism}}
{{Controversial-issues}}
{{Calm talk}}
{{to do}}
{{archives |auto=short |search=yes |index=/Archive index |bot=MiszaBot I |age=3 |units=weeks }}
__FORCETOC__ &lt;!-- Force table of contents to appear- it refuses to otherwise --&gt;
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|maxarchivesize = 250K
|counter = 52
|minthreadsleft = 4
|algo = old(21d)
|archive = Talk:Atheism/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=Talk:Atheism/Archive index
|mask=Talk:Atheism/Archive &lt;#&gt;
|leading_zeros=0
|indexhere=yes
}}

&lt;!----- // DISCUSSION TOPICS START BELOW // -----&gt;

== Demographics.. and '''up-to-date''' world dynamics of atheism ==

:I had edited the Atheism article in order to include the new (august 22, 2012) world survey on people self-statements of being &quot;religious&quot;, &quot;no religion&quot;, or &quot;declared atheists&quot;, produced by an undisputably reliable source, ''Gallup-International''.

:This was meant to '''complete''' the Demography section dedicated to &quot;how many atheists are there in the world now&quot;. 
:In fact, this section, as it stands up today,
:1) revolves mostly about &quot;how many atheists are there in the States --and Canada--, and ''eventually'' in Western Europe ;
:2) don't rely on studies... ''more recent than 2004-2005'' ! ! !
:Not only the Gallup study (conducted on 51,927 men and women from 57 countries) concerns the entire world, but it offers, '''''for the first time''''' as far as it seems, the invaluable possibility to '''see''' the evolution of the percentages, from 2005 up to 2012 !

:[[User:IRWolfie-|IRWolfie]], without coming on this talk page to expose '''why''' he disagreed about the adding of that world study, erased it only ''minutes'' after i posted it.
:It seems (''a posteriori'') that his argument is that this adding must be included inside the &quot;Demographics of atheism&quot; article. The problem is that this said-article deals more 1) with the difficulties to get precise figures about deep-thinkings of faith followers and/or &quot;shy&quot; atheists ; 2) the second part merely distributes the informations... ''country by country''... 

:Which is not at all the aim of the Gallup study, as it mainly shows ---not the '''static''' repartition of atheists in the world today &lt;small&gt;&lt;small&gt;(which '''is''' the legitimate purpose of the other article)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/small&gt;, but the '''global dynamics''' on these topics, objectively observed during the last 7 years !
:That's why i really think it has more it's place in &quot;Atheism&quot;.
:That's why i reverted the previous --and abrupt-- blanking. (I abandoned the idea to do a whole new section out of it, and included it in the existing one).

:I invite IRWolfie to come to this talk page and discuss the point, before erasing these paragraphs again.
:--[[User:Mezzkal|Mezzkal]] ([[User talk:Mezzkal|talk]]) 01:42, 25 August 2012 (UTC)
::'''Support''' inclusion of the material you tried to add on the survey.  I checked the BBC and the press release sources and they appear to be legit.  I would like to suggest to other editors here that they refrain from revert warring when someone tries to improve this article by adding content.  There is no requirement for editors to &quot;first obtain consensus&quot; before adding properly sourced, new material to an article.  There is, however, a prohibition on revert-warring. [[User:Cla68|Cla68]] ([[User talk:Cla68|talk]]) 04:03, 25 August 2012 (UTC)
:::Per [[WP:BRD]] it is fully normal to revert bold changes to an article pending consensus; it is not ok to restore it without discussion. Atheism is a featured article and the material needs to be trimmed down and some work and needs to be done on it to integrate it in. We need to reach a consensus on what should be included first. Much of the information added should be presented in a table in the [[Demographics of atheism]] article, with a short summary of the main findings in this article. [[User:IRWolfie-|IRWolfie-]] ([[User talk:IRWolfie-|talk]]) 12:16, 25 August 2012 (UTC)

::::[Thanx for your support, Cla68...]
::::[to IRWolfie] : What do you mean... &quot;bold changes&quot; ? First, you didn't even mention this argument as an &quot;explanation&quot; for you deletion, when you did it.. I'm amazed that you bring it up here for the first time (i.e.: ''after'' the discussion started on this talk page..) ''';''' second : to transcribe new statistical figures concerning the main topic of an article ''isn't'' really what one would call &quot;a '''bold''' change&quot;, is it ? We're not talking, here, about a dramatic new concept which would revolutionize atheism, aren't we ??? And anyway, '''''no one''''' had the slightest objection about the ''content'' of these new paragraphs... '''''not even you,''''' AFAIK ?? 
::::Also : in case you didn't know, the &quot;WP:BRD&quot; to which you refer, claiming that, according to it, &quot;it is fully normal to revert bold changes&quot;... '''is just an essay...''' In no way, it is part of an &quot;official&quot; WP guideline. It even starts by saying : &lt;small&gt;&quot;BRD is '''not''' a policy. This means it is '''not''' a process ''that you can require other editors to follow''.&quot;&lt;/small&gt;

::::By the way  ---as ''you'' refer to that BRD---, I attract your attention to the fact that it says : &lt;small&gt;&quot;BRD is '''not''' a valid excuse for reverting good-faith efforts to improve a page ''simply because you don't like the changes''. Don't invoke BRD as your reason for reverting someone else's work or for edit warring: instead, '''''provide a reason that is based on policies, guidelines, or common sense&quot;'''''.&lt;/small&gt;

::::So... eventhough &quot;your&quot; BRD required it, you didn't even begin to answer my argumentation about '''''why''''' this abstract of the Gallup study has more its place in the ''Demographics'' section of Atheism, with a short résumé in the other article, '''''rather than the way 'round,''''' as you keep saying without bringing any new support to your point...
::::--[[User:Mezzkal|Mezzkal]] ([[User talk:Mezzkal|talk]]) 18:25, 25 August 2012 (UTC)

*I want to comment on two parts of the editing that has gone on here.
**About the issues raised by Mezzkal, I don't see any compelling reasons to argue, in this case, about where BRD does or does not apply. I accept that Mezzkal has found some material that is reliably sourced, and is potentially appropriate to add to the article. However, I also find quite reasonable the concerns that I think led IRWolfie to revert. First, the amount of text was very long, relative to the amount of text this page devotes to other demographic studies. Consequently, I think that concerns about [[WP:UNDUE]], completely separate from any issues of &quot;is it true?&quot; or &quot;is it reliably sourced?&quot;, are valid. That would mean that this is a matter of stating the material more concisely, and I'm sure we can do that with some discussion. Also, the material began by saying, in Wikipedia's voice, that this new study showed that the author of a previous study was wrong. Unless we can point to somewhere in the new source that says that their major finding was that Schwadel was wrong, this would violate [[WP:SYNTH]], as well as being needlessly polemic. So I see nothing wrong with sorting these problems out in talk.
**Subsequently, there has been some back-and-forth about the sentence on Schwadel's study. I've restored the sentence, because the RfC cited as a basis for its removal, [[Talk:Atheism/Archive 51#RfC|here]], was actually about different material, if you look at it closely, and that material already was removed. The sentence in question now has recently been discussed just above, [[#I do not understand: Schwadel's study|here]], and I'm not aware of any discussion favoring its deletion.
*--[[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] ([[User talk:Tryptofish|talk]]) 18:54, 25 August 2012 (UTC)

:::Too much emphasis was given to the recent study. It should not refute in Wikipedia's voice any previous study. It should not say anything about [[irreligion]]—that's a different article. It should give a brief summary of numbers of declared atheists per country, and over time where that data is available. [[User:Binksternet|Binksternet]] ([[User talk:Binksternet|talk]]) 19:31, 25 August 2012 (UTC)
::::In my opinion, when an editor makes a good faith attempt to add new information to an article, reverting it in its entirety is unhelpful and hostile.  The two editors who reverted Mezzkal didn't even bother to start a discussion thread about it here on the talk page, they just made drive-by reverts.  Not good.  Instead, if an editor disagrees with the addition, they should start a discussion and say, like Tryptofish and Binksternet did above, what they agree with and what they don't agree with in the new addition, then the interested parties can work from there.  I think that's a much more productive approach. [[User:Cla68|Cla68]] ([[User talk:Cla68|talk]]) 03:26, 26 August 2012 (UTC)
::::::And in my opinion, it's not a big deal whether we discuss it with the material on the page, or with the material temporarily reverted, pending discussion. Anyway, it's really time to move on, to how to rewrite it. --[[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] ([[User talk:Tryptofish|talk]]) 21:23, 26 August 2012 (UTC)

:::::To [[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] : Thanks for your intervention. Now... &lt;u&gt;What do we do about this&lt;/u&gt; ?
:::::You're talking about ''&quot;we should do this with the &quot;material...&quot;'', or ''&quot;the &quot;material&quot; shouldn't state that...&quot;'' etc.
:::::Unfortunately ---thanx to the sense of &quot;ethical behaviour&quot; of IRWolfie, '''then''' of DVobisdu---, we're merely talking about [[Waiting for Godot|Godot]], as... '''''the aforementioned &quot;material&quot; isn't available, anyway, to any good-willing contributor to examine it !'''''
:::::My question is : what do you propose, concretely ?
:::::--[[User:Mezzkal|Mezzkal]] ([[User talk:Mezzkal|talk]]) 17:55, 26 August 2012 (UTC)
::::::You are very welcome! I guess what I'm proposing is that someone, anyone, take a stab at writing, here in talk, a shorter version that reflects what I and Binksternet said. (It's easy to find the previous version in the edit history.) And then we can take it from there. I was hoping that someone else, not me, would take the time to draft it. --[[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] ([[User talk:Tryptofish|talk]]) 21:23, 26 August 2012 (UTC)
::::Cla68, I left Mezzkal a personal message on his user talkpage when I reverted explaining why I did it. I hardly think that is inappropriate. [[User:IRWolfie-|IRWolfie-]] ([[User talk:IRWolfie-|talk]]) 16:01, 28 August 2012 (UTC)

== Error in the article ==

The article includes this line: &quot;In the US, in states with the highest percentages of atheists, the murder rate is lower than average. In the most religious US states, the murder rate is higher than average.&quot; However, the linked article states, &quot;the states with the highest murder rates tend to be highly religious, such as Louisiana and Alabama, but the states with the lowest murder rates tend to be among the least religious in the country, such as Vermont and Oregon&quot;. A state being more or less religious is different than a state having more or less Atheists percentage. Additionally, the difference in percentages may not be statistically significant, depending upon the standard deviations amongst the various states. As such, until more accurate information is located and referenced, the statement should probably be removed. [[User:Xuinkrbin.|Xuinkrbin.]] ([[User talk:Xuinkrbin.|talk]]) 00:00, 29 August 2012 (UTC) xuinkrbin.
:Maybe we should indeed change &quot;percentages of atheists&quot; to wording based instead on high or low religiousity, if that's all the source says (I didn't look). But as for statistical significance, it would be [[WP:OR]] for us to conclude that, unless the source actually says something about statistics. --[[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] ([[User talk:Tryptofish|talk]]) 22:14, 29 August 2012 (UTC)
::If the data tracks the lack of religiosity then the proper article for it is [[irreligion]]. The only way we can include it here is if it charts atheism. [[User:Binksternet|Binksternet]] ([[User talk:Binksternet|talk]]) 22:41, 29 August 2012 (UTC)
:::That's a good point; we should probably go through the statements in the Demographics section with that consideration in mind. The particular sentence discussed here is in [[Atheism#Association with world views and social behaviors]], and is sourced to a long source by Phil Zuckermann. I'm not going to read the whole thing now, but the study, overall, is specifically about atheism, so I think we would have to make sure that Zuckermann really was only talking about irreligion in this instance. --[[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] ([[User talk:Tryptofish|talk]]) 23:03, 29 August 2012 (UTC)
:::It does have some relevance to this article as well considering that atheism is a subset of irreligion. We just need to be careful that we don't say they are exactly the same thing, or equate a rise in irreligion with a rise in atheism. [[User:IRWolfie-|IRWolfie-]] ([[User talk:IRWolfie-|talk]]) 11:14, 30 August 2012 (UTC)

== Edit request on 9 October 2012 ==

{{edit semi-protected|answered=yes}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;

I looked at the page and I immediately thought of the most atheistic region in the world, Scandinavia.

I therefore tried to find a reliable source of how many atheists there really are.

http://www.pitzer.edu/academics/faculty/zuckerman/Ath-Chap-under-7000.pdf

There are huge spans here in which I think the most problem is the difference between atheist and agnostic, but I think Scandinavia is at least worth mentioning
because of its high concentration of atheists in the industrialized world.,even if you don't find this source reliable enough.

&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[User:Interestedman|Interestedman]] ([[User talk:Interestedman|talk]]) 00:54, 9 October 2012 (UTC)
::{{not done}} Sort of already included in the article in the Demographics section.  If you have a specific statement you want included you need to indicate where you wish it included, the precise statement, and appropriate sourcing.  [[User:Sailsbystars|Sailsbystars]] ([[User talk:Sailsbystars|talk]]) 06:19, 9 October 2012 (UTC)


== Inline citations in the lead ==

There is an excessive number of inline citations in the lead, contrary to the rules set out in [[WP:Lead]]. I can do some editing myself at a later date but is anyone available to take on this work? Thanks --[[User:Titanis Walleri|Titanis Walleri]] ([[User talk:Titanis Walleri|talk]]) 21:10, 17 October 2012 (UTC)

:Please read [[WP:LEADCITE]] carefully:
::&quot;The lead must conform to [[Wikipedia:Verifiability|verifiability]] and other policies. The verifiability policy advises that ''material that is challenged or likely to be challenged'', and quotations, should be supported by an [[Wikipedia:Inline citation|inline citation]]. Because the lead will usually repeat information that is in the body, editors should ''balance the desire to avoid redundant citations in the lead with the desire to aid readers in locating sources for challengeable material''. Leads are usually written at a greater level of generality than the body, and information in the lead section of ''non-controversial'' subjects is less likely to be challenged and less likely to require a source; ''there is '''not''', however, an exception to citation requirements specific to leads''. The necessity for citations in a lead should be determined ''on a case-by-case basis by editorial [[Wikipedia:Consensus|consensus]]''. Complex, current, or controversial subjects may require many citations; others, few or none.  ''The presence of citations in the introduction is neither required in every article nor prohibited in any article.''&quot;
:--[[User:JimWae|JimWae]] ([[User talk:JimWae|talk]]) 21:58, 17 October 2012 (UTC)

::I certainly agree there should be some inline citation in this lead, I just think its use is excessive here. Also, the last two paragraphs of the lead should be dropped, in my opinion, as one deals with religion/irreligion (very seperate topics from atheism/theism) and the other quotes 'atheist percentages' of a random half a dozen countries out of a possible 250! Also, the source for these percentages is misrepresented in this article. [[User:Titanis Walleri|Titanis Walleri]] ([[User talk:Titanis Walleri|talk]]) 22:54, 17 October 2012 (UTC)

::: We could omnibus the multiple footnotes into single footnotes naming multiple sources. ~ [[User:Robin Lionheart|Robin Lionheart]] ([[User talk:Robin Lionheart|talk]]) 15:00, 30 October 2012 (UTC)

== Religiosity/ intelligence/ Bell/ Dawkins' quote ==

I have removed the Paul Bell (as quoted by Dawkins) quote. It has been previously discussed [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Atheism/Archive_32#Religiosity_and_intelligence...  here] and, at length with no clear consensus, [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Atheism/Archive_37#Removing_demographics.3F here]
and also over at the [[Religiosity and intelligence]] talk page [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Religiosity_and_intelligence/Archive_2#Removal_of_Bell_.28Dawkins.29 here]. 
Despite numerous discussions, it seems that, consistently, no- one in any of those discussions has actually seen the article. It is not a peer reviewed article, so the methodology might be quite shonky. (It appears suspiciously similar in is conclusions to [http://www.skeptictank.org/files/atheist/religiq2.htm this work], which has multiple issues.) There are better citations in the article already, serving this purpose in a better way.[[User:WotherspoonSmith|WotherspoonSmith]] ([[User talk:WotherspoonSmith|talk]]) 00:49, 8 November 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>orbwkxpe7suswne3z3cbun8mjedh4jd</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
