<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Eastern Christianity</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1228537</id>
    <revision>
      <id>512140997</id>
      <parentid>489055009</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-13T08:14:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Magioladitis</username>
        <id>1862829</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>clean up using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8413)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13330">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Assyria|class=C|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Christianity|class=C|importance=Top|eastern-orthodoxy=yes|eastern orthodoxy-importance=Top|catholicism=yes|catholicism-importance=Top|oriental-orthodoxy=yes|oriental-orthodoxy-importance=Top|core-topics-work-group = yes|core-topics-importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=C|importance=Top}}
}}



==One mistake==
Great job i agree!

But i`ve find one mistake, in ch. 5 
&quot;&quot;The Eastern Orthodox Church includes the following churches

    * Autocephalous Churches&quot;
    ----
     The Church of Serbia (see also: The Church of Montenegro)&quot;
The link for &quot;church of Montenegro&quot; follow to the page of Montenegrin orthodox church (MOC)
th MOC isn`t autocephalous church, even not a canonical church, and couldn't stay on list of Autocephalous churches
of eastern orthodox church.

You can only put this data on some other list, of uncanonical  orthodox churches like:
Ukrainian orthodox church of kiev patriachty, Italian orthodox church, and Bulgarian alternative sinod 
This churches isn`t recognized of other orthodox churchex.


I've tried to flesh out this article with a list of Eastern Christian churches. I've tried to make it clear and consise, and show something of the realationship between the churches. It seems that the acceptance of Ecumenical Councils is the most straightforward way of describing a church's position without getting too technical/theological.

I hope no one minds too much about this rewrite, and I hope that it can form the basis for a better article.
: [[User:Garzo|Gareth Hughes]] 00:15, 1 Dec 2004 (UTC)

== Good job:  ??? ==

Good job overall, Gareth.  Perhaps you, me, or someone else could discuss the theological and practical commonalities and differences in Eastern Christianity, both in terms of the traditions involved and with the West?  Also, you state that there are small Eastern Churches which do not fit into this scheme.  Could you elaborate?  Thanks.--[[User:Midnite Critic|Midnite Critic]] 6 July 2005 21:26 (UTC)

== Need for new section on dissenting sects ==
: I don't know what mention of small Eastern churches you're referring to, Midnite Critic (maybe it's been edited out?), but I think there definitely should be a mention of Eastern Christian dissenting groups -- &quot;Eastern Protestants&quot; if you like, though that's probably too eurocentric a phrase for the article. I'm thinking of the [[Old Believers]] and the [[Spiritual Christianity]] movements in Russia, and also any other dissenting sects that I don't know about. If no one objects, I'll try to write something up in the next few weeks and add it (or if someone else wants to, go ahead). [[User:Zach Alexander|Zach]] ([http://www.wikiveg.org/s wv]) [[User_talk:Zach_Alexander|(t)]] 18:13, 15 September 2005 (UTC)

== eastern orthodox christianty ==

The name is eastern orthodox christianty, not just eastern christianty


: The broadly inclusive term ''Eastern Christianity'' includes a number of bodies other than the Eastern Orthodox Church, such as the [[Oriental Orthodox Church]] and others.  &amp;mdash;[[User:ASDamick|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;A.S. Damick&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:ASDamick|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup&gt;[[Special:Contributions/ASDamick|&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;contribs&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 21:57, 6 March 2006 (UTC)

== Eastern Christanity's calendar ==
Since Eastern Christanity has different date for Easter (and the other holidays whose dates are also tied to Easter) than Western Christanity, it would be useful to have a section on how that came about. [[User:Joncnunn|Joncnunn]] 20:26, 21 April 2006 (UTC)

== Tidying up Eastern Christian entries.  Merge proposals ==
I've just been trying to make sense of the names of the entries regarding the Eastern Churches. The whole matter is quite confusing since we have the following &quot;high level&quot; entries, [[Eastern Christianity]], [[Eastern Church]], [[Orthodox Christianity]], [[Eastern Orthodox Church]], [[Orthodox Church]].

I would like to suggest the following reorganisation:

# Make [[Eastern Church]] redirect to [[Eastern Christianity]] and merge its information into the latter.
#* The rationale being that while the word ''church'' technically can only be applied to Christians it is less explicit than actually using the word Christianity especially when we are referring to something more general than organisations labelled as ''churches''. This would be the place to talk about all eastern churches including oriental, assyrian, etc.
# Make [[Orthodox Church]] redirect to [[Orthodox Christianity]] and make the latter into a disambiguation page.
#* We use Orthodox Christianity rather than Orthodox Church for the same reason as above, and in many ways ''both'' terms are ambiguous. Here again we would disambiguate for all churches in the eastern tradition even ones that do not necessarily use the word orthodox.
# Leave the [[Eastern Orthodox Church]] page alone. This is the place, I think, for the article about Chalcedonian churches within the eastern traditions, including various schismatic groups.
#* Here we leave the word ''church'' since the article mostly refers to specific entities which are called Orthodox Churches.
# Leave the redirect [[Eastern Orthodox Christianity]] alone.

Any suggestions/additions/changes?

[[User:Dorotheus|Dorotheus]] 10:00, 20 August 2006 (UTC)

* As we say in Latin, ''placet''.  [[User:Chonak|Chonak]] 08:53, 27 August 2006 (UTC)
** On second thought: is there some way to put the main page for Orthodoxy under the term &quot;Orthodox Church&quot; or &quot;Orthodox Christianity&quot;, rather than the term &quot;Eastern Orthodox Church&quot;?   My impression is that the latter is not a self-designation. [[User:Chonak|Chonak]] 21:58, 27 August 2006 (UTC)
***I've merged [[Eastern Church]] into [[Eastern Christianity]]. [[User:Chonak|Chonak]] 22:58, 27 August 2006 (UTC)

I noticed that [[Orthodox Christianity]] is very short and almost complete duplicates material here at [[Eastern Christianity]].  To avoid confusing readers, I suggest it be merged here.

There was a &lt;s&gt;dormant&lt;/s&gt; merge proposal that [[Orthodox Churches]] merge with [[Orthodox Christianity]].  That is basically a list, and could also come here.  What do you think?  If enough people like it, someone should go ahead and do the merges a few days after the discussion quietens.  --[[User:Hro%C3%B0ulf|Hroðulf]] (or Hrothulf) ([[User talk:Hro%C3%B0ulf|Talk]]) 14:33, 4 September 2006 (UTC)

:Good point.   The content of [[Orthodox Christianity]] parallels [[Eastern Christianity]].  [[User:Chonak|Chonak]] 14:46, 4 September 2006 (UTC)

==Merged from [[Orthodox Christianity]]==
I've brought in material from the above page; some disambiguation cleanup remains to be done, as [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=Orthodox_Christianity numerous pages] and [[Template:Christianity]] have links to [[Orthodox Christianity]], now a simple disambiguation page.   [[User:Chonak|Chonak]] 06:12, 12 September 2006 (UTC)

== Christian Judaism ==

Would that count as Eastern Christianity, since it developed in the greece-rome-israel area? It's certainly not Western Christianity by a longshot..

== What does this sentence mean? ==

I'm having difficulty interpreting the second sentence of the article. Could someone clarify? [[User:Majoreditor|Majoreditor]] 14:42, 3 April 2007 (UTC)

::Much better now, thanks. [[User:Majoreditor|Majoreditor]] 04:23, 11 April 2007 (UTC)

== Changes made by Majoreditor ==
To Majoreditor: Can you comment on this edit?
:&quot;[[Western Europe]] (using the Medieval definition which excludes Greece).&quot; -&gt; &quot;[[Western Europe]].&quot;
If you read the Western Europe page, the statement here does not make sense unless you include that qualification, or something like it. If you want to rephrase go ahead but I don't understand the reason for removing this altogether.
--[[User:Mcorazao|Mcorazao]] 19:06, 16 April 2007 (UTC)

::Thanks for asking the question. I should have noted it in my edit.  There are two reasons why I removed &quot; (using the Medieval definition which excludes Greece) &quot; from the sentence.  The primary reason is that many post Cold War definitions place Greece in Southern Europe, not Western Europe. See the U.N. definition contained within the [[Western Europe]] article as an example.  The second reason is to eliminate unnecessary use of parenthetical statements.  
::If other editors feel that a casual reader is likely to think of Greece as part of Westren Europe, then by all means, feel free to clarify. [[User:Majoreditor|Majoreditor]] 19:30, 16 April 2007 (UTC)

Thanks. The point here is that the pages need to be consistent. If you are asserting that Greece is not conventionally considered part of Western Europe then the Western Europe page should be modified to deprecate Greece in that definition (note that the map at the top of the page clearly shows Greece as part of Western Europe). Sorry if I'm being anal but, given that &quot;Eastern Christianity&quot; largely has its origins in the Greek-speaking communities, defining Greece's position seems like something that should not be glossed over in this context.

BTW, regarding the edit to &quot;Orthodox Christianity&quot;, the &quot;Orthodox Church&quot; page links here. So presumably either Orthodox Christianity should be mentioned as an alternative naming (since this a popular term) or else Orthodox Church should not link here. Looking at the page since this page does discuss Eastern Catholicism probably Orthodox Church should link elsewhere. Do you agree?
--[[User:Mcorazao|Mcorazao]] 20:37, 16 April 2007 (UTC)

P.S. For what it's worth, I don't tend to think of Greece as being &quot;Western&quot; but, to be honest, I think including &quot;Greece&quot; in the West is a popular perspective (even among the Greeks to some degree). --[[User:Mcorazao|Mcorazao]] 20:41, 16 April 2007 (UTC)

::I agree that consistency is important.  Honestly, the [[Western Europe]] page could use some work.  It admits that its initial usage of the term is limited to the Cold War and that there are other definitions, such as that used by the U.N.  Since the Cold War has been over for some time and old definitions are muddled, I'd prefer that the Western Europe page change. That said, I'm not inclined to do it right now -- too many other commitments -- and I don't have a strong preference, so I leave the matter in your hands. Thanks. [[User:Majoreditor|Majoreditor]] 21:05, 16 April 2007 (UTC)
::Concerning Orthodox Christianity: what would you think about using a disamb. page? [[User:Majoreditor|Majoreditor]] 22:50, 16 April 2007 (UTC)

I kind of agree about the Western Europe page. I guess I'll think about trying to modify if I have time ...

Regarding the disamig, actually I was just noticing that &quot;Orthodox Christianity&quot; is a disambig page so I'm not clear why &quot;Orthodox Church&quot; hashes here. Any objections to redirecting Orthodox Church to that disamig page?
--[[User:Mcorazao|Mcorazao]] 02:10, 17 April 2007 (UTC)

::That's a good suggestion. I agree.  [[User:Majoreditor|Majoreditor]] 14:38, 17 April 2007 (UTC)

== Easy to separate east and west ==

If I understand correctly the most basic difference is that eastern christianity derive their root of authority from John (the apocalyptic evangelist) on Pathmos, while any western christianity rests on the power of Simon Peter in Rome. This predates brawls over those early synods or formal liturgical differences. [[User:81.0.68.145|81.0.68.145]] 20:09, 11 July 2007 (UTC)

:I do not believe you understand correctly. Both eastern and western christianity derive their root of authority from Christ who established His Church. [[User:TMLutas|TMLutas]] 21:09, 5 September 2007 (UTC)

== [[Ukrainian Autocephalous Orthodox Church]] ==

Should this be listed [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eastern_Christianity#Eastern_Orthodox_Churches here] or not?--[[User:Vidkun|Vidkun]] ([[User talk:Vidkun|talk]]) 14:17, 8 October 2008 (UTC)

== &quot;Nestorian Church&quot; ==

&quot;In the West, it is sometimes inaccurately called the Nestorian Church.&quot; Is this not POV? [[User:Deusveritasest|Deusveritasest]] ([[User talk:Deusveritasest|talk]]) 20:43, 27 April 2009 (UTC)

== Subject ==

The article seems confused about what it's about. The lead treats it as synonymous with Orthodoxy, but the body includes Eastern Catholics. [[User:Peter jackson|Peter jackson]] ([[User talk:Peter jackson|talk]]) 17:43, 20 August 2009 (UTC)

::I agree. The lead was recently altered without consensus. I'd prefer for the lead not to imply that all Eastern Orthodox Christians belong to the Eastern Orthodox Church. The lead either needs to clearly say that Eastern Christians comprose several confessions or it needs to return to its original phrasing. [[User:Majoreditor|Majoreditor]] ([[User talk:Majoreditor|talk]]) 00:38, 21 August 2009 (UTC)

:::Err, all Eastern Orthodox Chritian to belong to an Eastern Orthodox church. All Christians that would be called &quot;Eastern Christians&quot; by a Western-centric person would not belong to Eastern Orthodoxy.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by --[[User:Scyldscefing|Scyldscefing]] ([[User talk:Scyldscefing|talk]]) 21:10, 29 January 2010 (UTC)[[User:Scyldscefing|Scyldscefing]] ([[User talk:Scyldscefing|talk]]</text>
      <sha1>4b8smyb08cqe7u3j7fy6jww4vvcrkl6</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
