<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Human sacrifice</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>450044</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517367319</id>
      <parentid>517178738</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-12T10:35:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Graham87</username>
        <id>194203</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>straight revert to last version by H. 217.83</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="96290">{{WPReligion|class=B|importance=Top|attention=yes}}
{{Wikiproject mythology|class=B|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Death|class=B|importance=high}}
{{to do|2}}

==Central America==

The section entitled &quot;Central America&quot; should be renamed &quot;Middle America&quot; or &quot;Mesoamerica&quot;, as much of the information is about Mexico, which is not in Central America.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Hoplophile|Hoplophile]] ([[User talk:Hoplophile|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Hoplophile|contribs]]) 14:12, 18 December 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Done! [[User:Simon Burchell|Simon Burchell]] ([[User talk:Simon Burchell|talk]]) 16:33, 15 January 2009 (UTC)

==unsigned, undated posts==

:Has it occured to anyone that Christian heresy trials were a vestige of human sacrifice cults in earlier religions? There must be some studies on this. I'll look into it. This page strikes me as having an occidental biased pov.

== ==
:these paragraphs have an ass-load of linked words, it harms readability. if someone really doesn't know what &quot;mediaeval&quot; is they can type it in themself, is my opinion.

:

== Crete ==
True, I don't remember the Cretan reference. Also, why is it thought the people found in the foundation of buildings are necessarily sacrificial victims? Even today people sometimes end up in the foundation of buildings because of accidents and the impossibility of getting them out. 


'' Cretans tried to stop the destruction of their island this way.'' With human sacrifices to the volcano or something? Destruction of Crete? Was this an Atlantis movie? Can we remove this? [[User:Wetman|Wetman]] 05:19, 1 Feb 2004 (UTC)

: i remember an article in National Geographic, it was an excavation of what it seems it was a human sacrifice. An earthquake killed the priest, and his remains are beside the victim. The quake was estimated about the time of Thera eruption. I read it about 10 years ago, i will try to find the reference and see if it,s a propiated here.
[[User:Nanahuatzin|Nanahuatzin]] 00:47, 15 Mar 2005 (UTC)

The references to Cretan human sacrifice in both myth and recent archaeological publications have actually never been substantiated or accepted by the archaeological community at large. The two instances of 'human sacrifice'  on Crete are 1)burnt children's bones found in the basement of a Late Minoan IB house at Knossos and 2)a burnt skeleton at the 'shrine' at Anemospilia, slightingly above the site of Archanes, which is the example to which you are refering Nanahuatzin. Although the excavater of the house at Knossos, Peter Warren, advanced the idea of cannibalism based on the presence of cut marks on the bones, forensic scientists and archaeologists generally agree that these marks are simple prove the presence of defleshing of the bones which is common in many burial practices. As for Y. Sakellarakis and E. Sapouna-Sakellaraki, the excavators of Archanes and Anemospilia, they have never published a forensic scientist's report confirming their claim that the strange coloration of the bones of the alleged victim are a direct result of his being sacrificed. All other evidence that they site is circumstantial or incorrect. For a comprehensive overview of both sites I recommend the book 'Human Sacrifice in Ancient Greece' by Dennis D. Hughes.
[[User:ClaireAliki|ClaireAliki]] 20:02, 6 January 2006 (UTC)
:It always amazes me how touchy people get at the possibility that the Minoans weren't the flower-loving utopian civilization people want them to be. &quot;All other evidence is circmstantial or incorrect&quot;? what nonsense. The arguments against the evidence of human sacrifice always seems to go along the lines of &quot;the minoans (as the peaceful, creative, civilized people they were) wouldn't do that, so obviously it is untrue&quot;. It's all a left over of the romantic turn of the century fantasies of Arthur Evans. I mean, for god's sake, the children found in the 'basement' were tellingly found with the bones of sheep or goats, who had similar marks on the bones, etc. The young man in the tripartite shrine was found on a table, trussed up like the bull on the Hagia Triada sarcophagus! With a long knife blade mingled with his bones...and the table/altar was next to a column with a trough at its base.... near the feet of presumably what had been an image of a goddess or something. And out in the front room, there had been someone carrying a jar of blood. Animal blood, to be sure, but come on, explaining these details away requires venturing into absurdity. What I recommend is reading up on the historiography of Crete, in order to understand the century of baggage attached to &quot;Minoan&quot; Crete. 
[[User:Novium|Novium]] 13:21, 11 November 2006 (UTC)

== biblical sacrifice ==  
A comment on the article: &quot;Many places in the Hebrew Bible state that human sacrifice was a great abomination; these practices were associated with the worship of foreign gods, and were forbidden. See , however, Judges 11:39, in which the Israelite leader Jephthah offered his daughter as a sacrifice in fulfilment of a vow.&quot;

:Danny, this is an interesting example. However, we need to distinguish between the laws of the Bible (this is what a person should do) and the stories in the Bible (this is what this person did.) In this case, the Bible is not reccomending this course of action; I think it is showing that Jephthah made a tragic error.  According to ''Etz Hayyim: A Torah Commentary'', the point of this episode is to teach that this was really quite wrong: &quot;This is a final example of how a formal legalism can lead to violent ends&quot; (p.909)  The same conclusion is reached in the classic &quot;Pentateuch and Haftarahs&quot; by Rabbi Dr. Joseph H. Hertz.  (Herzt quotes a verse from Dante condemning the stupidity of blindly making and following vows.

Classical Jewish commentators, such as David Kimchi, the Ralbag and Abarbanel hold that his vow should never have led to sacrifice. According to Hertz, the rabbis severely blame Jephthah for nothaving his invalid vow annulled. [[User:RK|RK]] 03:02, Jun 11, 2004 (UTC)

:Actually, if you look at the verses, there is no judgement being made. It is simply stating the story very matter of factly. Yes, biblical commentators have condemned it. Some claimn that he never actually sacrificed her. All of that is irrelevant. They are imposing later religious values on a piece of text. That is not interpretting the verses, that is apologizing for them. As such, you are providing a medieval or enlightenment view of a erse, and ignoring what it indicates as a reflection of the beliefs of the people it describes. I'm not a big fan of rabbinic apologetics. [[User:Danny|Danny]] 03:08, 11 Jun 2004 (UTC)

::Danny, the Bible says that the Egyptians enslaved and killed Israelites. Does that mean that God wants us to do this as well? The Bible says that Cain slew Abel; does this mean that God is commanding fratricide? Of course not; We can't read the Bible like this. As you well know, the Bible presents stories of bad people as well as good people. This is not medieval rabbinic apologetics. So why are you insisting that we must read this story as a commandment to peform human sacrifice? I just can't see this anywhere in the text - and I don't know anyone else who reads it that way. Do any modern Bible historians hold that this story is a command for sacrifice? [[User:RK|RK]]

::As for the fanciful claims that his daughter was never sacrificed, yes, I agree that these are fanciful apologetics, and I am not a fan of them either. However, my main point stand: This story does not command Jews to perform human sacrifice, in any way. It merely offers a tragic story of a man who made a rash vow and stupidly fulfilled it, just like the story of Cain and Abel offers us a tragic story of sibling rivalry, punishment, and semi-redemption. [[User:RK|RK]] 03:29, Jun 11, 2004 (UTC)

:::Nowhere have I said that the Bible commands us to perform human sacrifice. I simply pointed out that the attitudes toward the practice are ambiguous, by pointing to a story which does not make an obvious value judgment about it (I could argue that the Akeidah does not make an obvious value judgment either, but if you can't see it in Jephthah there is no point). The point is especially important because it gives an insight into how the Bible should be tackled. It is not a homogeneous text, despite what the later commentators that you quote above are trying to prove. Furthermore, your comparison of Jephthah to the Egyptians (or Cain for that matter) is just plain misinformed. &amp;#1497;&amp;#1508;&amp;#1514;&amp;#1495; &amp;#1489;&amp;#1491;&amp;#1493;&amp;#1512;&amp;#1493; &amp;#1499;&amp;#1513;&amp;#1502;&amp;#1493;&amp;#1488;&amp;#1500; &amp;#1489;&amp;#1491;&amp;#1493;&amp;#1512;&amp;#1493;. Comparing the attitude toward an Israelite leader to the attitude toward an Israelite enemy is silly. Step back from 2000 years of interpretation and just read the verses. [[User:Danny|Danny]] 10:10, 11 Jun 2004 (UTC)

:The Bible does pretty clearly condemn the Egyptians for their treatment of slaves, and clearly condemns Cain for killing Abel. The curious thing about this passage is that it neither praises nor condemns it, which seems to indicate that at the time of the story, human sacrifice was not especially condemned. While the story does convey the message of &quot;Don't make promises that you are not prepared to keep&quot; (which was probably why the story was sufficiently noteworthy to record in the first place), Jephthah was clearly willing to perform human sacrifice. The tragedy in the story (from Jephthah's perpective) was that he had to sacrifice his daughter, not that he had to perform human sacrifice. The story probably would not have been noteworthy had a servant been the object of sacrifice.--[[User:RLent|RLent]] 22:31, 10 February 2006 (UTC) 

Danny, I have no idea what you aree talking about, and you have gotten your own thoughts confused. (A) You started off by saying that the Bible approved of human sacrifice, and you argued with me that we must read the verse this way. Now you have totally reversed yourself and have adopted '''my''' position, yet you still seem to arguing. I am glad that you now reject your earlier view. [[User:RK|RK]]

Danny, you write &quot;The point is especially important because it gives an insight into how the Bible should be tackled. It is not a homogeneous text, despite what the later commentators that you quote above are trying to prove.&quot; Again, I have no idea of what you are talking about. The references I gave made no such point, and I certainly made no such point. None at all. Rather, the point was very simple: They viewed this man's actions as immoral. ''This has nothing to do with how the Bible was edited,'' and I can't imagine why you are going off on this tangent. [[User:RK|RK]]

Danny, you write &quot;Furthermore, your comparison of Jephthah to the Egyptians (or Cain for that matter) is just plain misinformed. &quot; No, man, this is a ''fact''. Contrary to your claims, many ''modern day Bible scholars'', as well as traditional rabbis, have made precisely the same point. This has nothing to do with 2,000 year old commentaries. Just because the Bible mentions that something happened does not mean that the Bible views the event as moral or good. You are twisting my words to mean something they don't, and then you are attacking a position I simply do not have. Calm down. [[User:RK|RK]]

Should druid/druidic/etc. be capitalized or lower-case? [[User:Ground|Ground]] 21:13, 16 Oct 2004 (UTC)

==The [[thuggee]] did not practice human sacrifice==
Can somebody please provide a reference from a reputable source for the statement that [[thuggee]] practices human sacrifice. As far as I know they murdered people to rob them. They did not kill people as a sacrifice to [[Kali]]. [[User:Andries|Andries]] 18:11, 4 June 2006 (UTC)

:Thuggees justified their killings as sacrifices to kali although most of the time it was also profitable! I don't have a convenient reference to add. [[User:217.7.209.108|217.7.209.108]] 13:29, 28 March 2007 (UTC)

== Human Sacrifice in Hinduism ==

I dont know why material from hinduism is not added in this article. It is available in plenty at :

http://www.ambedkar.org/riddleinhinduism/21A1.Riddles%20in%20Hinduism%20PART%20I.htm#r01

See my text in the talk page

[[Talk:Purushamedha]]

This describes exact procedure for human sacrifice in hinduism. I would like that someone may please add material to this article from it, else I may do it in my capacity. 

--[[User:L.Gautam|L.Gautam]] 10:20, 3 July 2006 (UTC)

==[dead reference link]==

Under &quot;Modern Human Sacrifice,&quot; there is a mention of a ritual murder that supposedly took place in 1999; however, the external reference link is dead, and the website to which it was supposed to link is. . .well, I'll let you judge its reliability:
http://www.davidicke.com/content/view/293/43/
[[User:Shakantala|Shakantala]] 20:17, 3 July 2006 (UTC)

== folklore, antropology ==

I suggest to take also into account &quot;The Highest Altar&quot; by Patrick Tierny (Viking Penguin 1989).
Tierny cites several Hebrew scholars on (pre-biblical?) human sacrifice (p.394 etc). The work turns to the bible as a research document, not as a set of irrelevant 'commands'.
The book of Tierny also describes, convincingly, present day human sacrifice in Peru, both among villagers threaten by a flood and among drug trafficers before a big transaction.
All by all it seems difficult to device a folkloric geography of human sacrifice based on written sources. One paragraph  can colour centuries of a whole population, while the absence of proof is never a proof of absence... 
Maybe sacrifice has its origin in forefather cults of early farmers, while the value offered depends on the favour hoped for. Chicken are cheap, girls are expensive (Jephtah), boys even more (Abraham). If a modern state accepts to 'sacrifice' young men to keep borders intact, a primitive village might also accept to sacrifice a child to avoid a big loss of resources. 
This approach would make any research document relevant to specific socio-economic conditions, not to ethnic groups.

== POV/Religious partisanism ==

I don't have the time to rewrite it just now, but the section about human sacrifice in the
Hebrew Bible is clearly biased towards Christianity/Judaism and does not reflect the
conclusions of modern secular scholarship. 

If this site is not to be known as &quot;The LORD's very own Christian Wikipedia&quot;, this should change.

== the section headed &quot;Modern human sacrifice&quot; is ugly ==

and seems to be a catch-all heap for anything that vaguely resembles human [[sacrifice]] (by which I mean &quot;the killing of a human being in offering to supernatural powers&quot;), plus one reliably substantiated (in part) report of the genuine article. And a tacked-on bit about some human sacrifices that occurred ''over two millenia'' ago. 

:''Human sacrifice, in the context of religious ritual, still occurs in some traditional religions, for example in muti killings in eastern Africa.''
If the article on [[medicine murder]] is correct (I don't know offhand), then this isn't actually sacrifice as such, is it.

:''Some people in India are adherents of a religion called Tantrism. . .''
This appears to be the genuine article, but the second quotation needs a reference.

:''A group of the rich and powerful people gather for an annual mock human sacrifice of an effigy at the Bohemian Club in California.''

Silly me, I thought this article was about [[human sacrifice]], not [[fraternities doing silly things in the woods]]. Or [[burning in effigy]], for that matter.

:''In Western cultures no human sacrifice occurs beyond murders committed by serial killers or the largely unsubstantiated Satanic ritual abuse. '' 
Okay. The next sentence has a broken citation to [[David Icke]]'s website and needs scrutiny. The following one seems to concern a black metal musician looking for Viking credit, but maybe he really believed it, so okay.

:''Modern occultists consider such sacrifices unnecessary, or use them only in the symbolic form where the volunteer &quot;sacrifice&quot; is not actually killed.''
Another sentence about not practicing actual human sacrifice. I don't know, maybe misconceptions need correcting.

:''Some people have tried to extend the use of sacrifice-related terminology. . . .''
This is relevant.

:'' 	Modern [[Islamist terrorism|Muslim terrorist]] [[Suicide bombing|suicide bombers]] as well as [[Japan|Japanese]] [[kamikaze]] [[Aviator|pilots]] can also be claimed to be examples of human (self-)sacrifice.''
Sure they can, by someone who wouldn't recognize a [[blood libel]] if he were slapped in the face with one. I took this one out. 

::The original article may have been right with respect to kamikaze pilots.  Please see the Preface ([http://books.google.com/books?id=0tPjVJF8roYC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=kali+human+sacrifices&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=3FV0TNuND8GC8gbfroT2CA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=9&amp;ved=0CFQQ6AEwCA#v=onepage&amp;q=kali&amp;f=false page vii]) of ''The Strange World of Human Sacrifice'':
::&lt;blockquote&gt;In Japanese tales human sacrifice often takes the form of self-sacrifice, and there may well be a line from these early sacrifices to modern kamikaze.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
::[[User:Hokie Tech|Hokie Tech]] ([[User talk:Hokie Tech|talk]]) 23:36, 24 August 2010 (UTC)

:''The most prominent example in recent times was undertaken by the Buddhist monk [[Thich Quang Duc]].''
[[self-immolation]] in protest isn't exactly human sacrifice. I took this out too.

:''Historically prominent human sacrifices include:''
* [[Lindow Man]] in the [[United Kingdom]]
* [[Tollund Man]] in [[Denmark]] (from the article: ''At first, Tollund Man was believed to be a rich man who had been ritually sacrificed, but recent analysis suggests that he may simply have been a criminal who was hanged and buried in the peat bog.'')

and to crown it, two human sacrifices that are not modern in the slightest, both being over 2,000 years old. (And no mention of ''why'' they are historically prominent&amp;mdash;because they're preserved so well&amp;mdash;just the assertion that they are, indeed, prominent. (''And'' the first is already mentioned in the proper place above. People often don't read the article before they edit it.) I took this text out; the second example, with a shorter parenthetical doubt, might be replaced in the proper section. &amp;mdash;[[User:Mirv|Charles P._]]&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Mirv|(Mirv)]]&lt;/small&gt; 01:58, 8 September 2006 (UTC)

I believe that [[kamikaze]] pilots and [[Suicide bombing|suicide bombers]] falls under the definition of [[self-sacrifice]] A man or woman who willingly sacrifices their life. If they are volunteering, then I wouldn't consider it to be part of a ritual that is most commonly on a forcible bases. [[User:hunterkyrie.]]  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Hunterkyrie|Hunterkyrie]] ([[User talk:Hunterkyrie|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Hunterkyrie|contribs]]) 21:27, 15 March 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Roman Sacrifice==
I think it may need some work. Just off the top of my head, early gladitorial games were rarely to the death, IIRC. Additionally, there seems to be a lack of distinction between execution and human sacrifice. The Romans obviously had no problem executing people left and right, but I seem to remember that they had a horror of human sacrifice. The vestal virgin example given in the article, for example, was the punishment for breaking their vows of chastity. Which was supposed to spell doom for Rome, and thus was as treasonous as you could get... so  is it really human sacrifice? 
[[User:Novium|Novium]] 13:21, 11 November 2006 (UTC)
:I think that it's strange to think that romans had such a horror of human sacrifice since they killed thousands of persons mostly for entertainment... anyway, since you do a celebration to honor some god, some dead ancestor  or some deified emperor, it has connotations of human sacrifice...--[[User:Ozomatli-Tepoztli|Ozomatli-Tepoztli]] 04:16, 10 April 2007 (UTC)

::To you, perhaps. I find it strange because I was a classicist, so I'm not just making judgments with no regard of context or history.  It's not at all the same. Sacrifice- in the antique religious tradition- had a clear set of conditions and contexts. There were rituals. Simple execution, or the games, did not fill the criteria. [[Special:Contributions/75.54.122.212|75.54.122.212]] ([[User talk:75.54.122.212|talk]]) 04:30, 15 September 2010 (UTC)

::What shocked Romans was child sacrifice by Carthaginians. —[[User:Cesar Tort|Cesar Tort]] 04:38, 10 April 2007 (UTC)

:: Don't forget the druids. It was human sacrifice, period. They outlawed it six ways from Sunday.[[Special:Contributions/75.54.122.212|75.54.122.212]] ([[User talk:75.54.122.212|talk]]) 04:30, 15 September 2010 (UTC)

In objective ethnographic terms it is always difficult, if not impossible, to distinguish human sacrifice from &quot;simple&quot; execution. This is true of all cultures, not just of Roman antiquity.
In pre-modern society, the law is set by the gods, and there can therefore be no distinction between &quot;secular&quot; and &quot;sacral&quot; killings.
Capital punishment can only be clearly separated from human sacrifice if it is completely de-ritualized, i.e. casual mass executions by just shooting people on the highway. Such de-ritualized and thus de-sacralized mass killings recur in history (rebellion of Spartacus, French revolution, WWII, Communist China, etc.), but over time, as a society becomes stable, execution of capital punishment will automatically again become highly ritualized. 
I suspect that the ban of druidism has less to do with a distinction between secular vs. sacral killing, but rather the point that under Roman rule, nobody should be executed for whatever reasons except under Roman law. You cannot allow your subjects to keep their own customs on when and how to kill people because this interferes with your ruling them. This is of course an universal law of empires and not peculiar to the Roman-Celtic situation in any way. --[[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|(𒁳)]]&lt;/small&gt; 11:00, 15 September 2010 (UTC)

== Christian sacrifice ==

Christians sacrificed &quot;witches&quot; to God to save the populace. Why isn't this listed in the article? [[User:Jyrinnis|Jyrinnis]] 14:45, 21 November 2006 (UTC)

:Because it wasn't a sacrifice.  [[User:Goldfritha|Goldfritha]] 00:10, 22 November 2006 (UTC)

For all intents and purposes, yes it was. They believed God would be pleased and unplague their lands or
whatever they wanted if they killed off a few &quot;evil&quot; members of the community. [[User:Jyrinnis|Jyrinnis]] 08:12, 27 November 2006 (UTC)

:No, it wasn't.  They believed that these people had deliberately caused magical harm and were properly punished by death.
:Furthermore, executing people for witchcraft was common about people who ''did'' sacrifice to the gods to remove harm.  The largest witch hunts, in terms of victims, on record occured in the (pagan) Roman Republic.  The distinction is quite clear, even to those who practiced both.  [[User:Goldfritha|Goldfritha]] 01:31, 28 November 2006 (UTC)

I agree with Jyrinnis, it was a form of sacrifice. They were evil in the Christian eyes, but according to written or oral beliefs brought upon by the Christian myth. Any neo-pagan would agree with me that they were a form of ritual sacrifice, a pharmakos ritual which according to the scholar Hughes is classified as a human sacrifice, thus burning witches = pharmakos rite pharmakos = ritual human sacrifice, burning witches = human sacrifice. And on the other hand, Pagan victims all over the world were at least 10 times more than the Christian ones. I wrote a university paper on christian martyrs in the late roman empire, I can tell you that not more than 2000 Christians have been killer over 200 years and this is too high according to certain scholars. If we talk about the neo-platonist martyrs of Alexandria (killed by the Christian mob), murder of pagan priests, witch hunts, forced conversion and murder of new world people we reach a statistic which is huge in number of victims. Thus yes I would add a paragraph concerning christian sacrifice. Keltica

:Your references use the term too loosely.  The meaning of human sacrifice is rather more precise than that.  [[User:Goldfritha|Goldfritha]] 00:26, 7 December 2006 (UTC)

Not at all, I'm very precise. I'm concentrating on ritual murder of pagans being justified by &quot;God&quot;, it always represents at least a pharmakos which is a form of human sacrifice. I wouldn't mention it entirely in this article, I would place a link to a different article on this topic. Keltica

:I think this is a stupid point.  Witches were accused of killing people, destroying crops, etc.  Murder for example clearing falls under legal jurisdiction.  Just because our modernist world doesn't believe that a witch could not commit murder in a supernatural way, does not not mean that they still were not under legal jurisdiction of the time.  To read it any other way is to be anachronistic.  Also, if people are going to claim all the &quot;staggering statistics&quot; of people murdered by Christians, we might as well add the Christians murdered under Pagan Roman.  By the definition provided we might as well include all the genocides of the last century committed by (pseudo)science and godless ideologies, as those killed under the Great Leap Forward were more numerous than those claimed to be killed under any religious war.  I vote to keep this article pared down to REAL human sacrifices.

Just read the official reasons for MURDERING witches and the survivors of the ancient pagan creeds of heathens from the new world, you will clearly see that it is a form of human sacrifice, legal jurisdiction is an excuse to cover it and often isn't always employed, take the case of Joan of Arc. 

I think it is offensive to all pagans of the ancient times and modern times to label these murders as legal murders of people who infringe the law, I feel that we are protecting the church too much. I admit it, I'm not a Christian and I have strong personal reasons for this but it doesn't mean I'm trying to be objective. Anyways I can tell you that Christian martyrs are a lot less thsan pagan martyrs across the centuries, also because in many pagan societies Christians were tolerated in some way or another. The Christian society (late antiquity, mediaeval and renaissance) was far less tolerant. I agree with you it doesn't have a place on this page, but it deserves an article. I shall write it soon. This encyclopaedia should be open-minded, we shouldn't be protecting the Church or Christianity itself, this creed has spilt a lot of blood in history and still hides evil. Keltica
:I've read the official reasons.  They do not contain what you claim.  Furthermore, the evidence that the people executed for witcraft were not &quot;survivors of the ancient pagan creeds&quot; is rather stronger than you seem to be aware.[[User:Goldfritha|Goldfritha]] 16:56, 26 December 2006 (UTC)

If I said that I didn't mean it, paganism has evolved in time. It was a form of religious intolerance which brought upon the ritual murder of &quot;different&quot; beings. You cannot deny that to the eyes of the populace these were scapegoat rituals. Keltica
:&quot;If I said that&quot; -- your pronoun lacks a referent.  What are you denying meaning?  And given that your words are directly above mine, why should there be any question about what you said?
:There is absolutely no evidence whatsoever that the witchcraft trials sprung from &quot;religious intolerance&quot; because there is no evidence either that the people executed were practicing a different religion, or that a specific religion was the inspiration for the trials -- seeing as people have been executed for witchcraft all over the world, under every stripe of religion, and the biggest witch trials on record occured in the (pagan) Roman Republic.
:And in the eyes of the populace, they were certainly not scapegoat rituals.  [[User:Goldfritha|Goldfritha]] 16:07, 28 December 2006 (UTC)

All you said is open to discussion. And I feel you're biased. 
On the other hand your point regarding sacrifices under the Roman Republic is false. There were far more victims for witch trials. I assure you, it is true. Keltica (and btw, If I said that, I didn't mean it is correct)
:I assure you, I have the information on the Roman Republic from a reliable, published source.  And you give a few indication of bias yourself.[[User:Goldfritha|Goldfritha]] 23:53, 4 January 2007 (UTC)

Please cite it then. Because I can guarantee that my professor in University demonstrated that everything that is said about martyrdom and sacrifice in the Roman Republic is a Christian invention. I don't want to quarrel, but it's absurd to leave out the bloodthirsty crimes of the Christians in later ages. I'm going to write the article and you're welcome to add to it. But an encyclopaedia should be a bearer of truth and unbiased and it cannot be written by Christians alone. Keltica
:While I'm looking it up -- you do realize that the Roman Republic was gone before Christianity was around?  [[User:Goldfritha|Goldfritha]] 23:52, 5 January 2007 (UTC)

I'm sorry, I meant human sacrifice in the Roman Republic and Martyrdom during the Empire. Keltica

:Hey you should continue the roman subject on the &quot;Roman Sacrifice&quot; section. Hi Keltica. I reply to you the same i answered to Novium there --[[User:Ozomatli-Tepoztli|Ozomatli-Tepoztli]] 04:47, 10 April 2007 (UTC)

While the argument for spectral evidence in murder is a good point what about the murder of Jews by Christians, throughout the Rhine region during the Black Death in Europe, around the 1340s.  The History Channel’s &quot;THE PLAGUE&quot; notes that while some groups (falsely) blamed Jews for poisoning wells many Christians simply believed that the plague was caused by their God's displeasure at the toleration of Jews.  As a result they burned many Jews at the stake and attacked Jewish communities to appease God and end the plague.  As for the legal arguments many of these burnings were extrajudicial and officially condemned by Pope Clement VI via a papal bull on July 6, 1348.  I am simply curious whether these would be considered human sacrifices and if not why not?

Secondly what about persons burned during the medieval and renaissance period under heresy laws in Western Europe, the vast majority of these people were Christian but had different interpretations of Christianity then the State sponsored Churches and were burned to cleanse them and atone for their heresy. (In actually a whole host of other reasons existed but they were not behind the public reasoning for the burnings). Again just curious whether these would be considered human sacrifices and if not why not?[[User:Bored college student|Bored college student]] 08:43, 3 October 2007 (UTC)

: Generally speaking, a sacrifice is an offering to God or to a God, right?  That's the criteria by which Christians have never performed human sacrifice.  They burned witches, slaughtered Muslims and Jews, and behaved badly in all sorts of ways, but they never killed people as an offering to God.  Their misdeeds belong in other articles (eg. [[moral panic]], or whatever), not here. [[User:Niten|Niten]] ([[User talk:Niten|talk]]) 21:49, 17 December 2009 (UTC)

==Why==
This may sound like a weird question, but why do primitive cultures sacrifice humans or animals. I know the point is to please or appease a god or spirit, but is there any way to know what these people thought the supernatural beings wanted the sacrifices for? For example, when the biblical god told Abraham to sacrifice his son and then a ram, what would Yehwey have done with either of these after they had been sacrificed? Would he have (somehow) consumed their soul, for example? Would he have just been pleased that Abraham didn't have a ram to eat or a son, deriving pleasure from his lose? Do we just not have the answers to these questions. [[User:JesseHogan|JesseHogan]] 07:09, 26 November 2006 (UTC)

One possible answer is that people thought that Gods lived above them and they tried throwing stuff up to them and it came back down, but, when they burnt something and the smoke rose up in the air and it smelled good, the people might have thought that the Gods liked burnt offerings.  Another possible idea is that people might have thought that since stronger people tend to take what they want, and since the Gods must have been stronger than anyone, then the way to appease the Gods is to give them the best and most valuable items they had.  Ever have a dog or cat bring you an animal they just killed? I think it's the same idea. As far as [[Abraham]] was concerned; it was a test of his devotion to God.  Before that, Abraham acted as though God and he were partners; this showed that God was fully in charge, and God tested Abraham to see how he would react.  Some have said that Abraham failed the test because he should have argued on behalf on his son, (as he argued for the residents of [[Sodom and Gomorrah]]), but, at that period in time, human sacrifice was too common a practice for Abraham to say no. [[User:204.80.61.10|204.80.61.10]] 22:12, 29 November 2006 (UTC)Bennett Turk

Thanks for responding. Its interesting that history is replete with animal and human sacrafice but we can only speculate on its logic. Maybe this disparity will get some attention in the article. [[User:JesseHogan|JesseHogan]] 06:35, 30 November 2006 (UTC)

You know, I could have looked at the article on [[sacrifice]]. It has a list of explainations. [[User:JesseHogan|JesseHogan]] 07:26, 1 December 2006 (UTC)

For an explanation of the role of &quot;burnt offerings&quot; in Greek religion read &quot;The Birds&quot; by Aristophanes. --[[User:151.48.97.122|151.48.97.122]] 10:52, 13 February 2007 (UTC)

I never really thought about it that way of why people make sacrifices, but you have a point with the way that animals bring things that they catch to their masters. We may look down on human and animal sacrifice now but we still sacrifice things to our god. Monks sacrifice interaction with people. Chistians may sacrifice their Sunday to go to church. Buddist sacrifice their time in prayer or medittation. So whether it is a dead animal or a day of the week people still give something to their god no matter what religion. It is kind of interesting when you look at it. --[[Special:Contributions/71.101.159.205|71.101.159.205]] ([[User talk:71.101.159.205|talk]]) 20:29, 17 December 2008 (UTC)

In Judaism/Christianity, animal sacrifice was desigened to be a forshadowing of the sacrifce Christ would eventually make. God specificly states that He derives no pleasure from sacrifice.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/67.185.61.255|67.185.61.255]] ([[User talk:67.185.61.255|talk]]) 03:17, 22 April 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Tantrism ==

Can someone please make a distinction between Tantric philosophy and folk superstition in general? Tantrism is the tribal pre-Vedic folk religion of the Indian subcontinent and didn't evolve from Hinduism. It's the other way around. But saying Tantric beliefs lead to human sacrifice is as ridiculous as saying the Dalai Lama bathes in infants' blood or that any self-identified Christian murderer is purely motivated by a random bit in the Bible (or to compare on an equal scale of ignorance, motivated by whatever fire and brimstone his local priest has preached to him). Such sweeping generalisations are not NPOV.--[[User:Snowgrouse|Snowgrouse]] 02:50, 21 December 2006 (UTC)

== Tajin ==
Tajin was o Toltec city not Mayan. In article frescoes from Tajin are proof of human sacrifice in Mayan culture. [[User:Silthor|Silthor]] 10:28, 3 January 2007 (UTC)

== Indian Poors secrifice their children for Prosperity. ==

Indian Poors secrifice their children for Prosperity.

http://www.expressindia.com/fullstory.php?newsid=79072

Parents sacrificing sons to be prosperous

Press Trust of India
Posted online: Wednesday, January 03, 2007 at 1643 hours IST

Baripada (Orissa), January 3: Lured by promises of prosperity, a couple has allegedly sacrificed their two sons in Orissa's northern district of Mayurbahanj
Padmalochan Gan and his wife Tuni had been advised by a 'tantric' to sacrifice their sons Harish (9) and Dipu (7) and hold a puja to set themselves on the path to prosperity, police said on Wednesday. 
The couple sacrificed their sons at their home at Tilapada village, about 55 km from here, after observing some rituals in the presence of the tantrik, identified as Jagannath Tudu, police said. 
Though the incident had occurred about a week ago it came to light only this morning, when the foul smell emanating from the decomposed bodies alerted the local people. 
They found the bodies of the two boys and informed the police, which have arrested the couple. 
The tantrik is absconding. 
The couple also has a two-month-old daughter, who had been spared, police said.

[[User:Vkvora2001|vkvora]] 04:15, 7 January 2007 (UTC)

It seems that despite a ban there are many reported modern sacrifices in rural areas. Should this be included?
http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/8624269.stm
and a Time article from 2002 on the same subject http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,322673,00.html [[Special:Contributions/110.67.99.40|110.67.99.40]] ([[User talk:110.67.99.40|talk]]) 11:27, 16 April 2010 (UTC)weavehole

== Modifications in a section ==

Now that I and other editors have been working hard for a week to rewrite [[Human sacrifice in Aztec culture]] I made several modifications in this article.

Firstly, I re-titled “Mesoamerican sacrifice” to “Pre-Columbian sacrifice” since the Inca region is not in [[Mesoamerica]].

I also eliminated some of the material that is now replicated in the two articles and the phrases that downplayed the wide consensus among scholars of the historicity of the sacrifices (for example, the evidence of child sacrifice in the Inca civilization). On the other hand, since the Maya image is self-sacrifice, not ritual murder, I removed it.

I also divided the section in sub-sections for readability.

—[[User:Cesar Tort|Cesar Tort]] 17:49, 20 March 2007 (UTC)

:Cesar, I know you have been working hard on this and other articles (e.g. [[Human sacrifice in Aztec culture]]) and you have been doing a great job.  So, I hope you will take the following comment in a spirit of constructive criticism of the article and not of your work per se.  

::The &quot;Pre-Columbian&quot; section of this article is of distinctly lower quality than the rest of the article.  The reason for this is that is composed a lot of short subsections with only one or two sentences per section.  The rest of this article tends towards longer paragraphs.  

:I know that you have a lot of knowledge and interest in this area (certainly more than I do).  So, I hope you will work to expand the &quot;Pre-Columbian&quot; section to bring it up to the quality of the rest of the article.

:--[[User:Richardshusr|Richard]] 00:46, 21 March 2007 (UTC)

Yes: that section still needs a lot of work. Meanwhile I have made many copyedits and modifications.

For instance, I have eliminated self-references as per WP recommendations and a short obscure phrase in the Viking section. Also, I re-arranged sections chronologically. This was tricky. As an example of my rationale I placed the Incas at the end since it was the culture that was conquered in the late XVI century, thereby the last great culture to end the regular practice of human sacrifices. Similarly, I relocated the recent Sati sacrifice in the “Contemporary” section; and the Maya should precede the Aztecs for chronological reasons as well.

Also, I moved the [[Tlaloc]] section above the Xipe-Totec: Tlaloc was a more important god for Aztecs. I also changed some names of the headings. 

—[[User:Cesar Tort|Cesar Tort]] 02:47, 21 March 2007 (UTC)

== Chinese characters ==

An editor has inserted characters that look ??? in most computers. Since this article is not specific about the Chinese, the characters that in most computers appear as ??? ought to be removed. —[[User:Cesar Tort|Cesar Tort]] 18:14, 25 March 2007 (UTC)

:If you're talking about the Chinese characters in parentheses after Ximen Bao, they display fine on my screen. --[[User:Richardshusr|Richard]] 00:17, 26 March 2007 (UTC)

::But would those characters display fine in most computers? You are a wikipedian and perhaps have uploaded some programs; most people who read it have not. —[[User:Cesar Tort|Cesar Tort]] 08:17, 26 March 2007 (UTC)

::I have now checked in other PCs and the characters do not appear. As I said: this is not a technical article on Chinese matters and the odd characters ought to be removed. —[[User:Cesar Tort|Cesar Tort]] 01:04, 7 April 2007 (UTC)

::: I disagree; other PCs should improve... :P  They work fine on my system, and they're relevant and appropriate.  They're used throughout Wikipedia.  A few ??'s don't bother non-readers more than actual characters would, and they are the only accurate way to render the name for readers.  [[User:Niten|Niten]] ([[User talk:Niten|talk]]) 21:55, 17 December 2009 (UTC)

== removing section ==

I am removing the entire subsection placed by [[User:PBC]] —:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Human sacrifice today. 

Human sacrifice still continues in West Africa, southern Africa and other parts of Africa.&lt;ref&gt;http://anti-slaverysociety.addr.com/sacrifice.htm&lt;/ref&gt; It also continues in India.&lt;ref&gt;http://anti-slaverysociety.addr.com/sacrifice.htm&lt;/ref&gt; It is infrequent in South America and the West Indies.{{Talkfact}}   These incidents encompass human sacrifice and the collection of body parts for traditional medicine.  A related issue is the collection of body parts from graves.  The burial of people with chiefs, which lasted into the last century, has now ceased.

The publicity surrounding &quot;Adam&quot;, the torso of a boy found in the [[Thames River]] in London, lead to in investigation by [[New Scotland Yard]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

—due to this comment in [[User_talk:PBC#The_appearance_of_link_spamming| his or her talk page]]. If reinserted I expect the claims to be supported by reliable sources. [[User:Cesar Tort|Cesar Tort]] 00:00, 10 April 2007 (UTC)

:I think the information about &quot;adam&quot; should be kept, as it's sourced from BBC news. [[User:Blueshirts|Blueshirts]] 03:04, 10 April 2007 (UTC)

::This is the moved source (two references sourced with same link): [http://anti-slaverysociety.addr.com/sacrifice.htm]. You are most welcome, please, to find better sources and restore moved sentences. —[[User:Cesar Tort|Cesar Tort]] 03:36, 10 April 2007 (UTC)

== lovely vandalism ==

&lt;blockquote&gt;''Retrieved from [[Human sacrifice]] (Revision as of 07:32, 25 March 2007)''&lt;/blockquote&gt;

{{Cquote|Sacrifices to [[Xipe Totec]] were bound to a post and shot full of arrows. The dead victim would be skinned and a priest would use the skin. Earth mother [[Teteoinnan]] required [[flaying|flayed]] female victims. '''OMG Thats wrong!!!!!!!!!!!!!'''}}

I didn't revert the bold-type. It made me laugh! —[[User:Cesar Tort|Cesar Tort]] 21:36, 8 May 2007 (UTC)

:Um... presumably this describes two different kinds of sacrifice.  Elsewise, how would you flay a body that had been shot full of arrows? --[[User:Richardshusr|Richard]] 22:33, 8 May 2007 (UTC)

::Of course: Xipe-Totec, “Our Lord the Flayed One” (who demanded sacrifices in the month ''tlacaxipehualiztli'') is a male god; Teteo inan (who demanded sacrifices in the month ''ochpaniztli''), a female goddess. —[[User:Cesar Tort|Cesar Tort]] 23:38, 8 May 2007 (UTC)

How do you skin something after your archer have just filled it with arrows. Brings new meaning to the term a &quot;holy robe&quot; lol --[[Special:Contributions/71.101.159.205|71.101.159.205]] ([[User talk:71.101.159.205|talk]]) 20:31, 17 December 2008 (UTC)

==What's a dispute?==

Is it really necessary to note disagreement about Phoenician/Carthaginian human sacrifice when the only cited naysayer (note 14) speaks of &quot;my Phoenician Canaanites ancestors&quot; on the www.phoenicia.org website? There are doubtless many more people who disbelieve in the Holocaust, or &lt;i&gt;know&lt;/i&gt; Mohammed ElBaradei hid Saddam's WMDs to make trouble for President Bush... Wouldn't Wikipedia be better off taking a little less notice of crackpots and special pleaders?

&lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:DMaclKnapp|DMaclKnapp]] ([[User talk:DMaclKnapp|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/DMaclKnapp|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

:Absolutely agree. There's a lot of denialism about these matters. Unfortunately this article is no longer in my watchlist. —[[User:Cesar Tort|Cesar Tort]] 21:47, 29 June 2007 (UTC)

:There's a lot more information and evidence on those topics.  There's an acknowledged trend for people to attribute cannibalism, child sacrifice, and other barbaric activities to their enemies.  So, it's important to take ancient anecdotes with a grain of salt.  OTOH, yes, we could use better sources...  [[User:Niten|Niten]] ([[User talk:Niten|talk]]) 22:05, 17 December 2009 (UTC)

== Witch Burnings ==

Would this count as a form of human sacrifice? Although Witch Burnings seemed to lack the ritualistic aspect that the sacrifices of many other societies entailed, I don't see all that much of a difference between killing someone to appease an Aztec war god and killing someone to appease the Christian god. Does the nature of with burning categorize it as a form of persecution instead of sacrifice? Just curious.

I wouldnt consider witch burning sacrifice. During that time witches were hunted down and killed. Back then capital punishment burning at the stake. They were just killing the witches '''not''' sacrificing them. And besides the Christian God never instructed those people to sacrifice witches to Him. I would consider witch burners as vigilantes taking the law into their own hands. --[[Special:Contributions/71.101.159.205|71.101.159.205]] ([[User talk:71.101.159.205|talk]]) 20:42, 17 December 2008 (UTC)

==Islamic terrorism==

Might Islamic terrorism not also count as a form of human sacrifice? The terrorists dedicate themselves to God, and then they board airplanes and fly them into skyscrapers. Or they blow themselves up, or something. They see that as a religious duty. Some might see it as an act of human sacrifice. [[User:204.52.215.107|204.52.215.107]] 07:26, 13 September 2007 (UTC)

Might Christian crusading not also count as a form of human sacrifice? The crusaders dedicate themselves to God, then invade foreign countries and massacre the inhabitants. They see that as a religious duty. Some might see it as a form of human sacrifice. [[User:Imc|Imc]] 16:47, 21 September 2007 (UTC)

: ''(Sorry about the trolling. It just came over me after reading through the previous note. IMC.)''  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Imc|Imc]] ([[User talk:Imc|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Imc|contribs]]) 16:48, 21 September 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Yes, though members of both of these abrahamic religions would likely vehemently disagree with these conceptions and want to remove them. I could categorize both of those examples (Islamic Terrorism, Christian Imperialism) as forms of human sacrifice but as the article tends to focus on societally implemented ritual human sacrifice, those acts listed (which would more likely fall within the realm of opression or theocide) are not likely to find themselves on this page. Even the death pentaly, in my opinion, serves to appease the American deification of &quot;Justice&quot;. (I don't necessarily disagree with the death penalty, this is just my observation.) - Xvall  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/66.253.36.46|66.253.36.46]] ([[User talk:66.253.36.46|talk]]) 23:39, 2 December 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

warfare, and especially religious war, and capital punishment, especially capital punishment over religious issues, may indeed be considered human sacrifice. But the discussion of this needs to be based on [[WP:RS]] of course. The over-arching topic is [[religious violence]]. [[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|(𒁳)]]&lt;/small&gt; 09:25, 26 May 2008 (UTC)

Look the Christian God which the crusaders were &quot;fighting for&quot; never instructed them to massacare the Muslims who had captured Jerusalem. That was Pope Urban who told them to do that, see also the First Crusade[[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First_Crusade]]. We need to make sure we are not mixing in human actions with God's plan --[[Special:Contributions/71.101.159.205|71.101.159.205]] ([[User talk:71.101.159.205|talk]]) 20:52, 17 December 2008 (UTC)

==Sati is not sacrifice==
It's suicide, enforced suicide, or murder, depending on how it occurs and how it is seen. I don't see any justification for seeing it as sacrifice. There are some possible instances of human sacrifice in Hindu cultures, but I see no references to connect them to Sati. I'm therefore removing the references to Sati. [[User:Imc|Imc]] 16:57, 21 September 2007 (UTC)

Human sacrifice may be voluntary. A widow agreeing to be immolated is still engaging in human sacrifice just as much as king [[Domalde]], the daughter of [[Jephthah]] and the Rus slave girl described by [[Ibn Fadlan]]. All of these are instances of perfectly voluntary human sacrifices. [[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|(𒁳)]]&lt;/small&gt; 09:11, 26 May 2008 (UTC)

==Thugs or Thugees==
Should [[Thugs]] or [[Thugee]]s be included. [[User:Mamalujo|Mamalujo]] ([[User talk:Mamalujo|talk]]) 00:24, 17 January 2008 (UTC)

==In Modern Day Eruope==
Wasn't there a famous murder during the black metal chaos in Scandinavia that some people thought was a human sacrifice to odin?


[[Special:Contributions/75.161.225.25|75.161.225.25]] ([[User talk:75.161.225.25|talk]]) 03:10, 19 April 2008 (UTC)
:there were the murders by [[Bård Faust]] and [[Varg Vikernes]]. If either has been described as &quot;human sacrifice&quot;, the burden would be on you to provide a quotable source. [[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|(𒁳)]]&lt;/small&gt; 09:09, 26 May 2008 (UTC)

==Absence in Mesopotamia (?)==
While human sacrifice seems to have been practiced in the Levant and the Aegaean (and perhaps Old Kingdom Egypt), it might be notable to point out that in the urban civilizations of Mesopotamia, Assyria and Anatolia (Hittites), it seems to be conspicuously absent. This seems to be due to the use these cultures had for slave labour, and the standard punishment was enslavement, not death. At least in the Hittite laws, the standard punishment for pretty much any serious crime is blinding and enslavement, not death. [[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|(𒁳)]]&lt;/small&gt; 15:34, 26 May 2008 (UTC)

==In Judaism==
I have blanked the piece on &quot;Human sacrifice is permitted in certain circumstances in Judaism&quot; inserted by {{user|Exodus21v20}}. This isn't funny. --[[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|(𒁳)]]&lt;/small&gt; 11:57, 26 July 2008 (UTC)

The user TrtaTrticTrtinir is a troll. I've had my account for a long time, but I rarely spend much time here, so I'm not sure how to report him/her. He/she is the one who added the anti-Semitic language to the Judaism section, accusing Jews of killing and drinking the blood of Christian children as a &quot;secret&quot; holiday ritual. *eyeroll*

If someone could help me figure out how to report this troll, I'd appreciate it. [[User:Oktoberain|Oktoberain]] ([[User talk:Oktoberain|talk]]) 15:49, 8 January 2009 (UTC)Oktoberain
::No need. I've warned him he'll be blocked if he does it again. If he does, and I'm not around, take it to [[WP:ANI]]. [[User:Dougweller|dougweller]] ([[User talk:Dougweller|talk]]) 19:23, 8 January 2009 (UTC)

Leviticus 27:29 orders that someone who has been &quot;devoted&quot; to the Lord (in the same way that land, houses, animals can be devoted) must be put to death, and cannot be ransomed.  This has been cited as an example of human sacrifice in Biblical times.  The language is pretty clear and it will take some contortions to escape that meaning.  Or if I'm wrong, it should at least be mentioned, and the misunderstanding explained. [[Special:Contributions/67.86.225.217|67.86.225.217]] ([[User talk:67.86.225.217|talk]]) 19:05, 14 October 2011 (UTC)captcrisis

== In China == 
''Funeral human sacrifice was abolished by the Qin Dynasty in 384 BC''
I don't think this is true.  The First Emperor (221 BCE -210 BCE) was purportedly buried with a great number of live sacrifices, doesn't this mean that the Qin still practiced this tradition or was this a one time exception from the rule? [[User:Ctamigi|Ctamigi]] ([[User talk:Ctamigi|talk]]) 17:06, 5 August 2008 (UTC)

The section referring to Human Sacrifice in the East makes mention of Sikhism.  Perhpas it was worded incorrectly, but the intent seems at best to misrepresent Sikhism.  Sikhism explicitly forbids Sati. Did it still go on after the creation of sikhism among hindus, yes. Did it still go on after the British outlawed it, yes. The way the article is written makes it seem as if Sikhism condones sati. Nothing could be further from the truth. It is one of the major and most talked about differences between Sikhism and the prevailing religious superstitions of the day.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/67.172.165.150|67.172.165.150]] ([[User talk:67.172.165.150|talk]]) 05:43, 25 August 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Image copyright problem with Image:Tollundman2.jpg==
The image [[:Image:Tollundman2.jpg]] is used in this article under a claim of [[WP:NFC|fair use]], but it does not have an adequate explanation for why it meets the [[WP:NFCC|requirements for such images]] when used here.  In particular, for each page the image is used on, it must have an [[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|explanation]] linking to that page which explains why it needs to be used on that page.  Please check

:* That there is a [[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|non-free use rationale]] on the image's description page for the use in this article.
:* That this article is linked to from the image description page.
&lt;!-- Additional 10c list header goes here --&gt;

This is an automated notice by [[User:FairuseBot|FairuseBot]]. For assistance on the image use policy, see [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions]]. --15:15, 2 November 2008 (UTC)

== Phoenicia ==

Isn't Phoenicia in the Levant? Plus the Phoenicians were aslo as Semitic people, so I think the two sections should be condensed into one.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/128.211.249.239|128.211.249.239]] ([[User talk:128.211.249.239|talk]]) 17:49, 17 December 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== &quot;Funeral human sacrifice was abolished by the Qin Dynasty in 384 BC.&quot; ==

384 BC was Zhou dynasty...  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/69.253.96.138|69.253.96.138]] ([[User talk:69.253.96.138|talk]]) 09:18, 28 January 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

oops.--[[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|(𒁳)]]&lt;/small&gt; 06:57, 7 May 2009 (UTC)

==Masonic ritual killing==
It would be interesting of the article could discuss some of the alleged cases of Masonic ritual killing. For instance, Vatican banker [[Roberto Calvi]] was repotedly assassinated by P2 Masonic leaders in what investigators have described as a ritual sacrifice. [[User:ADM|ADM]] ([[User talk:ADM|talk]]) 21:58, 6 May 2009 (UTC)

==&quot;Accusations&quot;==

The only section of this article where the term &quot;accusations&quot; is used is in the section on &quot;blood libel.&quot; In the interest of racial, religious, and cultural impartiality, shouldn't the term &quot;accusations&quot; be used universally throughout the article? [[User:Bowdlerized|Bowdlerized]] ([[User talk:Bowdlerized|talk]]) 23:15, 13 July 2009 (UTC)

== Greek and Roman antiquity ==

This section is a jumble of unsourced stuff, with no citation of the plentiful secondary sources on this topic and some dubious claims. [[User:Cynwolfe|Cynwolfe]] ([[User talk:Cynwolfe|talk]]) 12:56, 13 October 2009 (UTC)


-I believe there are inaccuracies regarding this section : According to Pausanius, humans were sacrificed atop Mount Lyceum. 

-&quot;...town of Salamis, Cyprus...priest slaying a human victim to Zeus&quot; Lactantius

-Euseb., Praep. Ev., iv 17 mentions among peoples practicing human sacrifices, Rhodes, Salamis, Heliopolis, Chios, Tenedos, Lacedaemon, Arcadia, and Athens.

-Sacrifices for Dionysus the Cannibal, Plutarch Themist., 13; Porphyr., Abst., 11 55

-Sacrifices to Zeus Laphystius, Herodoyus vii

-Clemens Alexandrinus (i36) mentions Messinians sacrificing to Zeus, Taurians to Artemis. Pella, to Peleus and Chiron. Cretans to Zeus. Lesbos to Dionysus. 

-Consult Geusius de Victimis Humanis (1699)[[Special:Contributions/70.19.172.172|70.19.172.172]] ([[User talk:70.19.172.172|talk]]) 23:08, 26 December 2009 (UTC)

== Honor Killings ==

Should honor killings by Muslims be included? Since the victim is killed not so much as a punishment but to regain the family's honor, this seems akin to sacrifice. [[User:JoeFriday|&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot; size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;background-color: tan&quot;&gt;'''—joeFriday—'''&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/font&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{&lt;/nowiki&gt;[[User_talk:JoeFriday|talk]]&lt;nowiki&gt;}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;nbsp; 19:29, 22 November 2009 (UTC)

-I would say they deserve an honourable mention (ha!) ritualistic and what have you, but generally sacrifices are supposed to be &quot;perfect,&quot; which of course they do NOT consider the unfortunate young lass to be. As the homocide would tend to indicate.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/202.124.88.189|202.124.88.189]] ([[User talk:202.124.88.189|talk]]) 09:56, 17 January 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Witch Burning ==

I'm not sure witch burnings are sacrifices as they seem to have been executions. However like an ''auto da fé,'' they may have been presented as executions whilst taking on sacrificial overtones. [[User:JoeFriday|&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot; size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;background-color: tan&quot;&gt;'''—joeFriday—'''&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/font&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{&lt;/nowiki&gt;[[User_talk:JoeFriday|talk]]&lt;nowiki&gt;}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;nbsp; 19:29, 22 November 2009 (UTC)

the article is already aware of the fact that executions and human sacrifice cannot be separated in any objective manner. Both are ritualized killing sanctioned by society. How the society goes about rationalizing them is a case-by-case question and ultimately ideological in any case. --[[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|(𒁳)]]&lt;/small&gt; 09:23, 8 January 2010 (UTC)

== Uganda ==

See http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/programmes/newsnight/8441813.stm --[[User:Pjacobi|Pjacobi]] ([[User talk:Pjacobi|talk]]) 20:06, 7 January 2010 (UTC)

== &quot;Purushamedha&quot; Refuted ==

Please take a look at [http://www.sacred-texts.com/hin/sbr/sbe44/sbe44110.htm Section 13, Chapter 6, Brahmana 2] of the Satapatha Brahmana.  It clearly states that the victims are supposed to be released unharmed. [[User:Hokie Tech|Hokie Tech]] ([[User talk:Hokie Tech|talk]]) 01:16, 29 April 2010 (UTC)Hokie Tech

== Sacrifices to Kali ==

Arthur Avalon's [http://www.sacred-texts.com/tantra/htk/htk03.htm commentary on the Hymn to Kali] states that the animals listed for sacrifice are actually symbols for the six enemies:
&lt;blockquote&gt;This leads one to point out that the Hymn has other than these gross (Sthūla) meanings. In Brāhamanism everything has three aspects—Supreme (Para), Subtle (Sūkṣma) and Gross (Sthūla). Thus the nineteenth Śloka when referring to the sacrifice of various animals and of man himself intends according to the subtle sense the six great sins for which they stand, ranging from Lust (goat) to Pride (man). It is these which must be sacrificed by the knowers who are worshippers of the Mother the age of material sacrifice, so universal throughout the world, having passed away.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

We should include this in the article somewhere.  Also, we might want to get rid of the link to &quot;lifepositive.com&quot;; that doesn't seem very authoritative.
[[User:Hokie Tech|Hokie Tech]] ([[User talk:Hokie Tech|talk]]) 16:28, 28 May 2010 (UTC)

As far as I can see, the article doesn't discuss the Hymn to Kali at this point.
Human sacrifices to Kali are only discussed in the context of the Thuggee cult, which formed in the 17th century. 

Based on the information we have available at present, it seems that human sacrifice was more of a tribal practice and not part of Vedic ritual. The syncretism of Vedic ritual and indigenous tribal religion that gave rise to Pauranic Hinduism later introduced human sacrifice to the religious mainstream. This apparently happened around the 7th century AD. 
Obviously, there is no way to date the antiquity of the ritual practices of the individual Adivasi groups. --[[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|(𒁳)]]&lt;/small&gt; 19:43, 28 May 2010 (UTC)

:What do you mean &quot;Pauranic Hinduism&quot;?  Please see my comments on the [[Talk:Jarasandha|talk page for Jarasandha]]. [[User:Hokie Tech|Hokie Tech]] ([[User talk:Hokie Tech|talk]]) 20:14, 12 June 2010 (UTC)

By &quot;Pauranic Hinduism&quot; I mean classical, Vedantic, post-[[Adi Shankara|Shankara]] Hinduism as reflected by the Puranas. Basically, what we usually mean by &quot;Hinduism&quot; when no other qualifications are present. The point is that there may or may not have been human sacrifice in &quot;Hinduism&quot; before 700 CE, depending on your definition of &quot;Hinduism&quot; pertaining to that period. 
After 700 or so, Vedic Brahmanism syncretized with tribal religion and ritual to give rise to what we know as Hinduism today, including Kali, which certainly emerges as a Hindu goddess with her own cult by the 10th century and the [[Kalika Purana]]. Your Bhagavata Purana reference below also shows that human sacrifice to Kali had been present from around the 10th century, by which time Kali worship could certainly be considered part of Hinduism. --[[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|(𒁳)]]&lt;/small&gt; 14:05, 21 July 2010 (UTC)

:Dear Mr. Bachmann,
:Have you actually bothered to look at the page containing the Bhagavata Purana translation?  Here is a word-by-word translation of the Sanskrit verse:
:&lt;blockquote&gt;ye — persons who; tu — but; iha — in this life; vai — indeed; puruṣāḥ — men; puruṣa-medhena — by sacrifice of a man; yajante — worship (the goddess Kālī or Bhadra Kālī); yāḥ — those who; ca — and; striyaḥ — women; nṛ-paśūn — the men used as sacrifice; khādanti — eat; tān — them; ca — and; te — they; paśavaḥ iva — like the animals; nihatāḥ — being slain; yama-sadane — in the abode of Yamarāja; yātayantaḥ — punishing; rakṣaḥ-gaṇāḥ — being Rākṣasas; saunikāḥ — the killers; iva — like; svadhitinā — by a sword; avadāya — cutting to pieces; asṛk — the blood; pibanti — drink; nṛtyanti — dance; ca — and; gāyanti — sing; ca — also; hṛṣyamāṇāḥ — being delighted; yathā — just like; iha — in this world; puruṣa-adāḥ — the man-eaters.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
:As you can see, the word &quot;yajante&quot; was translated as &quot;worship&quot;, and the references to Kali and Bhadra Kali were inserted by the translator ([[Srila Prabhupada]]).  The original Sanskrit verse contains no reference to Kali. [[User:Hokie Tech|Hokie Tech]] ([[User talk:Hokie Tech|talk]]) 23:13, 19 August 2010 (UTC)

== Prohibition in the Srimad Bhagavatam ==

Please refer to [http://vedabase.net/sb/5/26/31/en Canto 5, Chapter 26, Verse 31] of the [[Bhagavata Purana]].  According to Srila Prabhupada's translation:

&lt;blockquote&gt;There are men and women in this world who sacrifice human beings to Bhairava or Bhadra Kālī and then eat their victims' flesh. Those who perform such sacrifices are taken after death to the abode of Yamarāja, where their victims, having taken the form of Rākṣasas, cut them to pieces with sharpened swords. Just as in this world the man-eaters drank their victims' blood, dancing and singing in jubilation, their victims now enjoy drinking the blood of the sacrificers and celebrating in the same way.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
[[User:Hokie Tech|Hokie Tech]] ([[User talk:Hokie Tech|talk]]) 00:03, 3 July 2010 (UTC)

Interesting reference, very possibly the oldest reference to human sacrifices to Kali. --[[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|(𒁳)]]&lt;/small&gt; 13:36, 21 July 2010 (UTC)

:No, it isn't.  See my comments above. [[User:Hokie Tech|Hokie Tech]] ([[User talk:Hokie Tech|talk]]) 23:14, 19 August 2010 (UTC)

You are right, it is not a reference to human sacrifice to Kali, as Kali is not mentioned explicitly. It is a reference to human sacrifice. --[[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|(𒁳)]]&lt;/small&gt; 06:57, 25 August 2010 (UTC)

==Blood Sacrifice==
Could somebody please review the following article of mine to see if it qualifies in the 'external links' section, and please insert it there. Per [[WP:ELNO]] #11 one can make exception to the &quot;recognized authority&quot; criterion according to this: ''The topic of an article should be notable, or &quot;worthy of notice&quot;; that is, significant, interesting, or unusual enough to deserve attention or to be recorded.'' If this is the case, then it needn't be written by a recognized authority. I think my article is thought-provoking: http://home7.swipnet.se/~w-73784/bloodsac.htm
[[User:Matswin|Matswin]] ([[User talk:Matswin|talk]]) 07:14, 20 August 2010 (UTC)

== Harappan Human Sacrifice ==

Please see [http://books.google.com/books?id=u8DfqDgiKPYC&amp;lpg=PA45&amp;dq=kalibangan%20fire%20altars&amp;pg=PA46#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false page 46] of the book ''Archaeology and World Religion'' by Timothy Insoll:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Both animal sacrifice and human sacrifice in some form have also been inferred for the Harappan civilization.  A scene on a seal from Harappa shows a man trying to kill a buffalo, and in the same scene there is a seated figure suggesting the presence of a deity.  A seal from Kalibangan shows a human figure being struck down before a deity.  Animal sacrifice is common in modern Hinduism, and human sacrifice was not entirely unknown in ancient India.&lt;/blockquote&gt;[[User:Hokie Tech|Hokie Tech]] ([[User talk:Hokie Tech|talk]]) 20:48, 29 August 2010 (UTC)
 &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:UsernameunavailableFCKU|UsernameunavailableFCKU]] ([[User talk:UsernameunavailableFCKU|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/UsernameunavailableFCKU|contribs]]) 06:45, 9 December 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;



:From [http://books.google.com/books?id=nzpYb5UOeiwC&amp;lpg=PA89&amp;dq=harappan%20human%20sacrifice&amp;pg=PA89#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false page 89] of the book ''Cultural History of India'' by Om Prakash:
&lt;blockquote&gt;A sealing from Harappa shows on the obverse a nude female figure, turned upside down with outspread legs and a plant issuing from the womb.  On the reverse of this sealing is depicted a man with a sickle in his hand and a woman seated on the ground with hand raised in the posture of prayer.  Obviously this depicts human sacrifice in honour of the Mother-goddess.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
:[[User:Hokie Tech|Hokie Tech]] ([[User talk:Hokie Tech|talk]]) 18:46, 1 October 2010 (UTC)


Seals and reliefs showing human figures struck down by a deity don't necessarily depict human sacrifice. Figures of gods killing demons can be found in most cultures around the world. The figure of a man with a sickle in hand and a woman kneeling to the deity described above might be a depiction of farmers and a fertility goddess. This can be supported by the fact that Harappan people were an agricutural community and mostly men worked in the fields while women prepared food, looked after the household and performed the religious rituals of prayers and offerings. The female figure depicted with a plant growing from the womb may be reference to Mother Earth, who is still regarded as a fertility deity in modern Hinduism, and is never offered any kind of animal sacrifice whatsoever.


From [http://books.google.com/books?id=H3lUIIYxWkEC&amp;lpg=PA173&amp;dq=harappa%20human%20sacrifice&amp;pg=PA173#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false page 173] of ''A History of Ancient and Early Medieval India'' by Upinder Singh:
&lt;blockquote&gt;A triangular terracotta cake found at Kalibangan has a carving of a horned deity on one side and an animal being dragged by a rope by a human on the other.  The latter has been tentatively interpreted as suggesting the practice of animal sacrifice.  A Kalibangan cylinder seal shows a woman flanked by two men who hold her with one hand and raise swords over her head with the other; this may represent a scene of human sacrifice.  The most striking evidence suggesting ritual practices comes from the 'fire altars' found on the citadel mound of Kalibangan.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
[[User:Hokie Tech|Hokie Tech]] ([[User talk:Hokie Tech|talk]]) 00:40, 6 October 2010 (UTC)

:From [http://books.google.com/books?id=uRMGDmdE9FkC&amp;lpg=PA164&amp;dq=harappa%20human%20sacrifice&amp;pg=PA164#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false page 164] of ''Prehistory and Harappan Civilization'' by Raj Pruthi:
:&lt;blockquote&gt;An interesting sealing from Harappa shows a nude female figure, turned upside down, with out-spread legs and a plant issuing from the womb.  The reverse side has a man with a sickle-shaped knife in hand and a woman seated on the ground with hands raised supplication.  Obviously this depicts a human sacrifice to the Earth Goddess, portrayed on the obverse with two genii.  A similar figure of the Gupta Age has been discovered in the United Provinces with a lotus issuing out of then neck of the goddess.  Perhaps the sealing represents a river gushing out of the goddess's womb.  The representation of a figure standing in the bifurcated branch of a &lt;i&gt;pipal&lt;/i&gt; tree also appears to depict the Mother Goddess.  To this goddess the worshiper brings a goat, probably for sacrifice, and a number of people standing in the lower register appear to be taking part in the sacrifice.  The &lt;i&gt;Pipal&lt;/i&gt; tree is still held to be sacred in India, but not associated with the cult of the Mother Goddess.  The goat sacrifice has survived in the worship of Sakit, another form of the Mother Goddess, in which the sacrifice of animals is the most characteristic feature.  It is still uncertain whether the female deity represented by pottery figurines was regarded as a virgin goddess or as the consort of the male god on the seal amulets.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
:[[User:Hokie Tech|Hokie Tech]] ([[User talk:Hokie Tech|talk]]) 00:54, 6 October 2010 (UTC)

From [http://books.google.com/books?id=wPB7XoSiboUC&amp;lpg=PA47&amp;dq=harappa%20human%20sacrifice&amp;pg=PA47#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false page 47] of ''World history from early times to A D 2000'':
&lt;blockquote&gt;A large number of terracotta figurines of a female elaborately decorated with a crescent-shaped head-dress have been found in many Indus cities.  So, it is assumed that these figurines represent the Mother Goddess.  To substantiate further, another seal from Harappa contains a scene depicting a human sacrifice being offered to the Goddess Earth.  Many historians believe that the Shakti cult was then very popular, particularly during the pre-Aryan age.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
[[User:Hokie Tech|Hokie Tech]] ([[User talk:Hokie Tech|talk]]) 01:05, 6 October 2010 (UTC)

:From [http://books.google.com/books?id=jMmYDrm_7NAC&amp;lpg=PA223&amp;dq=harappa%20human%20sacrifice&amp;pg=PA223#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false page 223] of ''Encyclopedia Indica: India, Pakistan, Bangladesh, Volume 100'':
:&lt;blockquote&gt;Another object which throws light on the cult of the Mother Goddess is a sealing from Harappa, on one side of which is depicted a nude female figure upside down with legs drawn apart.  A plant is issuing from the womb of the female and a pair of animal &quot;genii&quot; is also seen on the same side of the sealing.  On the reverse is a man holding a sickle-shaped knife, and a woman is seated on the ground in an attitude of supplication.  This scene is said to represent a human sacrifice offered to the Earth Goddess depicted on the obverse.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
:[[User:Hokie Tech|Hokie Tech]] ([[User talk:Hokie Tech|talk]]) 22:44, 6 October 2010 (UTC)

== In Ancient Israel ==

From [http://books.google.com/books?id=0tPjVJF8roYC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;ots=r1HjN46QGE&amp;dq=the%20strange%20world%20of%20human%20sacrifice&amp;pg=PA125#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false page 125] of ''The Strange World of Human Sacrifice'':

&lt;blockquote&gt;The harsh critics of the later prophets suggest that at a certain stage and under certain circumstances child sacrifice did indeed belong to the religious belief system and praxis of Ancient Israel.  The statement by Ezekiel that YHWH did give Israel 'statutes that were not good and ordinances by which they could not live' (20.25) and the astral character of Yahwism at the end of the monarchic period could refer to the background of that praxis.&lt;br/&gt;
Such a &lt;i&gt;praxis pietatis&lt;/i&gt; might seem strange to students of religion in the twenty-first century.  But in the long run of history it is not that long ago that we were burning witches.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
[[User:Hokie Tech|Hokie Tech]] ([[User talk:Hokie Tech|talk]]) 14:19, 3 October 2010 (UTC)

sure, this is just saying that prior to 600 BC, Israelite religion was simply one among many Levantine cults.
The prohibition of human sacrifice (&quot;binding of Isaac&quot;), as well as the term &quot;Judaism&quot;, does not apply to that period, it should only be used for the period [[Second Temple Judaism|after 500 BC]]. For this period (500 BC and later), I think it is undisputed that the prohibition of human sacrifice held good. &quot;Ancient Israel&quot; refers to 1000&amp;ndash;600 BC. --[[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|(𒁳)]]&lt;/small&gt; 09:10, 3 February 2011 (UTC)

==Tibet==
diffs [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Human_sacrifice&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=268979588][http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Human_sacrifice&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=371510789&amp;oldid=371095682]

So we have a problem with the Chinese blood libel against the Tibetans. 
It may be that there were tantric ritual killings in medieval Tibet. 
But today, Chinese propaganda is trying to demonize Tibetan Buddhism based on that. So we need to be very careful to discuss this based on credible academic sources. --[[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|(𒁳)]]&lt;/small&gt; 09:12, 3 February 2011 (UTC)

It turns out that there is some circumstantial evidence for human sacrifice in remote corners in Tibet up to the 1950s. Not in Lamaism.
The Chinese claims of baby-eating Tibetan lamas is pure blood libel. --[[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|(𒁳)]]&lt;/small&gt; 11:46, 3 February 2011 (UTC)
:In your revision of the section on Tibet, some of the statements appear unreferenced when in fact they should be attributed to their rightful author, ie Grunfeld.--[[User:Christian Lassure|Christian Lassure]] ([[User talk:Christian Lassure|talk]]) 21:35, 3 February 2011 (UTC)


==Buddhism==
The reference to buddhism in the Tantrism section should be clarified.  There is zero evidence for Buddhism supporting human sacrifice, but the article as it is might lead people to believe there is.  Unless someone can produce evidence of buddhist human sacrifice, I will clarify or remove the reference to buddhism.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.194.43.66|76.194.43.66]] ([[User talk:76.194.43.66|talk]]) 00:28, 18 April 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;


==Slavic people==
Removed: According to sixth century Byzantine emperor Mauricius's Strategikon wrote of the Slavs... etc.

Explanation: The reference was put to explain later comment by Leo the Deacon. Since that comment is removed, there is no reason for this reference to exist.



Replaced: In the 10th century, Persian explorer Ahmad ibn Rustah described funerary rights for the Rus included the sacrifice of a young female slave.

Replaced with: Similar to sati custom in hinduism in [[Al-Masudi]]'s work [[The Meadows of Gold|Meadows of Gold and Mines of Gems]] he explains burial rite of Slavic high noble that died, during which one of the women of his household would voluntarily sacrifice herself. Usually it was one of the daughters of the noble, as [[Ahmad ibn Fadlan|Ibn Fadlan]] informs us (Ibn Fadlan and the Rusiyyah, James E. Montgomery., Journal of Arabic and Islamic Studies,Volume III, 2000. pp. 1-25.).

Explanation: Same principle as in sati custom in hinduism, as [[Ahmad ibn Fadlan|Ibn Fadlan]] informs us. There is no reason to mention rather seldom practice if sati is not mentioned in the article also. 
You have far better sources in [[Al-Masudi]]'s work [[The Meadows of Gold|Meadows of Gold and Mines of Gems]] where on pages 408., 415. and 416., Vol I, he explains burial practices of Slavs. By the way, the sacrifice of a female was voluntarily and made only when high noble died. That one of the women of his household would voluntarily sacrifice herself. Usually it was one of the daughters of the noble, as  [[Ahmad ibn Fadlan|Ibn Fadlan]] informs us (Ibn Fadlan and the Rusiyyah, James E. Montgomery., Journal of Arabic and Islamic Studies,Volume III, 2000. pp. 1-25.).



Removed: Leo the Deacon describes prisoner sacrifice by the Rus lead by Sviatoslav during the Russo-Byzantine War &quot;in accordance with their ancestral custom.&quot;

Explanation: There is no evidence to support claim that this was indeed a human sacrifice. Furthermore, Leo the Deacon continues: &quot;For they are said to addicted to Hellenic mysteries, and to make sacrifices and libations to the dead in the Hellenic fashion, having been initiated in these things either by their own philosophers, Anacharsis and Zamolxis, or by comrades of Achilles.&quot; (cited in &quot;The History of Leo the Deacon: Byzantine Military Expansion in the Tenth Century&quot;,. Alice-Mary Talbot, Denis F. Sullivan, pp. 193-194.). In the other words this section has nothing to do with Slavic religion whatsoever. Authors hypothesize that this passage is actually rewrite of Herodotus (ibid).
Also, 6th century emperor [[Maurice (emperor)|Mauricius]], 6th century Byzantine scholar [[Procopius|Procopius of Caesarea]] and 10th century emperor [[Constantine VII|Constantine Porphyrogennetos]] make no mention of human sacrifices among Slavs. On the contrary, emperor [[Maurice (emperor)|Mauricius]] praises humane attitude of Slavs towards prisoners, although they were his enemies (Tiberius Augustus, Flavius Mauricius. Strategikon, Book XI - Characteristics and Tactics of Various Peoples.).


Replaced: According to the 12th century Russian Primary Chronicle, prisoners of war were sacrificed to Perun, the Slavic god of war. Sacrifices to pagan gods, along with paganism itself, were banned after the Baptism of Rus by Prince Vladimir I in the 980s.

Replaced with: According to the 14th or 15th editions of [[Primary Chronicle|Russian Primary Chronicle]], [[Vladimir I of Kiev|prince Vladimir]] attempted to reform Slavic religion by establishing the thunder-god, Perun, as a supreme deity and introducing human sacrifices. He tried to sacrifice young Cristian named Ioann to god Perun in 980., but he and his father Fyodor were killed by angry mob after insulting Slavic deities. Prince Vladimir converted to Christianity in 988. abandoning his earlier practices.

Explantion: To describe Perun as god of war is to show utter lack of knowledge on the topic. First of all, almost every Slavic male god was god of war. Second, Perun was primarily god of thunder and justice (Rex Germanorum - populos Sclavorum, Ivo Vukchevich, University Center Press, Santa Barbara California, USA, 2001., pp.27-28) and that it was practice to invoke him when giving oath of great importance and it was in name of Perun that oath breakers were killed it is easy to understand how carrying out sentence could be seen as human sacrifice in the eyes of Christians. Particularly if it was them that broke the oath in the first place (peace treaty between grand prince Oleg and emperor Leo in 907. and peace treaty between grand prince Igor and Byzantium in 945. were both sealed by making an oath to Perun).
[[Primary Chronicle|Russian Primary Chronicle]] was indeed compiled at the beginning of the 12th century, however the original was lost and in the reference is not clear whether the author uses 14th century [[Laurentian codex]] or 15th century [[Hypatian codex]]. Both were significantly edited for various reasons. Furthermore, it describes events in Kievan Rus, just a fraction of Slavic world. Description of human sacrifice mentions two victims by name, while indicated that it was prince Vladimir himself that introduced human sacrifices in 980. It is not clear whether these two were only victims or not, but with conversion to Christianity just 8 years later (or whenever prince Vladimir changed his mind about sacrificing humans), the alleged practice of sacrificing humans lasted very briefly and was limited to Kiev, with rather insignificant number of victims. It needs to be point out that Russian Primary Chronicle was edited in a manner to glorify prince Vladimir.
Here is just a tiny sample of references on Perun:
*Überlegungen zur vorchristlichen Religion der Slaven im Lichte der slavischen Sprachwissenschaft, [[Oleg Trubachyov]], Z. slav. Philol. – 1994. – Bd. LIV. – S. 1–20.
*Na sladach kultu Peruna, Machnik J., Dawna kultura. R. 1955. Warszawa, 1955. Z. 3. S. 97-176; 
*Sprawca Piorunуw w mitologii clowianskiej, Gieysztor A., Ars historica, Poznan, 1976 
*К этимологии балтийского и славянского названий бога грома, Иванов В. В., Вопросы славянского языкознания, в. 3, М., 1958
*Трагови Перунова култа код Јужних словена, Филиповић М.,  Гласник Земаљског музеја у Сарајеву. Нова сериjа, t. 3, Сарајево, 1948 
*Топор как символ Перуна в древнерусском язычестве, Даркевич., Советская археология В. П.  1961. № 4.
*&quot;Slavic religion&quot;, [[Marija Gimbutas|Gimbutas, M.]], The Encyclopedia of Religion, vol. 13, ed. Mircea Eliade, New York: Macmillan, 1987, pp. 353-361. 
*Perkunas/Perun: Thunder God of the Balts and Slavs, [[Marija Gimbutas|Gimbutas, M.]], The Journal of Indo-European Studies, 1973, pp. 466 - 479
*O Perunovom kultu kod Južnih Slovena, P.Z. Petrović, Glasnik 1-2, 1952.
*O Perunovu kultu u Istri, Historijski zbornik 6, 1954.
etc.
I'm not even sure that the event that is described can be qualified as human sacrifice, but since there was intent to make a human sacrifice, I'll leave it be.


Removed: Archeological findings indicate that the practice may have been widespread, at least among slaves, judging from mass graves containing the cremated fragments of a number of different people.

Explanation: Unsubstantiated claim. How exactly does &quot;cremated fragments of a number of different people&quot; prove that human sacrifice was &quot;widespread&quot;, or that human sacrifice existed at all, for that matter?! Slavic burial rites included cremation and remains of nobles were treated with more respect than remains of commoners. In what way does it spell human sacrifice?

This section is still not completed since Western primary sources need to be added and exact citation from [[Primary Chronicle|Russian Primary Chronicle]] as a primary source, though heavily edited several times.

[[User:Zvezdara Forest|Zvezdara Forest]] ([[User talk:Zvezdara Forest|talk]]) 10:39, 9 June 2011 (UTC)



Replaced: According to the 14th or 15th editions of [[Primary Chronicle|Russian Primary Chronicle]], [[Vladimir I of Kiev|prince Vladimir]] attempted to reform Slavic religion by establishing the thunder-god, Perun, as a supreme deity and introducing human sacrifices. He tried to sacrifice young Cristian named Ioann to god Perun in 980., but he and his father Fyodor were killed by angry mob after insulting Slavic deities.

Replaced with: According to the 14th century and 15th century editions of [[Primary Chronicle|Russian Primary Chronicle]] ([[Laurentian codex]] and [[Hypatian codex]]), [[Vladimir I of Kiev|prince Vladimir]] attempted to reform Slavic religion by establishing the thunder-god, Perun, as a supreme deity and introducing human sacrifices. After successful military campaign he tried to sacrifice young [[Varangians|Varyag]] to god Perun in 983., but the Varayg and his father were killed by angry mob after insulting Slavic deities.

Explanation: After consulting the originals of [[Laurentian codex]], [[Hypatian codex]] and their translations to Russian, English and Serbian.

[[User:Zvezdara Forest|Zvezdara Forest]] ([[User talk:Zvezdara Forest|talk]]) 20:39, 13 June 2011 (UTC)

:This site operates off of secondary sources whenever possible, '''not''' [[WP:OR|original research or personal interpretation]] of primary sources.  When primary sources are used, we can only summarize the text without explanation.  [[WP:IDHT|This sort of thing has been explained to you before, don't be tendentious]].  Do not remove that section again.  Quit trying to [[whitewash (censorship)|whitewash]] this article with your original research.  The sources cover the different evidence human sacrifice, both for and against.  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 00:01, 14 June 2011 (UTC)
:Regarding the Strategikon and Leo the Deacon, when we are forced to use primary sources, we do not comment on them and we do not put our own research into them.  We do not cross reference them with other sources that are not specifically about the source being used.  We only summarize what the source says on the subject and nothing else.
:Regarding the &quot;unsubstantiated&quot; claim of human sacrifices: that too had a secondary source, which cited different archeological studies.
:Regarding your strawman argument about which edition of the Primary chronicle is being used, this sort of issue is why we use secondary resources.  There was a reference that supported the statement concerning the Primary Chronicle mentioning human sacrifice.  Your own original research does not beat a secondary source. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 00:18, 14 June 2011 (UTC)

::Only we are not &quot;forced&quot; to use primary sources. You yourself referenced Leo the Deacon from a secondary source that claims the passage in question is rewrite of Herodotus. Also, Leo the Deacon clearly mentions Hellenic religion, not Slavic. In what way that passage is relevant to this section of the article?! Furthermore, phrase &quot;ancestral custom&quot; is vague at best, and can mean a lot of things, among which human sacrifice is just one of many possibilities.[[User:Zvezdara Forest|Zvezdara Forest]] ([[User talk:Zvezdara Forest|talk]]) 06:38, 14 June 2011 (UTC)
::What &quot;different archeological studies&quot;?! None is referenced in the section. And remains of cremated bodies in a culture where the burial rites include cremation is no evidence of human sacrifice. [[User:Zvezdara Forest|Zvezdara Forest]] ([[User talk:Zvezdara Forest|talk]]) 06:38, 14 June 2011 (UTC)
::What &quot;straw man argument&quot;?! I've stated a simple fact - the earliest manuscripts of the Russian Primary Chronicle are from 14th and 15th century ([[Laurentian codex]] and [[Hypatian codex]], respectively ). In what way does it spell [[Straw man| straw man argument]]?!
::There is no secondary source that can change what is written in Russian Primary Chronicle, and if that secondary source claims that Russian Primary Chronicle says something it doesn't, than that secondary source is either flawed or not using the text of Russian Primary Chronicle. However, no reference in the section is given for this claim. The reference you've given is simply a translation of Russian Primary Chronicle.[[User:Zvezdara Forest|Zvezdara Forest]] ([[User talk:Zvezdara Forest|talk]]) 06:38, 14 June 2011 (UTC)
::I've given you enough references, primary and secondary sources to show that the section that you've written is [[WP:OR|original research or personal interpretation]] that has not been backed up by primary and secondary sources. I've taken an effort to write down an explanation for every change I've made backing it up by primary and secondary sources. Please, take time to at least read it, if you don't have the time examine the references. I have no problem to admit that I'm wrong. I'm only human after all, and as we all, can make mistakes from time to time, but I need to see for myself a hard evidence that I'm wrong. Such an evidence regarding this section of the article, so far I've not seen. If you feel that I'm wrong, please make an effort and provide such an evidence. If I may suggest start with Russian Primary Chronicle.
:: I do find your claims of me using straw man argument and whitewashing to be bordering insults. Please, in the future refrain yourself from such a style of discussion and base your complains strictly on the sources.
::I hope you understand that further disruptive behavior on your behalf will result in me filing a report to the administrator.
[[User:Zvezdara Forest|Zvezdara Forest]] ([[User talk:Zvezdara Forest|talk]]) 06:38, 14 June 2011 (UTC)
[[User:Zvezdara Forest|Zvezdara Forest]] ([[User talk:Zvezdara Forest|talk]]) 06:56, 14 June 2011 (UTC)

:::[[WP:TALK|Do not thread comments, it makes the discussion harder to follow]].  By all means get other editors involved. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 20:48, 14 June 2011 (UTC)

== Political-war propaganda and human sacrifice. ==


Often it is difficult to know the true for human sacrifice indeed for example [[Carthage]]. The human sacrifice wa a important subject to [[Propaganda|political propaganda]].
Often the romans/and greeks used this accuse against the enemies.
Stop the human sacrifices was one of the themes that were used to finance the Scipio campaign against Carthage.

The economic crisis of Carthage and the Roman embargo probably has led to an increase in infant mortality from malnutrition, the Tofets are concetrated in the time. The Romans used cinically the accuse.

In the late Roman Empire, Christians and pagans accused each other of human sacrifices.
I remember two events. The persecution against Christians by Nero and destruction of the Temple of Serapis in Alexandria obviously in the two events the accuses were false.

A bit like in Europe in the nineteenth century it was said that the Communists and Jews eat children. It was the same accuse that existed in Roman Empire agains the Christians.

I think the we must write a some word on this.....  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/84.222.77.167|84.222.77.167]] ([[User talk:84.222.77.167|talk]]) 12:13, 8 September 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
==File:Windeby I reconstruction.jpg Nominated for Deletion==
{|
|-
| [[File:Image-x-generic.svg|100px]] 
| An image used in this article, [[commons:File:Windeby I reconstruction.jpg|File:Windeby I reconstruction.jpg]], has been nominated for deletion at [[Wikimedia Commons]] in the following category: ''Deletion requests September 2011'' 
;What should I do?
''Don't panic''; a discussion will now take place over on Commons about whether to remove the file. This gives you an opportunity to contest the deletion, although please review Commons guidelines before doing so.
* If the image is [[WP:NFCC|non-free]] then you may need to upload it to Wikipedia (Commons does not allow fair use)
* If the image isn't freely licensed and there is no [[WP:FUR|fair use rationale]] then it cannot be uploaded or used.

''This notification is provided by a Bot'' --[[User:CommonsNotificationBot|CommonsNotificationBot]] ([[User talk:CommonsNotificationBot|talk]]) 13:58, 20 September 2011 (UTC)
|}

== what is  &quot;O-Kee-Pa Ceremony&quot;?  ==

When I went to the article Mandan linked through the caption of the picture The Last Race, Mandan O-Kee-Pa Ceremony I found no reference to human sacrifice.  Ritual self-torture, yes, but not sacrifice. --[[Special:Contributions/199.91.207.3|199.91.207.3]] ([[User talk:199.91.207.3|talk]]) 16:01, 22 November 2011 (UTC)

== Human sacrifice in Islam ==

Someone should add information on human sacrifice in Islam. I can't believe that this lengthy article mentions gladiatorial battles and ceremeonial burnings of wives/concubines, but when it comes to Islam it merely says that Islam &quot;opposes&quot; human sacrifices as defined by Islam itself. That's not an objective qualification and seems to flagrantly violate Wikipedia's NPOV policy. A Wikipedia article cannot use the Koran as a measuring tool for what is or what is not human sacrifice just as it cannot (and does not, AFAIK) use the Bible as a measuring tool for determining what is and what is not human sacrifice in Christianity. You need to step out of the religious rhetoric/context and judge things for what they are irrespective of what a partiular sacred scripture calls it.

So, to get to the point regarding human sacrifice in Islam... As far as I know, Islam is the only religion that to this day still practices human sacrifice as codified in Islamic Sharia law. Basically, crimes and capital offenses against God and his prophet (Muhammad) such as apostasy and blasphemy merit the ritual killing of the offender usually through his/her beheading or stoning under religious supervision and ceremonial chanting. Quite often, the point is made in these cases that God has been affronted by the offender and that Muslims need to set this straight by killing him in an Islamically sanctioned ritual execution.

In Saudi Arabia, people are executed for blasphemy and apostacy to this very day and there have been cases elsewhere in the Islamic world. Of particular note is also an unknown number of ritual killings for blasphemy and apostacy performed by organisations that are not official government institutions but that nevertheless have their own Islamic courts (e.g. the post-9/11 Talibans, the Islamic Courts militias in Somalia, etc). One recent noted and still pending case was that of a Saudi imam calling for the death of Saudi blogger Hamza Kashgari for alleged apostacy. The Saudi imam cited Koranic passages describing the devastation that God inflicted upon Sodom and Gomorrah, saying that he feared God's reaction and wrath if this blogger's &quot;blasphemy&quot; remained unpunished by the Islamic courts of Saudi Arabia. [[User:Abvgd|Abvgd]] ([[User talk:Abvgd|talk]]) 07:21, 22 August 2012 (UTC)

:What we need are reliable sources calling these human sacrifices. [[User:Dougweller|Dougweller]] ([[User talk:Dougweller|talk]]) 08:41, 22 August 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>pw46q3m263gqv6gespjn6uqphyill6l</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
