<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Demigod</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>856615</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516887353</id>
      <parentid>511981062</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-09T20:58:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>176.27.144.46</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Jesus */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13220">{{Wikiproject mythology|class=start|importance=top}}

==Comment==
|-
User_Talk:Nat Krause|e]] 15:44, 25 Jul 2004 (UTC)

i really think the two items in this area both need citations.--[[User:The undertow|The undertow]] 22:59, 24 September 2006 (UTC)

==&quot;Greeks had no such category, however, which consequently introduces unnecessary confusion.&quot;==
This perfectly sensible sentence, which makes a necessary point here, correcting past confusion in this article (see Article history), was deleted by [[User:Alterego]], who has not made any previous contributions to this article, with the pert Edit Summary: &quot;remove unnecessary sentence&quot;.  I restored it of course and received the following little note: &quot;Please read the official Wikipedia policy regarding [[Wikipedia:Ownership_of_articles|article ownership]].&quot; I merely lay this all out publicly, for I see no reason to be bullied in private. There will be nothing further from me on this subject. --[[User:Wetman|Wetman]] 6 July 2005 05:16 (UTC)

:&quot;since We already provide a link to the greek concept, this sentence is redundant. additionally, it is distinctly POV&quot; (Edit summary of [[User:Alterego]], reverting again) (The reader may judge whether this assertion reflects a neutral&amp;mdash;or even an informed&amp;mdash; point-of-view.)

== Demigod of mythological context. ==

Demigod--half man, half god... 50% god and 50% man.

The Greeks have their Heroes and Titans, born of heaven and earth.
The Hebrews have their Nephilim, born of women and the sons of god.

The distinguishing aspect of these demigods is their enormous strength and stature, and influence on ancient civilization--due to their supernatural birth.
--[[User:71.215.154.31|71.215.154.31]] 23:30, 1 April 2007 (UTC)

:Titans were gods I'm afaid. ;-) An older generation of gods than the Olympians (Zeus &amp; co.).

:The attitude to divinities also effects the way demigods (if we can call the nephilim that...demiangels would be more like it) are viewed in Greek and Hebrew culture: for the Hebrews there was only one god, so the offspring of angels and humans were blasphemous and viewed as evil (though superhuman). The Greeks had no such compunctions about deities and interbreeding however, so demigods are viewed as heroes, and often play the role of culture heroes (heroic figures who establish traditions, found cities, invent culturally-signifcant things, etc) that mortal Hebrew patriarchs do. [[Special:Contributions/86.174.121.238|86.174.121.238]] ([[User talk:86.174.121.238|talk]]) 18:01, 6 May 2009 (UTC)

== A text about alittle more about a &quot;demigod&quot;. ==


Well,a demigod is a half Person and half god. You see there are many gods, but somepeople focus on only say about 7/8. But its a big difference bacause uaslly a demigod is called a half-blood. ok so a demigod can speak ancient greek or greek or they learn by tring to look on wepons they get then slowy they amerge to the language  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/68.209.242.103|68.209.242.103]] ([[User talk:68.209.242.103|talk]]) 03:42, 23 February 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Nooo...in mythology demigods are born like normal humans and learn Greek/Roman/etc culture just like everyone else does. They aren't born as fully-formed adults, only gods can be created like that. [[Special:Contributions/86.174.121.238|86.174.121.238]] ([[User talk:86.174.121.238|talk]]) 17:56, 6 May 2009 (UTC)

==Demi-gods of India==
Can anyone recast the following, apparently well-intentioned insertion with some source, and a little context? ([[User:Wetman|Wetman]] ([[User talk:Wetman|talk]]) 00:40, 9 May 2008 (UTC))
:&quot;Often people with an enlightened soul are given a demi-god like stature and they witnessed by say members of the family or some friends.&quot;

== Posibility of mixing seed ==

&lt;blockquote&gt;
the seed of the two fathers is mixed in her womb (not a modern biological possibility, but one that was firmly established in Antiquity).
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

I am not a biologist but is it not theoretically possible that child have 2 fathers? I.e. dizigotic chimera? [[User:Uzytkownik|Uzytkownik]] ([[User talk:Uzytkownik|talk]]) 23:48, 25 May 2008 (UTC)

== Jesus ==

Wouldn't Jesus be a demigod as well? With God being his father, and Mary, a human, his mother?  —Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/62.163.79.83|62.163.79.83]] ([[User talk:62.163.79.83|talk]]) 03:20, 10 September 2008 (UTC)&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Yes. But I think you are going to have a hard time getting any mention of Jesus on this page past the Christian Wikipedians.--[[User:Editor2020|Editor2020]] ([[User talk:Editor2020|talk]]) 00:46, 11 September 2008 (UTC)

::Jesus should be mentioned but requires a special note since while being &quot;half-god&quot; is also in a way, a third of a god but then also being God at the same time...  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/69.254.79.182|69.254.79.182]] ([[User talk:69.254.79.182|talk]]) 11:00, 11 July 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

POSSIBILITY OF MIXING SEED
It is possible and has happened in a modern case involving a prostitute.
There are times where two sperm will enter and egg and simply not create faternal twins rather create only one. Dont have time to explain it but if you look it up online you will definatly find it. (google it)  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/71.198.3.193|71.198.3.193]] ([[User talk:71.198.3.193|talk]]) 06:04, 25 September 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

&quot;Jesus is not a good example of a demigod, and that's not simply a subjective religious opinion of Christians. Jesus simply does not fit the definition of a demigod, according to this page's own criterion: that of being half god, and half human. According to every major Christian demonimation, Jesus is fully god AND fully human.&quot; 

Then perhaps the page definition needs addressing? Demigod was never so precisely defined and Dionysus whilst having both human and divine parents was fully divine, unlike for instance Hercules who had to earn his divinity. Most mainline Christians would agree that Jesus has fully divine and human natures, excepting the non-chalcedonian (monophysite)Oriental Orthodox confessions. The monophysite Jesus, being fully divine and not human by his nature, may escape the accusation of being a demigod as he is more of a theophany or full incarnation of God. The Gnostic Jesus of the Valentinus is absolutely divine, passing through Mary as water through a pipe and therefore not a demigod. Also the Jesus of the Monarchians for similar reasons.


Jesus is not a good example of a demigod, and that's not simply a subjective religious opinion of Christians. Jesus simply does not fit the definition of a demigod, according to this page's own criterion: that of being half god, and half human. According to every major Christian demonimation, Jesus is fully god AND fully human.

This is explicitly stated in very broadly accepted Christian creeds such as the Nicene Creed and the Athanasian Creed. (For example, the latter creed states that &quot;Jesus Christ, the Son of God, is God and man, God of the substance of the Father, begotten before the worlds; and man of substance of his mother...Perfect God and perfect man...Who, although He is God and man, yet He is not two, but one Christ.&quot;) The other figures listed on this page, such as Heracles, are listed because they were believed by the Greeks to be half god and half man. By the same standard, you must only list Jesus if he is believed by his followers to be half god and half man. And, demonstrably, he is not.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Alg0207|Alg0207]] ([[User talk:Alg0207|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Alg0207|contribs]]) 05:38, 23 July 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Jesus is a perfect example of a demigod and the very idea was of course lifted from Greek tradition.  It is hardly relevant that the Christians who wrote the Nicene Creed (a document drafted three centuries too late to be anything but legalistic conjecture) or any other tract appear to disagree with Christ as demigod because of a point of semantics.  The basic facts are: Jesus was born of a woman who was impregnated by a god.  Christians will argue until the next religion comes along about whether he was, a god, a man, or both.  The objective fact is that was a demigod.  The Christian thought police don't want to recognize this fact because it reveals that the Christian story is strongly influenced by the myths of the middle east and Greece.    

[[Special:Contributions/206.125.70.58|206.125.70.58]] ([[User talk:206.125.70.58|talk]]) 02:56, 23 March 2010 (UTC)

Demigods are generally considered to be mythical, Jesus is generally considered to be historical. [[User:Paul August|Paul August]] [[User_talk:Paul August|&amp;#9742;]] 01:15, 6 April 2012 (UTC)

The historicity of Jesus is debatable. However, the Jesus god-claim is definitely mythical. Jesus is a demi-god.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/202.89.148.177|202.89.148.177]] ([[User talk:202.89.148.177|talk]]) 01:04, 20 April 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Jesus is arguably a demi-god. In fact, the Christian church argued about that until writing the oft-quoted creeds mentioned above. However, the conclusion of &quot;fully god, fully human&quot; was not merely semantics. That distinction makes a very real and highly important difference in the Christian faith. As such, it is universally acknowledged among all branches of Christian faith and those who disagree (but might still claim the title Christian) must perforce qualify that they differ from normal Christianity in this regard. Since the preservation of the Jesus story has been historically carried out by Christian church, it is reasonable and academically sound to accept the Christian definition. (e.g. One could argue that a particular teaching of any religion was nonsensical but it still remains the teaching of that religion.) In other words, Jesus should not be listed as a demi-god even though he may seem to fit that description.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.236.183.144|76.236.183.144]] ([[User talk:76.236.183.144|talk]]) 19:32, 22 August 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

If Thor and Hercules had known you guys were going to have this argument, they would have said that they were both god and man, too.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.27.27.100|24.27.27.100]] ([[User talk:24.27.27.100|talk]]) 21:19, 29 August 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Demigod vs. Demi-god ==

What is the proper way to write demigod?
Is it demigod or demi-god? Are the two interchangeable?  
Shouldn't the article be consistent with what they call it? 
[[User:Prplfz9|Prplfz9]] ([[User talk:Prplfz9|talk]]) 05:39, 19 February 2009 (UTC)

==Moved comment on article page just below header to discussion page==

The definition given above would make [[Theseus]] a demi-god, demonstrating that the category, which applies in some sense to Heracles alone, is not a functioning category in [[ancient Greek religion]].{{Clarifyme|date=February 2009}}

==Literary/Fictional Reference==

I removed the line: &quot;Also, in the Percy Jackson and the Olympians series, Percy and his friends are mostly demigods, or half bloods.&quot;  It was at the least out place and uncited, and at the most completely irrelevant.  Maybe if someone wants to create a section of artistic depictions of these demigods, it could be included there...  [[User:Alex8541|Alex8541]] ([[User talk:Alex8541|talk]]) 18:04, 17 July 2010 (UTC)


Should the Olympian Series be mentioned at all? It seems almost every wikipedia page on Greek Mythology mentions that series, and almost exclusively which makes it seem more like advertising than trivia. Theyre mentioned in hundreds of currently popular fiction, from Xena to the X-men and yet only Percy Jackson is mentioned and mentioned everywhere.
[[Special:Contributions/219.88.182.68|219.88.182.68]] ([[User talk:219.88.182.68|talk]]) 08:50, 12 September 2012 (UTC)

== Ansel ==

Who the hell is Ansel?  I've been searching all over the place online for him and I can't figure out who this is meant to be in reference to.

[[Special:Contributions/216.54.22.188|216.54.22.188]] ([[User talk:216.54.22.188|talk]]) 23:04, 13 December 2010 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>hkxu7xusc6u0dc02e97nw1ws4tzyyvi</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
