<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Continuous revelation</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>186369</id>
    <revision>
      <id>340331536</id>
      <parentid>340198009</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-01-27T13:55:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Magioladitis</username>
        <id>1862829</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>expanding WikiProject Bahá'í Faith to make it readable, replaced: WPBF| → WikiProject Bahá'í Faith| using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="4900">{{ChristianityWikiProject|importance=Low|class=B|theology-work-group=yes|theology-importance=Mid|quakers=yes|quakers-importance=Mid|latter-day-saint-movement=yes|latter-day-saint-movement-importance=Mid|charismatic-christianity=yes|charismatic-christianity-importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Bahá'í Faith|class=B|importance=}}

==Theologies==
It would be good to discuss how this concept is used in [[progressive theology]] and [[feminist theology]] as well. Not exactly the same, but similar. Probably shows up in other theologies as well that I'm not thinking of. 

Also, the idea of the Church being guided by the Holy Spirit is common to most branches of Christianity, Orthodox, Catholic, and the thousands of Protestant denominations. It's hardly unique to the LDS.
[[User:Wesley|Wesley]]

:True, (although in Mormonism, as in others, it goes beyond just &quot;being guided by the Holy Spirit&quot; to direct communication with divine messengers), but generally Protestant fundies sure don't like continuous revelation. [[User:BoNoMoJo|B]] 22:51 15 Jul 2003 (UTC)

:: Direct communication with divine messengers (esp. angels) shows up in most Christian traditions; it's far from unique to Mormonism. What most Christians dislike is new revelation that contradicts earlier revelation. [[User:Wesley|Wesley]] 23:34 15 Jul 2003 (UTC)

:::Ok, Wesley, please don't point out to me a third time somthing I've understood since childhood regarding what is &quot;hardly unique to the LDS&quot; or &quot;far from unique to Mormonism&quot;. It's quite patronizing and condescending, especially after having explicitly acknowledged that by stating &quot;as in others&quot;. But besides that, fundamentalists do not get uptight merely over revelation that contradicts earlier revelation; they would be very reluctant to expand their canon. For them the Bible is it, period. If they claim revelation, they would be unlikely to give it status equal to anything in the Bible.  [[User:BoNoMoJo|B]] 00:13 16 Jul 2003 (UTC)

After rereading this thread, I apologize for sounding condescending; I see now that your statements had already acknowledged the (weak?) point I was making. And yes, I agree with you that for most Christians the Biblical canon is closed; further revelation would be expected to build on top of what is already revealed in the Bible, not add to or replace that foundation. [[User:Wesley|Wesley]] 16:20 16 Jul 2003 (UTC)

:Ok, please overlook my defensiveness. You do make a point though...this article does need more rounding out as now it only states the LDS view generally. If the article is not likely to be expanded much it should probably be moved to &quot;Continuous Revelation (Mormonsim)&quot;. I've not been brave enough to write a broader article partly because, like [[Great Apostasy]], while the underlying concept is probably common to various sects, the phraseology may be unique to only one or a few sects. If this article is to be well developed, I think we need to determine how widely the article's phrase is used, and what is the most basic/common formulation of this concept among various sects. [[User:BoNoMoJo|B]] 18:30 16 Jul 2003 (UTC)

== Use of &quot;continuous&quot; and &quot;continuing&quot; in LDS terminology ==
The words &quot;'''continuous'''&quot; and &quot;'''continuing'''&quot; are not synonymous.  The leaders of [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] have repeatedly made it clear that the doctines of their faith teach '''continuing revelation''', and not continuous revelation.  Therefore this article has been incorrectly titled, or at least this sub section has been incorrectly placed under it. ''Original comment by [[User:The fiddler]], moved from article.''
:See [http://library.lds.org/nxt/gateway.dll/Magazines/Ensign/1989.htm/ensign%20november%201989.htm/continuous%20revelation%20.htm here] for a conference talk by General Authority James E. Faust on the use of the term &quot;continuous revelation.&quot; [[User:Tijuana Brass|Tijuana Brass]] 17:23, 12 April 2006 (UTC)

==Bahá'í not here!==
Bahá'í don't belong to here. Their revelation system is progressive, not continuous. LDS have a prophetic institution that, according to their system, is entitled to continuous or continuing revelation (which is '''not''' distinguishable in my language), i.e. updating, improving and rewriting the system simply because ''they're prophets''. Bahá'í don't have this in their system. They have one last prophet for this millenium, and that's Bahá'u'lláh, '''STOP'''. Nobody have the right to update and make prophesies (according to their view) for at least 1000 years into the future. Bahá'í is very well written about in the article of [[Progressive revelation (Bahá'í)]] so it need not a section in this article too — a link to there will be enough. [[User:Rursus|Rursus]] dixit. ([[User talk:Rursus|&lt;span style=&quot;color: red; background: yellow&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;m&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;u&gt;bork&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]]!) 20:29, 26 January 2010 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>fyoopcc0nq6v1wp67nqae10hgou2pbf</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
