<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Indulgence</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>860220</id>
    <revision>
      <id>513880954</id>
      <parentid>513877655</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-21T15:00:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Johnbod</username>
        <id>2563820</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Help:Reverting|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/99.246.60.33|99.246.60.33]] ([[User talk:99.246.60.33|talk]]) to last version by Grey=Brown&amp;Tan</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="30493">{{talk header}}
{{WikiProject Christianity
 |class=B|importance=Low
 |catholicism=yes|catholicism-importance=Mid
 |eastern-orthodoxy=yes|eastern orthodoxy-importance=
 |lutheranism=yes|lutheranism-importance=mid
 |theology-work-group=yes|theology-importance=
}}

== Historical Signifigance ==

There is currently no section in the acticle concerning the way in which the refutation of the doctrine of indulgences started Martin Luther on the road toward the Reformation. There should be a section that deals with this. More importantly this article reads like a piece of Roman Catholic doctrine than a proper encyclopediac entry. To not mention the important controversy regarding them, and then to paint the Catholic practise as proper but give modern examples of unethical behaviour by protestant televangilists also clouds this article with political bias. Indulgences do have a historical signifigance to Western culture that extends beyond their Roman Catholic dogma.  [[User:Humbleservant|Humble Servant]] 20:54, 17 October 2006 (UTC)
:I agree 100%.  Besides being barely understandable to a non-catholic reader, this article has a strong church-apologist POV [[User:PermanentE|PermanentE]] 23:23, 27 December 2006 (UTC)
::I agree as well, the article's POV is seems very much as though it was coming from a member of the church. This article needs to be re-written as NPOV. 16:56, 6 September 2007 (UTC)  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/199.4.143.83|199.4.143.83]] ([[User talk:199.4.143.83|talk]]) {{{2|}}}&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:I find this article to be a well written explanation of Catholic Doctrine.  As a catholic, seeking a current indulgence offered by Pope Benedict, I had some specific questions about indulgences answered by reading this article.  Where better to get an explanation of catholic doctrine than from somebody closely associated with the church?  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/64.33.143.164|64.33.143.164]] ([[User talk:64.33.143.164|talk]]) 19:31, 11 February 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Do indulgences still exist in the Roman Catholic Church ==

:''Today, indulgences does not exist in Roman Catholic Church''

Is this true?  I can understand why they might not be ''selling'' them anymore.  But my understanding is that indulgences could still be obtained by performing ritual acts like praying to certain saints or going on pilgrimages to shrines and so forth.  At least, this was the impression I got last time I spoke with the Blue Army rosary ladies, which has been a few year.  [[User:Ihcoyc|Smerdis of Tlön]] 04:12, 27 Jul 2004 (UTC)

Also, can we withhold judgment on whether Luther was correct in characterizing the marketing of indulgences as a sale of indulgences? [[User:Hasdrubal|Hasdrubal]] 02:51, 5 Apr 2005 (UTC)

:Why?  Your remark suggests that there isn't really a controversy to withhold judgment on, there being no difference between &quot;marketing&quot; and &quot;selling&quot;.  -- [[User:Ihcoyc|Smerdis of Tlön]] 04:13, 5 Apr 2005 (UTC)

*The statement &quot;Today, indulgences does (''sic'') not exist in Roman Catholic Church (''sic'')&quot; is incorrect, both doctrinally and grammatically. Indulgences do still exist in the RCC, and they are earned (never sold) for performing various actions. (In 1567, Pope Pius V, following the Council of Trent, forbade the attachment of indulgences to any financial act, including the giving of alms.) 

:For example, praying the Angelus each day earns a partial indulgence. 

:As for whether Martin Luther was correct or not, I believe this is an issue of POV. What should be said is &quot;Martin Luther characterized the marketing of indlugences as a sale of indulgences.&quot; If anything else, it could be said, equally NPOV, that the RCC denies this. ''Whether'' Luther was or was not correct in his assessment is a matter of opinion, not fact, and is inherrently POV, but ''that'' he made the assessment is a matter of fact and NPOV. Equally so, ''whether'' the RCC is or is not correct in believing that Luther was incorrct is a matter of opinion; ''that'' the RCC holds this position is a matter of fact.  [[User:Essjay|Essjay]] 06:25, Jun 8, 2005 (UTC)

:Indulgences do exist in the Roman Catholic Church today.  The Council of Trent abolished all connections indulgences had with money, but they did not abolish indulgences themselves.  The Handbook of Indulgences Norms and Grants is still authorized and published by the Catholic Book Publishing Corp. with a version copyrighted as recently as 1991. [[User:Andy120|Andy120]] 17:22, 17 August 2006 (UTC)

:I think they upgraded the spell so you have to be an [http://www.chick.com/reading/tracts/0046/0046_01.asp 8th level cleric] to cast Plenary Indulgence now. -- [[User:Rogerborg|Rogerborg]] 11:20, 30 January 2007 (UTC)

:Seriously, I think that Rogerborg is ignorant, cynical and anti-catholic and he is mocking our catholic faith because he is brain-washed by Chick Publications, which is banned in many countries around the world and simply using anti-catholicism to enrich their coffers. The Catechism of the Catholic Church teaches in Part Two, Section Two, Chapter Two, Article 4, Item X that &quot;an Indulgence is a remission before God of the temporal punishment due to sins whose guilt has already been forgiven, which the faithful Christian who is duly disposed gains under certain prescribed conditions through the action of the Church which, as the minister of redemption, dispenses and applies with authority the treasury of the satisfaction of Christ and the saints. An indulgence is partial or plenary according as it removes either partial or all of the temporal punishment due to sin. The faithful can gain indulgences for themselves or apply them to the dead.&quot; (CCC 1471 to 1498). The authority to forgive sins and to grant indulgences that is bound on earth and in heaven was given to the Church by Christ Himself. (Mt 16:19). However, an Indulgence is only effective in so far as there's true repentant or contrition for the sins forgiven. [[User:Benitus|Benitus]] ([[User talk:Benitus|talk]]) 00:41, 30 December 2007 (UTC)

==Overhaul==

I've overhauled this article; I'd appreciate a review or imput on the &quot;other Christian traditions&quot; section, as I can only speak to the Catholic and DOC positions. [[User:Essjay|Essjay]] 09:24, Jun 8, 2005 (UTC)

==Other Christian Traditions==

The section on other Christian traditions may require some nuances. Most Protestants reject a doctrine of purgatory, but not all. C.S. Lewis is an obvious (but not lone) example. Orthodox Christians definitely reject &quot;Purgatory&quot; under that Latin name, but many suggest other ways that souls may be cleansed or purified after death that most Catholic theologians would consider &quot;a distinction without a difference&quot; (c.f. [http://www.geocities.com/swickersc/get-clean.html this Catholic &quot;Cleansed After Death&quot; article]). So while it is generally safe to say that neither Protestants nor Orthodox believe in purgatory or grant indulgences, there are some similar beliefs and practices among them. [[User:Johnaugus|Johnaugus]]
: I can't recall anything in Lewis that suggests that he believed in Purgatory (The Great Divorce, for example, begins with an explicit disclaimer that he is *not* speculating about conditions in the afterlife, but presenting an allegory).  The article on Purgatory makes a similar claim for Lewis -- any citations?
--[[User:Jrcagle|jrcagle]] 23:58, 27 April 2006 (UTC)

: C.S. Lewis's position is sketchy at best in regards to purgatory, but his belief's, as representative of protestant doctrine, is immaterial. A review of mainline Protestant churches, Anglican, Luthern, Presbyterian, United, all refute the dogma of purgatory. There is no similar belief or practise I am aware of among Protestants. [[User:Humbleservant|Humble Servant]] 03:20, 19 October 2006 (UTC)

I added a reference to something like Indulgences in the Pharisaic tradition. [[User:Jonathan Tweet|Jonathan Tweet]] 14:32, 4 October 2006 (UTC) -

--I would like to know the reference for the quotation from Patriarch Dositheus regarding the distribution of indulgences to the Eastern Orthodox. --[[User:Cristianispir|Cristianispir]] 14:23, 14 November 2006 (UTC)

: I have now found a related reference to a similar citation alleged to be that of Dositheus: &quot;We have the custom and ancient tradition, which is known to all, that the most holy Patriarchs would give the people of the Church a certificate for the absolution of their sins.(Sinhorohartion) '''in''' ''A. Papadopoulos-Kerameus, Symvolai eis tin istorian tis arkhiepiskopis tou orous Sina (Towards a History of the Archbishopric of Sinan). Saint Petersburg, 1908. p. 133.''&quot;--[[User:Cristianispir|Cristianispir]] 14:44, 14 November 2006 (UTC)

== Confession ==

In another occurrance of the continual war to change Reconciliation to Confession, this page has now been hit. I've said it before, and I'm sure I will have to say it again. The Catechism says Reconciliation, the Code of Canon Law says reconciliation, JP2 said reconciliation, B16 says reconciliation, and Francis Cardinal Arinze of the Congregation for Divine Worship and the Discipline of the Sacraments says reconciliation. It isn't called confession anymore, it is RECONCILIATION! -- [[User:Essjay|Essjay]] ·  [[User_talk:Essjay| Talk]] 04:17, August 7, 2005 (UTC)

:I disagree; The Code of Canon Law says [http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG1104/__P3E.HTM Penance](Cann. 959 - 997), not reconciliation. [[User:Andy120|Andy120]] 17:27, 17 August 2006 (UTC)

::Maybe when the old/alternative term is as widely recognised as this, it would be worth mentioning it at the first use in the article - if only for the benefit of readers less well versed in contemporary terminology? Something like sacrament of reconciliation (sometimes known as confession)? Or the other way round, I suppose - I have no axe to grind. - [[User:Paul|Paul]] 04:20, 20 April 2007 (UTC)

:Please allow me to throw in my two-bits worth because I was recently researching this Sacrament to prepare to teach my Religious Instruction class for some elderly baptists and I found some disquieting truths. Yes, this Sacrament used to be known as the Sacrament of Penance and still is known as such. In the Catechism of the Catholic Church (Article 4, CCC 1422 to 1498), it is officially described as the Sacrament of Penance and Reconciliation, although it is equally referred to as the Sacrament of Penance and the Sacrament of Reconciliation at different places, depending on the topic being discussed. &quot;Confession&quot; has always been a colloquial and practical term used to refer to the reception of the Sacrament of Penance, although many lay catholics (both past and present) have often referred to it as being the Sacrament of Confession, which is allowed for within the Catechism, e.g. the Sacrament of Penance and Reconciliation is variously called the &quot;sacrament of conversion&quot;, the &quot;sacrament of Penance&quot; (CCC 1423), the &quot;sacrament of confession&quot;, the &quot;sacrament of forgiveness&quot;, and the &quot;sacrament of reconciliation&quot; (CCC 1424). The Code of Canon Law was revised before the revision of the Catechism of the Catholic Church was released, which may account for the apparent anomaly but Pope JP2 himself did encourage the use of the term &quot;Sacrament of Reconciliation&quot; rather than the term &quot;Sacrament of Penance&quot; (although both are equally correct and acceptable) because &quot;penance&quot; suggests negativity whereas &quot;reconciliation&quot; suggests positivity and the church encourages us to be positive about all the seven holy sacraments, which were instituted to restore us to a state of sanctifying grace or an increase of sacramental grace. Hence, the elderly people (even for Pope B16 himself) tend to refer to it as the Sacrament of Penance (more by force of habit than anything else) while the younger or newer catholics and converts like myself would prefer to refer to it as the Sacrament of Reconciliation. At the end of the day, as long as we know what we're talking about, anything that works for anyone of us is equally acceptable to the church, so we shouldn't lose any sleep over the use of different terminology. [[User:Benitus|Benitus]] ([[User talk:Benitus|talk]]) 22:01, 29 December 2007 (UTC)

== Simony ==

Does the concept of [[Simony]] relate to the practice of Indulgences especially during the dark ages when Indulgences were one of the main issues spawning the Reformation?
: Simony (the selling of church offices) begins not in the &quot;dark ages&quot; -- which are generally taken to  be the period between the fall of Rome and the ascendency of Charlemagne or perhaps Otto I -- but somewhat later.  The practice occurred at the highest levels in the 11th century with Gregory VI; Gregory VII condemned it [http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/source/g7-reform1.html].  The Reformation is linked to simony in a way.  The Archbishop of Mainz had to pay a rather large fee in return for his post, and his authorization of Tetzel to sell indulgences was a way to recoup the losses (Cameron, p. 100).  Whether or not this was ''simony'' is probably debated; the fee was I believe technically a fee for the dispensation to allow the under-age Mainz to take the post.--[[User:Jrcagle|jrcagle]] 00:18, 28 April 2006 (UTC)
'''Bold text'''

== Manual of Indulgences ==

The revised Manual of Indulgences (1999) is now out in an English version. It is excellent. The USCCB is the publisher.

== Image removed ==

I've removed the image of an alleged indulgence by Tetzel ([[:Image:Indulgence.png]]). There are serious doubts as to its authenticity. See [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=User_talk:Ihcoyc&amp;oldid=143164751#Indulgence] . [[User:Future Perfect at Sunrise|Fut.Perf.]] [[User talk:Future Perfect at Sunrise|☼]] 09:42, 8 July 2007 (UTC)

== granted AFTER the sinner confesses? ==

There is a crucial point glossed over here. The article states that indulgences only apply to sins already confessed and forgiven, and the &quot;Myths About Indulgences&quot; reference specifically states that a person can't &quot;buy forgiveness&quot; or apply indulgences for sins yet committed; yet when Luther wrote his Theses, many people (both priests and laymen) believed that indulgences could be used that way. That was one of the primary reasons for the controversy, and also a primary reason that many people now believe indulgences are no longer part of Church teaching. This article states a specific technical definition of an indulgence without mentioning the common understanding, which was and is widely held. Shouldn't it mention the difference, so as to shed light on the controversies?
[[User:keno]] 20:55, 17 August 2007 (UTC)

::Mortal sins forgiven in confession can still leave time in [[Purgatory]]. Indulgences are for time in Purgatory, but never for time in Hell. In the Reformation period some people were giving a misrepresentation of the indulgenced act of [[almsgiving]] and making it seem like buying. It was supposed to be charitable ''donations''. I think it is important for the article to always explain this misunderstood Catholic concept too. [[User:Grey&amp;#61;Brown&amp;#38;Tan|GreyTanBrown]] ([[User talk:Grey&amp;#61;Brown&amp;#38;Tan|talk]]) 01:54, 27 April 2012 (UTC)

== Merge &quot;Treasury of Merit&quot; into &quot;Indulgences&quot;  ==

I suggest merging [[Treasury of Merit]] into this article. &quot;Treasure House&quot; is very short, marked as having quality issues, and at one time the subject of a delete discussion. It essentially just a definition needed for this article. The only other link to it comes from [[Martin Luther]] which would probably do better by pointing here instead.  [[User:Hult041956|Hult041956]] 17:51, 9 November 2007 (UTC)

I'm not a cradle catholic but I've been a very active student of catholic history and the catholic church. I used to be a bible-quoting, gung-ho protestant before God led me into the catholic church, so I'm very familiar with the arguments of both sides of the christian divide. I don't believe that the catholic church practises any such thing as a &quot;Treasure House of Merit&quot;. In fact, personal merits acquired by individuals cannot be sold or transferred to another person, although we can secure favors from God for people we care about through our prayers and merits. Our Lord only spoke about the need for us to store treasure in heaven through our acts of charity, prayers, sacrifices, penances, self-denials, atonement, etc. The so-called practice of selling indulgences or even of merits was un-catholic and un-christian, limited to some zealots or corrupted few of the Middle Ages within the church (who sought to raise funds among the nobles of that time to build churches or to pay for the defence of the church against muslim expansion) before the Catholic reformation prompted by the Council of Trent, which banned or banished such un-catholic activities that were not approved by the magisterium of the church. Only anti-catholics would continue to use such mistakes by a limited few to attack the catholic church and the christian faith it professes, which has largely remained unchanged since the time of Christ. Yes, Martin Luther had strong objections to such practices and rightly so but he was wrong to take it upon himself to use such mistakes to attack the church in a vain attempt to force the church to make changes, rather than to work on securing changes within the church because his actions were tantamount to placing himself above God, which resulted in creating his own church (and setting a very bad example for others to do the same which ended up with more than 30,000 different christian churches) that was not of God's making, i.e. he founded a church to believe in God in his own way and not the way that Jesus had taught us. The Catholic Church was founded by Jesus Himself and established by His Apostles, which is the only true church of Christ, regardless of whatever shortcomings that may have been created by the leaders of the church, and Jesus promised that the gates of Hell would not prevail against it (Mt 16:18-19). God allowed the human leaders of the church to make mistakes that led to dissatisfaction which prompted reforms that were necessary for change with the times but never once, did any of the Popes or Bishops change the constitution of the church, i.e. the dogmas of the church, to justify their wrong-doings and all of them died repentant of their sins.

Therefore, the very entry for &quot;Treasure House of Merit&quot; is wrong by itself (as there is no such thing, other than what was alleged of the catholic church by protestants and anti-catholics) but if you decide to merge it with the entry on &quot;Indulgence&quot;, then Wikipedia would run the risk of being biased and be considered irrelevant by both catholics and non-christians seeking the truth of historical facts. Wikipedia should in fact remove the entry &quot;Treasure House of Merit&quot; itself, simply because there is no such thing within the doctrines of the catholic church. You may refer to the Catechism of the Catholic Church or the Catholic Encyclopedia to confirm whether such a thing as &quot;Treasure House of Merit&quot; truly exists or not within the catholic church. Thank you. [[User:Benitus|Benitus]] ([[User talk:Benitus|talk]]) 21:27, 29 December 2007 (UTC)

If Martin Luther felt it important enough to mention in his 95 theses, then it is worthy of mention here, even if he was mistaken. As long as there are verifiable sources and a neutral POV, that is. Perhaps merging with the article on Martin Luther would be more appropriate though[[User:Beeblbrox|Beeblbrox]] ([[User talk:Beeblbrox|talk]]) 00:04, 28 January 2008 (UTC)

: Then that article should discuss Luther's notion of the &quot;Treasure House of Merit&quot;, and not portray it as current or historical Catholic doctrine. I will, as I have time, be rewriting this article considerably. [[User_talk:Gimmetrow|''Gimmetrow'']] 02:48, 18 February 2008 (UTC)

== Neutrality issues  ==

The section on mortal sin versus versus in particular seems to present Catholic theology as fact. It seems to me a POV edit is needed here.[[User:Beeblbrox|Beeblbrox]] ([[User talk:Beeblbrox|talk]]) 23:20, 27 January 2008 (UTC)
: Precisely what would that involve? putting &quot;According to Catholic theology&quot; before every sentence? [[User_talk:Gimmetrow|''Gimmetrow'']] 20:58, 11 February 2008 (UTC)
:: We could add the &quot;In-universe&quot; template. [[User:Gigs|Gigs]] ([[User talk:Gigs|talk]]) 07:46, 8 June 2008 (UTC)

I changed contrary to &quot;dogmatic truth&quot; for &quot;dogmatic teachings&quot;!!!!!!!!!, Abuses?.....it was the church that was selling those indulgences sponsored by the pope who was financing the church this way, the article makes it sound as if it were some rogue christians. it sound like if it had been written by a priest, it has no neutrality what so ever.....  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/216.95.235.216|216.95.235.216]] ([[User talk:216.95.235.216|talk]]) 20:56, 10 February 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Plenary Indulgences ==

Yes they still exist in RCC. To earn one, the faithful must confess his/her sins and receive the body of Christ within a short period of time after the indulgence is granted.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/64.134.224.90|64.134.224.90]] ([[User talk:64.134.224.90|talk]]) 17:18, 9 February 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

need more info  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.143.130.161|24.143.130.161]] ([[User talk:24.143.130.161|talk]]) 23:19, 24 April 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:The article says: &quot;To gain a plenary indulgence, a person must exclude all attachment to sin of any kind, even venial sin, must perform the work or say the prayer for which the indulgence is granted, and must also fulfil the three conditions of sacramental confession, Eucharistic communion and praying for the intentions of the Pope.&quot; It gives several examples of actions for which plenary indulgences are granted (on those conditions).  What more do you want?  [[User:Lima|Lima]] ([[User talk:Lima|talk]]) 04:06, 25 April 2008 (UTC)

== Function ==
The article addresses nicely the function of indulgences according to Catholic beliefs. It does not, however, address the function of indulgences from an objective or impartial perspective. This is frequently a problem with Wikipedia articles on religion. The function of indulgences is to perpetuate Catholicism by making people go back to &quot;the flock&quot; if they steer away from it. For example, if a person does something suggesting that they are not obeying the priests, the priest tells the person to attend a retreat or to attend an absolution by the bishop as part of the indulgence - in this way, as people inevitably &quot;sin&quot; and feel guilty for it, the Church guarantees that there will be regular attendance of its retreats and the bishop's ceremonies. The function is  clearly preservation and perpetuation of the religion, whereas Catholics believe that it has something to do with spirituality. These are two different explanations of the function of indulgences, but the article addresses only the internal one and omits the objective explanation.   &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/99.36.7.54|99.36.7.54]] ([[User talk:99.36.7.54|talk]]) 14:41, 6 July 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Firstly, new comments go on the bottom of the page. Secondly, to call any of what you wrote here as &quot;objective&quot; is laughable. It clearly is anti-religious in tone and content. It certainly doesn't belong in the article, as this article, like most religous topics, exists to describe what people believe, not give credance to attempts at explaining away other's beliefs. If you want to do that, get a blog. [[User:Oknazevad|oknazevad]] ([[User talk:Oknazevad|talk]]) 23:42, 1 January 2010 (UTC)

== Temporal Punishment ==
There doesn't seem to be a good explanation in this article or in the WikiPedia of &quot;temporal punishment&quot;.  Could someone please provide more definition and examples?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/134.134.139.71|134.134.139.71]] ([[User talk:134.134.139.71|talk]]) 01:20, 12 January 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== [[simony]] ==

are there not historic attestations to indulgences that were acts of [[simony]]? [[Special:Contributions/67.171.233.221|67.171.233.221]] ([[User talk:67.171.233.221|talk]]) 13:22, 5 March 2011 (UTC)

== Eastern Orthodoxy ==

From what I've read on the subject, indulgences crept up in the Greek Church as a Latinization.  There were apparently a number of councils that formed to directly address these Latinizations, it was just that the matter of the absolution certificates wasn't realized as one until the 19th century, and it wasn't until the 20th century that they were completely rooted out.  I assume that they were excused for so long due to the heavy taxes, which the article does mention, that were levied on Christians (especially the Church) by the Ottomans; they excused their extortion of the laity to pay off Ottoman extortion of the Church.  The evidence available shows no real history of them before the 16th century, yet the article makes it sound like they were there since the beginning.  They were only officially noted in Church writings somewhere in the 17th or 18th century.  I think, as currently written, it sounds a bit misleading. -[[User:HawkeyE|HawkeyE]] ([[User talk:HawkeyE|talk]]) 06:01, 9 May 2011 (UTC)
:It would be a good idea to insert into the article the evidence of reliable sources about the relatively recent origin of those certificates. That evidence would then correct (or counterbalance?) the statement by Patriarch Dositheos at the end of the 17th century that it was &quot;an established custom and ancient tradition, known to all, that the Most Holy Patriarchs give the absolution certificate to the faithful people … they have granted them from the beginning and still do.&quot;  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 06:44, 9 May 2011 (UTC)

== Mischaracterizes Luther and the 95 theses ==

This article misrepresents Luther's critique in the 95 theses, or at least is so unclear as to be misleading. Luther did not &quot;reject the Pope's authority to grant pardons.&quot; In fact in the theses he specifically affirms that the Pope, along with bishops, has the authority to absolve sins. His criticism has to do on the one hand with the impression that common people were receiving, which was that buying indulgences could free loved ones from purgatory or somehow granted them the right to sin with impunity. On the other Luther pointed out that temporal punishments associated with sin could not be remitted by the church because those punishments were not determined by clergy or the church but by God, and moreover that the temporal punishments inflicted by God on earth or in purgatory (which Luther still acknowledged in the writing of the theses) were beneficial for the forgiven sinner. Truly penitent sinners, he writes, are glad to receive afflictions from God because through them God crucifies the old man. He acknowledges that the Pope can remit ecclesiastical penalties laid out in canon law, but raises several strong objections--first of all, those penalties had fallen into disuse anyway, so the indulgence is superfluous. Secondly, canon law does not impose ecclesiastical penalties on the dying or the souls in purgatory anyway. Third, if the pope did have the authority to remit temporal punishments either in purgatory or on earth, charity would seem to dictate that he simply grant plenary indulgences gratuitously, just as absolution is granted to penitent or contrite sinners without payment. A reading of the 95 theses--which are not very long--would make it clear that the present wording of the article misrepresents Luther's critique. Even after maturing in his theology, Luther taught until the end of his life that ministers had been given the authority to forgive sins in Christ's name. Whatever footnote is cited to back up the claim that Luther denied that bishops or the pope have the authority to pardon needs to be checked. Finally, since the sale of indulgences is so critical to the history of Lutheranism in particular and by extension to the rest of protestantism, this ought not simply to be an article detailing catholic dogma concerning indulgences but needs to have an extended section discussing the implications of Rome's teaching on indulgences for the larger critique of the Roman church by fully developed Lutheran and Reformed theology. The Luther who wrote the 95 theses does not seem to express the &quot;Lutheran&quot; doctrine of justification by faith in Christ alone that came to characterize the reformation of the church triggered by these abuses of indulgences in Germany.  In general, doing justice to this topic requires acknowledging the significance of indulgences for protestants, getting what the 95 theses say right, and making clear that the critique of the 95 theses is not at all the same as the general protestant rejection of catholic teaching on indulgences, nor is it even Luther's later critique, nor does it represent Lutheran teaching on confession and absolution, repentance, human merit, or justification.  It is very much a criticism written by a Roman Catholic monk not outside of the mainstream of catholic theology at the time.  The 95 theses were very well received by church leaders who were unwilling to follow Luther's later teaching.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/99.31.123.200|99.31.123.200]] ([[User talk:99.31.123.200|talk]]) 17:12, 29 October 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;</text>
      <sha1>ojylutd0lhn8q4g9pmlws9bfg5yyvud</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
