<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Assumption of Mary</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1780070</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516330875</id>
      <parentid>516330785</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-06T16:08:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>History2007</username>
        <id>3684925</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Mary's holy death */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="39727">{{WikiProject Christianity|class=B|importance=High|theology-work-group=yes|theology-importance=High|catholicism=yes|catholicism-importance=Top|anglicanism=yes|anglicanism-importance=low|saints=yes|saints-importance=Top|eastern-orthodoxy=yes|eastern orthodoxy-importance=High|oriental-orthodoxy=yes|oriental-orthodoxy-importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Women's History|class=b|importance=mid}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2008-08-15|oldid1=232177881|date2=2009-08-15|oldid2=307859850|date3=2009-08-28|oldid3=310468499|date4=2010-08-15|oldid4=378821194|date5=2010-08-28|oldid5=381246738|date6=2011-08-15|oldid6=444882019|date7=2011-08-28|oldid7=447056963|date8=2012-08-15|oldid8=507558906|date9=2012-08-28|oldid9=509618644}}
{{Copied|from=Assumption of Mary|from_oldid=http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Assumption_of_Mary&amp;oldid=389338245|to=Catholic views on Mary|diff=http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Catholic_views_on_Mary&amp;oldid=389451226}} 

==Meaning==
This entry defines what the term &quot;Assumption of Mary&quot; ''means'', but does not explain its ''origins'' or history. Although dogmatically defined in 1950, we know that this ''ex cathedra'' statement of [[Papal infallibility]] requires that &quot;his teaching cannot contradict anything the Church has taught officially and previously.&quot; So, where did it really come from originally? Who first spoke of this concept?

::I concur with the above remarks. Anyone who knows how to use the internet will see that this entry is inadequate.

:Yes, a historical account is needed. [[User:Paul Barlow|Paul B]] 07:30, 6 June 2006 (UTC)

== The dogma of the Assumption ==

I was raised a Catholic, and I understand the importance of church history and tradition, but how can this dogma exist with zero documentary evidence to support it for over 3 centuries after Jesus's crucifiction?  Calling this &quot;dogma&quot; only puts into question the, for me, incontrovertible dogma of Jesus's bodily resurrection.  Don't mix up this Assumpton issue with truly fundamental Christian dogma like the resurrection.  There is no comparison in terms of textual evidence.[[User:Vertex11|Vertex11]] 19:23, 12 April 2007 (UTC) &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[User:Vertex11|Vertex11]] ([[User talk:Vertex11|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Vertex11|contribs]]) 02:48, 11 April 2007 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;

I was raised a Catholic too ! and I believe the Holy Mother went up. up, body and Soul to heaven.Never mind Dogma
you should Know Mary's Canticle, &quot; My being proclaims the greatness of the Lord. My spirit finds joy in God my savior.
For he has looked upon his servant in her lowliness.all ages to come shall call me blessed.God who is mighty has done
great things for me,holy is his name,His mercy is from age to age on those who fear him. He has shown might with his arm,
he has confused in their inmost thoughts . He has disposed the mighty from their thrones and raised the lowly to high places.
The hungry he has given every good thing,while the rich he has sent empty away. He has upheld Israel his servant,ever mindful of his
mercy: Even as he promised our fathers,promised Abraham and his descendents forever. Luke 1. 40-55 and when our Lady went up
I guess she said pray for yourselves ! (four tildes)[[Special:Contributions/65.92.98.29|65.92.98.29]] ([[User talk:65.92.98.29|talk]]) 10:22, 15 August 2011 (UTC) 15 August, 2011 6:20 a,m,        



Hi. I'm a Catholic, but of the more broad-minded variety. The idea behind the proclamation of the dogma by Pius XII was that, since the generality of Catholics believed in the Assumption of Mary since the year dot, they must have believed in something that was passed down by the Apostles of Jesus. There are other reasons behind it too, connected with the idea of the [[Immaculate Conception]], that is, the idea that Mary was preserved from [[original sin]]. Original Sin was the cause of death. If Mary did not have original sin, then she could not die. Though she could choose to die, as Jesus did, in imitation of her son, and be resurrected, as he was.  Cheers. --[[User:Gazzster|Gazzster]] 09:56, 29 April 2007 (UTC)

There is a factual error on this page.  The Lutheran Church does not teach or believe in the bodily assumption of Mary.  Nor does the Lutheran Church believe that Mary was without sin.  Martin Luther stated that Mary was unique because God chose her to give birth to his Son, but in every other way she was just like the rest of us sinners dependent of God's grace.  All of the Lutheran Confessional Documents found in the Book of Concord and other historical documents agree on these points.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/190.84.122.20|190.84.122.20]] ([[User talk:190.84.122.20|talk]]) 17:53, 17 August 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:I have seen sources that say certain Lutheran churches teach that Mary was indeed eather Immaculately Conceived or spared from sin. And the [[Anglo-Lutheran Catholic Church]] even goes so far to agree with Papal infallibility. --[[User:Willthacheerleader18|Willthacheerleader18]] ([[User talk:Willthacheerleader18|talk]]) 23:36, 14 August 2010 (UTC)
::The argument above is somewhat incorrect, as the Blessed Virgin did actually die (though that is not de fide). However, even, I believe it was St. Augustine (I read it in a citation of St. Thomas's) concludes somewhere, seemingly with surprise, that &quot;not everything seems in the Bible, since ''even'' Mary's assumption is not in the Bible&quot;. We may however find it in the idea of &quot;the Lord exalts the lowest&quot; in the Blessed Virgin's own prophetical Magnificat, or even the commandment &quot;Honor your [...] mother&quot; that the Lord himself fulfilled, all the more since the Blessed Virgin was worthy of this Honour. --[[Special:Contributions/77.4.118.194|77.4.118.194]] ([[User talk:77.4.118.194|talk]]) 21:37, 21 October 2010 (UTC)
:::The argument is not incorrect, as the Roman Catholic Church and the Anglican Communion teach that the Blessed Virgin Mary did not die, but was assumed body and soul into the glory of heaven. The Orthodox churches, however, do teach the [[Dormition of the Theotokos]], or that Mary did die and then was assumed body and soul into heaven. --[[User:Willthacheerleader18|Willthacheerleader18]] ([[User talk:Willthacheerleader18|talk]]) 21:53, 21 October 2010 (UTC)
::::Well, no, here it is you that are incorrect, sorry to say so. The Orthodox teach the Dormition and the Catholic Church has done so too in its liturgy in the 9th century, and though this liturgy is not present, its teaching has never been retracted and should thus be still considered the official teaching of the Church. Nor does it contradict the Dogma of the Assumption, which only says that the Blessed Virgin was either (possibly with the infallible dogmatic formulation, but thus rather contrary to ordinary Church doctrine) assumed without death or, and this seems to be Church doctrine, was assumed quite soon &lt;small&gt;though possibly with some &quot;three days intermediate&quot; that could be explained as hindering any way of surpassing Our Lord's glory. -- I correct myself. The Easterners celebrate Dormition on the 14th afaik and if this were the case, we'd rather celebrate assumption on the 16th.&lt;/small&gt; ''after'' her death in ''body and'' soul, as opposed to the &quot;ordinary&quot; glory of the blessed before the Last Day, a priviledge that she shares with some* but is far from generality, but which, after the Last Day, all the Blessed will have equally. [*&quot;Some&quot; is of course our Most Holy Redeemer in His human nature, that's the doctrine of the Ascension, and maybe only Him. It was however a pious belief of the Middle Ages that it includes St. John the Evangelist, a pious belief of the Opus Dei Founder that it includes St. Joseph, and some speculation that it includes at least some of the departed of the Old Covenant which &quot;appeared to many&quot;, as recorded in the Gospels.] A rumour has it that Pius XII. was not far from unconscientously con-dogmatising the Dormition, when somebody told him to have received a Marian apparition about not to do so. That he didn't in fact doesn't, on the other hand, say that he believed in the respective apparition (an apparition gives no new doctrine), but only that it reminded him what it was precisely he wished to dogmatise. The same--[[Special:Contributions/84.154.106.75|84.154.106.75]] ([[User talk:84.154.106.75|talk]]) 10:26, 30 October 2010 (UTC)
:::::As a practicing Roman Catholic, and of the Traditional kind, the Assumption is dogma in our church, and we do not celebrate the Dorminition. The Catholic Church does not REJECT the Dorminition, but we do not celebrate it either, mainly because most Catholics do not believe Mary died. (Death is caused by sin, and since Catholics believe Mary was sinless ([[Immaculate Conception]]) she did not die.) --[[User:Willthacheerleader18|Willthacheerleader18]] ([[User talk:Willthacheerleader18|talk]]) 00:27, 2 November 2010 (UTC)
::::::Actually the Church does not officially say either way, only that she was Assumed.  Whether the assumption happen right before she would have died or right after has not been defined.  Both options are left up to the person to believe.  Different Saints, theologians, and different traditions within the Church maintain either view.  All that is required is that a Catholic believe she was Assumed into heaven.  The Franciscans even maintain a Tomb of Mary in the Holy Land. There would be no need for a tomb if they didn't believe she died before being assumed. [[User:Marauder40|Marauder40]] ([[User talk:Marauder40|talk]]) 13:13, 2 November 2010 (UTC)
:::::::It could have been the tomb prepared for Mary, that she never was layed in. But Common catholic belief holds she did not die because she was [[Immaculate Conception|Immaculate]], and death would contradict that dogma. --[[User:Willthacheerleader18|Willthacheerleader18]] ([[User talk:Willthacheerleader18|talk]]) 22:22, 2 November 2010 (UTC)
::::::::You are incorrect in your understanding of the doctrine.  Read the documents.  The Church has not explicitly defined if she was assumed before or after a natural death. They specificially left it open either way.  The Immaculate Conception doctrine only says she was kept free of original sin, it doesn't say she wasn't going to die.  You are drawing a parallel and many theologians have drawn that parallel but there have been many theologians on the other side of the spectrum to.  The doctrine of the Assumption only says that she was assumed, it doesn't say before her death and it doesn't say after her death.  It is a valid Catholic belief to believe in either scenario. The following addresses both issues and doesn't state either way when the assumption happened. &quot;5. Now God has willed that the Blessed Virgin Mary should be exempted from this general rule. She, by an entirely unique privilege, completely overcame sin by her Immaculate Conception, and as a result she was not subject to the law of remaining in the corruption of the grave, and she did not have to wait until the end of time for the redemption of her body.&quot; Pope Pius XII[[User:Marauder40|Marauder40]] ([[User talk:Marauder40|talk]]) 14:20, 3 November 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::The thing is, it is common theology that it is natural for man to die, and that it is a a result from sin is because of the fact that in Paradise, this would have been prevented by the Tree of Life. I think it is even a tolerated opinion to the least that man would have even died in Paradise, and the &quot;death caused by sin that God did not want&quot; so many Scripture verses and dogmas speak of is only the death in the sorrowful form it has now. If we look at the dogma, there is no statement whether Mary died or not. But that, on the other hand, doesn't say it is open to personal belief, only that it isn't part of the dogma; and if previous teaching says she died, this previous teaching is not retracted. And the older liturgies may be not formally teaching documents but are so at least to a degree. Ludwig Ott holds it as the more common, though not certain sentence that Mary did die, and explains that her body was submitted to natural death in conformity with her Son's, though she was not punished for sin. --[[Special:Contributions/77.4.59.69|77.4.59.69]] ([[User talk:77.4.59.69|talk]]) 17:31, 8 November 2010 (UTC)
::::::::::A good explanation of the Catholic belief on the Immaculate Conception and Assumption is here [http://www.catholic.com/library/Immaculate_Conception_and_Assum.asp] It says the same thing I did.  The Church officially has only defined that Mary was assumed, whether it happened before or after a natural death is left open and hasn't been officially defined. The provided explanation has both a Nihil Obstat and an Imprimatur. [[User:Marauder40|Marauder40]] ([[User talk:Marauder40|talk]]) 19:26, 8 November 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::::Yes, I know the official dogma has not said anything about whether she really did die. However, as I was saying, MOST (almost ALL) catholics believe that Mary never died. Because we believe death is caused by sin, so therefore Mary (sinless) did not die. I am just stating a common belief, even if the church has never touched on it. -[[User:Willthacheerleader18|Willthacheerleader18]] ([[User talk:Willthacheerleader18|talk]]) 00:30, 9 November 2010 (UTC)
::::::::::::That is what you say. But the majority of the theologians of the 1950s and 1960s said the contrary, at least in the perception of Ludwig Ott, who wouldn't otherwise have stated that &quot;Mary underwent temporal death&quot; is a sententia communior. And I don't know of any substantial change in the matter either. Also, it still is the fact that one time, the Church - not just private believers - prayed: &quot;[we celebrate] this day, when the Holy Mother of God underwent temporal death, but could not be hold by the bonds of death she who bore Thy incarnate Son Our Lord.&quot; But the Church has never prayed, and I wonder whether even private prayers of the kind have been imprimaturised, anything saying &quot;Christ, who spared his Mother from suffering temporal death, but received her into heaven without dying&quot;, or the like.--[[Special:Contributions/77.4.59.69|77.4.59.69]] ([[User talk:77.4.59.69|talk]]) 09:24, 9 November 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::::I think by the way that the internet source cited above by you, @Marauder40, is in a certain point, well, untraditional. That is in saying &quot;the doctrine of the Assumption says that at [...] Mary was assumed, body and soul, into heaven, just as ''Enoch, Elijah,'' and perhaps others had been before her.&quot; First, I think the common opinion, though no dogma of course, of the Church fathers was that Enoch and Elijah were not assumed into the same heaven Christ ascended to and Mary was assumed to, but to another place in the presence of God (&quot;None have ascended into heaven&quot;, says Christ at a time quite after them), and are still to die being the two witnesses mentioned in the Revelation. --[[Special:Contributions/77.4.59.69|77.4.59.69]] ([[User talk:77.4.59.69|talk]]) 09:43, 9 November 2010 (UTC)
::::::::::::As to your statement about Enoch and Elijah, I will even give you a link that isn't a Catholic link to explain that one. [http://www.lookinguntojesus.net/ata20020915.htm] What is important here is what was and wasn't defined by the doctrine.  We can discuss this all we want but as of yet I do not see any proposals for changing the article.  Remember, this is not a forum.  If you want to discuss this feel free to go to one of the numerous religious forums out there.[[User:Marauder40|Marauder40]] ([[User talk:Marauder40|talk]]) 14:18, 9 November 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::::::Sorry for the misuse of the talk page. However, I don't want, if I may frankly say so, to explain Our Lord's words &quot;from context&quot; unless absolutely necessary. And I remember that St. Thomas Aq. wrote in discussing the transfiguration, quoting Jerome first: &quot;He (Christ) gives a sign from heaven, Elias coming down thence, whither he had ascended.&quot; [...] And St. Thomas adds: &quot;Elias appeared in his own body, not that he was brought down from the empyrean heaven, but from ''some place on high'' whither he was taken up in the fiery chariot.&quot;--[[Special:Contributions/77.4.91.211|77.4.91.211]] ([[User talk:77.4.91.211|talk]]) 19:56, 10 November 2010 (UTC)
::::::::::::::Look, Thomas Aquinas also opposed Immaculate Conception, but later by the 16th century that became open question, then after a few centuries a dogma after [[sensus fidelium]] built up. As Willthacheerleader18 said there is some sensus fidelium now, but I think it is anyone's guess as to how much. And as Marauder said, the Church has left the issue open. My suggestion: let the 4 of us get together on this talk page in exactly 250 years from today and discuss it again. Do we have a date? [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 20:48, 10 November 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::::::::Sounds good to me ;) By the way IP user, if you would like a good forum to discuss Catholic things with Catholics (and some non-Catholics) I suggest [http://forums.catholic.com] it is run by [[Catholic Answers]].  We can even continue this discussion over there. [[User:Marauder40|Marauder40]] ([[User talk:Marauder40|talk]]) 21:02, 10 November 2010 (UTC)
::::::::::::::::Hahaha sounds like a plan to me. --[[User:Willthacheerleader18|Willthacheerleader18]] ([[User talk:Willthacheerleader18|talk]]) 22:17, 10 November 2010 (UTC)
::::::::::::::::Ok, then let us each take an extra multi-vatimin every day, to make the date. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 22:20, 10 November 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::::::::::Just so much, Thomas Aquinas said Mary was sanctified after animated and this is, speaking of the terms, as a matter of fact the case. What was evolved later, and different from the previous teaching of a &quot;sanctification of her unanimated flesh&quot; that ran under the title of Imm. Conc., is the simple fact that the &quot;epsilon&quot;, in language of analysis, of time in between could actually be = 0. --[[Special:Contributions/77.4.91.211|77.4.91.211]] ([[User talk:77.4.91.211|talk]]) 23:45, 10 November 2010 (UTC)

== Episcopal's church view on Mary ==

There possble could be error in this section, because they episcopal/anglican churches agree with sinlessness of Mary, and with her body and soul being taken into heaven. This is half right and needs to be better researched. They said there is some bibical view within it, but did not say all anglican would agree with it. So this is wrong and please let thrid person view on this topic. I would be wrong, but I think right after reading it.(~~)

Question: In the Episcopal Church, August 15 is observed as the commemoration &quot;Of the Blessed Virgin Mary&quot;, and the recent Anglican-Roman Catholic agreed statement on the Virgin Mary assigns a place for both the Dormition and the Assumption in Anglican devotion.

Is there any truth to this ? I have the book on this and  I got idal Mary will be view more, but the Immaculate Conception and Assumption are still in limbo for the episcoplian/anglican. Would you agree with my statement or this other person who did on wikipedia? I agree with you.

I'm sure there are a few Anglican congregations celebrating these feasts, but they are not in our official calendar.
Faithfully,
Clay Morris
The Rev. Dr. Clayton L. Morris
Office for Liturgy and Music[[User:Irishmonk|Irishmonk]] 21:54, 8 June 2007 (UTC)

I am an Anglican and BOTH holidays are celebrated at my church with the utmost seriousness.  After Christological holidays they are the highest ones on the calendar - not mere saint days, something VERY special.  I don't know that this is the norm in the communion, but I am sure we are not the only ones who behave in this manner.  I will look at the artical and add what I can.-
[[User:Secisek|SECisek]] 19:50, 1 July 2007 (UTC)

:The days are a greater festivle in High-Church and Anglo-Catholic Parishes, a lesser festivle in the Broad-Church Parishes, and some Low-Church parishes celebrate it while others do not. --[[User:Willthacheerleader18|Willthacheerleader18]] ([[User talk:Willthacheerleader18|talk]]) 23:37, 14 August 2010 (UTC)

== dogma and controversy ==

The Church repeatedly uses dogmatic declarations to settle spirtitual and loving controversies; these help us to think of Mary: Nicene Creed (Arian controversy), Council of Trent (Protestant controversy), etc. Was there a controversy about Mary's assumption that the Pope settled? The text is really vague: &quot;Theological debate about the assumption continued until 1950 when it was defined as definitive doctrine.&quot; Was there particular controversy before 1950 that motivated the promulgation of doctrine? [[User:Jonathan Tweet|Jonathan Tweet]] 15:24, 1 July 2007 (UTC)

==Declaration==
For some reason, Pius's Declaration is given in full twice at the moment; this is, obviously, unnecessary and interrupts the flow of the article.  Unless there is some reason currently hidden for this duplication, I will remove it.  If I am mistaken, feel free to revert me. Cheers, '''[[User:LindsayH|Lindsay]]''' 06:46, 19 February 2008 (UTC)

== Wrong Painting!!! ==
[[Image:La Inmaculada de Soult, 1678, Bartolomé E. Murillo.jpg|thumb|100px]]
I'm surprised no one has fixed this, but the painting by Murillo shown is actually a depiciton of the Immaculate Conception (in the Escorial Palace outside of Madrid) and NOT the Assumption. Generally, in post-Mediæval art, when Mary's hands are crossed on her bosom it is a depiction of the Immaculate Conception; when her arm is extended out or her hands are folded in prayer it is the Assumption. [[User:MiguelJoseErnst|Miguel]] ([[User talk:MiguelJoseErnst|talk]]) 18:39, 16 August 2008 (UTC)

[[Image:Juan Antonio de Frías y Escalante. Inmaculada Concepción.jpg|thumb|left|100px]]
:Do you have a reference for that art statement please Miguel? I would be interested, for I will add it to the art page, if valid. Thanks. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 03:35, 17 August 2008 (UTC)

:On the other hand, she's standing on the crescent moon, and I thought ''that'' was always a sign of the Assumption. —[[User:Angr|'''An''']][[User talk:Angr|''gr'']] 18:55, 16 August 2008 (UTC)

Please tell me why after all the sex abuse cases, the paintings of naked babies everywhere is not politically incorrect?  Can't angels be adults?  What it the facination with this in the eyes of Catholics?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/75.45.177.233|75.45.177.233]] ([[User talk:75.45.177.233|talk]]) 02:54, 18 August 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Please ask [[User:Johnbod]], for he would know best. Also see [[Roman Catholic Marian art]]. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 21:23, 16 August 2008 (UTC)

Miguel is probably right that it is the wrong painting. Please see image above on the right which is the same painting with the Immaculate title. I will use another image now. However, the image above on the left, suggests that the artistic assumption (pun intended) about hands being open or closed is not universally correct. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 06:04, 17 August 2008 (UTC)

:Yes, the one above right here is an IC - see [[Roman_Catholic_Marian_art#Depiction_of_the_Immaculate_Conception]]. The position of the hands is typically as Miguel said, but (as in the one on the left) capable of variations. The crescent moon is usually an attribute of the IC. As the Commons category shows, the Assumption usually includes other figures, either above in heaven or below on earth, or at the least angels. [[User:Johnbod|Johnbod]] ([[User talk:Johnbod|talk]]) 14:58, 17 August 2008 (UTC)
:: There are over twenty Immaculata  paintings by Murillo, starting around 1640. After 1652, he created a number of Immaculatas, in which Mary wears a huge flowing cape as in the picture on the left. This is to symbolize her assumption. I don't think he ever painted an Assunta on her own or with that name. There are a number of Murillo Immaculata exemplars in US museums (Fort Worth, Kimbell Art; Kansas City William Rockhill; Detroit, Institute of Arts;Baltimore, Walters Art)--[[User:Ambrosius007|Ambrosius007]] ([[User talk:Ambrosius007|talk]]) 17:11, 17 August 2008 (UTC)

== Fact tag requested ==
Hi. I'm just wondering about this line I found in the first section of this article, &quot;According to Catholic theology, Mary is the pledge of the fulfillment of Christ's promise.&quot; Can we get a CITATION NEEDED stamp on that sentence?  [[User:rtadopaw, Andrew B]] 10:39a PDT, 12 March, 2009  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Rtadopaw|Rtadopaw]] ([[User talk:Rtadopaw|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Rtadopaw|contribs]]) 17:40, 12 March 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Hi, welcome to Wikipedia. When you see a claim that needs sourcing, you can type &lt;tt&gt;&amp;#123;{subst:dated|fact}&amp;#125;&lt;/tt&gt; next to it. —[[User:Angr|'''An''']][[User talk:Angr|''gr'']] 22:18, 12 March 2009 (UTC)

:It's taken from JP2's homily. I've moved the reference to the appropriate place. [[User:Carl.bunderson|carl bunderson]] [[User talk:Carl.bunderson|(talk)]] [[Special:Contributions/Carl.bunderson|(contributions)]] 17:26, 14 August 2009 (UTC)

== Changes to lead etc. ==

I have made a few changes, including the first sentence of the lead. WP policy states that the lead should start with a sentence including the title name and explaining the notability of the subject. I have added this. It also stresses the fact that this is an ecumenical article on the subject and not only about the Catholic viewpoint. 
I also added a more comprehensive list of countries celebrating August 15th with a public holiday. [[user:Xandar|'''''&lt;font color=&quot;003366&quot;&gt;Xan&lt;/font&gt;''''']][[User talk:Xandar#top|'''''&lt;font color=&quot;00A86B&quot;&gt;dar&lt;/font&gt;''''']] 23:12, 27 March 2009 (UTC)

== Top-importance Christianity articles ==
I am removing the Christianity &quot;importance=top&quot; rating.

See [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Christianity/Core topics work group/Topic list]] for the list of Top-importance Christianity articles. As of 1 April 2009, there are just 80 articles on the list. If you would like to remove one or add one, start a discussion on the talk page first (the list is designed to be smaller than 100 articles). &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Carlaude|{{#if:|&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:Carl;color:red;&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;|&lt;span style=&quot;color:red;&quot;&gt;Carl&lt;/span&gt;}}{{#if:|&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:aude:;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;aude:&lt;/span&gt;}}]][[User talk:Carlaude|{{#if:|&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:Talk;color:purple;&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;|&lt;span style=&quot;color:purple;&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/span&gt;}}]]&lt;/sup&gt; 19:29, 29 August 2009 (UTC)


== Ascension? ==
This article contains the text &quot;The first Church author to speak of the bodily ascension of Mary ...&quot; The use of the word &quot;ascension&quot; is at odds with other Christian ideology, in which the only entity to have gone bodily to Heaven under the entity's own power (&quot;ascending&quot; is the English word chosen to refer to that) is Christ. All other entities who went bodily to Heaven did so not by their own propulsive power but, rather, by Heaven's attractive-power, and the English term chosen to refer to that is &quot;being assumed&quot;, not &quot;ascending&quot;. However, the correction to &quot;assumption&quot; may not be the correct remedy. The text is a quotation from Ludwig Ott. If these are Ott's exact words then a &quot;[sic]&quot; should be added after the word &quot;ascension&quot;. If Ott's words are in German then please check and see if a translator, not Ott, made the ascension/assumption mistake. [[Special:Contributions/69.86.126.190|69.86.126.190]] ([[User talk:69.86.126.190|talk]]) 00:20, 14 April 2010 (UTC) Christopher L. Simpson
:I don't have &quot;the Ott&quot; at hand but I can't remember from reading that he used Latin there, which would be unmotivated. In German both Assumption and Ascension are in popular language Himmelfahrt, though officially the term Aufnahme in den Himmel has been stressed theologically. It might even be that Ott wrote Aufnahme himself; I'm quite certain he didn't write &quot;ascensio&quot;. --[[Special:Contributions/84.154.99.240|84.154.99.240]] ([[User talk:84.154.99.240|talk]]) 12:30, 24 July 2010 (UTC)

::I think you made a good edit. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 12:43, 24 July 2010 (UTC)
:::Concur with rationale and edit. ----[[User:Morenooso|moreno oso]] ([[User talk:Morenooso#top|talk]]) 16:43, 24 July 2010 (UTC)

==Catholics not in communion with Rome==
Do [[Old Catholics]], [[Independent Catholic Churches|Independent Catholics]], [[Liberal Catholic Church|Liberal Catholics]], the [[Anglo-Lutheran Catholic Church]], the [[Polish National Catholic Church]], the [[African Orthodox Church]], the [[Apostolic Catholic Church]], [[Lusitanian Orthodox Church]], [[Philippine Independent Church]], and any other Catholic Churches not in communion with the Roman Catholic Church celebrate the Assumption of Mary? I know that Old Catholics deny Papal Infallibility, but do they also deny the Assumption, or just that it is dogma? I think if any of these churches celebrate the holiday it would be important to include in the article. --[[User:Willthacheerleader18|Willthacheerleader18]] ([[User talk:Willthacheerleader18|talk]]) 23:41, 14 August 2010 (UTC)

:I do not know, but the answers may be here: ''The Ancient Traditions of the Virgin Mary's Dormition and Assumption by Stephen J. Shoemaker 2006 ISBN 0199210748'' if you want to look. Yet those groups are so small in number that I do not see this as a key to teh article's quality. Cheers. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 11:49, 15 August 2010 (UTC)

== citation #12 broken? ==

The link referenced by citation #12 is returning error 404 page not found. It links to &quot;http://www.christiantruth.com/assumption.html&quot; It appears the correct web address may be &quot;http://www.christiantruth.com/articles/assumption.html&quot;?
[[Special:Contributions/72.76.134.165|72.76.134.165]] ([[User talk:72.76.134.165|talk]]) 23:10, 29 May 2012 (UTC)

:It does not matter if it is broken. That is not a [[WP:RS]] website and should not even be used. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 23:22, 29 May 2012 (UTC)

== Lutheranism ==
Although Lutherans do not, at least officially, recognize the Assumption, they do celebrate &quot;Mary, Mother of Our Lord&quot; on August 15th.. the same day Catholics celebrate the Assumption. Should this be added to the article? -- [[User:Willthacheerleader18|Willthacheerleader18]] ([[User talk:Willthacheerleader18|talk]]) 03:05, 30 May 2012 (UTC)

:If they do not recognize it, it is a date coincidence of some type. So I would not suggest it. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 03:46, 30 May 2012 (UTC)

== Article name ==

Names of established articles can only be changed with prior discussion - not at the whim of an editor who prefers another name. I have therefore reverted the recent name change. I cannot at present see any justification for the change based on &quot;full title&quot;. [[User:Anglicanus|Anglicanus]] ([[User talk:Anglicanus|talk]]) 18:39, 21 June 2012 (UTC)

:FYI HeartyBowl1989 is most probably a [[User:LoveforMary]] sock puppet. See his talk page. And your revert was correct. Blessed is by and large a Catholic title. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 13:13, 22 June 2012 (UTC)
::Agreed. [[User:Johnbod|Johnbod]] ([[User talk:Johnbod|talk]]) 13:37, 22 June 2012 (UTC)

== Merge from Ferragosto ==
&lt;div class=&quot;boilerplate metadata discussion-archived&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #f5f3ef; margin: 2em 0 0 0; padding: 0 10px 0 10px; border: 1px solid #AAAAAA;&quot;&gt;
:''The following discussion has concluded. &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify this section.'''&lt;/span&gt; Result of discussion: '''No merge.'''
Please see [[Talk:Ferragosto#Merge to Assumption of Mary discussion]] ([[Ferragosto]] is actually another name of the same holiday in Italian). --[[User:Uno nessuno e 100000|Uno nessuno e 100000]] ([[User talk:Uno nessuno e 100000|talk]]) 07:01, 15 August 2012 (UTC)

:It makes zero sense to merge. This article is not about the &quot;feast of the assumption&quot; but the theology/devotion and a religious feast as a secondary part. It takes place in the whole world, not just Italy. The Italian holiday has zero religious connection. No point in merging. 

:The fact that they happen on the same day is irrelevant, unless you are viewing the world through Italian lenses. The same day is also Independence Day in the Congo (1960) and [[Independence Day (India)]] (1947) and  Liberation Day in South Korea ([[Gwangbokjeol]]) - all big feasts. Do you want to merge them all too because they are on August 15? Try suggesting a merge with [[Gwangbokjeol]] - would be less funny... [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 07:34, 15 August 2012 (UTC)
{{div col end}}

== Mary's holy death ==

Why does the article state &quot;While Catholic dogma leaves open the question of Mary's death before rising to Heaven&quot;? It is doctrine that Mary died, it is not open for theological debate. From the Dogma of the Assumption of Mary:

:Now God has willed that the Blessed Virgin Mary should be exempted from this general rule. She, by an entirely unique privilege, completely overcame sin by her Immaculate Conception, and as a result she was not subject to the law of remaining in the corruption of the grave, and she did not have to wait until the end of time for the redemption of her body.

:Christ's faithful, through the teaching and the leadership of their pastors, have learned from the sacred books that the Virgin Mary, throughout the course of her earthly pilgrimage, led a life troubled by cares, hardships, and sorrows, and that, moreover, what the holy old man Simeon had foretold actually came to pass, that is, that a terribly sharp sword pierced her heart as she stood under the cross of her divine Son, our Redeemer. In the same way, it was not difficult for them to admit that the great Mother of God, like her only begotten Son, had actually passed from this life. But this in no way prevented them from believing and from professing openly that her sacred body had never been subject to the corruption of the tomb, and that the august tabernacle of the Divine Word had never been reduced to dust and ashes. 

:In the liturgical books which deal with the feast either of the dormition or of the Assumption of the Blessed Virgin there are expressions that agree in testifying that, when the Virgin Mother of God passed from this earthly exile to heaven, what happened to her sacred body was, by the decree of divine Providence, in keeping with the dignity of the Mother of the Word Incarnate, and with the other privileges she had been accorded. 

:&quot;Venerable to us, O Lord, is the festivity of this day on which the holy Mother of God suffered temporal death, but still could not be kept down by the bonds of death, who has begotten your Son our Lord incarnate from herself.

:&quot;...As he kept you a virgin in childbirth, thus he has kept your body incorrupt in the tomb and has glorified it by his divine act of transferring it from the tomb.&quot;

:So it was that the Feast of the Assumption was elevated from the rank which it had occupied from the beginning among the other Marian feasts to be classed among the more solemn celebrations of the entire liturgical cycle. And, when our predecessor St. Sergius I prescribed what is known as the litany, or the stational procession, to be held on four Marian feasts, he specified together the Feasts of the Nativity, the Annunciation, the Purification, and the Dormition of the Virgin Mary.

:They offered more profound explanations of its meaning and nature, bringing out into sharper light the fact that this feast shows, not only that the dead body of the Blessed Virgin Mary remained incorrupt, but that she gained a triumph out of death, her heavenly glorification after the example of her only begotten Son, Jesus Christ-truths that the liturgical books had frequently touched upon concisely and briefly.

:Thus St. John Damascene, an outstanding herald of this traditional truth, spoke out with powerful eloquence when he compared the bodily Assumption of the loving Mother of God with her other prerogatives and privileges. &quot;It was fitting that she, who had kept her virginity intact in childbirth, should keep her own body free from all corruption even after death...&quot;

:...and have looked upon the Ark of the Covenant, built of incorruptible wood and placed in the Lord's temple, as a type of the most pure body of the Virgin Mary, preserved and exempt from all the corruption of the tomb and raised up to such glory in heaven.

:Thus, during the earliest period of scholastic theology, that most pious man, Amadeus, Bishop of Lausarme, held that the Virgin Mary's flesh had remained incorrupt-for it is wrong to believe that her body has seen corruption-because it was really united again to her soul and, together with it, crowned with great glory in the heavenly courts.

:...St. Robert Bellarmine exclaimed: &quot;And who, I ask, could believe that the ark of holiness, the dwelling place of the Word of God, the temple of the Holy Spirit, could be reduced to ruin? My soul is filled with horror at the thought that this virginal flesh which had begotten God, had brought him into the world, had nourished and carried him, could have been turned into ashes or given over to be food for worms.&quot;

:&quot;What son would not bring his mother back to life and would not bring her into paradise after her death if he could?&quot;...&quot;Jesus did not wish to have the body of Mary corrupted after death, since it would have redounded to his own dishonor to have her virginal flesh, from which he himself had assumed flesh, reduced to dust.&quot;

:...that she should be preserved free from the corruption of the tomb and that, like her own Son, having overcome death, she might be taken up body and soul to the glory of heaven...

It is superficial to claim that the dormition or Assumption are separate doctrines or separate feasts, even if Catholics and Orthodox have different understandings of them. They are the same event and same holy day. If you want to treat them differently, than make one article for Catholics and one for Orthodox about the Assumption. [[User:Oct13|Oct13]] ([[User talk:Oct13|talk]]) 23:05, 5 October 2012 (UTC)

:Actually they are separate feasts and the theology is different among different denominations. So I think the presentation and structure is correct as is. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 06:25, 6 October 2012 (UTC)

{{od}}
Aaaaaaaaagh, I saw you edit again. One of these days you need to read up on theology my friend. See:

:* Dogmatics I: The Christian Doctrine of God - Page 105
:* Encyclopedia of American Religion and Politics - Page 141

The only formal dogma in the East Orthdox Church goes back to the Nicene period. So your edit is just confused, mixing Catholic dogma with EO ideas... sigh... [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 16:07, 6 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>g1d95ij5ul6yktdn64j0wu3w9aehswz</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
