<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Altar server</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>4315683</id>
    <revision>
      <id>479886865</id>
      <parentid>479247354</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-03-02T22:15:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Turris Davidica</username>
        <id>7555679</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9888">{{ChristianityWikiProject|importance=Low|class=B|anglicanism=yes|anglicanism-importance=Low|catholicism=yes|catholicism-importance=Low|eastern-orthodoxy=yes|eastern-orthodoxy-importance=Low}}

==Eastern Orthodox==
When adding this section I realized that I may have introduced a problem in [[Acolyte]].  I claimed there that Orthodoxy no longer had a separate office of &quot;taper-bearer&quot; based on the service books available to me, but these all reflect the Slavic tradition.  I knew that Greek altar boys were ordained to ''something'', but as I wrote this it occurred to me that I didn't know exactly what.  I said [[Reader (minor orders)]] here in the event, but it may be that the Greeks still have a distinctive &quot;taper-bearer&quot; and that's what their altar boys are ordained as.  I would appreciate it if someone who knows for sure would fix this. ''[[User:Csernica|TCC]]'' &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Csernica|(talk)]] [[Special:Contributions/Csernica|(contribs)]]&lt;/small&gt; (old comment)

==List of famous altar boys==

I think it'd be interesting if we had a list of famous (former) altar boys.

== comment at the beginning of RC altar boy ==

As a former altar server as well, I can tell you for a fact that there was formal training involved. After your training, you received your cassock and surplus from the parish priest. --[[Special:Contributions/209.244.30.235|209.244.30.235]] ([[User talk:209.244.30.235|talk]]) 18:59, 20 April 2008 (UTC) 

== comment at the end of RC altar boy ==

'Many altar servers see themselves usually not as priesthood candidates, even if the church sometimes tries to influence them in this direction.'

This i think, is not 'entirely' true.. All the altar boys in my parish (including myself) and lots in most other parishes ive served at etc all feel they have a vocation to the sacred Priesthood, which is the only reason we are serving! :). I dont know for sure, but im thinking this is a genreal sweeping statement, feel free to discuss though.

:The &quot;gold standard&quot; for Wikipedia entries is verifiability. This article is sadly unreferenced overall, mainly becuase it's not a topic much written on. Editors are therefore writing from their personal experience. In this case that's mainly reliable as far as what being an altar server entails, but when it comes to subtopics that really should be statistically based, personal experience is a hazardous guide. If a study or two could be cited, giving the proportion of priests who were altar boys, or the proportion of altar boys who became priests, that would be much more reliable. ''[[User:Csernica|TCC]]'' &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Csernica|(talk)]] [[Special:Contributions/Csernica|(contribs)]]&lt;/small&gt; 22:51, 8 June 2006 (UTC)

== 'Other churches' ==

Ive corrected/added to the point made at the bottom of the article on other churches. Mostly based on my own past experiance and understanding with Anglo-Catholic churches. Feel free to correct if needed.

== Rape ==

Why is there no talk of the rape of altar boys in this article?
:Win  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.2.230.166|76.2.230.166]] ([[User talk:76.2.230.166|talk]]) 15:36, 11 June 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Is there a point to your bigotry?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/173.73.13.157|173.73.13.157]] ([[User talk:173.73.13.157|talk]]) 00:04, 15 June 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Replace Missal with Sacramentary ==

I believe that since the 1960's, the missal has been phased out and replaced with the Sacramentary that contains all the prayers related to the mass. Would it be correct to change references to the missal in this article to the Sacramentary? [[User:Benrr101|Benrr101]] ([[User talk:Benrr101|talk]]) 23:52, 2 January 2008 (UTC)

== Altar server vs altar boy ==

The article's assertion that altar server has &quot;almost completely replaced&quot; altar boy may well be true within the church itself, but it certainly is not so in general/colloquial use. &quot;Altar boy&quot; is, at least here in the UK, ''far'' more common (unless, of course, the person in question is not a boy). See, for example, [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/london/7395323.stm this BBC article], which uses &quot;altar boy&quot; while mentioning the past of a murder victim. [[Special:Contributions/86.132.140.207|86.132.140.207]] ([[User talk:86.132.140.207|talk]]) 01:54, 12 May 2008 (UTC)

== Female altar servers ==

The material on female altar servers is well sourced, so I have restored it again.  Please discuss any problems with it here rather than continuing to remove it.  Thanks!  -- [[User:Cat Whisperer|Cat Whisperer]] ([[User talk:Cat Whisperer|talk]]) 23:34, 21 July 2008 (UTC)

== Altar boy ==

&quot;Alter boy&quot; is not the usual term anymore, incorrectly stated in the article. Alter server is much more popular, as is female altar servers.[[User:Mazeau|Mazeau]] ([[User talk:Mazeau|talk]]) 21:12, 26 August 2008 (UTC)

The appropriate term is &quot;altar boy,&quot; and girls serving as altar boys are called &quot;female altar boys.&quot;[[Special:Contributions/75.27.148.62|75.27.148.62]] ([[User talk:75.27.148.62|talk]]) 20:51, 24 February 2012 (UTC)
:Hey, there are new things under the sun: female boys. -- [[User:Turris Davidica|Turris Davidica]] ([[User talk:Turris Davidica|talk]]) 23:12, 24 February 2012 (UTC)
::No, they are girls doing the duties of boys as if they were also boys.[[Special:Contributions/75.27.148.62|75.27.148.62]] ([[User talk:75.27.148.62|talk]]) 05:29, 26 February 2012 (UTC)
:::No Sir, this is why we call it altar server. --[[User:Turris Davidica|Turris Davidica]] ([[User talk:Turris Davidica|talk]]) 20:23, 26 February 2012 (UTC)
::::Your opinion does not change the fact that girls are serving as altar boys, hence the term &quot;female altar boys.&quot;[[Special:Contributions/75.27.148.62|75.27.148.62]] ([[User talk:75.27.148.62|talk]]) 04:34, 28 February 2012 (UTC)
:::::They are serving as altar servers (what abount adult men? Boys too?). There is no such term as female altar boy. But there's no point in discussing this here, since &quot;female boy&quot; is unsourced. --[[User:Turris Davidica|Turris Davidica]] ([[User talk:Turris Davidica|talk]]) 22:15, 2 March 2012 (UTC)

== Merge with [[Acolyte]] ==

These two articles discuss the same subject; they should be merged. [[User:Neelix|Neelix]] ([[User talk:Neelix|talk]]) 02:29, 22 January 2009 (UTC)

No, an altar server is different from an acolyte even if their duties largely overlap.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/81.243.57.98|81.243.57.98]] ([[User talk:81.243.57.98|talk]]) 18:00, 13 April 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

I think, me being a former [[Lutheranism|Lutheran]], now [[Roman Catholic Church|Roman Catholic]], that they are two completely different people, with different duties. [[User:Shark96z|Shark96z]] ([[User talk:Shark96z|talk]]) 04:07, 10 June 2009 (UTC)

==Gay altar servers==
I noticed that there was a controversy surrounding the existence of gay altar servers, notably about one such altar server in the Canadian province of Ontario, who announced he was launching a human rights complaint against the Church for having been dismissed while he was living with his male partner. The issue of gay altar servers is not really the same as gay altar boys, given that the former are adults, while the latter were often involved in clerical child abuse cases. [http://www.xtra.ca/public/Toronto/Catholic_Church_dismisses_gay_altar_servers-7259.aspx] [[User:ADM|ADM]] ([[User talk:ADM|talk]]) 15:09, 12 August 2009 (UTC)

==Merge==
please merge this article with [[acolyte]] --[[User:Camilo Sanchez|Camilo Sanchez]] ([[User talk:Camilo Sanchez|talk]]) 02:09, 25 October 2009 (UTC)

==Do not merge==
The lay ministry of altar server, usually filled by young laypersons (usually now both boys and girls), is not the same- not as expansive a role- in the Catholic churches as the former minor order of Acolyte. An instituted acolyte is (especially since Pope Benedict XVI's instruction limiting the role of Acolyte to the following cases) usually a seminarian in graduate theology school or a permanent deacon in formational training who has not yet been ordained a deacon (or who may have been allowed to retain the role when he left beforehand).  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/98.223.133.1|98.223.133.1]] ([[User talk:98.223.133.1|talk]]) 02:41, 15 September 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:You are right in stating the expressions should not be confused. Just let me add that of course the acolyte, although instituted, is also a lay minister.--[[User:Turris Davidica|Turris Davidica]] ([[User talk:Turris Davidica|talk]]) 17:48, 18 September 2011 (UTC)

== Altar '''boys''' since when? ==

Is it true that the tradition to have &quot;normal&quot; boys (rather than adult men or seminarists) as altar servers dates from the pontificate of [[Pope Pius X]], i.e. after 1900? Generally there is too little on the history of altar servers in this article! -- [[Special:Contributions/77.7.142.251|77.7.142.251]] ([[User talk:77.7.142.251|talk]]) 09:49, 1 November 2011 (UTC)

== Traditional Catholics ==

There should be some mention of girls being disallowed service at the altar in [[Traditional Catholicism|Traditional Catholic]] parishes, as well as by [[Sedevacantism|Sedevacantists]].[[Special:Contributions/75.27.148.62|75.27.148.62]] ([[User talk:75.27.148.62|talk]]) 20:51, 24 February 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>3cfe5bpgmq8kxdy1muz0kla3cbmj8nd</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
