<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Sanskrit</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>27705</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521604464</id>
      <parentid>521604267</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T01:57:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>99.226.203.145</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14712">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=FAC
|action1date=15:50, 10 Jan 2005
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Sanskrit language
|action1result=not promoted
|action1oldid=9260163

|action2=PR
|action2date=13:05, 14 September 2006
|action2link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Sanskrit/archive1
|action2result=reviewed
|action2oldid=75563079

|action3=GAN
|action3date=23:44, 17 April 2007
|action3result=listed
|action3oldid=123195813

|action4=GAR
|action4date=13:40, 8 June 2007
|action4result=delisted
|action4oldid=136810149

|currentstatus=FFAC
}}
{{calm talk}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1={{WP India|class=B|importance=High}}
{{LanguageTalk|class=B|importance=Top}}}}
&lt;!--Template:Archivebox begins--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;infobox&quot; style=&quot;width: 315px&quot;&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;[[Image:Vista-file-manager.png|50px|Archive]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[Wikipedia:How to archive a talk page|'''Archives''']]
&lt;/div&gt;
----
# [[Talk:Sanskrit/Archive 1|July 2001 – September 2005]]
# [[Talk:Sanskrit/Archive 2|October 2005 – October 2006]]
# [[Talk:Sanskrit/Archive 3|February 2007 – April 2008]]
# [[Talk:Sanskrit/Archive 4|April 2008 – November 2008]]
# [[Talk:Sanskrit/Archive 5|November 2008 – ??]]
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!--Template:Archivebox ends--&gt;

{{User:MiszaBot/config
|maxarchivesize = 80K
|counter = 6
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Sanskrit/Archive %(counter)d
}}

{{WikiProject Pakistan}}
{{WikiProject Bangladesh}}
{{WikiProject Nepal}}
== नामविश्व भाषांतरण ==

:Dear Friends,
:undersigned wants to put following request at  https://bugzilla.wikimedia.org/   to programmers of MediaWiki software to make apropriate changes in Sanskrit Language Wikipedia.Undersigned requests openions or support from those who know Sanskrit Language.Please do reply at your earliest or post your comment directly at [http://sa.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Wikipedia:%E0%A4%B5%E0%A4%BF%E0%A4%95%E0%A4%BF%E0%A4%AA%E0%A5%80%E0%A4%A1%E0%A4%BF%E0%A4%AF%E0%A4%BE:%E0%A4%97%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%B0%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%AE%E0%A4%B8%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%AF_%E0%A4%9A%E0%A5%8C%E0%A4%AA%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%B2%E0%A4%AE%E0%A5%8D&amp;action=edit&amp;section=4 संस्कृत विकिपीडिया:ग्रामस्य चौपालम्]

:[[योजकः:Mahitgar|Mahitgar]] १५:०३, १ पौषमाघे २००९ (UTC)


:Dear Wikimedia Programmers, The first paragraph is self-contradictory how can Sanskrit be both Historical language and an official language of a state. Only one of the facts can be correct

:Since undersigned wants to create new articles in Sanskrit Language  Wikipedia specialy in &quot;Wikipedia&quot; and &quot;Help&quot; Namespace;Correction in Namespace Names will help me and Sanskrit Language Wikipedia a Long way. We kindly request following localisation of Sanskrit Language Wikipedia at https://bugzilla.wikimedia.org/  

*Namespace Current English Name 'Wikipedia' change the same to Sanskrit विकिपीडिया
**Namespace Current semi-English Name 'Wikipediaसंभाषणं' change the same to Sanskrit  विकिपीडिया संभाषणं

*Namespace Current English Name 'MediaWiki' change the same to Sanskrit मिडियाविकि
**Namespace Current English Name 'MediaWiki talk' change the same to Sanskrit मिडियाविकि संभाषणं

*Namespace Current English Name 'Template' change the same to Sanskrit बिंबधर
**Namespace Current English Name 'Template talk' change the same to Sanskrit बिंबधर संभाषणं

*Namespace Current Sanskrit Name 'उपकार:'(stands for 'Help') change the same to Sanskrit  साहाय्य
**Namespace Current Sanskrit Name 'उपकारसंभाषणं' (stands for 'Help talk') change the same to Sanskrit  साहाय्य संभाषणं

:Notes:
:1)बिंबधर is a newly created applied term for Template.बिंब means an image that can transclude,and since a wikipedia template holds and helps transclude an image term created in sanskrit is बिंबधर

:2)Help  Namespace  'उपकार:' is being requested  to be changed since  'उपकार:' means 'favour' where as right word for 'Help' in Sanskrit is available and is साहाय्य so this namespace change is being requested.  

:Please do reply at your earliest or post your comment directly at [http://sa.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Wikipedia:%E0%A4%B5%E0%A4%BF%E0%A4%95%E0%A4%BF%E0%A4%AA%E0%A5%80%E0%A4%A1%E0%A4%BF%E0%A4%AF%E0%A4%BE:%E0%A4%97%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%B0%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%AE%E0%A4%B8%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%AF_%E0%A4%9A%E0%A5%8C%E0%A4%AA%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%B2%E0%A4%AE%E0%A5%8D&amp;action=edit&amp;section=4 संस्कृत विकिपीडिया:ग्रामस्य चौपालम्]
 

:[[योजकः:Mahitgar|Mahitgar]] १५:०३, १ पौषमाघे २००९ (UTC)  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Mahitgar|Mahitgar]] ([[User talk:Mahitgar|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Mahitgar|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Why are these headings all in Devangari?

== Sanskrit विकिपीडिया:लोगो,लेखन चर्चा ==

:A Request from [[:sa:|sanskrit language wikipedia]] was made at [[https://bugzilla.wikimedia.org/show_bug.cgi?id=16857 bugzill bug no.16857]]  bugzill has requested that,'''The image should be no bigger than 135 x 155 pixels, please fix it and reopen this bug.''' undersigned does not have requisite skills needed for the same please some one do help by providing needful change to bugzill

Thanks and regards

[[:sa:योजकः:Mahitgar|Mahitgar]] ०७:५८, ८ फेब्रुवारी २००९ (UTC) 
(Copyright image from Marathi Language wikipedia is being taken for using as matches with gramatically correct Sanskrit language wording and writing system.Image was posted by user user:कौस्तुभ on Marathi Language Wikipedia &amp; commons as authorised logo for Marathi Language Wikipedia and '''the same is proposed tobe used on Sanskrit Language Wikipedia''' )

[[:sa:चित्रं:Wiki.png]]

Image is updated 
*at Sanskrit Wikipedia [[:sa:चित्रं:Wiki.png]]
*at [[:commons:File:Wikipedia-logo-sa.png]]
* at [[:meta:Wikipedia_in_other_languages]]

समर्थन करोति
[[:sa:योजकः:Mahitgar|Mahitgar]] ०९:२०, १ पौषमाघे २००९ (UTC)

Though I am not a great expert on Sanskrit, I do agree that second change to use &quot;Sahay&quot; instead of &quot;upkar&quot; makes sense. This is from my understanding of other indian languages , especially Hindi.


: [[:mr:चित्र:wiki1.png]] [[:mr:चित्र:wiki3.png]] [[:mr:चित्र:myWiki4.png]] - suggessions received so far [[:mr:सदस्य_चर्चा:कोल्हापुरी|कोल्हापुरी]] १३:२९, ९ फेब्रुवारी २००९ (UTC)

{{Template:WikimediaCopyrightWarning}}

== Edit request on 5 July 2012 ==

{{edit semi-protected|answered=yes}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;

In the portion of the artical  &quot;6.5 Computational linguistics &quot; following content should be added.

&quot;Samskrit is a very scientificly designed language. Everything is based on rules. There is no exception.  Although some advanced rules are taught as exception in primary classes but in higher classes they are taught as rules.

All of first we start from alphabet.  Samskrit's alphabet is arranged in the order of  the origin in our vocal system from they are pronounced. For instance प फ ब भ म
all these five letters are pronounced from lips.

	Secondly definition of vowels and consonant is given very clearly. Letter  which can be pronounced without the help of any other letter is vowel and the letter which can not be pronounced without the help of  vowels is consonant.
	Third point is Sandhi ( सन्धि ) and Samas ( समास ). The basic concept behind the rules of Sandhi and Samas is to make pronunciation easy. It is much more easy to speak Vidhyalaya( विद्यालय ) rather than speaking Vidya ( विद्या )and then after giving a short break and then speaking Aalya ( आलय ). If you continuously and repeatly say  “Jagat Guru” ( जगत्  गुरू) then after some time you will automaticly find that you are saying “Jagadguru” ( जगदगुरू ).
	For poetry purpose it has rules of Chhand (छन्द) and Alnkar (अलंकार ).
	The fourth point is that Samskrit uses Devnagri Lipi. So its written form is same as its verbal form. Means every word has a definite pronunciation which can be easily known just by looking on the written word.&quot;


&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[User:CuteIndian|CuteIndian]] ([[User talk:CuteIndian|talk]]) 08:07, 5 July 2012 (UTC)

:{{ESp|n}} The content you propose appears to be [[WP:NOR|original research]], which isn't permitted; please include [[WP:RS|reliable sources]] with any further requests. There are also numerous errors of spelling and grammar which would need to be fixed, and I really must question how &quot;Samskrit&quot; [sic] can be &quot;scientifically designed&quot; when it predates the very concept of science. [[User:Rivertorch|Rivertorch]] ([[User talk:Rivertorch|talk]]) 11:04, 5 July 2012 (UTC)

:The &quot;regularity&quot; that you are talking about appears to be about the Devangari writing system, not the Sanskrit language itself.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/101.166.150.53|101.166.150.53]] ([[User talk:101.166.150.53|talk]]) 12:50, 8 October 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Phonology Section ==

The phonology section seems to be written by someone with a poor familiarity with English pronunciation. How are English 't' and 'd' retroflex before a vowel? They are clearly alveolar. 'ch' and 'j' would be better approximations.
Instead, 't' and 'd' should be used to represent the dental series. In its current state the section relies too much on Spanish phonology. This is the English wikipedia, it should not be assumed that every reader speaks Spanish. And even those who have learnt Spanish will probably still pronounce the Spanish dentals as alveolar. They really do not sound that different to an English-speaker.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/101.166.150.53|101.166.150.53]] ([[User talk:101.166.150.53|talk]]) 12:46, 8 October 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:The approximations may have been added by someone from India. Check [[Indian English#Consonants]]. Indians regularly (and characteristically) identify English alveolar stops with their retroflex series instead of their dental series (as alveolars are further back than Indian dental stops), while they identify the English interdental fricatives with their own dental stops, as is well-known. I agree with your criticism; however, English ''tr'' and ''dr'' or (in rhotic dialects, especially where ''r'' is retroflex) ''rt'' and ''rd'' are probably better approximations for retroflex stops than ''ch'' and ''j'' (which are already used for the Sanskrit palatal series anyway); compare the use of such digraphs to represent retroflex stops in Australian languages, notably in the strongly Anglicised place-name ''Coolgardie''. --[[User:Florian Blaschke|Florian Blaschke]] ([[User talk:Florian Blaschke|talk]]) 20:32, 21 October 2012 (UTC)
:Also note that in Hindi, the retroflex series is more precisely described as apico-alveolar, allophonically even alveolar, as explained in [[Hindi-Urdu phonology#Consonants]], which seems to have have influenced the decision (and the Indian English pronunciation). Of course such details of Sanskrit phonetics cannot be known for certain. --[[User:Florian Blaschke|Florian Blaschke]] ([[User talk:Florian Blaschke|talk]]) 20:45, 21 October 2012 (UTC)

== Edit request on 17 October 2012 ==

{{edit semi-protected|answered=yes}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;
Please include this topic,as this is most scientifically proven research and there are a lot more scientific facts associated with this ancient language. - 
==== '''Sanskrit and Science''' ====
.
The physiological effects of reading Sanskrit are similar to those experienced during the Transcendental Meditation® technique, according to research recently completed by Dr. Fred Travis, director of the ERG/Psychophysiology lab of Maharishi University of Management in Fairfield, Iowa, USA.

Dr. Travis asked his test subjects to read passages from the Bhagavad-Gita in Sanskrit and in modern foreign languages (Spanish, French, or German). In each case they could pronounce the sounds but did not know the meaning. He measured brain wave patterns (ERG), heart and breath rate, and galvanic skin resistance during two reading sessions and during a 15-minute session of the Transcendental Meditation technique. 

He found that while they read Sanskrit their physiology was similar to those measured during the Transcendental Meditation technique, but significantly different from reading a modern language.

Their skin resistance steadily increased during reading Sanskrit and during practice of the Transcendental editation technique (showing greater stability in their physiology) but remained the same during the reading of a modern language.

Their ERG alpha power and coherence during reading Sanskrit were also similar to that during the practice of the Transcendental Meditation technique, and both of these were higher than when the subjects read a modern language. 
&lt;ref name=undefined /&gt; Travis, F.T., Olsen, T., Egenes, T., &amp; Gupta, H.K. (2001). Physiological patterns during practice of the Transcendental Meditation Technique compared with patterns while reading Sanskrit and a modern language. International Journal of Neuroscience, 109, 71-80.
&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[User:Rockthemind|Rockthemind]] ([[User talk:Rockthemind|talk]]) 04:58, 17 October 2012 (UTC)

:Sounds like utter bullshit. 'D like to see some peer review. — [[User:Kwamikagami|kwami]] ([[User talk:Kwamikagami|talk]]) 05:41, 17 October 2012 (UTC)
::{{ESp|nfn}} I'm quite sceptical, if you can provide some peer review, or a link to the entry in the Journal I'll consider it further. '''[[User:Callanecc|Callanecc]]''' ([[User talk:Callanecc|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Callanecc|contribs]] • [[Special:Log/Callanecc|logs]]) 06:08, 17 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>rkjyytfve7mi2ijvn65srgcmdq0uoy3</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
