<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Prakrit</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>24499</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519419862</id>
      <parentid>519419598</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-23T17:06:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnonMoos</username>
        <id>21047</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* The Prakrits became literary languages, generally patronized by kings identified with the Kshatriya caste, but were regarded as illegitimate by the Brahmin orthodoxy. */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13585">{{WikiProject India|class=c|importance=mid|history=yes|history-importance=high|assess-date=April 2012}}
{{LanguageTalk|class=start|importance=high}}

==old talk==
Changed &quot;The original crude language from which Sanskrit was derived could be Prakrit&quot; to &quot;Some have suggested that the original crude language from which Sanskrit was derived could be Prakrit, but this contradicts the findings of comparative linguistics, which are that Sanskrit is closer to earlier Indo-European linguistic forms than Prakrits are&quot;. -- AnonMoos 06:58, 29 July 2004

:Moved that whole paragraph to a &quot;Traditional accounts&quot; and did a little cleaning up.[[User:Kukkurovaca| -- &amp;#2325;&amp;#2369;&amp;#2325;&amp;#2381;&amp;#2325;&amp;#2369;&amp;#2352;&amp;#2379;&amp;#2357;&amp;#2366;&amp;#2330;]]|[[User talk:Kukkurovaca|Talk&amp;#8253;]] 16:32, 29 Jul 2004 (UTC)

Sorry that my edit apparently messed up the formatting -- I was using an older version of Netscape which was apparently not fully compatible with the editing form -- AnonMoos 06:46, 30 July 2004

== Serious error in definition ==


I wish you wiki-people would [[read]] a [[book]] before they write these definitions.

It is quite false to define a Prakrit as a vernacular: these were artificial, poetic and literary languages that were *never* anyone's &quot;mother tongue&quot;.  It is true that Sanskrit grammarians pour scorn on Prakrits --but that is because Prakrits are not &quot;The language of the gods&quot;, but are considered secular and imperfect by contrast to the language of the Vedas (the lattering being supposed to be of divine origin).  Naturally, this was disputed by members of rival religions --e.g., [[Jain Prakrit]] is certainly considered sacred by the [[Jainism|Jains]].

Various prakrits were associated with various ruling dynasties, each of which respectively patronized the given prakrit as a literary language, and for certainly highly ritualized forms of communication from the state --e.g., the inscriptions of Ashoka (which are in Prakrit, by the way).

:Thank you for your suggestion&amp;#32;regarding [[:&amp;#32;regarding [[:{{{1}}}]]]]! When you feel an article needs improvement, please feel free to make whatever changes you feel are needed.  Wikipedia is a [[wiki]], so ''anyone'' can edit almost any article by simply following the '''{{MediaWiki:edit}}''' link at the top. You don't even need to [[Special:Userlogin|log in]]! (Although there are some [[Wikipedia:Why create an account?|reasons why you might like to]]…) The Wikipedia community encourages you to [[Wikipedia:be bold|be bold]]. Don't worry too much about making honest mistakes&amp;mdash;they're likely to be found and corrected quickly. If you're not sure how editing works, check out [[Wikipedia:how to edit a page|''how to edit a page'']], or use the [[Wikipedia:Sandbox|sandbox]] to try out your editing skills.  [[Wikipedia:Welcome, newcomers|New contributors are always welcome]]. - [[User:Nat Krause|Nat Kraus]][[User_Talk:Nat Krause|e]] 08:06, 24 Apr 2005 (UTC)

::In reply to &quot;sofixit&quot; --apparently you didn't bother to notice that I completely re-wrote the article.  Thanks for your non-reply, telling me to edit the article rather than complain.  I did both; and my complaints are hardly without justification.  I hope I don't have to re-write the thing again, after the next generation of proud graduates to &quot;Intro to Hindi 100&quot; decide to reduce the article to their level of understanding.

:::I've seen recent academic references use prakrit as a synonym for vernacular. The issue of purely literary vs. vernacular languages seems to be far from settled scholarship. I'm certainly open to the idea that the vernacular == prakrit equation is incorrect or incomplete if there is compelling evidence otherwise, but so far we have nothing other than a blanket statement that the belief that prakrit was vernacular language is a novice error.  Please provide some references so that people can assess the foundation of your contribution- otherwise, the result is 'to the obstinate go the spoils' as the reverts and counter-reverts pile up.  --[[User:Spasemunki|Clay Collier]] 08:42, 2 September 2005 (UTC)

::::I'm hardly qualified to correct the situation, but I'd like to point out that the current definition we have at the beginning of this article is incoherent. This intro, consisting half of which was written by anon and half of which was there previously, says &quot;'''Prakrit''' ... refers to the broad family of the Indic [[language]]s and [[dialect]]s spoken in ancient [[India]]. The Prakrits were literary languages, generally patronized by kings identified with the ksatriya caste ...&quot; If it really refers to broad family of Indic languages, then it can't be just a group of artificial, literary languages, right?
::::Furthermore, Clay is correct that what the situation calls for is citations, rather than snide remarks. - [[User:Nat Krause|Nat Kraus]][[User_Talk:Nat Krause|e]] 11:09, 3 September 2005 (UTC)

The word prakrt or prakrit never means vulgar. Further defining &quot;prakrit&quot; as vulgar creates unnecessary negative and demeaning connotations. [[User:Abhijna|Abhijna]]

::According to Sinhala usage, I mean as Sinhalese understand, who mix Sanskrit in speech often 50/50, prakRta means natural (as it appears) as against saMskRta means made (formed). This seems to suggest that Sanskrit was of those who wanted to manage the language in a precise way like the snobs nowadays and Prakrit is what generally everybody used? I may be totally wrong (and don't mean to offend anyone) but, the meanings of the words, I give are correct to the best of my knowledge. [[User:Ahangama|JC]] 06:02, 7 June 2007 (UTC)

:::Yes, definately. Prakrit means natural(from prakruthi- nature). Sanskrit on the other hand means refined or scholarly(from samskruthi).[[Special:Contributions/117.99.85.33|117.99.85.33]] ([[User talk:117.99.85.33|talk]]) 08:07, 15 December 2010 (UTC)

== Arhamagadhi Dictionary ==

It wiill be great if a Ardhamagadhi dictionary can be setup.

== The Prakrits became literary languages, generally patronized by kings identified with the Kshatriya caste, but were regarded as illegitimate by the Brahmin orthodoxy. ==

The statement is very offending - Brahmin Orthodoxy - who these people are? do they really have origion? do they really maintain family history? do they ever respect the nation? do they ever have love for Dharma? what dharma principles they are following or ever followed? There are no brahmins neither their legitimates.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/202.80.57.2|202.80.57.2]] ([[User talk:202.80.57.2|talk]]) 11:49, 24 October 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

::It means that for many centuries Brahmins would have regarded the idea of a non-Sanskrit holy book as absurd, at the same time that Buddhists were enthusiastically developing Pali... [[User:AnonMoos|AnonMoos]] ([[User talk:AnonMoos|talk]]) 13:41, 21 February 2011 (UTC)

----
prakrit language is ancient. In acient time prakrit language was talking language.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/117.96.55.46|117.96.55.46]] ([[User talk:117.96.55.46|talk]]) 08:10, 16 August 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

::Prakrits were distinct by the time of Asoka, but from a comparative Indo-European perspective, Sanskrit (especially Vedic Sanskrit) represents a much earlier stage of linguistic history... [[User:AnonMoos|AnonMoos]] ([[User talk:AnonMoos|talk]]) 13:41, 21 February 2011 (UTC)

----
|^^^ What is the definite proof of this? Aren't the earliest Indo-Iranian inscriptions written in India all Prakrits?|[[User:CormanoSanchez|CormanoSanchez]] ([[User talk:CormanoSanchez|talk]]) 07:46, 20 January 2012 (UTC)

:The proof is that historical linguists use Vedic Sanskrit as a basis for proto-Indo-European comparison/reconstruction more often than prakrits... [[User:AnonMoos|AnonMoos]] ([[User talk:AnonMoos|talk]]) 17:06, 23 October 2012 (UTC)

==The lead==
Dear editors of this article. I am no expert in this subject and hence can't do the changes myself, and that is why am posting this message (because I often hear people saying- ''if you dont find it ok, just do it yourself rather than passing comments!''). Well, my concern is about the lead. The lead doesn't say that it is a ''broad family of the [[Indic languages]]'' untill you read till the third line (although the same sentence). Can the lead be changed a bit for ease of the reader? Thanks &lt;font color=&quot;Orange&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;[[User:Wikiality123|Wiki San Roze]]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;i&gt; &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Wikiality123|†αLҝ]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 12:31, 17 April 2008 (UTC)

== inline references ==

this article needs more references as notes...--[[User:Esteban.barahona|Esteban Barahona]] ([[User talk:Esteban.barahona|talk]]) 03:30, 30 August 2008 (UTC)
:I'm assuming that this is simply the result of lacking citations rather than lacking sources, hence the {{tl|Nofootnotes}}.  We may need to change it to {{tl|refimprove}} if we feel that the sources listed at the bottom aren't cutting it.  — [[User:Aeusoes1|Æµ§œš¹]] &lt;span title=&quot;Representation in the International Phonetic Alphabet (IPA)&quot; class=&quot;IPA&quot;&gt;[[User talk:aeusoes1|&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[aɪm ˈfɻɛ̃ⁿdˡi]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 04:40, 30 August 2008 (UTC)

== X3nodox ==

Hi, as a reader I find the opening paragraph could be more clear to what Prakrit is. The sentences throughout the article are also a little long and convoluted. Breaking some of the longer sentences into two would be helpful. Secondly, how do these vernaculars differ linguistically? There are articles linked to each one but a brief mention would be good.[[User:Rofflebuster|Rofflebuster]] ([[User talk:Rofflebuster|talk]]) 14:05, 13 April 2009 (UTC)

The opening sentences are wordy and confusing. Possibly split the two interpretations up, and also give a general definition.
I also found the last paragraph of forms to be vague, and lacking details. Including more details of how each Prakrit is used (with references!) would be useful, and interesting. (The existing examples are interesting already!)
Also explanations of the differences between Prakrits could add to this article. [[User:Scatter89|Scatter89]] ([[User talk:Scatter89|talk]]) 02:27, 14 April 2009 (UTC)


128.253.110.123 is me, for the record ... 
[[User:X3nodox|X3nodox]] ([[User talk:X3nodox|talk]]) 20:54, 29 April 2009 (UTC)

Prakrit did not derive from &quot;Classical Sanskrit&quot;, a form that was not formed until 1st century, and there are may questions regarding PRakrits relation to what is now called Vedic Sanskrit, they probably both share a parent language, the Prakrit can also be compared to slang, street or common talk with all sorts of allowable simplifications, while the Sanskrit was highly ARYA-sticratic  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/68.38.215.42|68.38.215.42]] ([[User talk:68.38.215.42|talk]]) 12:18, 10 May 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Parallels with other language groups? ==

If Prakrits are vernaculars as opposed to &quot;classical&quot; Sanskrit, are there parallels with vernaculars around classical Latin?  The contemporary Indic vernaculars I'm most familiar with -- Hindi and Nepali -- have substituted prepositions for declensions.  The same holds for most Romance languages, except Romanian apparently retains declension to some extent.  [[User:LADave|LADave]] ([[User talk:LADave|talk]]) 21:45, 14 February 2010 (UTC)

:You can analogize Sanksrit to Latin, but there's a greater time-depth in the case of Sanskrit --  Prakrits/Pali were already distinctive languages being written down for some purposes at a time when Latin was rarely spoken outside the Italian peninsula.  Technically, Hindi has &quot;postpositions&quot;... [[User:AnonMoos|AnonMoos]] ([[User talk:AnonMoos|talk]]) 05:36, 25 February 2011 (UTC)

== What is this Jain Tirthankar reference? ==

The first paragraph says &quot;But there are scholars who believe that Prakrit is older than Sanskrit, and it is on the base of Prakrit (original) that the Sanskrit (refined) language was made. This also is in tune with the Jain religion, where the first Tirthankar is Adinath himself.&quot; It is not at all clear what the relation of the second sentence to the first is. Could someone in the know clarify this please?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Sundaryourfriend|Sundaryourfriend]] ([[User talk:Sundaryourfriend|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Sundaryourfriend|contribs]]) 22:51, 26 February 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Where is the language? ==

Sorry for criticism, but nothing in the article talks of the language, all material is about and around the language. Neither morphology, nor phonology, nor typology are even mentioned. Anybody knows anything about the language to add meat to the bluff? [[User:Barefact|Barefact]] ([[User talk:Barefact|talk]]) 20:30, 27 March 2012 (UTC)

:Prakrit  is more of a language classification than a single language (though Magadhi can be considered the most important prakrit by Hindus, and Pali by Buddhists). There's some discussion at [[Magadhi Prakrit]]... [[User:AnonMoos|AnonMoos]] ([[User talk:AnonMoos|talk]]) 17:05, 23 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>ef9fw1j5gzxjxu3mo23r01czpgkqc0q</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
