<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:New Age</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>204674</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517632276</id>
      <parentid>515600450</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-13T21:23:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Skaruts</username>
        <id>17617960</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Atheism included in &quot;spiritual and religious traditions&quot;? */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14687">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=PR
|action1date=05:51, 19 May 2009
|action1link=Wikipedia:Peer review/New Age/archive1
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=290049011

|action2=GAN
|action2date=03:00, 14 November 2010
|action2link=Talk:New Age/GA1
|action2result=listed
|action2oldid=396567600

|currentstatus=GA
|topic=Religion, mysticism and mythology
}}
{{Notforum}}
{{Todo}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1={{WPReligion|class=GA|importance=High|NRM=yes|NRMImp=Top}}
{{Rational Skepticism|class=GA|importance=mid}}
{{Spirituality project|class=GA|importance=high}}
{{WPOccult|class=GA|importance=mid}}
{{Philosophy|class=GA|importance=mid|religion=yes}}
{{WikiProject Neopaganism|class=GA|importance=mid}}
{{WP1.0|v0.7=pass|class=GA|category=Philrelig}}
}}
{{Onlinesource|year=2004|section=May 2004 (12 articles)
| title=Merchant offers 'alternative' to spirituality
| org=''[[Herald &amp; Review]]'' (Decatur, Illinois, U.S.)
| date=May 1, 2004
| url=http://www.herald-review.com/lifestyles/article_4af6ff1b-9d8f-5696-b674-b9badcc4184f.html}}
{{Archive box|[[/Archive 1|Archive 1]]&lt;br&gt;[[/Archive 2|Archive 2]]&lt;br&gt;[[/Archive 3|Archive 3]]&lt;br&gt; [[/Archive 4|Archive 4]]&lt;br&gt;[[/Archive 5|Archive 5]]&lt;br&gt;[[/Archive 6|Archive 6 (2006)]]&lt;br&gt;[[/Archive 7|Archive 7 (2007)]]&lt;br&gt;[[/Archive 8|Archive 8 (2008)]]&lt;br&gt;[[/Archive 9|Archive 9 (2009)]]&lt;br&gt;[[/Archive 10|Archive 10 (2010)]]&lt;br&gt;[[/Archive 11|Archive 11 (2011)]]}}

__TOC__

{{Talk:New Age/GA1}}

==Improved sourcing==
It's been a while since I looked at this article, and it is nice to see, at long last, some authoritative scholarly sources like Hannegraaff, Heelas and Drury represented. Well done, and good luck with the GA. --'''&lt;font color=&quot;#0000FF&quot;&gt;[[User:Jayen466|JN]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot; #FFBF00&quot;&gt;[[User_Talk:Jayen466|466]]&lt;/font&gt;''' 17:35, 4 October 2010 (UTC)

== &quot;non-religious&quot;? ==

In relation to the contemporary debate and academic diversity regarding the problem of defining religion, to generalize such a broad concept as New Age as &quot;non-religious&quot; is (and I can't believe no one has questioned this yet) misguiding, questionable, or simply incorrect. Consider how one supposedly reacts to some christian or other religious movements that claims to be &quot;not a religion&quot;, religions and/or religious persons do avoid the word &quot;religion&quot;, for reasons that are ideological, theological, that is: for RETHORICAL purposes. And usually the story follows with &quot;..it is rather a relationship&quot;, refering to God or Christ etc. Furthermore the word &quot;religion&quot; is cearly politized and ideologically &quot;infected&quot;. Rethorics such as above have implicit theological/metaphysical statements. My point is that Wikipedia would'nt simply let religious organisation represent themselves in defining and describing what it is. The same should go for New Age. My concern is, first of all, quote: &quot;The New Age movement is a non-religious Western spiritual movement&quot; sounds like a &quot;insider&quot; stance, that is, to make such a (sharp) distinction between &quot;religious&quot; and &quot;spiritual&quot; is a typical normative-&quot;theological&quot; viewpoint from the perspective of most self-identified new-age/spiritual/personal belief-person, but certainly not a self-evident or factual distinction which should be taken for granted. I would gladly discuss this further. But not to be misunderstood, I'm not saying new-age is a religion, it is obviously not A religion. But isn't it just as obvious, according to most (or all) definitions of what &quot;religious&quot; means, that it is in no way correct to claim or imply that New Age is a &quot;non-religious&quot; movement!? (and if I do have any kind of agenda it is simply from the perspective of contemporary academic sources, and the theoretical view of science of religion/religious studies, sociology of religion etc.) &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding comment added by [[User:Justathought|Justathought]] ([[User talk:Justathought|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Justathought|contribs]]) 19:18, 6 December 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:IP [[Special:Contributions/141.217.232.209|141.217.232.209]] [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=New_Age&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=399876342 changed the wording] from &quot;quasi-religious&quot; to &quot;nonreligious&quot; on December 1, 2010; no explanation was given in the edit summary. [[User:All Is One|All is One]] ([[User talk:All Is One|talk]]) 21:54, 7 December 2010 (UTC)

*'''Comment''' Perhaps changing the wording from:&quot;The '''New Age movement''' is a [[spirituality|spiritual]] and non[[religion|religious]] Western movement that developed in the latter half of the 20th century.&quot; ......... Too: The '''New Age movement''' is a [[spirituality|spiritual]], [[religion|religious]] alternative movement that developed in the latter half of the 20th century. Perhaps this wording reflects the idea more correctly, perhaps not.--[[User:Warrior777|User:Warrior777]] ([[User talk:Warrior777|talk]]) 10:22, 2 July 2011 (UTC)

== Bias ==

Article only highlights viewpoints supporting it's overall slant. In particular a few writers are quoted and referenced extensively. Scientology appears to be added and deleted often. Should it be added or removed and why? Please discuss. Please add criticism section to balance viewpoint. Anything from difference of opinion of prominent New Age adherents to outright dismissal of concept. Refs always. Discuss if unsure. [[User:Daffydavid|Daffydavid]] ([[User talk:Daffydavid|talk]]) 14:02, 26 February 2011 (UTC)
:Disagree. Criticism sections are poor form and should not be added. Instead, the &quot;Reception&quot; section adequately addresses other perspectives. &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Georgia;font-size:80%;&quot;&gt;'''/[[User:Fetchcomms|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#000;&quot;&gt;ƒETCH&lt;/span&gt;]][[User talk:Fetchcomms|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#000;&quot;&gt;COMMS&lt;/span&gt;]][[Special:Contributions/Fetchcomms|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#000;&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;]]'''&lt;/span&gt; 16:20, 23 March 2011 (UTC)

::[[User:Fetchcomms|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#000;&quot;&gt;ƒETCH&lt;/span&gt;]], article is still lacking in balanced perspective as per wikipedia standards, but I note you have a vested interest in this article so I understand your personal view on the topic. Removing the tag based on just your opinion is bad form, but I'm not interested in a edit war, so have it your way. Just know that the article is likely to fail a Good Article test if challenged. It won't be me. Just thought I'd point it out. [[User:Daffydavid|Daffydavid]] ([[User talk:Daffydavid|talk]]) 17:10, 23 March 2011 (UTC)
:::Troll behaviour concerning Scientology and tagging; most likely another form of: Category:Wikipedia sockpuppets of DavidYork71. Recommend checkuser on [[User:Daffydavid|Daffydavid]]. [[User:All Is One|All is One]] ([[User talk:All Is One|talk]]) 23:38, 23 March 2011 (UTC)

::::[[User:All Is One|All is One]], I'm disappointed in you. I'm suddenly a troll because I asked if Scientology should be included? I have no idea if it should or not. I just noticed that it was added and removed several times. I tagged the article because Wikipedia standards say the amount of material in each article should be proportionate to the world view. Given that there has been a significant decline in the number of Naturopaths, Homeopaths and other similar professions it would be reasonable to infer that the New Age movement is in decline. Maybe it's increasing. I don't really care enough about this topic to research more than I already have. I note with interest that instead of addressing the topics I brought up you instead attempt to brand me as A troll and a &quot;sockpuppet&quot;.  Perhaps you should read the Wikipedia article on the &quot;Straw man argument&quot;. Check away on my username, [[User:Daffydavid|Daffydavid]] all you want. This is my one only account on Wikipedia. If you wish to debate the points I raised, either to enlighten me or otherwise convince me of the error of my ways, it would make more sense to post on my page  ([[User talk:Daffydavid|talk]]) than to conduct personal attacks on the New Age talk page. All I can say is &quot;convince me&quot;, attempts at slander and denigration do nothing to prove you are right. [[User:Daffydavid|Daffydavid]] ([[User talk:Daffydavid|talk]]) 03:22, 24 March 2011 (UTC)

:Bad form? Actually, it's called [[WP:BRD|BRD]]. I am not a sockpuppet, Daffydavid, and I would recommend avoiding such accusations in the future (as well as you, All is One). If either of you would like to request a [[WP:SPI|CheckUser]], please go ahead. I look forward to seeing the results. &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Georgia;font-size:80%;&quot;&gt;'''/[[User:Fetchcomms|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#000;&quot;&gt;ƒETCH&lt;/span&gt;]][[User talk:Fetchcomms|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#000;&quot;&gt;COMMS&lt;/span&gt;]][[Special:Contributions/Fetchcomms|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#000;&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;]]'''&lt;/span&gt; 17:07, 24 March 2011 (UTC)

:: Fetchcomms, My apologies for the comment and I agree with your [[WP:BRD|BRD]] point. I was hoping for a reply on some of my queries, but it seems that is not to be. To clarify, I expected a discussion on the Talk Page rather than tag removal. Perhaps I am wrong but it seems that the tagging supersedes [[WP:BRD|BRD]]. Happy Editing.

Seems unbiased overall. Shocking for a government/banking propaganda psy op like Wikipedia.

==How New Age differs from counter-culture==

I think it would be good if this article were to explain how the New Age of the 1990s differs quite radically from the [[counter-culture]] of the [[1960s]]. The former tends to be a more middle class exercice, and can be quite entrepeneurial, as is evident from the title of Peter LeMesurier's book &quot;This New Age Business&quot;. [[Paul Heelas]] described the New Age as being like [[angels]] in pinsuits! This contrasts with the counter-culture, with its emphasis on dropping out from society. The counter-culture was, in many ways, a much more radical and unorthodox movement. [[User:ACEOREVIVED|ACEOREVIVED]] ([[User talk:ACEOREVIVED|talk]]) 14:53, 5 April 2011 (UTC)

== New Age as a reaction to traditional religion ==
One thing that is lacking to me is a discussion of how New Age philosphies are a reaction to &quot;that old time religion&quot; of the 1950s and earlier times. I'd like to see some history that discusses people's unhappiness with attending Church on Sunday with the &quot;right&quot; social crowd in order to be seen to be pious and then ignoring religion and spirituality the rest of the time. Along with this, there were much doctrinal hair splitting which seemed to many to be a manifestation of the Biblical image of gnats and camels. I also would give more emphasis to intentional communities including Christian ones because they are trying to do something new as well. I did find many articles about the decline in traditional religion but was unable to easily find references that linked the growth of New Age with reasons for the decline of traditional religion.
[[User:Jerryfern|Jerryfern]] ([[User talk:Jerryfern|talk]]) 18:09, 23 June 2011 (UTC)

==Nagualism==

I would respectfully suggest that woven somewhere into the article be mentioned: [[Carlos Castaneda]],[[ Don Juan Matus]], Neo-[[Nagualism]] or a reference be made to &quot;modern day&quot; [[Toltecs]] perhaps making the article more complete. I only suggest and leave that decision up to you. --[[User:Warrior777|User:Warrior777]] ([[User talk:Warrior777|talk]]) 09:56, 2 July 2011 (UTC)
:Agree. It's one of major influences in the New Age. -- [[User:Nazar|Nazar]] ([[User talk:Nazar|talk]]) 19:02, 5 March 2012 (UTC)
Also Deepak Chopra.
[[User:Henry123ifa|Henry123ifa]] ([[User talk:Henry123ifa|talk]]) 13:08, 25 May 2012 (UTC)

== No Criticism section? ==

New Age is often criticised as wishy-washy blather. Many articles on WP include a Criticism section. This one doesn't. It should. [[Special:Contributions/86.135.115.218|86.135.115.218]] ([[User talk:86.135.115.218|talk]]) 02:52, 5 February 2012 (UTC)

:The  Reception section contains criticisms from a  wide range of cultural perspectives.[[User:Lumos3|Lumos3]] ([[User talk:Lumos3|talk]]) 11:13, 7 February 2012 (UTC)

::It, quite noticeably, lacks a subsection of atheist\skeptic\materialist\scientific (pick the most appropriate) views. —&amp;nbsp;[[User:Jeraphine Gryphon|Jeraphine&amp;nbsp;Gryphon]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Jeraphine Gryphon|talk]])&lt;/sup&gt; 11:28, 4 March 2012 (UTC) 

:::For further information about the topic, see [[Wikipedia:Criticism]]. [[User:All Is One|All is One]] ([[User talk:All Is One|talk]]) 02:31, 8 February 2012 (UTC)

::::I have just added a section on the New Age as a social and political movement, and it includes a sub-section of fairly pointed criticisms from both the left and the right. - [[User:Babel41|Babel41]] ([[User talk:Babel41|talk]]) 00:45, 4 September 2012 (UTC)

== Atheism included in &quot;spiritual and religious traditions&quot;? ==

&quot;''The New Age movement includes elements of older spiritual and religious traditions '''ranging from atheism and monotheism''' through classical pantheism,(...)''&quot;
&lt;br /&gt;This implies that atheism is a religion, when atheism is the antithesis of theism. This is misleading and should be corrected. [[User:Skaruts|Skaruts]] ([[User talk:Skaruts|talk]]) 21:41, 1 October 2012 (UTC)
:You are quite right! And, as it is not sourced and doesn't appear anywhere else in the article, please feel free to be bold and remove it. [[User:Lova_Falk|&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Segoe Print;color:#e75e03&quot;&gt;'''Lova Falk'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Lova Falk|&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Segoe Print;color:#336699&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 09:07, 2 October 2012 (UTC)
::I removed the word atheism from it. But from what I heard some atheists may take part of this movement. Someone with better understanding of the movement should probably include atheism in there once more, as long as it's not in the same context of religious tradition as I perceived it was. [[User:Skaruts|Skaruts]] ([[User talk:Skaruts|talk]]) 09:58, 2 October 2012 (UTC)
:::Sure some atheists take part of this movement! But that is not the same as stating that &quot;The New Age movement includes elements of older spiritual and religious traditions&quot; such as atheism. There is no mention in the article of elements of atheism that are incorporated into the New Age movement. An if someone wants to put this in, well, as long as there is a good source for it, that is absolutely fine! [[User:Lova_Falk|&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Segoe Print;color:#e75e03&quot;&gt;'''Lova Falk'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Lova Falk|&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Segoe Print;color:#336699&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 10:02, 2 October 2012 (UTC)
:::: Then it's all good. Thanks for the feedback. [[User:Skaruts|Skaruts]] ([[User talk:Skaruts|talk]]) 21:23, 13 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>pnky5qoub7g8adzkhwka7c38vwiul5s</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
