<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Jihad</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>70803</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520185340</id>
      <parentid>504202496</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-27T23:54:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>R. la Rue</username>
        <id>15432783</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* David Cook */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24929">{{Skip to talk}}
{{talk header |search=yes }}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 13
|minthreadsleft = 5
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Jihad/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Auto archiving notice |bot=MiszaBot I |age=3 |units=months }}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn 
|target=/Archive index |mask=/Archive &lt;#&gt; |leading_zeros=0 |indexhere=yes 
}}
{{controversial}}
{{not a forum}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell |1=
{{WPMILHIST |class=B |Science-task-force=yes
&lt;!-- 1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points are appropriately cited. --&gt;
|B-Class-1=yes
&lt;!-- 2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2=yes
&lt;!-- 3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3=yes
&lt;!-- 4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
Get more prominent source.This article is complete biased..
|B-Class-5=yes }}
{{WikiProject Sociology|class=B|importance=Top}}  
{{WikiProject Islam|class=B|importance=Top|Islam and Controversy=yes}}
{{WikiProject Terrorism|class=B}}
{{WPMA|class=B|importance=High|Crusades-task-force=yes}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=B|importance=Top}}
}}
{{oldpeerreview|archive=1}}
{| width=&quot;100%&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; cellspacing=&quot;5&quot; style=&quot;border: 0px solid #C0C090; background-color: #FFFFFF; margin-bottom: 0px;&quot;
|align=left valign=center| &lt;nowiki&gt;(~~~~Guest~~~~)&lt;/nowiki&gt;, and read [[Template:talk header|this]]. As a courtesy to other users, editors may use {{tl|unsigned}} to help mark any unsigned comments. See Pending Tasks [[Talk:Jihad/to_do|here]].'''
|}

&lt;div style=&quot;clear:left;&quot;&gt;

== A correction request ==

Please, correct the following sentence from the chapter Origins so its meaning is clear and understandable in English: &quot;The struggle for Jihad in the Quran was originally intended for the nearby neighbors of the Muslims, but as time passed and more enemies arose, the Quranic statements supporting Jihad were updated for the new adversaries.&quot;
Since jihad means struggle than the phrase &quot;struggle for Jihad&quot; does not make sense as meaning &quot;struggle for Struggle&quot;. Does it, please? Thanks.--[[Special:Contributions/24.44.108.229|24.44.108.229]] ([[User talk:24.44.108.229|talk]]) 16:30, 20 June 2011 (UTC)
:{{Resolved}}
:Thanks [[User:adamrce|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:gray 3px 3px 2px;&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#663300&quot;&gt;'''''   ~ AdvertAdam'''''&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]][[User Talk:adamrce|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:gray 3px 3px 2px;&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;  talk&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 05:49, 21 June 2011 (UTC)
::Not entirely. There is still missing the meaning of jihad according to Quran making the following sentence unclear as well: &quot;Jihad in the Quran was originally intended for the nearby neighbors of the Muslims, but as time passed and more enemies arose, the Quranic statements supporting Jihad were updated for the new adversaries.&quot;
::I only presume that the intention of that sentence was to say that: &quot;Jihad in the Quran originally meant 'to struggle against' and referred to the nearby neighbors...&quot;. Am I right? You need first to clarify the meaning of jihad and only then say to whom it pertained to.--[[Special:Contributions/24.44.108.229|24.44.108.229]] ([[User talk:24.44.108.229|talk]]) 23:37, 21 June 2011 (UTC)

== A [[WP:SELFPUBLISH]]? ==

The current source seven[http://www.sunnah.org/fiqh/jihad_judicial_ruling.htm] by [[Hisham Kabbani]] seems to be self-published. If this is the case it should not be used or at least &quot;According to Hisham Kabbani&quot; should be added. --[[User:Davidelah|Davidelah]] ([[User talk:Davidelah|talk]]) 11:19, 24 November 2011 (UTC)

== Dictionary of Islam ==

If the &quot;Dictionary of Islam&quot; is authoratative why isn't there a reference to it instead of to &quot;Morgan, Diane (2010). Essential Islam: a comprehensive guide to belief and practice&quot;? [[User:HughesJohn|HughesJohn]] ([[User talk:HughesJohn|talk]]) 13:38, 28 January 2012 (UTC)

And, which &quot;Dictionary of Islam&quot;?  Hughes?  Penguin?  Oxford?  Some other one?

Ah, it appears to be Hughes: &quot;JIHAD Lit. &quot;An effort, or a striving.&quot; A religious war with those who are unbelievers in the mission of Muhammad.. It is an incumbent religious duty, established in the Qur’an and in the Traditions as a divine institution, and enjoined specially for the purpose of advancing Islam and of repelling evil from Muslims.&quot;

Is &quot;A DICTIONARY OF ISLAM Being A CYCLOPAEDIA OF THE DOCTRINES, RITES, CEREMONIES, AND CUSTOMS, TOGETHER WITH THE TECHNICAL AND THEOLOGICAL TERMS, OF THE MUHAMMADAN RELIGION BY THOMAS PATRICK HUGHES, B.D., M.R.A.S. LONDON W.H. ALLEN &amp; CO., 13 WATERLOO PLACE, PALL MALL S.W. 1895 &quot; the authoratative source? http://answering-islam.org/Books/Hughes/

Jihad means Diligence, which is constant and earnest effort to accomplish what is undertaken; persistent exertion of body or mind and in Islam it is to confront injustice and misguidance and justice and goodness.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/85.154.253.67|85.154.253.67]] ([[User talk:85.154.253.67|talk]]) 09:35, 7 April 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
 Jihads in Arabic language means diligence and do the most ones can do with maximum effort and energy, the religious meaning is to achieve true faith and what comes from it, and fight all that God abhor of heresy, immorality and ethical dissolution.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/85.154.253.67|85.154.253.67]] ([[User talk:85.154.253.67|talk]]) 10:17, 7 April 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
: The definition of the term Jihad has been discussed exhaustively. [[User:Peter Deer|Peter Deer]] ([[User talk:Peter Deer|talk]]) 12:00, 7 April 2012 (UTC)

== Andrew G. Bostom is not reliable ==

{{User|SudoGhost}} has [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jihad&amp;diff=492812234&amp;oldid=492810797 restored] [[Andrew G. Bostom|Bostom]]'s reference claiming that:
:&quot;Expertise&quot; of the kind you're referring is not required for a favorably reviewed and apparently well-received book. There are a few others here that would fail your criteria as well, but it isn't cause to remove them.

I don't think any Wikipedia policy supports SudoGhost's claims. Also if similar authors here are similarly &quot;nothing more&quot;, then remove them as well, I do not object to that. [[User:Al-Andalusi|Al-Andalusi]] ([[User talk:Al-Andalusi|talk]]) 04:49, 16 May 2012 (UTC)
:What policy supports your position that the individual must have certain unclarified scholarly qualifications or the books written by these individuals are not to be placed in an article, no matter how the books themselves are received? - [[User:SudoGhost|Sudo]][[User_talk:SudoGhost#top|Ghost]] 04:54, 16 May 2012 (UTC)
::You can't be serious ! The Bible is well-received, should we quote it in the article on [[Earth]] (being flat and 6000 years old) ? 
::It seems that Bostom's reference is problematic as other editors have already raised concerns over its use at [[Wikipedia:Reliable_sources/Noticeboard/Archive_11#Bostom and Prometheus books]]. [[User:Al-Andalusi|Al-Andalusi]] ([[User talk:Al-Andalusi|talk]]) 05:00, 16 May 2012 (UTC)
:::Since the Bible says nothing about the earth being flat and/or 6,000 years old, that's not really a valid comparison.  The discussion you linked was concerning its use as a [[WP:reliable source|reliable source]] for directly supporting information, not in a [[WP:Further reading|Further reading]] section. - [[User:SudoGhost|Sudo]][[User_talk:SudoGhost#top|Ghost]] 05:06, 16 May 2012 (UTC)
::::You're not addressing the reliability issue here. In fact, you formulate a new &quot;rule&quot; of your own (and falsely assume that WP endorses it) with every reply you post. You first started with the claim that academic expertise is not required, and then you added that it's fine to keep Bostom's source in the article since the article is already tainted with other references of similar status (instead of showing effort to correct that), and now this: that the above decision of the RS board applies only to inline citations but not the &quot;further reading&quot;. [[User:Al-Andalusi|Al-Andalusi]] ([[User talk:Al-Andalusi|talk]]) 05:49, 16 May 2012 (UTC)
:::::I did not &quot;formulate&quot; anything, nor do I &quot;falsely assume&quot; anything.  Your [[WP:NPA#WHATIS|personal commentary]] on [[WP:AGF|my statements]] is both unnecessary and inaccurate.  Reliability is not an &quot;all or nothing&quot; situation, reliability depends on the information it is intended to verify; what would be appropriate and reliable for one statement would be wholly inappropriate and completely unreliable for another.  &quot;Further reading&quot; verifies nothing, but rather provides a list of additional reading material that is relevant to the article's subject.  Also, I see no solid consensus of the discussion you linked above, that topic appeared to have died before any sort of consensus could form. - [[User:SudoGhost|Sudo]][[User_talk:SudoGhost#top|Ghost]] 06:26, 16 May 2012 (UTC)
::::::Al-andalusi, you clearly have an agenda in removing his post claiming he is &quot;not reliable&quot;. Burden of proof is on you to show why he is any less reliable than the others, since his notability is equal to the other authors there - '''proof for him has already been established.''' A &quot;Further reading&quot; section merely denotes books on the matter. The book is published by a reliable publishing house, a reliable, third-party, published sources with a reputation for fact-checking and accuracy. The author also has news coverage: http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2008/may/20/islams-history-of-anti-semitism/  by the Washington Times, a mainstream, well-respected newspaper, which notes that he used &quot;a vast collection of important documents&quot;. Same goes for CBS News: http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2005/12/13/opinion/main1123459.shtml. There is nothing which says specific expertise is needed for a work to be reliable, in fact quite the opposite. From [[WP:SOURCES]] itself: &quot;Material from reliable '''non-academic''' sources may also be used, particularly if it appears in respected mainstream publications.&quot; So, swallow your words already, that's glaring proof right there that you are wrong. Funny you accuse him of formulating new &quot;rules&quot; - you are the one who appears to be formulating the &quot;rule&quot; that the author needs to be an academic to write, when [[WP:SOURCES]] says the exact opposite! Also, bringing in the Bible example is stupid, this is not an article about the Bible, so stop with ''ignoratio elenchi''. I've provided evidence in the form of two mainstream publications reviewing and noting the verifiability of the author. &quot;claim that academic expertise is not required,&quot;? Academic expertise ''is not required!'' [[WP:SOURCES]] says it all. You are quite completely wrong.
::::::If you revert one more time without establishing consensus, you are in violation of 3RR, just so you know. [[User:Overmage|&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;smallcaps&quot; style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;&quot;&gt;'''&amp;theta;v&amp;xi;r'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]][[User talk:Overmage|&lt;span style=&quot;border-bottom: 1px double #000; color: #000; text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;smallcaps&quot; style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;&quot;&gt;'''mag&amp;xi;'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt; [[Special:Contributions/Overmage|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;contribs&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 06:46, 16 May 2012 (UTC)
:::::::Your silly &quot;agenda&quot; accusations aside, you haven't established in any way, how [[Prometheus Books]] can be considered (1) a respected and (2) a mainstream publisher per the following from [[WP:Sources]]: &quot;''Material from reliable non-academic sources may also be used, particularly if it appears in '''respected mainstream''' publications''&quot;.
:::::::which btw, you haven't quoted honestly, as it was preceded by: &quot;'''Where available''', academic and peer-reviewed publications are usually the most reliable sources, such as in history, medicine, and science. But they are not the only reliable sources in such areas.&quot;
:::::::And yes, there are thousands of academic and peer-reviewed sources '''available''' on the topic of Jihad, so there is no reason to rely on a doctor with NO credentials (and with an agenda). [[User:Al-Andalusi|Al-Andalusi]] ([[User talk:Al-Andalusi|talk]]) 15:04, 16 May 2012 (UTC)
::::::::You saved me the work of re-quoting the source, since within the statement you placed you have shot yourself in the proverbial foot. &quot;'''usually''' the most reliable sources, such as in history, medicine, and science. '''But they are not the only''' reliable sources in such areas.&quot; Usually, but they are not the only. I have given examples of notability and favourable reviews. You, on the other hand have not established why non-academia is unreliable (nor that this doctor has an agenda as you so propose - at this stage it is a baseless accusation and a sign of your bias). Find me any wikipedia policy which establishes that, and come back when you have done so. I still see none, I see a lot of 'may be's, 'not only's. No 'is's.[[User:Overmage|&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;smallcaps&quot; style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;&quot;&gt;'''&amp;theta;v&amp;xi;r'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]][[User talk:Overmage|&lt;span style=&quot;border-bottom: 1px double #000; color: #000; text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;smallcaps&quot; style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;&quot;&gt;'''mag&amp;xi;'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt; [[Special:Contributions/Overmage|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;contribs&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 01:01, 17 May 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::For the second time, notability is NOT sufficient grounds for inclusion; we are discussing its *reliability*, which you are yet to establish. Those so-called &quot;favourable reviews&quot; do not come from people with expertise in any relevant field. That discredits your reference. In addition, Bostom is a known critic of Islam, as noted by the editors in the [[WP:RSN]] I linked above, which you clearly have not bothered to read. In fact one of your &quot;favourable reviews&quot; ends with the following statement that best summarizes Bostom's intentions behind his work: &quot;...you won't have to feel guilty about the Crusades any more&quot;.
:::::::::Now that I've established that Bostom is unreliable, and cleared myself of your &quot;bias&quot; charges, let's talk about your role here. So far you have not explained your insistence on favouring a doctor's work with an partisan agenda over hundreds of academic publications and journals ? You are the biased one here I'm afraid. [[User:Al-Andalusi|Al-Andalusi]] ([[User talk:Al-Andalusi|talk]]) 01:56, 17 May 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::&quot;established that Bostom is unreliable&quot; how? Because he disagrees with Islam? Does that make him biased? So, those who support Islam are biased, by that same token? Work by anybody who is Islamic should be unreliable, then? That's a terrible argument that's not covered in wikipedia policy. I'll be honest- I do not give two hoots about Jihad or Islam in general, and was just randomly browsing. I posted here because I saw a clear misintepretation of wikipedia policies, namely by you. You haven't established or proven anything. I have no agenda other than stopping people with agendas. (If you see my edits, they are mostly gaming-related) You have already established that you have an anti- anti-Islam agenda. That is not constructive. Wikipedia is not censored and strives for NPOV - that means presenting both sides of the equation, both critical and supportive. '''All I want is for you to actually come up with some solid proof, a policy that says his non-academic source cannot be used, or a solid reference that states his work is unreliable. You have not.''' I remain, as always, unimpressed. (P.S. I have actually read the RSN. Consensus was not established. Other than giving additional information, it cannot factor into my decisions as it makes none itself.) [[User:Overmage|&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;smallcaps&quot; style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;&quot;&gt;'''&amp;theta;v&amp;xi;r'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]][[User talk:Overmage|&lt;span style=&quot;border-bottom: 1px double #000; color: #000; text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;smallcaps&quot; style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;&quot;&gt;'''mag&amp;xi;'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt; [[Special:Contributions/Overmage|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;contribs&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 03:12, 17 May 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::::I did not say that he was unreliable &quot;because he is a critic of Islam&quot;. It's disingenuous of you to put words in my mouth. I said that he is (1) unreliable because he has no qualifications and then I *added* that (2) he is biased because of his anti-Muslim views. You said that &quot;a solid reference that states his work is unreliable&quot;, sorry that's an unheard-of policy that I'm just going to ignore. The response from the RS board clearly states:
::::::::::::&quot;For a mainstream academic topic like Islam, many hundreds of scholarly books and many thousands of peer-reviewed articles in recognized journals are available. While it make sense to use high-level introductory books for an overview, there is no reason to go to borderline sources on anything remotely controversial. This is not a fringe topic where we must be thankful for any scrap of material.&quot;
:::::::::::So for the fourth time Overmage I'm asking you, why are you favouring this non-academic (and biased) reference over academic sources ? If you are going to respond with another accusation of an &quot;agenda&quot;, then you better meet me at the ANI board. For now, I'm tagging the disputed reference until consensus is reached. [[User:Al-Andalusi|Al-Andalusi]] ([[User talk:Al-Andalusi|talk]]) 20:27, 17 May 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::::You're confusing notability and reliability.  Reliability is ''required'' to use as a reference.  This is not a reference, not a source.  &quot;In addition, Bostom is a known critic of Islam...&quot; is irrelevant.  Are people biased because of their pro-Muslim views? Of course not.  Yet the reverse is somehow true by default?  No. - [[User:SudoGhost|Sudo]][[User_talk:SudoGhost#top|Ghost]] 20:35, 17 May 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::::::You are wrong: [[Wikipedia:Further reading#Reliable]]. [[User:Al-Andalusi|Al-Andalusi]] ([[User talk:Al-Andalusi|talk]]) 15:14, 18 May 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::::::For being so quick in declaring &quot;wrong&quot;, it seems you've missed the entire content of an ''unaccepted essay''. - [[User:SudoGhost|Sudo]][[User_talk:SudoGhost#top|Ghost]] 16:12, 18 May 2012 (UTC)

:::::::::::::&quot;and then I *added* that (2) he is biased because of his anti-Muslim views&quot; - If that's not an agenda I don't know what that is. Why bother adding this? It should not factor into any decision to keep it or not. There are in fact wikipedia policies specifically discouraging removal of material on the grounds of it being biased or overly critical (forgot the name, lazy to find it). Is that so hard to get? Also, last I checked the ANI board wasn't used for petty disputes between editors, but for actual editing related problems. You're more likely to waste some poor admin's time over something that could have been brought up at the [[Wikipedia:Dispute resolution noticeboard|DRN]] ;) Why am I favouring this? I am not favouring anything - I am saying that your removal of the source was not in line with wikipedia policy and that you haven't established proof. RS board provided no consensus, so it's useless as far as this dispute is concerned, it might as well be a wikipedia essay for all the quoting you do. If your best source for why his work violates policy is an RS thread with no firm consensus established, tough luck - that's an 'unheard-of policy'! And speaking of &quot;unheard-of policy&quot;, how many unheard-of policies have you brought up here alone? I counted about six thousand, what about you? :) (P.S. I am completely fine with the disputed tag. If you had done that earlier it would have saved us all quite some time.) [[User:Overmage|&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;smallcaps&quot; style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;&quot;&gt;'''&amp;theta;v&amp;xi;r'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]][[User talk:Overmage|&lt;span style=&quot;border-bottom: 1px double #000; color: #000; text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;smallcaps&quot; style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;&quot;&gt;'''mag&amp;xi;'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt; [[Special:Contributions/Overmage|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;contribs&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 00:35, 18 May 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::::::It's not that Bostom has written objectively on the subject, and happens to hold or express some anti-Islamic or anti-Muslim views in his work; his entire work from cover to cover is critical of Islam and Muslims, hence why I brought this up. The fact that Wikipedia assesses (and weighs) even the ideas expressed in reliable academic sources per [[Wikipedia:Fringe theories]] and [[WP:UNDUE]], it really highlights the danger of including a work that combines the qualities of being non-academic and one-sided. 
::::::::::::::You keep saying that there is no consensus on the RS board. Fine, this [[Wikipedia:Reliable sources/Noticeboard/Archive 5#Consensus]] clearly states the following regarding the use of [[Robert Spencer]]'s sources in [[Criticism of the Quran]]:
:::::::::::::::&quot;Consensus was reached...that: we agree he is notable, and we agree he should be mentioned as a critic. However, we argue that he is not a reliable source, and should not be given undue space (except on his own article). Still if there are secondary sources that quote him, we let him stay&quot;.
::::::::::::::Bostom's status is exactly the same as that of Spencer, both are not academic and both are critics of Islam (and keep in mind that the consensus above applies to [[Criticism of the Quran]] and not the main article [[Qur'an]]). Hence, I'm removing Bostom's reference per the above. If you still have issues, then raise them to the RS board (oh and come back only if you have a &quot;solid consensus&quot;) [[User:Al-Andalusi|Al-Andalusi]] ([[User talk:Al-Andalusi|talk]]) 15:58, 18 May 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::::::::Except this is ''not being used as a source''.  Therefore your quote above seems to suggest this very thing, that ''further reading'' is an appropriate place, whereas as a ''reliable source'' it is not.  You keep arguing against something that isn't being done, and isn't being discussed; use as a reliable source. - [[User:SudoGhost|Sudo]][[User_talk:SudoGhost#top|Ghost]] 16:12, 18 May 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::::::::The policies of reliability and inclusion apply to all sections of a WP article, not just inline citations. Produce any evidence to the contrary if you have, and please stop wasting our time. [[User:Al-Andalusi|Al-Andalusi]] ([[User talk:Al-Andalusi|talk]]) 22:35, 2 June 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::::::::&quot;Consensus was reached...that: we agree he is notable, and we agree he should be mentioned as a critic. However, we argue that he is not a reliable source, and should not be given undue space (except on his own article). Still if there are secondary sources that quote him, we let him stay&quot;: EXACTLY. He is mentioned as a critic, but not as a primary source. That's where he is in: further reading. ????? Or is there something you are misunderstanding about the very statement you quoted? (and you should have a &quot;solid consensus&quot; before you remove stuff)[[User:Overmage|&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;smallcaps&quot; style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;&quot;&gt;'''&amp;theta;v&amp;xi;r'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]][[User talk:Overmage|&lt;span style=&quot;border-bottom: 1px double #000; color: #000; text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:blue&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;smallcaps&quot; style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;&quot;&gt;'''mag&amp;xi;'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt; [[Special:Contributions/Overmage|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;contribs&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 00:45, 21 May 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::::::::::Per [[Wikipedia:Further_reading#Reliable]], the sources used should be reliable. It is clear that Bostom is not a reliable source.[[User:Bless sins|Bless sins]] ([[User talk:Bless sins|talk]]) 22:21, 1 June 2012 (UTC)

== Assassinations ==

The history of jihad is long and complex, and usually involved Muslim armies waging war. Political assassinations are usually not considered Jihad. The source cited in this article,[http://books.google.ca/books?id=OZbyz_Hr-eIC&amp;lpg=PR4&amp;ots=eWmnwDqSW7&amp;dq=(2009).%20Encyclopedia%20of%20Islam&amp;pg=PA238#v=onepage&amp;q=assassins&amp;f=false] doesn't refer to fedayeen as conducting a jihad. Such material should be replaced with actual history of jihad.[[User:Bless sins|Bless sins]] ([[User talk:Bless sins|talk]]) 16:19, 25 July 2012 (UTC)

== David Cook ==

David Cook should have an article. Therefore there should be a (red) link. Because the article is closed, I can't do that. There are often citations of his books in the literature. --[[User:R. la Rue|R. la Rue]] ([[User talk:R. la Rue|talk]]) 23:54, 27 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>ag898zkz5io6e1irr2ctawyoz028rdn</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
