<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Vibhuti</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>5599081</id>
    <revision>
      <id>112060746</id>
      <parentid>105494067</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-03-02T12:47:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GourangaUK</username>
        <id>715857</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>project tags</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2874">{{WikiProject Hinduism|class=Start|importance=Mid}}
----

== What is this ash made from? ==

It is not clear from the article what was burned to create this ash. Is the sacred ash from cremated human remains? Or some specific source (like palms leaves for [[Ash Wednesday]])? Or can they be any type of ash made sacred through ritual? --[[User:Knulclunk|Knulclunk]] 17:41, 22 January 2007 (UTC)

see [[veerashaiva]] subheading-Ashtavarana. [[Lingayat]]s prepare it through a prescribed method as laid down in ritual scriptures like  shaiva [[agama]]'s. Dried cow dung is burned and processed through a series of rituals only then it accepted as holy ash.
[[User:Lokesh 2000|Lokesh 2000]] 05:13, 24 January 2007 (UTC)

:Thanks! Should there be a metion of it in this article? or at least a link to another page describing the process?  --[[User:Knulclunk|Knulclunk]] 12:27, 24 January 2007 (UTC)

vibhuti ([[Sanskrit]]:{{lang|sa|विभूतिः}}; {{IAST|vibhūtiḥ}}; also  spelled ''vibhuti'' or ''vibhooti'') is a Sanskrit word that has several meanings, but when used to refer to ash, it means the ashes that are left after the burning of a sacred fire.  In routine daily worship the fuel source typically would be cow dung with a little ghee to accelerate burning.  It is possible that in the course of a fire ceremony some other substance might be added, depending on the deity being honored or other factors, so the exact composition could vary.  But the common definition would be &quot;ashes of cow-dung&quot; as defined in Apte's ''The Practical Sanskrit Dictionary'' p. 866. Monier-Williams ''Sanskrit Dictionary'' p. 979 defines them as &quot;ashes of cow-dung etc.&quot; and the additional &quot;etc.&quot; is significant because it clarifies that other materials may have been burned to make the ash.  They are defined as &quot;Holy ash, prepared by burning cow dung along with other precious substances, milk, ghee, honey, etc.  It symbolizes purity and is one of the main sacraments given at pūjā in all Śaivite temples and shrines&quot; on page 692 of Satguru Sivaya Subramuniyaswami, ''Loving Ganesa''.  The statement in the current article that &quot;Placed on the forehead of devotees, it covers the mark of the spiritual third eye (mystic insight as the primary path to Self-realization).&quot; sounds like it may need some clarification, as the pattern used for placing the ash on the forehead is determined by the sectarian affiliation.  For Śaivites the ash is applied in three horizontal lines, with variations in placement that make fine distinctions between sects.  These lines may cover the entire forehead, or they may be smaller.  I have been to pujas where I have received vibhūtiḥ in various patterns that I did not recognize.  So the comment in the article does not convey the complexity of the marking systems used. [[User:Buddhipriya|Buddhipriya]] 03:20, 4 February 2007 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>m13r3q4uwsrxhakio6a8cke4sj0n3l5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
