<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Islamism</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>15013</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520401173</id>
      <parentid>520401073</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-29T09:27:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SirteP</username>
        <id>7990761</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* islamist should not be redirected to islamism */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="38783">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Islam|Islam and Controversy=yes|class=B|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Politics|class=B|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Conservatism}}
}}
{{Talk header}}
{{Not a forum}}
{{afd-merged-from|Islamism in London|Islamism in London|21 September 2009}}
{{Archive box|search=yes|
* [[Wikipedia:Articles for deletion/Islamism|Deletion discussion]] &lt;small&gt;(2003)&lt;/small&gt;
* [[Talk:Islamism/Archive 1|Archive 1]] &lt;small&gt;(Feb 2002–Sept 2003)&lt;/small&gt;
* [[Talk:Islamism/Archive 2|Archive 2]] &lt;small&gt;(Sept 2003–March 2004)&lt;/small&gt;
* [[Talk:Islamism/Archive 3|Archive 3]] &lt;small&gt;(May 2004–Oct 2005)&lt;/small&gt;
* [[Talk:Islamism/Archive 4|Archive 4]] &lt;small&gt;(March–April 2006)&lt;/small&gt;
* [[Talk:Islamism/Archive 5|Archive 5]] &lt;small&gt;(April 2006–August 2009)&lt;/small&gt;
}}
__TOC__
{{Clear}}

==Islamism in London==
This used to be a separate article but after a 
[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Articles_for_deletion/Islamism_in_London vote] it was moved here as a section. Wikipedia prevents it from becoming a separate article since the vote has been made against it. Trouble is, it's quite long, and this article is already too long.  I'm going to summarize it and put a main article link to [[Londonistan (term)]] 

Here's the [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Islamism&amp;diff=316331047&amp;oldid=316322412 summary] --[[User:BoogaLouie|BoogaLouie]] ([[User talk:BoogaLouie|talk]]) 16:14, 26 September 2009 (UTC)

For those who object I suggest they create an [[Islamism in Europe]] article. --[[User:BoogaLouie|BoogaLouie]] ([[User talk:BoogaLouie|talk]]) 16:59, 26 September 2009 (UTC)

== Unsourced material: &quot;Islamic Flag&quot; ==

Not only this so called &quot;Islamic Flag&quot; is out of place, but the whole description and meaning of it seem to be taken out of some B-movie involving a stereotypical plot about &quot;terrism&quot;. Either provide sources that it is indeed an &quot;Islamic Flag&quot; and that the description is true, or it will be deleted in accordance to '''[[WP:NOCITE]]'''. --[[User:Kray0n|Kray0n]] ([[User talk:Kray0n|talk]]) 11:18, 13 November 2009 (UTC)

== Islamism should be subsumed under the &quot;Left-Wing&quot; category ==

According to the same principles of notability and common agreement as applied to nazism being right-wing - popular tendency is to put islamism on the left wing of the political axis, and because Wikipedia is not a matter of original research, this tendency should result in Islamism actually being counted as left-wing on Wikipedia as well. The argument can be lifted verbatim from the article about nazism being right-wing. Maybe someone who knows the system here better can make the required changes, although I can provide references to individuals calling Islamism left-wing.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/158.143.136.254|158.143.136.254]] ([[User talk:158.143.136.254|talk]]) 21:31, 30 November 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:What? --[[User:BoogaLouie|BoogaLouie]] ([[User talk:BoogaLouie|talk]]) 19:31, 3 December 2009 (UTC)


==Trimming==

I [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Islamism&amp;diff=329507653&amp;oldid=329300267#Relation_between_Islam_and_Islamism trimmed] this from the [[Islamism#Relation between Islam and Islamism]] section 

&lt;blockquote&gt;Scholars like like [[Javed Ahmad Ghamidi]] have argued that all the actions of the Prophet Muhammad do not form an example for Muslims to follow, a sunnah. He holds that the da'wah (preaching and propagation) by a Messenger of God has targets defined by God and are specific to him. The role of the individual believer, the scholars and even a state with Muslim domination is different from that of a Prophet. The Prophet can after making the message clear to his addressees, under God's direction, fight the rejecters of the message. The Qur'an, after this stage in the Prophetic mission of Muhammad, did not leave the polythiests of Arabia with an option to live and adhere to polythiesm. They were to be executed if they did not enter Islam. This option is not available to any after the Prophet since no one can know who is rejecting the Message knowingly for no one is in a position to interact with God and no one receives revelation from Him.[http://www.al-mawrid.org/pages/dl.php?book_id=56 Political Canon of Islam] &lt;/blockquote&gt;

Reason: The article is already very long, the author is not particularly notable, and the text better belongs in [[Criticism of Islamism]] or [[Political aspects of Islam]]. --[[User:BoogaLouie|BoogaLouie]] ([[User talk:BoogaLouie|talk]]) 19:31, 3 December 2009 (UTC)


==Central figures==

An anon poster keesp adding [[Ismet Özel]] as a central figure of Islamism. He is an elected leader of a large country, but his he influential as an islamist? Does anyone have a source stating he is a central figure? In the mean time I'm deleting it again. --[[User:BoogaLouie|BoogaLouie]] ([[User talk:BoogaLouie|talk]]) 19:44, 16 December 2009 (UTC)
Whos saud Al Qaeda is Islamist, or have any relation with islam? Wikipedia in my eye is losing its respect, its so racist.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/92.96.110.121|92.96.110.121]] ([[User talk:92.96.110.121|talk]]) 12:55, 24 August 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Better Criticism Section Needed ==

Okay, this article is pretty dumb as it is.  It should be linked with other racist and imperialist terms like [[Cracker]] and [[White Trash]].  The criticism section should not be a criticism of &quot;Islamism&quot; as a movement, which doesn't exist, but a criticism of the simpletons who coined this term in the first place.  The word &quot;Islam&quot; itself means &quot;submission&quot;.  Sure, there are Islamic people -25 percent of the world, the world's fastest growing religion, etc....  But someone who subscribes to Islam is a &quot;Muslim&quot; -i.e., &quot;one who submits&quot;.  Okay, so some non-religionists and Christianists on Fox news and CNN use the term &quot;Islamist&quot; everday -doesn't mean its not a bigoted stereotype.  This article should not be deleted, but should be put in the category of stereotypes and hate-speech. Remember, as [[Edward Said]] points out, there is a long history of purposivly mislabeling Muslims -who were for centuries called &quot;Mohammedans&quot;, just as much of the media refused to call [[Cassius Clay]] by his real name [[Muhammad Ali]].  Lets rewrite the criticism section here and make sure readers know that this terms is a wilfull misrepresentation and not a description of anything at all.  [[User:Teetotaler|Teetotaler]] 5 January, 2010  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/75.67.81.197|75.67.81.197]] ([[User talk:75.67.81.197|talk]]) 17:51, 5 January 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:As the article says, [[al jazeera]] uses the term islamist. Are they simipletons and racists? --[[User:BoogaLouie|BoogaLouie]] ([[User talk:BoogaLouie|talk]]) 17:12, 12 January 2010 (UTC)

::African-Americans often use the term 'nigger' to refer to themselves, that doesnt stop the term from being an ethnic slur. Similiarly, al jazeera using the term islamist to refer to themselves doesnt validate the use of the term as a non-racist term. 203.128.4.254
:::What validates it's use as a non-racist term is that &quot;Islamism&quot; refers to a political movement, not a race. Aside from that do you think there is a difference between gangsta bad boy talk and one of the leading world news agencies? Do you think an influential political movement of Muhammad Iqbal, Jamal al-Din al-Afghani, Abul Ala Maududi, Sayyid Qutb, Hasan al-Banna, and Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini, deserves a term to describe it? --[[User:BoogaLouie|BoogaLouie]] ([[User talk:BoogaLouie|talk]]) 15:34, 22 February 2010 (UTC)
'''This is the talk page for discussing improvements to the Islamism article. 
This is not a forum for general discussion of the article's subject.''' --[[User:BoogaLouie|BoogaLouie]] ([[User talk:BoogaLouie|talk]]) 17:12, 12 January 2010 (UTC)

==edits by 95.147.234.97 in lead==

I deleted edits by 95.147.234.97 (and he has [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Islamism&amp;diff=347723371&amp;oldid=347723159 restored them]) as they are unsourced opinions, the topic (of diversity in Islam and Islamism) is already covered, and the article is already very long. --[[User:BoogaLouie|BoogaLouie]] ([[User talk:BoogaLouie|talk]]) 16:25, 4 March 2010 (UTC)

==Radical Islam==

Why does [[Radical Islam]] redirect here? Is there no way to distinguish violent Jihadists and the poltics of Al Queda from other more moderate Muslims? [[User:Bachcell|Bachcell]] ([[User talk:Bachcell|talk]]) 00:19, 19 March 2010 (UTC)
:(I fixed your link.) Because someone created it as a redirect to here, plain and simple. Should someone wish to turn Radical Islam into a separate article from this one, possibly as an offshoot of this one, then it will be otherwise. [[User:Largoplazo|—Largo Plazo]] ([[User talk:Largoplazo|talk]]) 03:04, 19 March 2010 (UTC)
This is racist, how come all the citations are from christian sources? HUH  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/92.96.110.121|92.96.110.121]] ([[User talk:92.96.110.121|talk]]) 12:51, 24 August 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
How about radical christianity and jewish?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/92.96.110.121|92.96.110.121]] ([[User talk:92.96.110.121|talk]]) 13:06, 24 August 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

If Islam is a universal and interracial religion, then it follows that any discussion, negative or otherwise, about it's spread throughout the world cannot be deemed &quot;racist&quot;. Logic trumps bias.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Gutumnbagem|Gutumnbagem]] ([[User talk:Gutumnbagem|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Gutumnbagem|contribs]]) 09:41, 8 January 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Accusations of Islamism==

An editor can't pull out a quote by someone, and accuse the quote of being Islamist. A reliable source needs to have made that allegation.

This is the same as pulling a quote from [[Daniel Pipes]], and putting it at [[Islamophobia]] as an example. A reliable source needs to have made the allegation.[[User:Bless sins|Bless sins]] ([[User talk:Bless sins|talk]]) 11:55, 26 March 2010 (UTC)


==&quot;Bigotry&quot; section==

Amanisa please stop putting [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Islamism&amp;diff=353280422&amp;oldid=353231700 this section] in the article. 
:''NYT: Bigotry in Islam, The Islamic world represses women, spawns terrorism, is prone to war, resists democracy and promotes bigotry against Jews (anti-semitism) [180], The Daily Telegraph: Islamic bigotry, In revealing that violent, intolerant prejudice continues to be preached, even by women, in centres of &quot;moderate Islam.&quot; [181] .... ''

This is an article about the political movement Islamism, not the religion Islam! Your text is not written in wikipedia format and not encyclopedic. --[[User:BoogaLouie|BoogaLouie]] ([[User talk:BoogaLouie|talk]]) 14:17, 2 April 2010 (UTC)

Please stop your edit war, it's highly relative.
This is about 'Islamic activism' AKA Political Islam, AKA Islamism.
It's written in encylopedic form, though some improvement can help...

Not sure I follow your '''real''' &quot;objection&quot;? Is it that you prefer us to insert this valuable information in the [[Islam]] page?

If you want more info about Islamic bigotry, we can provide more.

[[User:AmAnisa|AmAnisa]] ([[User talk:AmAnisa|talk]]) 23:38, 2 April 2010 (UTC)

:This is absurd. Edits must be [[WP:Consensus|based on consensus]]. [[User:AmAnisa|AmAnisa]] was bold[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Islamism&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=353630093&amp;oldid=353575225] (a [[WP:BOLD|good thing]]). [[User:BoogaLouie|BoogaLouie]] disagreed with the edits (meaning that no consensus existed) and so reverted the edits, requesting that the suggestions be posed on the talk page. That, as far as I can tell, is where we stand. AmAnisa, I have reverted your edits; please take your ideas to the talk page. Let's please avoid resorting to [[WP:DR|dispute resolution]].[[ User:dmyersturnbull | &amp;nbsp;&lt;font color=&quot;#005000&quot;&gt;dm&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#555555&quot;&gt;yers&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#005000&quot;&gt;t&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#555555&quot;&gt;urnbull&lt;/font&gt;&amp;nbsp; ]] ⇒ [[User_talk:Dmyersturnbull|talk]] 02:26, 3 April 2010 (UTC)

:Presently, [[User:AmAnisa|AmAnisa]]'s [[Islamism#Bigotry|section on bigotry]] remains.
:I object to the section for three primary reasons:
:1. It is not, to my knowledge, a significant component of Islamism, which is political Islam. [[User:BoogaLouie|BoogaLouie]] is correct; the section addresses bigotry used in conjunction with Islam, not any component of Islamism. The section never addresses Islamism, failing even to use the term. The second sub-section even begins by introducing &quot;Islamic bigotry&quot;. Meanwhile, the section fails to assert any relationship between Islamism and bigotry coupled with Islam.
:2. Your edit is entirely [[WP:NPOV|non-neutral]] and seems dedicated to painting Islamism in an overtly negative light. The quotations are entirely opinion, and your section uses [[WP:Avoid neologisms|neologisms]] such as &quot;jihadi&quot;. It reads almost like a this-is-why-I-think-Islam-is-bad section. I see no statistics, no facts, and no opposing perspectives.
:3. The citations are garbage. Editorials and random blogs do not constitute legitimate sources. Thanks to your edits, I now know who [[Mark Humphrey]] is, but his opinion on Islam is not relevant to an encyclopedic article on Islamism. Neither is [[Christopher Hitchens]]'s. With the possible exception of #197, not a single source is credible; they're all blogs and editorials.
:If you verify the relevance of bigotry in Islam to the Islamist movement using reliable secondary resources, I'll help add a section on bigotry. Until/unless an clear link is demonstrated by a legitimate source, I think it should be removed entirely.[[ User:dmyersturnbull | &amp;nbsp;&lt;font color=&quot;#005000&quot;&gt;dm&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#555555&quot;&gt;yers&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#005000&quot;&gt;t&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#555555&quot;&gt;urnbull&lt;/font&gt;&amp;nbsp; ]] ⇒ [[User_talk:Dmyersturnbull|talk]] 05:49, 5 April 2010 (UTC)
::Agree that the sources are not reliable. Also, I don't see the sources accusing Islamists directly (they make broad comments about Muslims and Arabs). Perhaps, with a lot of caution, this material can be moved to articles about the authors (to show what the author's opinions are of radical Islam, bigotry, racism, Arab-Israeli conflict etc).[[User:Bless sins|Bless sins]] ([[User talk:Bless sins|talk]]) 17:43, 5 April 2010 (UTC)
:::Good. Some of the referenced authors have WP entries already, including [[Mark Humphrey]] and [[Christopher Hitchens]], so their ideas on Islam and Islamism can be added there. Also, perhaps some the content, if properly cited, could be added to [[Criticism of Islamism]]. The new section has certainly trespassed on [[WP:POV|POV]] territory and does not comply with [[WP:CITE]].[[ User:dmyersturnbull | &amp;nbsp;&lt;font color=&quot;#005000&quot;&gt;dm&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#555555&quot;&gt;yers&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#005000&quot;&gt;t&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#555555&quot;&gt;urnbull&lt;/font&gt;&amp;nbsp; ]] ⇒ [[User_talk:Dmyersturnbull|talk]] 06:14, 9 April 2010 (UTC)
Guys, I don't see anything with criticizing the '''undisputed''' bigotry in Islam, that user did not post it in Islam, which makes it even more moderate and less contentious.
If someone has a problem with markhumphrey, still doesn't make it unreliable. why do the pro-Islamism keep on in the edit war while no consensus was reached?[[Special:Contributions/190.122.171.58|190.122.171.58]] ([[User talk:190.122.171.58|talk]]) 21:50, 18 April 2010 (UTC)
:Actually, it looks like consensus HAS been reached...see above. --[[User:N5iln|Alan]] ([[User talk:N5iln|talk]]) 00:50, 19 April 2010 (UTC)

AmAnisa has been blocked as a sock of [[User:Toothie3]]. It wouldnt surprise me if this IP were the same user. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 23:20, 18 April 2010 (UTC)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
:Yep. [[User:190.122.171.58|190.122.171.58]]'s very first edit[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Islamism&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=356715557] was re-adding the bigotry section, which happened immediately after [[User:User:AmAnisa|AmAnisa]]'s block. Its second edit[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:Islamism&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=356863072] was this comment. Its third edit[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Islamism&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=356863658] was re-adding the bigotry section, again. Looks awfully suspicious.[[ User:dmyersturnbull | &amp;nbsp;&lt;font color=&quot;#005000&quot;&gt;dm&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#555555&quot;&gt;yers&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#005000&quot;&gt;t&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#555555&quot;&gt;urnbull&lt;/font&gt;&amp;nbsp; ]] ⇒ [[User_talk:Dmyersturnbull|talk]] 17:24, 19 April 2010 (UTC)

== Request - Pakistan movement ==

This article does mention even smaller movements, but fails to mention the [[Pakistan movement]] and the resultant blood-soaked [[partition of India]]. Without doubt, Pakistan movement is one of the most quintessential pieces of islamism in all of history. I am not used to this editing stuff, so i request editors to please see to this. [[Special:Contributions/117.204.80.116|117.204.80.116]] ([[User talk:117.204.80.116|talk]]) 19:29, 1 July 2010 (UTC)

== Christianism, Islamism, Judaism ==

Hi, fine to use term like &quot;Islamism&quot; and &quot;Christianism&quot; to represent political movements within these religions, if we do the same also for &quot;Judaism&quot;, Buddhism&quot;, &quot;Hinduism&quot; etc.

However, you will notice that for other religions, the suffix &quot;-ism&quot; in no way carries a political connotation but rather describes the lump sum of religious content within the religion.  E.g. Judaism (V. 13.10.2010, 12:12) &quot;Judaism is the &quot;religion, philosophy, and way of life&quot; of the Jewish people.&quot;  And Buddhism: Buddhism is a religion and philosophy encompassing a variety of traditions, beliefs and practices, largely based on teachings attributed to Siddhartha Gautama, commonly known as the Buddha (Pāli/Sanskrit &quot;the awakened one&quot;).

By contrast Islamism: &quot;Islamism is a set of ideologies holding that Islam is not only a religion but also a political system, and that modern Muslims must return to their roots of their religion, and unite politically.&quot;  And &quot;Christianism&quot; as above.

Shouldn't we be more consistent in application of the suffix &quot;-ism&quot;? And preferably use it only to apply to a body of religious content, as opposed to political movements, to avoid confusion.

To be consistent I have also added this discussion to the &quot;Christianism&quot; page.

There is criticism i Islamism, and radical Islam, but no criticism in radical christianity, or christianism, Wikipedia is so racist and annoying  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/92.96.110.121|92.96.110.121]] ([[User talk:92.96.110.121|talk]]) 13:00, 24 August 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

--[[User:Musa Emre|Musa Emre]] ([[User talk:Musa Emre|talk]]) 10:35, 13 October 2010 (UTC)
:[[User:Musa Emre|Musa Emre]] - I see point.  Potentially someone with a negative POV regarding Islam wrote this lead.  What you really have to do though is find a variety of reliable sources on this issue and see how they define the word. [[User:NickCT|NickCT]] ([[User talk:NickCT|talk]]) 12:18, 13 October 2010 (UTC)

::Please see [[Islamism#History of usage]] for clarification. --[[User:BoogaLouie|BoogaLouie]] ([[User talk:BoogaLouie|talk]]) 20:39, 9 December 2010 (UTC)
::The English language is not always logical or consistent (Why &quot;rapist&quot; and not &quot;raper&quot;? Is rape an ideology with theorists?) The issue is that there is an ideology of Islamism and it needs a word, even if the people professing the ideology do not like the use of that word. --[[User:BoogaLouie|BoogaLouie]] ([[User talk:BoogaLouie|talk]]) 20:47, 9 December 2010 (UTC)
::I've restored a short paragraph in the lead that was deleted that contains the sentence &quot;Islamism is a controversial term and definitions of it sometimes vary.&quot; --[[User:BoogaLouie|BoogaLouie]] ([[User talk:BoogaLouie|talk]]) 20:54, 9 December 2010 (UTC)

== Contested word ==

The terms Islamist&quot;  and &quot;Islamism&quot; are problematical because:
--They are almost entirely used  by outside critics and are not accepted by their target. Therefore they are not neutral terms.
--They have no agreed on definitions
--They are most often used with progandistic intent.
Note the fact there is no term &quot;Christianist&quot; in common usage even though there is a similar (though much smaller) movement among Christians. This nonparallelism partly reflects the fact that speakers who use the term &quot;Islamist&quot; are overwhelmingly from Christianized countries. 
We do need a term for politically mobilized fundamentalist Islamic ideology, and unfortunately there is no alternative term that is in wide use.
At the very least this article needs a separate section pointing out how problematic these terms is. The section on &quot;relation with Islam&quot; touches on these issues but has the wrong header for such a discussion.
[[User:Burressd|Burressd]] ([[User talk:Burressd|talk]]) 18:54, 22 October 2010 (UTC)

:Please read [[Islamism#History of usage]], comment above and revised lead for clarification. --[[User:BoogaLouie|BoogaLouie]] ([[User talk:BoogaLouie|talk]]) 20:40, 9 December 2010 (UTC)

==Hizb ut-Tahrir ==
We need citations as to which cou ntires this group operates in.[[User:Slatersteven|Slatersteven]] ([[User talk:Slatersteven|talk]]) 16:35, 3 November 2010 (UTC)

==Weasel tag==
[[WP:Weasel]] tag was added in September 2010 but ther has been no specific discussion of what problem it refers to ...  unless you include complaints above (Christianism, Islamism, Judaism and Contested Word) about the term Islamism itself and there not being an eqivalent article on Christianism in wikipedia. --[[User:BoogaLouie|BoogaLouie]] ([[User talk:BoogaLouie|talk]]) 20:43, 9 December 2010 (UTC)

== Islamic fanaticism ==
Typed in &quot;islamic fanaticism&quot; and got redirected here... WTF????
--[[User:Spmoura|Spmoura]] ([[User talk:Spmoura|talk]]) 14:05, 7 March 2011 (UTC)

== There is no article yet about the 'green corridor' (in the Balkans) ==

Those possibly interested could base themselves upon this article written by Srđa Trifković ( http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sr%C4%91a_Trifkovi%C4%87 ) at http://gatesofvienna.blogspot.com/2009/05/green-corridor-in-balkans.html .

I'll also put a link to this suggestion on the discussion page at http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sr%C4%91a_Trifkovi%C4%87 .  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/173.208.90.139|173.208.90.139]] ([[User talk:173.208.90.139|talk]]) 07:44, 29 April 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Dialectical Logic of Islamists ==

'''Dialectical Logic of Islamists''' [http://www.FrankHatchiii.com/The_Lost.html (i.e., of the Lost)]:

''Dialectical logic'' is found in the core of Eastern and Western thought. It is a common flaw to the human species. Although the various human cultures have developed their own methods of using this flaw, it is not simply a cultural defect. However, since each culture uses this flaw to to defend and to define itself, every attempt to correct the flaw is perceived to be an attack on the culture itself. '''Islamists''' are particularly sensitive to this perceived attack; because the dialectical Absolute of the Koran is found in the attempt to synthesize the Old and New Testaments [http://www.FrankHatchiii.com/Mayor.html (i.e., &quot;the Book&quot;)].
--[[User:FinalNotice|FinalNotice]] ([[User talk:FinalNotice|talk]]) 19:16, 13 May 2011 (UTC)
==File:Portrait of Imam Khomeini.jpg Nominated for speedy Deletion==
&lt;!--TSTAMP:{{{4}}}--&gt;
{|
|-
| [[File:Image-x-generic.svg|100px]] 
| &lt;!--IMAGES--&gt;
An image used in this article, [[:File:Portrait of Imam Khomeini.jpg|File:Portrait of Imam Khomeini.jpg]], has been nominated for speedy deletion for the following reason: ''All Wikipedia files with unknown copyright status'' 
&lt;!--/IMAGES--&gt;
;What should I do?
''Don't panic''; you should have time to contest the deletion (although please review [[WP:CSD|deletion guidelines]] before doing so). The best way to contest this form of deletion is by posting on the image talk page.
* If the image is [[WP:NFCC|non-free]] then you may need to provide a [[WP:FUR|fair use rationale]]
* If the image isn't freely licensed and there is no fair use rationale, then it cannot be uploaded or used.
* If the image has already been deleted you may want to try [[WP:DRV|Deletion Review]]

''This notification is provided by a Bot'' --[[User:CommonsNotificationBot|CommonsNotificationBot]] ([[User talk:CommonsNotificationBot|talk]]) 13:02, 3 November 2011 (UTC)
|}

== updating needed ==

The article should include recent developments of the Arab Spring ... admittedly still in progress. --[[User:BoogaLouie|BoogaLouie]] ([[User talk:BoogaLouie|talk]]) 00:06, 10 November 2011 (UTC)

== Does it really exist? ==
I found a text that questions the whole existence of islamism, saying that islam and islamism are actually the same thing.[http://www.jihadwatch.org/2011/09/islam-versus-islamism----a-distinction-without-a-difference-1.html] I think that the source is not quite good enough, but once someone finds a better one, it could be included in the article as a criticism. A parallel: If someone heavily or even violently supports democracy, then is he a democraticist whose idea is democraticism, or is he simply a democrat? --[[User:Uikku|Uikku]] ([[User talk:Uikku|talk]]) 21:05, 12 December 2011 (UTC)
::Its as real as Christianism, i.e. no it doesn't really exist in any real sense. Yes people of the Islamic faith also form governments, and just like every other religion, their values system and moral framework influence their politics. Not that I think this article shouldn't be here. Wikipedia is all about hair thin distinctions and the separation of these isms comes from the secular crowd I think.[[User:Drunkenduncan|Drunkenduncan]] ([[User talk:Drunkenduncan|talk]]) 00:33, 27 January 2012 (UTC)

== islamist is now a common and accepted designation for politically active religious Muslims ==

Islamism is a concocted term by various Orientalists, neo cons and Israelis.  Islamists on the other hand which started out as a derogatory term has now changed and become normative for describing Islamic activists esp in Arab spring revolutions in Egypt, Libya, and Tunisia.
This redirection to Islamism should be stopped and islamist should have its own page along with links to the islamic activists and movements involved in the Arab spring revolutions.  For example islamist.com seems to be a pro islamist news web site (http://www.islamist.com/index.php[http://www.islamist.com/index.php http://www.islamist.com])  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Wholetruth123|Wholetruth123]] ([[User talk:Wholetruth123|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Wholetruth123|contribs]]) 19:33, 3 February 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:we have to have a reliable source [[WP:RS]] saying the term was &quot;concocted by various Orientalists, neo cons and Israelis&quot;. The article does state that Islamism is a &quot;controversial term&quot;, and it deals with the controversy:
&lt;Blockquote&gt;The concept ''Islamism'' is controversial, not just because it posits a political role for Islam, but also because its supporters believe their views merely reflect Islam, while the contrary idea that Islam is, or can be, apolitical is an error. Scholars and observers who do not believe that Islam is a political ideology include [[Fred Halliday]], [[John Esposito]] and Muslim intellectuals like [[Javed Ahmad Ghamidi]].&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;

Islamists have asked the question, &quot;If Islam is a way of life, how can we say that those who want to live by its principles in legal, social, political, economic, and political spheres of life are not Muslims, but Islamists and believe in Islamism, not [just] Islam?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Abid Ullah Jan]], [http://web.archive.org/web/20060406064405/http://www.aljazeerah.info/Opinion+editorials/2006+Opinion+Editorials/February/27o/Wikipedia+Good+Intentions,+Horrible+Consequences+By+Abid+Uallah+Jan.htm Wikipedia: Good Intentions, Horrible Consequences], Al-Jazeerah Op-Ed, 27 February 2006. (archive.org accessed 2007-10-24).&lt;/ref&gt;  Similarly, a writer for the [[International Crisis Group]] maintains that &quot;the conception of 'political Islam'&quot; is a creation of Americans to explain the [[Iranian Revolution|Iranian Islamic Revolution]]. In reality, apolitical Islam was an historical fluke of the &quot;shortlived heyday of secular Arab nationalism between 1945 and 1970,&quot; and it is [[Political quietism|quietist]]/non-political Islam, not Islamism, that requires explanation.&lt;ref name=&quot;ICGUnderstandingIslam&quot;&gt;[http://www.crisisgroup.org/en/regions/middle-east-north-africa/north-africa/037-understanding-islamism.aspx Understanding Islamism] Middle East/North Africa Report N°37 2 March 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;

On the other hand, Muslim-owned and run media (not just Western media) have used the terms &quot;Islamist&quot; and &quot;Islamism&quot; — as distinguished from Muslim and Islam — to distinguish groups such as the [[Islamic Salvation Front]] in Algeria&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/NR/exeres/23E2EB3C-7B4F-4447-80CD-26EDAFEF18E8.htm Algerian group joins al-Qaeda brand]&lt;/ref&gt; or [[al-Gama'a al-Islamiyya|Jamaa Islamiya]] in Egypt,&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated4&quot;&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/archive/2006/04/200841010710321761.html Egypt frees 900 Islamist militants]&lt;/ref&gt; which actively seek to implement Islamic law, from mainstream Muslim groups.

Another source distinguishes Islamist from Islamic &quot;by the fact that the latter refers to a religion and culture in existence over a millennium, whereas the first is a political/religious phenomenon linked to the great events of the 20th century&quot;. Islamists have, at least at times, defined themselves as &quot;Islamiyyoun/Islamists&quot; to differentiate themselves from &quot;Muslimun/Muslims&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Final Report of the National Commission on Terrorist Attacks Upon the United States, The 9/11 Commission Report'', W.W. Norton &amp; Company, New York, (2004), p.562&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/Blockquote&gt; --[[User:BoogaLouie|BoogaLouie]] ([[User talk:BoogaLouie|talk]]) 18:20, 6 February 2012 (UTC)&lt;p&gt;

I see many references in Islamic movements news and some literature referring to themselves as Islamist. I see none refer to their thinking as Islamism. Booga I checked all your references above except Abidullah Jan which the link was not working. The only mention of Islamism was in the International crisis group which is yet another neo con hydra and is not an Islamist or Muslim site.  Booga, please clarify your terms and distinguish between the usage of Islamist and Islamism.  Do not be evasive in referring to both while the citation only refers to Islamist. Booga could you give us some citations of Islamic movements referring to Islamism as an ideology?. &lt;p&gt;
As a quick [http://www.google.com/search?q=islamist+site%3Aikhwanweb.com&amp;hl=en&amp;tbo=1&amp;biw=1321&amp;bih=812&amp;num=10&amp;lr=&amp;ft=i&amp;cr=&amp;safe=images search for Islamist on Ikhwanweb.com via google] generates 97,600 hits with numerous references in self descriptions of Islamic political parties identifying themselves as Islamist.  [http://www.ikhwanweb.com/article.php?id=29408 Why Islamists Are Better Democrats - Ikhwanweb] or [http://www.ikhwanweb.com/article.php?id=28459 Tunisia's Islamist Nahda Wins Impressive Landslide Victory]
&lt;p&gt;The term Islamist and Islamism are distinct and different.  Islamist is how Islamic political movements describe themselves while Islamism is a term used primarily by their detractors. Therefore The wiki entry for Islamist should not be redirected to Islamism. Free speech and free debate should prevail.&lt;p&gt;
[[User:Wholetruth123|Wholetruth123]] ([[User talk:Wholetruth123|talk]]) 22:29, 14 February 2012 (UTC)

=== islamist should not be redirected to islamism ===


@shadihamid Shadi Hamid
I don't get why ppl have such a problem w- the word &quot;Islamist.&quot; That's what (most) Islamists call themselves. There's no btr alternative.

Director of Research at the Brookings Doha Center &amp; Fellow at the Saban Center for Middle East Policy at the Brookings Institution. Shamid [at] Brookings.edu. Http://www.brookings.edu/experts/hamids.aspx  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/75.19.161.171|75.19.161.171]] ([[User talk:75.19.161.171|talk]]) 07:43, 6 February 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:English is a very hard language for non-native speakers.  I will try to explain.
:*'''Islamism''' is a noun for describing an abstract political concept - like national socialism or communism.  Nobody would stand up and say, &quot;I am a communism!&quot;, though they might say, &quot;I am a communist.&quot;
:*'''Islamist''' is both a noun and an adjective.
::*As an adjective, it is correct to refer to islamist beliefs (&quot;Islamist&quot; being the adjective, and &quot;Beliefs&quot; the noun).  There are also adjectives &quot;national socialist&quot; and &quot;communist&quot;.
::*As a noun, it refers to people.  Someone can be a communist, or a national socialist, or an islamist.  It is wrong, to use this noun to refer to an abstract political concept.
:--[[User:Toddy1|Toddy1]] ([[User talk:Toddy1|talk]]) 16:33, 18 February 2012 (UTC)

::Toddy, Thank you kindly for your lecture on basic English. I am a native speaker having grown up in Michigan.  Kindly avoid such insulting comments.  The term Islamism is a concoction used typically by various neo con think tank types along with various Orientalists.  Islamist are Muslims who are active in the political arena. There is no such thing as Islamism as far as the Muslims are concerned. It is is simply Islam which encompasses both personal religious observations and  societal obligations to establish equity and Justice (Islamic term ::[[Adl]]). &lt;p&gt;
::The redirect of Islamists to Islamism is similar to redirecting African Americans to nigger.  It is highly biased and insulting. Complete depiction of the entire movement of political Islam (Islamist) using a term derived from their opposition (Islamism) is very biased and unbalanced.
::&lt;p&gt;
::[[User:Wholetruth123|Wholetruth123]] ([[User talk:Wholetruth123|talk]]) 16:33, 20 February 2012 (UTC)&lt;p&gt;
:::I am sorry.  I had seen some of your comments and deleted contributions, and assumed that you were probably a Palestinian, for whom English was a foreign language, making edits in good faith.  I see now that I was entirely wrong in my assumptions about you.  Please accept my apologies.--[[User:Toddy1|Toddy1]] ([[User talk:Toddy1|talk]]) 20:23, 20 February 2012 (UTC)
&lt;p&gt;
Toddy, appreciate the kind word. I am trying in all good faith to get this redirect of Islamist to Islamism stopped and have an independent page for Islamist where it can cover some of the movements involved in the Arab spring revolutions.  I strongly feel that many wiki readers would benefit from a frank look at the workings of Islamist parties in the middle east with both pro and con viewpoints clearly elucidated. The Islamism entry can stay and the debate on Islamism can stay as it is.&lt;p&gt;
Which editor or editors can undo the redirect?&lt;p&gt;
[[User:Wholetruth123|Wholetruth123]] ([[User talk:Wholetruth123|talk]]) 20:39, 20 February 2012 (UTC)
:There is a pattern:
:*[[Communist]] redirects to communism.
:*[[Marxist]] redirects to Marxism.
:*[[Socialist]] redirects to socialism.
:*[[National socialist]] redirects to Nazism.
:*[[Conservative]] redirects to conservatism.
:*[[Capitalist]] redirects to capitalism.
:*[[Islamist]] redirects to Islamism.
:--[[User:Toddy1|Toddy1]] ([[User talk:Toddy1|talk]]) 19:05, 21 February 2012 (UTC)
&lt;p&gt;
So following your logic stupid should be redirected to stupidism?&lt;p&gt;
Islamism is not an ism. On the other hand there are clearly people who are Islamists.  Islamist generally describes politically active people following the Islamic faith.  Islamism is like the term Mohammedanism which was constructed by 19th century orientalists looking to justify European colonial rules and policies.  Islamism is a construct of the same modern day Orientalists as the old Imperial orientalists who coined the term Mohammedanism&lt;p&gt;
Another way to explain it is to redirect Christ to Christism. Christism is an artificial construct and no Christians refer to themselves as following Christism.
WT
[[User:Wholetruth123|Wholetruth123]] ([[User talk:Wholetruth123|talk]]) 23:02, 28 February 2012 (UTC)
And the N word simply means  black. Same way a sombrero means a hat?  The term Islamist is derogatory for Muslims. We don't like it. You cannot seperate the Rules of the Shariah from the lives on a Muslim. Granted that there are some Muslims that do not adhere to it totally but that does not mean that those who do are now &quot;Islamists&quot;. It just means they are more practicing Muslims. I'm surprised this hasn't caused more of a stir yet.
[[User:BrYounus|BrYounus]] ([[User talk:BrYounus|talk]]) 21:11, 4 July 2012 (UTC)

&lt;BR&gt;&lt;BR&gt;This statement
&quot;In reality, apolitical Islam was an historical fluke of the &quot;shortlived heyday of secular Arab nationalism between 1945 and 1970,&quot; and it is quietist/non-political Islam, not Islamism, that requires explanation&quot;
has no place in a Wikipedia article. Please remove it or provide evidence of the said condition. (A reference is not evidence.)
[[User:SirteP|SirteP]] ([[User talk:SirteP|talk]]) 15:39, 28 October 2012 (UTC)

== Misleading title. ==

Islam by nature is political so why the need for Islamism title. [[User:Giftanodegiftanode|Giftanodegiftanode]] ([[User talk:Giftanodegiftanode|talk]]) 22:22, 3 August 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>krredj3xl4sgdh57as21loefvruastb</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
