<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Laity</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2814210</id>
    <revision>
      <id>498528675</id>
      <parentid>494211494</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-20T17:43:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Felix Folio Secundus</username>
        <id>6547367</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rating</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7448">{{talk header|noarchive=yes}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell |1=
 {{WikiProject Religion|class=start|importance=Top}}
 {{WikiProject Christianity |class= start |importance= Mid 
  |anglicanism= yes |anglicanism-importance=Low 
  |catholicism= yes |catholicism-importance=Low  
  |latter-day-saint-movement= yes |latter-day-saint-movement-importance=low
  |methodism-work-group= yes |methodism-importance=Low 
 }}
}}

== Divide article? ==

Since &quot;laity&quot; means two completely different things, I think we should cut up the article in two (one referring to the  reigious meaning, the other the common meaning)

--[[User:Msoos|Msoos]] 08:00, 2 October 2005 (UTC)

i also agree that this should be divided

::What other meaning? I am glad to build a disambiguation page, but I don't know any other meaning besides this one. Give me a source or two to read and I'm glad to help with this. [[User:Sarum blue|Sarum blue]] 17:04, 24 April 2006 (UTC)

:::I also think that if changes are to be made, it should be mentioned that while the expression &quot;lay people&quot; is often used in common speech, the word &quot;laity&quot; itself is not, and is still mostly restricted to its religious meaning. [[User:Loganberry|Loganberry]] ([[User talk:Loganberry|Talk]]) 02:34, 5 September 2006 (UTC)

== Any place for mention of groups that don't distinguish? ==

I don't want to clutter up the article with irrelevancies, so I won't make an addition on this topic myself. However, I'd like to raise the point that in some Christian groups, the concept of &quot;the priesthood of all believers&quot; (based on a biblical text) causes them to resist making a clergy/laity distinction. In the [[Church of Christ]], as one example, a congregational may have one or more minister (often paid by the congregation), but there is an understanding that any believer &amp;mdash; most commonly restricted to any ''male'' believer, however &amp;mdash; has an equal authority. [[Mormonism]], on the other hand, officially rejects having a paid preacher at all and seems to have no office clearly corresponding to that of priest, though they have elders, bishops, and at the top level, apostles. It seems a topic that should at least be touched on, but I've no clue how to do it without seeming to take the article down a tangent. [[User:Lawikitejana|Lawikitejana]] 02:15, 10 September 2006 (UTC)

:This does seem to be a problem for this article. The claim that in Anglicanism, the three orders are priests, deacons and lay ministers is misguided; Anglicanism observes the traditional three orders of bishops, priests and deacons; lay ministers are not consecrated in the same way as ordained ministers. However, Anglicanism is still moderately supportive of the idea of the 'priesthood of all believers', and the article correctly notes the important role of laity in synodical government. [[User:AlexTiefling|AlexTiefling]] 21:27, 3 October 2007 (UTC)

== Roman Catholic history ==
The history of the laity is not historically accurate, but I don't have many sources at my fingertips. This section is also simplistic, and the shifting role of the laity is pretty complex... [[User:Freder1ck|Freder1ck]] 00:02, 11 November 2006 (UTC)Freder1ck
:: When I get a chance, I want to incorporate the following bit into the section: Catechism of the Catholic Church 1268 The baptized have become &quot;living stones&quot; to be &quot;built into a spiritual house, to be a holy priesthood.&quot;74 By Baptism they share in the priesthood of Christ, in his prophetic and royal mission. They are &quot;a chosen race, a royal priesthood, a holy nation, God's own people, that [they] may declare the wonderful deeds of him who called [them] out of darkness into his marvelous light.&quot;75 Baptism gives a share in the common priesthood of all believers.1268 The baptized have become &quot;living stones&quot; to be &quot;built into a spiritual house, to be a holy priesthood.&quot;74 By Baptism they share in the priesthood of Christ, in his prophetic and royal mission. They are &quot;a chosen race, a royal priesthood, a holy nation, God's own people, that [they] may declare the wonderful deeds of him who called [them] out of darkness into his marvelous light.&quot;75 Baptism gives a share in the common priesthood of all believers.
::: The Catholic understanding of the common priesthood of the baptised is not new, but ancient. It's also found in the 1917 Catholic Encyclopedia: [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/08748a.htm|Laity] [[User:Freder1ck|Freder1ck]] 16:34, 12 November 2006 (UTC)Freder1ck
:::: I've made some changes, but the paragraph following the blockquote still needs work. Also, I think it's valuable to directly block quote from LG 31 as the passage succintly synthesizes a broad Catholic perspective on the laity. [[User:Freder1ck|Freder1ck]] 14:29, 30 November 2006 (UTC)Freder1ck


oi oi is there any famous laity christians please cos i dont want to get shot by ma r.e teacher lol cos i cant find any usefull information on any laity christians and what they have done usefull to help others cheerz  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/79.67.197.74|79.67.197.74]] ([[User talk:79.67.197.74|talk]]) 12:53, 3 February 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Wrong order? (no pun intended....) ==

(OK, the pun was not intended in advance, but I am suffering it to remain after I noticed it.)
: 
The article says:
: 
::: lay persons, bishops, priests, and deacons
: 
One is ''first'' (chronologically) a lay person, ''then'' a deacon, ''then'' a priest, and ''finally'' a bishop.  In that order.  So it would seem natural to list them in that order, especially when one applies ordinal numbers to them, speaking of a &quot;fourth order&quot;.  [[User:Michael Hardy|Michael Hardy]] ([[User talk:Michael Hardy|talk]]) 04:25, 6 June 2008 (UTC)

==Pay, pray and obey==
There should be some dissertation on the slogan ''Pay, pray and obey'', commonly used by reformers, which denotes the previous ecclesiology of Leo XIII. This ecclesiology was eventually ''upgraded'' during the Second Vatican Council. (cf ([http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0MKY/is_7_29/ai_n13681061]) [[User:ADM|ADM]] ([[User talk:ADM|talk]]) 01:29, 31 January 2009 (UTC)

==Super-laity==
Another issue that could be included in the article is the notion of super-laity, laypeople who become so integrated to the ecclesial structure that they begin to think and act like clerical bureaucrats. This issue has been discussed in certain European Catholic publications. [http://eucharistiemisericor.free.fr/index.php?page=2501083_obeissance] [[User:ADM|ADM]] ([[User talk:ADM|talk]]) 05:43, 30 April 2009 (UTC)

== lay man ==

I see no link to [[Layman]] which seems a later, derived but related concept - seems to expand the religous aspect to cover other actual activity that is not officially endorsed. [[user:leevanjackson|L&amp;there4;V]] 14:53, 1 August 2009 (UTC)

The block of text added in this diff doesn't really belong.  I'm adding to Talk: for completeness, and to .  Appeals to etymology over current usage, it doesn't flow with whole text, etc.
http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Laity&amp;diff=344725476  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:YhnMzw|YhnMzw]] ([[User talk:YhnMzw|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/YhnMzw|contribs]]) 08:48, 5 May 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;</text>
      <sha1>5ujwvw3g2ucaegtn99xg6ai44zm3yjv</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
