<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Dispensationalism</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>322217</id>
    <revision>
      <id>484495038</id>
      <parentid>484460755</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-03-29T05:41:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MiszaBot I</username>
        <id>3797869</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Archiving 1 thread(s) (older than 100d) to [[Talk:Dispensationalism/Archive 2]].</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8477">{{Talk header|noarchive=yes}}
{{not a forum|personal beliefs, nor for engaging in [[Apologetics]]/[[Polemic]]s}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell |1= 
{{WikiProject Christianity |class=C |importance=High |theology-work-group=yes |theology-importance= |latter-day-saint-movement=yes |latter-day-saint-movement-importance= mid}}
{{WikiProject Religion |class=C |importance=Low |NRM=yes |NRMImp=High }}
}}
{{archives |search=yes }}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 2
|minthreadsleft = 4
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|algo = old(100d)
|archive = Talk:Dispensationalism/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Auto archiving notice |bot=MiszaBot I |age=100}}

== Regarding the &quot;Start of the Church Age&quot; and Dispensationalism History Chart ==

Here is a quote from Darby showing he held to the church beginning at Pentecost (Acts 2):

In the Ephesians, however, when the body is fully spoken of, the apostle refers to the elect saints, who are created again in Christ Jesus, and are sealed for the day of redemption; that is, united to the Head, as God knows it; quickened, raised, and seated in heavenly places in Christ the Head. That which was wrought this unity is the baptism of the Holy Ghost, under which the elect and manifested remnant were brought on the day of Pentecost. (''The House of God; The Body of Christ; and the Baptism of the Holy Ghost,'' The Collected Writings of J. N. Darby, Vol. 14, pages 24-25 (1860).

Therefore Darby cannot be regarded as a &quot;Mid-Acts&quot; proponent. The statement and the chart should be changed to reflect this. [[User:Lamorak|Lamorak]] ([[User talk:Lamorak|talk]]) 16:16, 19 July 2011 (UTC)

:Please re-read Darby's (admittedly, as always, rambling) writing (my bolding added).  &quot;The first great element promised in scripture, and given after the exaltation of Jesus, was the baptism of the Holy Ghost. The assembly being now formed, the Lord added to it daily the remnant of Israel whom He was sparing from judgment. Hereafter they will form the '''body of Israel''' itself&quot;.  &quot;the assembly of God was ... not yet brought out ...that Jews and Gentiles should form one body without distinction.&quot; &quot;They are together as stones in a building, and as a priesthood; but it is not a body growing in itself with joints of supply.&quot; [[http://www.plymouthbrethren.org/article/10912|''The House of God; The Body of Christ; and the Baptism of the Holy Ghost,'' The Collected Writings of J. N. Darby, Vol. 14, pages 24-25 (1860)]]  &quot;Stephen formed the link between Jewish rejection and the position and state of the church which followed...Stephen was the closing of the Jewish ‘possibility of the dispensation.' But a new scene now opens—the regular Gentile form and order of the dispensation in the hands of the apostle Paul, the apostle of the uncircumcision, the apostle of the Gentiles. Did he then derive it from the apostles? or was he indeed a successor to our Lord by earthly appointment and derivation? No; in no wise.&quot; [[http://www.plymouthbrethren.org/article/10884|The Collected Writings Of J. N. Darby, Ecclesiastical No. 1, Volume 1: The Character Of Office In The Present Dispensation]].  The chart should be changed to reflect this [[User:Duke Ganote|Duke Ganote]] ([[User talk:Duke Ganote|talk]]) 12:02, 25 July 2011 (UTC)

::The quotes don't really address the issue. A Mid-Acts advocate would never say that the church began on Acts 2 and the day of Pentecost. Yet Darby's quote is quite clear in stating that the beginning of the church is in Acts 2. Its not the only quote - Darby stated this Acts 2 view multiple times in his writings. Also scholars and writers on the history of dispensationalism do not think Darby originated the Mid-Acts view. They think Bullinger originated the Mid-Acts view, since he was clearly the first to write about it. [[User:Lamorak|Lamorak]] ([[User talk:Lamorak|talk]]) 03:40, 28 July 2011 (UTC)

:::I think that's the fine grained distinction, the difference between the then-church/&quot;body of Israel&quot; (Matthew 16; Acts 2) and the now-church/&quot;body of Christ&quot; (mid-Acts) wherein conversion to Judaism is neither presumed nor essential.  Do you have references for the &quot;scholars and writers on the history of dispensationalism&quot; you're thinking of? I've read a few; the Larry V. Crutchfield quote is the clearest; the others I've read are vague on the point.  (I'm beginning to be skeptical that many people have read Darby; not that I blame them, Darby certainly makes the apostle Paul look like the epitome of brevity.)[[User:Duke Ganote|Duke Ganote]] ([[User talk:Duke Ganote|talk]]) 13:26, 28 July 2011 (UTC)

== Comparisons with &quot;Roman&quot; Catholic ==

Catholics mostly believe the same thing: those based in Rome, Anglicans/Episcopals, Orthodox Christians, and often Lutherans, when it comes to general stuff like &quot;dispensationalism.&quot; Not sure why &quot;Roman Catholics&quot; are singled out here. [[User:Student7|Student7]] ([[User talk:Student7|talk]]) 12:49, 15 October 2011 (UTC)
: What are you talking about? The churches you just mentioned do not subscribe to dispensationalism. --'''[[User:Confession0791|Confession0791]]''' '''[[User_talk:Confession0791|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]]''' 14:31, 15 October 2011 (UTC)

::Exactly. Which is why I just removed Catholics from the article. Catholics believe the same as most Christians on this issue: They don't subscribe to dispensationalism. Nor should they be singled out for treatment on this issue, one way or another, without involving all the other churches, as well. Nor did the reference(s) support that idea. [[User:Student7|Student7]] ([[User talk:Student7|talk]]) 21:24, 18 October 2011 (UTC)

== Unsourced material ==

Certain statements have recently been added which appear to be interpretations of the Bible by the editor without support from a [[WP:RS|reliable source]].
:&quot;However, this view and others following do not agree with Stephen's inspired and authoritative statement (Acts 7:38) that the 'church', as the 'assembly' of God's people has been in existence from, at least, the wilderness wanderings - the same 'God's people' brought out of Egypt.&quot;
The only support offered for this statement is the following statement which also appears to be the work of the editor:
:&quot;Stephen’s defence before the Sanhedrin. Notably, the Scriptures indicate that Stephen did great wonders and miraculous signs, and was a man full of God's grace and power of the Spirit and wisdom (Acts 6:3, 5, 8, 15). Given Stephen’s character and spiritual disposition his inspired understanding of the nature of the Church remains authoritative and unassailable by any ancient or modern theories of the Church’s origin and make-up. Consequently, the idea of a post-resurrection 'start of the church/church age' remains a misnomer to those who hold to Stephen's perspective.&quot;
The problem is that there is only a primary source, the Bible, and this interpretation of it by editor. The Bible itself is not a reliable source for anything except it's exact wording. Any interpretations of the Bible such as the authority of Stephen or whether the statements of Stephen even relate to Dispensationalism, require a reliable source that interprets the bible in this way. Editor's own opinions and interpretations of primary sources, i.e. original research, are inappropriate.

Unless someone can provide reliable secondary sources that make these interpretations of the Bible, these edits should be removed. &lt;font color=&quot;#500000&quot;&gt;[[User:Jojalozzo|Joja]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#005000&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Jojalozzo|lozzo]]&lt;/font&gt; 01:53, 25 October 2011 (UTC)

== Request for plain english in introduction ==

The introductory sentence is unintelligible... &quot;Dispensationalism is a nineteenth-century evangelical development based on a futurist biblical hermeneutic that sees a series of chronologically successive &quot;dispensations&quot; or periods in history in which God relates to human beings in different ways under different Biblical covenants.&quot; 

I plugged it into an online Flesch-Kincaid Reading test at readability-score.com. A good score is 90-100. A bad score is 30 or below. This sentence got a readability score of *negative* 28.  Anyone want to rewrite?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/115.70.41.254|115.70.41.254]] ([[User talk:115.70.41.254|talk]]) 00:07, 29 March 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;</text>
      <sha1>saoj1mdb4s4sa367hs4jpomzmx47dhd</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
