<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Easter</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>39708</id>
    <revision>
      <id>499669921</id>
      <parentid>496557560</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-27T22:30:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>75.73.114.111</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* No NPOV Tag Allowed on Article on Threat of Block */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="86470">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Christianity|class=B|importance=top|core-topics-work-group = yes|core-topics-importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Holidays|class=B|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=B|importance=Top}}
}}
{{onlinesource|year=2004|section=April 2004 (28 articles)
|title=Who knew: Bunnies &amp; bilbies.
|org=Dallas Morning News
|date=April 8, 2004
|url=http://www.dallasnews.com/sharedcontent/dws/fea/breakroom/stories/040804brwhoknew.1011aff4a.html}}
{{OnThisDay |date1=2005-03-27|oldid1=16334956|date2=2005-05-01|oldid2=16335189|date3=2006-04-16|oldid3=48688594|date4=2006-04-23|oldid4=49522071|date5=2007-04-08|oldid5=121212400|date6=2008-03-23|oldid6=200242596|date7=2008-04-27|oldid7=208444519|date8=2009-04-12|oldid8=283317436|date9=2009-04-19|oldid9=284807032|date10=2010-04-04|oldid10=353671900|date11=2011-04-24|oldid11=425605379|date12=2012-04-08|oldid12=486177685|date13=2012-04-15|oldid13=487339150}}
{{splitfrom|page=Easter customs|date=15 November 2010}}
{{archive box|
#[[/Archive 1|through June 2006]]
#[[/Archive 2|July 2006 to –––]]
#[[/Archive 3]]
#[[/Archive 4]]
#[[/Archive 5]]
#[[/Archive 6]] (2011)
}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{talkarchivenav|noredlinks=y}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 6
|minthreadsleft = 3
|algo = old(60d)
|archive = Talk:Easter/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Auto archiving notice |bot=MiszaBot I |age=60 |small=yes |dounreplied=yes}}

== Request for Comment regarding NPOV, UNDUE, NOR, IRS and possibly other issues relating to balance of Christian/pagan/secular elements of holiday ==

Debate and disagreement regarding Christian/pagan/secular issues relating the subject cannot be resolved and the community at large is asked to please contribute to discussion. — '''[[User:FoxCE|&lt;font face=&quot;Lucida Fax&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#990000&quot;&gt;FoxCE&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]]''' &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:FoxCE|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/FoxCE|contribs]])&lt;/small&gt; 22:25, 5 April 2012 (UTC)

:&lt;s&gt;This article has shown a long pattern of rejecting material not specifically handling Jesus or Christianity. Note that it almost entirely avoids any mention of secular Easter in favor of a strictly Christian interpretation. Users policing the holiday have recently rejected a cited, scholarly reference to the revival of veneration of Ēostre among some Germanic neopagan groups. Let's be clear: Ēostre, Paschal season (which combined with Ēostre-month to produce Old English Christian ''Ēostre''—yes, the same noun as the goddess name—leading to a series of linguistic changes that became modern ''Easter''), and modern secular celebrations are what make up modern ''Easter'', it is not solely a Christian celebration with no earlier history. Indeed, it appears that this desire to keep this article solely about the Christian event is not unintentional, as the talk page makes clear, and a summary of the etymology section that I've tried to add to the lead has been repeatedly reverted (with the reasoning that an unqualified internal link is enough). I suspect a strong ideologic bias at work here. Again, for many Easter consists of little more than chocolate rabbits, grassy baskets, and an egg hunt. This article does not reflect this reality.&lt;/s&gt; [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 23:06, 5 April 2012 (UTC)

::''Wait, wait, scratch that!'' Because ''I've also'' gotten the nothing-but-Jesus-in-my-Wikipedia-Easter-article fever! But between you and me there's some stuff we should be concerned about, so keep this stuff under wraps, will you? Well, see, there's these articles on Easter-related customs from Watts's ''Encyclopedia of American Folklore'' discussing those cursed secular components of Easter with some comments about pre-Christian origins of certain customs, which we have thus far fortunately managed to nearly completely bar from the article:
::* Watts, Linda S. (2007). ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=2dce6_CA76MC&amp;pg=PA122&amp;dq=secular+easter+customs&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=Ok9-T__nCob-9QTYutHjDg&amp;ved=0CDsQ6AEwADgK#v=onepage&amp;q=secular%20easter%20customs&amp;f=false Encyclopedia of American Folklore]''. Infobase Publishing.
::Here is another reliable source discussing the wretched fact that Easter is actually a dualistic holiday celebrated by both Christians and the secular; &quot;[Easter] is also a secular event in which the children of Christian and non-Christian families participate in Easter egg hunts and receive baskets of candy from the Easter Bunny. Often, non-Christians also spend the day with their family by sharing a meal.&quot;
::The source then goes on to discuss the Easter Bunny and Easter egg hunt, argh! Curse those pesky non-Christian customs sneaking up on our Jesus-filled Wikipedia article!
::* Duchak, Alicia (1999). ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=qWkoF8eJ07kC&amp;pg=PA99&amp;dq=secular+easter+customs&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=2k5-T-CJBZOW8gTe6qWLDg&amp;ved=0CEUQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=secular%20easter%20customs&amp;f=false A-Z of Modern America]''. Psychology Press.
::And wouldn't you know it! Those damned pagans are at it again, reviving filthy veneration in that pesky goddess we thought we stamped out so long ago. And some scholar went and wrote about it! Now, maybe we can make an argument that ''Ēostre'' is somehow different and ''Easter''. Hopefully nobody will notice that the Old English Christian celebration was in fact also spelled ''Ēostre'', ha-ha-ha! That way we could keep it off the article, by golly!
::* Cusack, Carole M. (2008). &quot;[http://books.google.com/books?id=rwzttsI9-NwC&amp;pg=PA6&amp;dq=handbook+modern+paganism+return+of+the+goddess&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=hFJ-T4n2NZGg8QS02oCeDg&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=easter&amp;f=false The Return of the Goddess: Mythology, Witchcraft and Feminist Spirituality]&quot; as published in Pizza, Murphy. Lewis, James R. (Editors). ''Handbook of Contemporary Paganism. Brill Publishers''. ISBN 9004163735
::And I'm sure there's piles more out there to be listed here. I fear that it's only a matter of time before this article gives into the evils of secularism and modern neopaganism! But don't you fret, we can keep making excuses for barring every non-Christian thing that comes along from this article over some it not being the ''real'' Easter, no matter what relation it might have. Why, if we keep playing our cards right, we might finally be able to compete with that wellspring of ''right'' information, [[Conservapedia]]! [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 02:28, 6 April 2012 (UTC)

I think there's been overreaction on the part of some folks to a time a few years back when there was a spate of &quot;Easter isn't AT ALL Christian&quot; noise flying around. There have been many attempts made over the years to &quot;prove&quot; that there is nothing at all Christian about Easter. I would say the article, to be encyclopedic, does need to mention all aspects of the holiday as it is currently celebrated. It just does not need to go into unsubstantiable claims about &quot;real meanings&quot; or &quot;real origins&quot; that are only believed by fringe groups and not accepted to reputable historigraphers and historians. Of course, don't let me be a voice of reason, if that sort of thing is no longer sufficiently popular and ill-tempered displays of hurt feelings are now deemed a better way to conduct oneself.[[User:Dogface|Dogface]] ([[User talk:Dogface|talk]]) 03:08, 6 April 2012 (UTC)

I agree with the sensible parts of bloodofox's comments: the article should work to incorporate secular traditions. Since nobody has a problem with that, let's get on it! [[User:Jordanson72|Jordanson72]] ([[User talk:Jordanson72|talk]]) 03:27, 6 April 2012 (UTC)

'''Per RfC''' Wow, some real strange contortions going on here to try to claim that a Christian holy day is actually a pagen holiday. The English (and for that matter German) etymology has no bearing on the historical basis of the holy day which was established by people who spoke Ancient Greek and Aramaic. The article is seriously burying the lede by making the etymology section the most important section of the article. The most important aspect of Easter is that it is the principle holy day of one of the world's major religions. The second most important aspect is it's celebration by non-Christians. A very distant third is the etymology of the English term and speculation that etymology means people from 1st century Judea co-opted Germanic tribes' pagan celebrations. [[User:Eastshire|Eastshire]] ([[User talk:Eastshire|talk]]) 12:16, 6 April 2012 (UTC)
:&quot;Speculation that etymology means people from 1st century Judea co-opted Germanic tribes' pagan celebrations&quot;—where on Earth did you find this? This is the sort of pure nonsense from thin air that  we ''need'' to keep this article free of anything but Jesus! Bravo! [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 02:34, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
::It's implicit in your argument, with its assertions that Easter is somehow a &quot;Christianised&quot; Germanic festival. If the celebration had begun in Germanic countries and then spread elsewhere, you might have had a case, but the opposite is true, as you well know. [[User:Paul Barlow|Paul B]] ([[User talk:Paul Barlow|talk]]) 14:14, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
:::Comrades in keeping this article Jesus-only, I must show you the light. For, as you know, Christianization in Anglo-Saxon England did not occur in 1 CE, and it was not done by &quot;Judae&quot;. Indeed, my friends, England did not yet come to exist until half a millennia later. Therefore comments such as &quot;speculation that etymology means people from 1st century Judea co-opted Germanic tribes' pagan celebrations&quot; simply cannot be ridiculed, for they simply cannot be made in the first place. Oh woe! [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 15:59, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
::::Your witless sarcasm is utterly unfunny. I am not a Christian, so I have no interest in 'keeping' this page Christian. It just so happens that Easter ''is'' a Christian festival. It also just so happens that an Anglo-Saxon month name was adopted in English.  &quot;Good Friday&quot; is taken from an Anglo-Saxon day-name, but I don't see even you claiming that Good Friday originated from a festival dedicated to Frigg. This article, like all articles on a global topic, should be global in its coverage. Easter was not invented by the English. It is international, and only the English ''name'' links to Ostara. Your comments about when &quot;England&quot; came to exist are irrelevant and frankly silly. Ist century Judea is where the events took place that ''defined the date''. [[User:Paul Barlow|Paul B]] ([[User talk:Paul Barlow|talk]]) 16:11, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
:::::Now, now, Paul, surely you've got some humor in there somewhere. And what isn't there to laugh about comments such as &quot;speculation that etymology means people from 1st century Judea co-opted Germanic tribes' pagan celebrations&quot;? Indeed, comparisons to Friday are invalid totally invalid in the light that various scholars have discussed the level of synthesis that occurred with Paschal season and Easter. It's the same situation as with Yule and Christmas. Of course, this article is to be &quot;global&quot;, but it's also clear that both ''Easter'' and ''Ostern'' are special cases that this article also covers; they have unique histories all of their own, and encompass both pre-Christian Eostre/Eostre-month and the importation of Paschal season. In other words, this article is going to necessarily be different than other Paschal-season articles. [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 18:11, 7 April 2012 (UTC)

The focus of the article on the Christian holiday is appropriate.  The tone is consistent with NPOV.   What folklorists call &quot;calendar customs&quot; associated with this festival can be the subject matter of other pages.[[User:Mockingbird0|Mockingbird0]] ([[User talk:Mockingbird0|talk]]) 01:14, 9 April 2012 (UTC)

'''Comment''' It seems to me that a case has been made for secular observation of the Easter season in the USA. While there are many claims to Easter having its antecedents in other traditions, it needs to be noted that it has a lunar form of dating for celebration date, as do many other religious festivals in other faith traditions. It seems there is a reasonable case to link to another article entitled, ''Easter as observed in other traditions and countries'' or a title to this effect. This battleground will then lose its raison d'etre. [[User:Whiteguru|Whiteguru]] ([[User talk:Whiteguru|talk]]) 00:41, 24 April 2012 (UTC)


===Seriously, this has to take place now??===
You realize that Easter is this Sunday, right? And that with the big {{tl|NPOV}} tag on the article, we are going to have to omit it from [[Wikipedia:Selected anniversaries/April 8]] and thus it's not going to be listed on the Main Page. Do any of you realize what a huge embarrassment that will be for Wikipedia?? '''Please sort this out as soon as humanly possible.''' Thank you for your cooperation. &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Verdana; &quot;&gt;—'''[[User:Howcheng|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#33C;&quot;&gt;howcheng&lt;/span&gt;]]'''  &lt;small&gt;{[[User talk:Howcheng|chat]]}&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 04:27, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
:I've removed the NPOV tag. It was added by one editor who has made very recent, fairly controversial changes to the article - the fact that one editor has a problem with POV on this article does not require a tag. What if a Christian editor started making [[WP:UNDUE]] changes to the article [[Beltane]] on April 30th? Would we let them slap an NPOV tag there? I think not. I will ask the editor in question to stay away from this article until after Easter and then restart the discussion in a more measured way. Full disclosure: I am a neopagan [[Wicca|Wiccan]] priest and admin with no interest in inter-religious point scoring.) [[User:Kim Dent-Brown|&lt;font face=&quot;century gothic&quot;  color=&quot;#0E6E2D&quot;&gt;Kim Dent-Brown&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Kim Dent-Brown|&lt;font face=&quot;century gothic&quot; size=&quot;1&quot; color=&quot;#0E6E2D&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;(Talk)&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 10:54, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
::If there's any sort of neutrality discussion on the talk page with any kind of merit—such as the ongoing discussion about exactly why any discussion of the secular on this article has been so far stonewalled and/or ignored, and to what extent the article needs to include the pre-Christian precursor and modern revivals of veneration thereof—then that tag needs to be on the article page notifying users as such. Assumptions of people waiting around until right before Easter to do these things and thus &quot;gaming the system&quot; rather than assuming that people are reminded of Easter by seeing chocolate bunnies and pastel colors everywhere and have thus decided to check out how this article is doing—and therefore spotted the flaws—assumes bad faith. It's also wrong, in my case. [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 18:18, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
:::This article does need to include more information on the secular aspects of Easter celebrations ''and'' their prechristian origins if applicable, but modern revivals of Eostre commemoration should be outlined at [[Eostre]]. Any examples of contemporary pagans worshiping Eostre do not constitute celebrations of Easter, which is the subject of this article. Presenting information that implies that &quot;modern revivals of [Eostre] veneration&quot; and &quot;Easter&quot; are the same thing is, as you surely know by now, [[WP:Synthesis|synthesis]]. Your attempt to use [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=rwzttsI9-NwC&amp;pg=PA6&amp;dq=The+Return+of+the+Goddess:+Mythology,+Witchcraft+and+Feminist+Spirituality&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=wKiAT92NBcXE8QPU1ZCcBg&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=present-day%20Easter&amp;f=false this] as a source for &quot;celebrates the goddess Ēostre [in] (Germanic neopaganism)&quot; in the significance section of the infobox is an example of this. The source does ''not'' say that modern pagans celebrate Easter in commemoration of Eostre, and in fact describes Easter as a &quot;Christian festival&quot;. [[User:Jordanson72|Jordanson72]] ([[User talk:Jordanson72|talk]]) 21:10, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
::::The source I provided states that event that pre-Christian Ēostre, as in the goddess, as come to be again venerated, and expressly links it to the modern holiday name. As is the case with Christmas and Yule, Christian Ēostre and heathen Ēostre intrinsically linked. As a result, it is worth noting on this article that pre-Christian veneration has been revived and was therefore not entirely snuffed out with Christianization and syncretism. This is not [[WP:SYNTH]]. [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 21:18, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
::::: An express link to the English name of the holiday does not justify it's inclusion in the significance section of the infobox under &quot;celebrates the goddess Ēostre [in] (Germanic neopaganism)&quot;. The source simply does not say that modern pagans celebrate Easter (which is described in the source as a &quot;Christian festival&quot;) as part of their worship of Eostre. Hence its inclusion in the infobox falls under [[WP:SYNTH]]. [[User:Jordanson72|Jordanson72]] ([[User talk:Jordanson72|talk]]) 21:29, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
::::::So, you're stating that the inherent, direct relation isn't enough and that both were synonymous in English isn't enough, but the source must explicitly state that the event occurs ''on modern Easter''. Alright. Well, let's see what we can find. [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 21:43, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
::::::: Either the source matches the claim or it does not. In your case, it doesn't. If you find sources that actually back up the claim (''directly'', as [[WP:OR]] requires), then add it. I don't have a problem with the information, provided it is accurate. I have a problem with your attempts at inserting [[WP:SYNTH]]-breaching material and hoping that nobody notices. What the source &quot;must say&quot; is that modern pagans celebrate &quot;Easter&quot; in commemoration of the goddess Eostre. Anything not directly attesting to that fact violates [[WP:SYNTH]], period. [[User:Jordanson72|Jordanson72]] ([[User talk:Jordanson72|talk]]) 21:52, 7 April 2012 (UTC)

===Well, why not debate what Easter is on Easter?===
Coming here from a Google search to explain to my children the history, etymology, anthropology, and archeology related to Easter was a huge waste of time.  I (much) later learned more from bizarre and unreputable sources like:
http://www.lasttrumpetministries.org/tracts/tract1.html
http://www.theholidayspot.com/easter and
http://www.religioustolerance.org/easter.htm

The last has an introduction that seems more balanced to me (I'm a U.S. &quot;None&quot; -- not a Germanic Neopagan): &quot;Modern-day Easter is derived from two ancient traditions: one Judeo-Christian and the other Pagan. Both Christians and Pagans have celebrated death and resurrection themes following the Spring Equinox for millennia.&quot;  Maybe you can find common ground by working on re-writing this article to accurately describe the cultural complexity that is &quot;Modern-day Easter&quot; and then branch to: Easter as a Christian feast; Eostre as a Neo/Pagan goddess; as well as the other topics listed under http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Easter_%28disambiguation%29 and Easter bunny and Easter egg hunt.  I'd also suggest checking the Wikipedia analytics to see if the latter two dominate your traffic, or not.

Given that (as of ~2008) there's 10x as many Christians as Nones in the U.S. and 2x as many on the planet, I can see why some editors would start this article &quot;Easter is a Christian feast.&quot;  But after reading the discussion, it seems that Christians didn't coin the word &quot;Easter&quot; (like they did Christmas?).  The None growth rate in the U.S. is 20x the Christian one and their respective populations are already equal in France, so the trends suggest that some day the '''truth''' about bias that Bloodofox first patiently and then sarcastically articulated will manifest as a more balanced article.  I'll check back in 20 years. 
[[User:Scottveirs|Scottveirs]] ([[User talk:Scottveirs|talk]]) 09:22, 7 April 2012 (UTC)

:Allow me to compare the colloquial name of another holiday to the Easter vs. Eostre issue here. [[Independence Day (US)|''Independence Day'' (US)]] is commonly referred to as the &quot;Fourth of July&quot;, which is acknowledged as a secondary title in the article. Since July is named for [[Julius Caesar]], does that mean that the term &quot;Fourth of July&quot; is somehow honoring or celebrating Julius Caesar? Clearly not, so the same can be said for &quot;Easter&quot;, which is the ''colloquial Germanic-language word'' for the Christian festival celebrating the resurrection of Jesus that was used ''because'' the resurrection was believed to have occurred during Eostur-monath, the month named after Eostre (vs. ''4th of July'' celebrated in month named for Julius Caesar). 

:Crass comparison or not, it works to show why Eostre, Eostur-monath and the modern form Easter are totally separate and why this article should only focus on (1) the Christian festival, (2) the '''etymology''' behind the word Easter (in the appropriate section) and (3) the modern secular aspects (Easter Bunny, eggs, etc). I agree that the latter point is poorly represented and needs work in this article, and would welcome added information regarding the growing modern secular commercial aspect of Easter. — '''[[User:FoxCE|&lt;font face=&quot;Lucida Fax&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#990000&quot;&gt;FoxCE&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]]''' &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:FoxCE|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/FoxCE|contribs]])&lt;/small&gt; 10:01, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
::Fox, comparing July to Julius Caesar and Easter to Eostre is a false analogy; there's a lot of scholarly work out there discussing levels of potential synthesis between today's Christian Easter and yesterday's heathen Eostre-monath/Eostre-celeberations out there. Indeed, the fact that the name is used points to synthesis on par with [[Yule]] and [[Christmas]]. The two are to some extent combined, and there's plenty of commentary on this. Further, ''Easter'' is not the &quot;''colloquial Germanic-language word'' for the Christian festival&quot;, but appears only in German and English, both specifically West Germanic branches. Of course, all roads here point to Proto-Indo-European, but presenting it as a &quot;colloquial Germanic-language word&quot; is inaccurate. We have no North Germanic or East Germanic attestations of it.  [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 18:36, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
:::The comparison is entirely accurate. I've seen no evidence whatever that there is a &quot;lot of scholarly work work out there discussing levels of potential synthesis between today's Christian Easter and yesterday's heathen Eostre-monath&quot;. How many times does it have to be repeated to you? The festival of Easter does not derive from &quot;Eostre month&quot;. It derives from Passover. It's named after Passover in almost every language except English. The English do not have a separate festival from everyone else. It's the same international Christian festival. This is purely a quick of English naming conventions. [[User:Paul Barlow|Paul B]] ([[User talk:Paul Barlow|talk]]) 09:33, 8 April 2012 (UTC)
::::Paul, I guess you're not doing a lot of reading about Easter customs then, are you? Try some digging around about this whole egg, hare, easter-fire, and, well, extra-Biblical Easter customs in general business outside of Christian, non-academic sources. There is and has been obviously much discussion about these customs [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 12:23, 8 April 2012 (UTC)

:The secular aspects of the festival should certainly be covered, but the fact that the event has been secularised is pretty much par-for-the-course for all religious festivals. It's nothing to do with its origins. The fact is that Easter is the same as the Christianised &quot;Passover&quot;. Yes, it coincides with the coming of spring in Western Europe, so much of the &quot;death and resurrection&quot; imagery overlaps with &quot;rebirth of the land&quot; imagery. That's what all the eggs and rabbits are about. But it would be very disingenuous to pretend that neo-pagan obsessions with nature imagery represents a survival of some Germanic pagan festival that has been somehow &quot;Christianised&quot;. The Biblical source for the date of the crucifixion is absolutely clear and has nothing to do with paganism. [[User:Paul Barlow|Paul B]] ([[User talk:Paul Barlow|talk]]) 11:57, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
::Paul, much has been discussed about these customs and imagery in scholarly circles, and denigrating them to &quot;neo-pagan obsessions&quot; is inappropriate and unhelpful. While images such as hares, eggs, and whatnot may naturally, independently occur, there are numerous customs picked up on by Grimm and others that appear to be entirely extra-biblical and may quite logically be simply be a continuation of earlier, pre-Christian customs. This is hardly unique; this very evident with [[Yule]] and [[Christmas]], for example. [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 19:09, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
:::Your empty pomposity just masks an inability to parse. I was saying that modern neo-pagans are preoccupied by the idea that &quot;nature&quot; is somehow linked to &quot;paganism&quot; (of course this is truer of the Wiccan-related traditions than of all forms of neo-paganism). But this is essentially confused. There is no inconsistency between Christian belief and celebration of nature, since in Christian thought the cycle of nature is part of God's plan. Secular and fetility aspects of celebrations do not contradict Christian aspects - indeed they are entirely consistent with them. What you are doing is in fact the opposite of &quot;balance&quot;. You are suggesting that a worldwide festival should be interpreted through the lens of some parochial north European traditions and that speculation about their origins, for which there is zero evidence, should be given a central role in the article. [[User:Paul Barlow|Paul B]] ([[User talk:Paul Barlow|talk]]) 09:51, 8 April 2012 (UTC)
::::::::Well, Paul, I can assure you that my &quot;pomposity&quot; is hardly empty, and my &quot;ability to parse&quot; is well sharpened. But it definitely sounds to me like it's best that you leave it to the scholars to debate what may and may not be a pre-Christian practice. On top of that, I highly suggest you leave it to the neopagans to decide what they do and do not want to believe. It certainly seems that you're giving Christians a free pass. Exactly what makes you think you can come to a talk page and write things about &quot;neo-pagan obsessions with nature&quot;? Seriously, try to show some basic respect for other belief systems, if just for Wikipedia. Regarding &quot;you are suggesting that a worldwide festival should be intwerpreted through the lens of some parochial north European traditions and that speculation about their origins, for which there is zero evidence, ashould be given a central role in the article&quot; is simply wrong; this article is about Easter, and it will necessarily have information about what came together to make Easter in the Anglosphere, i.e. Eoster-monath + paschal season. Then there's the huge, entirely secular element to the article involving easter baskets, egg hunts, and chocolate bunnies that this article does an impressive job of ignoring, but for which we're not allowed to tag as NPOV due to the threat of at least one administrator. [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 11:41, 8 April 2012 (UTC)

:Scott, while you may not have to wait 20 years, it seems that you are unfortunately going to need to wait until after Easter. It has been decided here that any attempts at adding a &lt;nowiki&gt;{{NPOV}}&lt;/nowiki&gt; tag to this article until after Easter is over will result in a block until after Easter is over. Given that there are few users on this talk page that have not come around to agreeing that this article does ''not'' reflect the secular aspects of the holiday—and is therefore ''not'' neutral—you can probably see the level of absurdity that is going on here. This is evidently being done so that the article can meet some technical requirement to appear on the main page on Easter Sunday, and I have now been threatened with a ban from two users if I edit the article before Easter Sunday is over. One of said users already wasted a lot of my time banning me, although the ban was swiftly overturned. Of course, any such future bans are likely to again be overturned fairly swiftly, but it requires a lot of time wasted on my part to bother with them. If you want to see some of my handiwork and to the level I'd like to see this article developed to (i.e. to [[WP:GA]] level), see my user page for a list of articles I've rewritten. [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 18:36, 7 April 2012 (UTC)

::Such a &quot;ban&quot; on an [[WP:NPOV]] tag would seem to allow others to add even more mostly off-topic sentences to the first paragraph and to crowd out any attempt at balance.--[[User:JimWae|JimWae]] ([[User talk:JimWae|talk]]) 20:15, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
::::Off-topic, unreferenced or unencyclopaedic material that has been added without discussion can always be removed per [[WP:BOLD]], as far as I'm concerned. I don't regard that as disruptive - on the contrary, it's expressly encouraged by policy. [[User:Kim Dent-Brown|&lt;font face=&quot;century gothic&quot;  color=&quot;#0E6E2D&quot;&gt;Kim Dent-Brown&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Kim Dent-Brown|&lt;font face=&quot;century gothic&quot; size=&quot;1&quot; color=&quot;#0E6E2D&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;(Talk)&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 20:26, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
:::::Note that Kim here is one of said two users threatening a ban for the addition of a &lt;nowiki&gt;{{NPOV}}&lt;/nowiki&gt; tag to the article. [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 20:30, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
:::::: A [[WP:BLOCK|block]], not a [[WP:BAN|ban]]. But yes, that's me. [[User:Kim Dent-Brown|&lt;font face=&quot;century gothic&quot;  color=&quot;#0E6E2D&quot;&gt;Kim Dent-Brown&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Kim Dent-Brown|&lt;font face=&quot;century gothic&quot; size=&quot;1&quot; color=&quot;#0E6E2D&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;(Talk)&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 20:36, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
:::::::Out of curiosity, and as I note that you're an involved administrator, are you somehow denying that there is not only a long history of editors claiming a bias in this article and/or a widespread agreement here that this article is not neutral in that it does not reflect the secular aspects of the holiday? [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 20:37, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
:::::::: No. And I don't regard myself as [[WP:INVOLVED]]; my only edits here have been in an administrative capacity. I have no editorial history or interest here - the content of the article is for you folks to sort out here on the talk page. [[User:Kim Dent-Brown|&lt;font face=&quot;century gothic&quot;  color=&quot;#0E6E2D&quot;&gt;Kim Dent-Brown&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Kim Dent-Brown|&lt;font face=&quot;century gothic&quot; size=&quot;1&quot; color=&quot;#0E6E2D&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;(Talk)&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 20:53, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::After your attempted ban on my account, another user cited your involvement, which I agree with. Further, you have not answered my other questions. Please do so. [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 20:58, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::Once again, I didn't ban you, I blocked you. And I answered your questions. They were: ''&quot;are you somehow denying that there is not only a long history of editors claiming a bias in this article and/or a widespread agreement here that this article is not neutral in that it does not reflect the secular aspects of the holiday? &quot;'', and my answer was &quot;No&quot;. WP:INVOLVED states: ''&quot;One important caveat is that an administrator who has interacted with an editor or topic area purely in an administrative role, or whose prior involvement are minor or obvious edits which do not speak to bias, is not involved and is not prevented from acting in an administrative capacity in relation to that editor or topic area. This is because one of the roles of administrators is precisely to deal with such matters, at length if necessary. Warnings, calm and reasonable discussion and explanation of those warnings, advice about community norms, and suggestions on possible wordings and approaches, do not make an administrator 'involved'.&quot;'' That's exactly my role this far. [[User:Kim Dent-Brown|&lt;font face=&quot;century gothic&quot;  color=&quot;#0E6E2D&quot;&gt;Kim Dent-Brown&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Kim Dent-Brown|&lt;font face=&quot;century gothic&quot; size=&quot;1&quot; color=&quot;#0E6E2D&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;(Talk)&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 21:06, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::::Ahem, let's be clear; you ''attempted'' to block me, but that was pretty quickly rescinded. But, more importantly, in your own words, what is your reasoning for threatening a block or any user who adds &lt;nowiki&gt;{{npov}}&lt;/nowiki&gt; to the article, as you agree that there is widespread consensus that the article is not neutral? [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 21:11, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::::I ''did'' block you, and the block was correctly lifted by another editor because you had not been warned properly by the editor who first took this discussion to AN/I. I'd point out that in [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=User_talk%3ABloodofox&amp;diff=486109355&amp;oldid=486106934 lifting the block], the editor concerned strongly suggested that you should ''&quot;limit yourself to talk page discussion about Easter for the next day or so, &quot;'' - which I'm pleased to see you are doing. My reasoning for saying I will block a user who restores the NPOV tag is because the disagreement has been going on for a long time, but adding the tag this close to the date of Easter seemed needlessly [[WP:POINTY|pointy]]. Now I'm going to leave you folks to the content discussion here, this process bickering is not particularly constructive. Bloodofox if you have further questions, please come to my talk page. [[User:Kim Dent-Brown|&lt;font face=&quot;century gothic&quot;  color=&quot;#0E6E2D&quot;&gt;Kim Dent-Brown&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Kim Dent-Brown|&lt;font face=&quot;century gothic&quot; size=&quot;1&quot; color=&quot;#0E6E2D&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;(Talk)&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 21:19, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::::::No, you blocked me under false pretenses, and then another editor came along and stated that it was inappropriate as you had not followed process. Their suggestion ''probably'' has something to do with the possibility of you trying to do it again. Just maybe. Anyway, that tag needs to go on this article—there are numerous issues being brought up by a variety of users, and ''you're'' the one being disruptive at this point. Quit trying to hide the neutrality problem. Seriously, Kim, get out of the way of this article's progress; you're not helping and you're wasting not only my time but the time of others. [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 21:24, 7 April 2012 (UTC)

:::Agreed, yet I've got not one but two editors threatening me with exactly that and for exactly the reasons I've stated. Try adding the tag to the article and see how it goes for you. [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 20:23, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
::::I submit that sentences 2 &amp; 3 are not sufficiently about Easter to be in the first paragraph--[[User:JimWae|JimWae]] ([[User talk:JimWae|talk]]) 20:41, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
:::::These sentences are indeed relevant, as they discuss the days of the [[Easter Triduum]], connecting Jesus' resurrection, with His [[Passion of Jesus|Passion]] and [[Crucifixion of Jesus|Death]]. Cheers, [[User:Anupam|Anupam]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Anupam|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 20:52, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
::::::That Easter is a culimination of something (Lent) is truly part of what Easter IS, but Easter also IS a celebration that includes fertility observances. Right now, sentences 2 &amp; 3 are more a wall  of text that crowds out mention of anything that is not religious - they go far beyond information central to what Easter is. The crucifixion is already mentioned in sentence 1--[[User:JimWae|JimWae]] ([[User talk:JimWae|talk]]) 20:59, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
::::::There are so many blue links in there that I need to correct myself. Sentences 2, 3 AND 4 need to be made more relevant &amp; concise - and room needs to be made for the pagan aspects (Easter bunny, eggs, perhaps women parading their fashions). Right now, those 3 sentences in paragraph 1 are more a recitation of Christian observances than an explication of what Easter means to people who celebrate it. The overwhelming theme in newspaper articles about the day includes eggs, rabbits, and candy. The lede does not reflect any balance regarding the culture of Easter. ---[[User:JimWae|JimWae]] ([[User talk:JimWae|talk]]) 21:08, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::Balance meansd giving a ''worldwide perspective''. It does not mean treating British and US popular culture as an international norm. That should be one of the fundamentals of an article such as this. [[User:Paul Barlow|Paul B]] ([[User talk:Paul Barlow|talk]]) 10:15, 8 April 2012 (UTC)
Uninvolved editor responding to RfC... 
The disambiguation notice makes the content of this article clear:
: ''This article is about the Christian festival.  For other uses, see Easter (disambiguation).''
In English, we say Easter instead of Pascha.  Contributions regarding Spring, goddess, fertility and other festivals have articles.  This article is not the place.--[[User:Crews Giles|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;cregil&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Crews Giles|&lt;small&gt;(''talk'')&lt;/small&gt;]] 06:02, 8 April 2012 (UTC)

::Please see [[WP:POVFORK]] :&quot;The generally accepted policy is that all facts and major points of view on a certain subject should be treated in one article. As Wikipedia does not view article forking as an acceptable solution to disagreements between contributors, such forks may be merged, or nominated for deletion.&quot;--[[User:JimWae|JimWae]] ([[User talk:JimWae|talk]]) 08:01, 8 April 2012 (UTC)
:::I can make no sense of this reply. Easter is a Christian festival. In some countries, like Christmas, it has become largely secularised. But that has very little to do with goddesses and fertility and almost everything to do with chocolate. Popular culture traditions around the world associated with the date should, of course, be included. No-one has ever said they shouldn't. [[User:Paul Barlow|Paul B]] ([[User talk:Paul Barlow|talk]]) 10:26, 8 April 2012 (UTC)
::::I am replying to the person (directly above that comment) who was content to have this entire article be about the Christian festival. I did not want anyone to interpret that as being ''good'' support for focussing ONLY on the Christian aspects of the festival. WP policy is that articles (including this article) should cover all the aspects of the topic - and this Easter article is only now barely beginning to acknowledge any aspects that are not confined to Xn aspects. --[[User:JimWae|JimWae]] ([[User talk:JimWae|talk]]) 18:51, 8 April 2012 (UTC)
:::::Cregil said no such thing. He said &quot;contributions regarding Spring, goddess, fertility and other festivals have articles. This article is not the place.&quot; He was quite right. this article is about Easter - that includes popular culture aspects, which in fact are already represented, if relatively poorly. No-one disputes that so there is no issue. The &quot;argument&quot; is about an attempt to appropriate the topic for a neo-paganist agenda, something quite quite different. [[User:Paul Barlow|Paul B]] ([[User talk:Paul Barlow|talk]]) 19:07, 8 April 2012 (UTC)
:::::::I did not say he &quot;said&quot; that - I wanted to be pre-empt it being interpreted as support for that.--[[User:JimWae|JimWae]] ([[User talk:JimWae|talk]]) 20:02, 8 April 2012 (UTC)
:::JimWae-- this is not forking-- those articles already exist and the disambiguation page lists those articles. They are very different articles and happily co-exist, side by side, neither crowding another.  

:::The breadth and depth of any one article may overwhelm-- as would be the case in this one-- and thus require multiple articles for the different meanings-- not due to a disagreement, but due to context.  That is NOT the same as &quot;forking.&quot;  The various usages of Easter are not in conflict-- there are simply different meanings from context.

:::As has been pointed out-- none of the pagan or cultural traditions exist in the context of the Judeo-Christian religious one, neither do they share a common root; but only share the term (and, now, the method of dating).  Likewise the [[pasha]] article links to a disambiguation page listing Easter, Passover and others.  They are not all on the same article there, nor should they be here.

:::Forking is &quot;No! It is not!&quot; whereas disambiguation is &quot;Yes, it is both/all/either/any&quot;--[[User:Crews Giles|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;cregil&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Crews Giles|&lt;small&gt;(''talk'')&lt;/small&gt;]] 19:46, 8 April 2012 (UTC)

::::1&gt; Room needs to be made on this article for parts of the Easter festival that are not necessarily Xn. This would not &quot;overwhelm&quot; this article. It has been difficult to get any mention in this article of the Easter festival being celebrated by anyone other then Xns. The process has had a minor beginning &amp; needs to continue. Forking all nonXn aspects to other articles is POV-forking - - but it does differ in that it makes the main article POV rather than the forks. 2&gt; 3 of the 5 sentences in the 1st paragraph still are not centrally about what Easter IS, but about other things connected to Easter. There can be room made in the 1st paragraph to include typical ways the day is celebrated- whether they be Xn or not. 3&gt; Whether we agree it is forking does not change the policy that all facts and major points of view on a certain subject should be treated in one article. This has not been achieved yet. --[[User:JimWae|JimWae]] ([[User talk:JimWae|talk]]) 19:58, 8 April 2012 (UTC)
:::::No, this festival is about the celebration of Easter globally, not just about its secularization in the United States. Certain aspects of the festival that are practiced in the USA are not practiced in India, the Philippines, etc. However, across the world, Easter IS recognized as the Christian celebration of the Resurrection of Jesus. The lede paragraph ''does'' appropriately mention some secular aspects like Easter parades, the Easter Bunny, etc. However, it also appropriately gives the main emphasis on the Resurrection, which is why the celebration is so widely known and celebrated in the first place. Thanks, [[User:Anupam|Anupam]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Anupam|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 20:55, 8 April 2012 (UTC)

'''RfC Comment''' - I certainly would have no objection to an article in [[Easter in the United States]], or for that matter articles on significant, notable variations on the celebration of Easter in any locations. I seem to remember that in Japan, for instance, [[Christmas]] has been reported to be more or less an occasion for sexually-oriented hotel stays by younger people. I also note that there are several reference books which relate to the different ways that various holidays are celebrated around the world, and see no reason why if they are notable similar articles should not exist here. But all that is rather a separate matter from what should be the main content of the main article on the subject itself. Perhaps another separate article on [[Proposed pagan precursors to Easter]] could also be created. But, in general, I do think that [[WP:WEIGHT]] and the content of this article should be very much weighted toward the specifically Christian elements. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 00:51, 11 April 2012 (UTC)

:Got RfC invite. You do realize that the etymology of the Anglo-Germanic &quot;Easter&quot; isn't appropriate in the lead ([[WP:WEIGHT]]), and the Christian holiday's original name is actually [[Pascha]], and is a '''Christianized Jewish feast, ''not'' a Christianized pagan feast'''? Just as &quot;Halloween&quot; was &quot;All Hallows' Eve&quot;, and &quot;Christmas&quot; was &quot;Christ's Mass&quot; (yes, as in a Roman Catholic Mass, of all things, not a Satanic Black Mass)? Many of these comments (especially bloodfox's) remind me so much of that old legendary, unhistorical myth of the &quot;suppressed underground pagan tradition of ye olde wytche-crafte&quot; that Gerald Gardner was the magical heir to? Coincidentally, I support and lend my voice to everything Paul B said. Mention secular aspects like one would do with any other holy-day-cum-holiday - that Christmas happens to coincide with the day of Sol Invictus, that it has turned in to a massive orgy of consumerism, etc. while observing [[WP:UNDUE]] and [[WP:FRINGE]], which means, &quot;not in the lead&quot;. [[User:JohnChrysostom|St&amp;nbsp;'''John&amp;nbsp;Chrysostom''']]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:JohnChrysostom|Δόξα]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/JohnChrysostom|τω&lt;sup&gt;&amp;nbsp;Θεώ&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;/sub&gt; 05:18, 26 April 2012 (UTC)

:: '''Uninvolved editor.'''

:: I agree with the above from [[User:JohnChrysostom|St&amp;nbsp;'''John&amp;nbsp;Chrysostom''']].

:: I am having difficulty imagining a reader consulting the article to find out about the Christian festival of Easter and NOT walking away with a general &quot;understanding&quot; that the Christians began celebrating the Resurrection of Christ Jesus as a derivative of the pagan festival.  We mislead the reader.

:: The etymology section is HUGE, and irrelevant to the article; yet it is the first section and includes a sub-section, called &quot;origin of Easter&quot; which is not at all about the origin of Easter-- but only of the word.  The entire etymology section may be easily reduced to one sentence, &quot;The term Easter is taken from the archaic name of the month used in a medieval Germanic calendar.&quot;  Beyond that, the linguistic study is off topic and is covered in the [[Ēostre]] article already linked in the lede (and from the disambiguation page).

:: The Fourth of July analogy, above, was excellent-- in that no one expects to read about Julius Caesar in regard to that celebration-- not even a single summarizing sentence such as I have proposed here. 

:: A centering question:  '''What does an understanding of the name of a month on an archaic calendar have to to with the Christian festival of Easter?'''  The answer (&quot;Not at all&quot;) is clear, and so does not support the etymolgy section's primary placement with five sub-sections and fifteen paragraphs. --[[User:Crews Giles|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;cregil&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Crews Giles|&lt;small&gt;(''talk'')&lt;/small&gt;]] 16:04, 27 April 2012 (UTC)

:::Etymologies are usually front and center for good reason; terminology is crucial when approaching a subject. With English Easter it's a particular mess. As for attempts to hoist the etymology off of the article, I suppose this would help certain ideology bents, but it doesn't help the reader. No discussion of Easter—yes, ''Easter'', not simply Paschal season— in an academic context will avoid discussing the syncretism by way of at the very least the celebration name. It's a huge topic on the subject. Currently the article remains a mess that totally sidesteps the major secular element of the holiday (which any academic approach will discuss side by side with the Christian element), and that still needs to be addressed. In addition, the lead is a summary of the body, and therefore all sections should receive concise mention in the lead section.
:::As to John, I'm willing to accept your apology for comparing my argument to the Gardner's when you're ready to make it. After you've taken the time to read up on what I'm discussing, you'll find that that I've based my comments entirely on modern scholarship. [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 19:51, 27 April 2012 (UTC)

:::: So as not to repeat myself, [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]], I ask you to read the statements I made immediately prior to asking the question.  Such reading may render your answer moot. Intended or not, the etymology section obfuscates the subject addressed by the article-- it does not clarify. --[[User:Crews Giles|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;cregil&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Crews Giles|&lt;small&gt;(''talk'')&lt;/small&gt;]] 02:14, 28 April 2012 (UTC)

:::::I think it's very clear. It just so happens that in the English speaking world and in the German speaking world, this holiday was placed on a heathen foundation, and the name of the deity was intentionally taken from the month name and used for the event. As I said, there's been plenty of scholarly ink spilled about this, and even plenty of discussion about &quot;secular&quot; elements stemming from this same syncretic process. As a result, exactly why we use ''Easter'' rather than the terminology common everywhere else (but German) requires a prominent explanation; this is is the English Wikipedia, after all, and we're using English terminology. As &quot;international&quot; as the article may be, we're still using English, thus making the history of our branch of the &quot;paschal season&quot; a special case requiring explanation. [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 16:16, 28 April 2012 (UTC)

:::::: The main article on the etymology, [[Ēostre]] does not state what you are claiming, and that your attempts to include such information into this article's lede and not that one is telling, I think.
:::::: Your point being that the calendar did not use Jedeo-Christian names for the months is equivocal to the holiday being placed on a heathen foundation... is a hard argument to follow and I believe it is unsupportable.  Neither this article, nor the main article say that, but you make my point-- because of the amount of material beginning the etymology section, it appears to suggest that the goddess and the Christian celebration are related in anyway beyond a relation if the festival were called &quot;April.&quot;  A typical reader may well be expected to ''assume'' that the discussion of the goddess is necessary to understand the Christian Easter when it clearly is not. 

:::::: Are you suggesting that the Church in Germanic-based languages had different faith and practice than the rest of the Church?  At no time and in no place did the Church acknowledge the existence, much less honor, the goddess,  Ēostre.  I'll not prove the negative, so you will need to to prove otherwise.

:::::: The entire sub-section may be reduced to &quot;The term Easter is taken from the archaic name of the month used in a medieval Germanic calendar in which the feast fell.&quot;  That one statement is accurate, clear, concise, and meets your expectations for ''clarity'' regarding etymology, does it not?

:::::: I take you at your word that &quot;much scholarly ink&quot; has been spent on the synchornicity-- but that does not change the fact (fact, mind you) that this article is not about the etymology or about synchonicity -- another article exists in which the etymology discussion is contained.  I can think of no other encyclopedia article which gives space for equivocal terms in all other languages.

:::::: As for your claim: &quot;Etymologies are usually front and center ...&quot;  Well, No.  They are not.  In fact etymologies are found in any good dictionary following the definition and easily understood without requiring fifteen paragraphs in five sections.  I am aware of no comparable encyclopedic entry which even includes-- much less begins with-- and essay on the etymology of the title word. In the English speaking world, &quot;Happy Easter&quot; and &quot;Easter Day&quot; are not confusing and so do not beg for clarification.

::::::  Concerning your statement that &quot;the name of the deity was intentionally taken from the month name and used for the event.&quot;  To the contrary, Grimm uses the words &quot;the christian teachers ''tolerated'' the name, and applied it to one of their own grandest anniversaries.&quot;  ''Toleration'' is one thing and your use of &quot;intentionally&quot; connotes a very different other.  If your intention is to claim that ''because'' the month name is &quot;heathen&quot; the Christian Holiday is also heathen, that would be a ''non sequitur''.  If your intention is to declare that the Church chose the name to honor the goddess from which the month's name is derived, then I point out that the fuller [[Ēostre]] article does not make that claim.

::::::  If I understand you correctly, it is not the etymology which is of central importance to you in this article but the synchronicity of cultural artifacts from non-Christian Spring rites which have remained.  If I am correct, then perhaps you may immediately see the POV problem you have faced with beginning an article about the Christian Festival with a discussion of the accretion of non-Christian observances?

:::::: Your words:
:::::::''And wouldn't you know it! Those damned pagans are at it again, reviving filthy veneration in that pesky goddess we thought we stamped out so long ago. And some scholar went and wrote about it! Now, maybe we can make an argument that Ēostre is somehow different and Easter. Hopefully nobody will notice that the Old English Christian celebration was in fact also spelled Ēostre, ha-ha-ha! That way we could keep it off the article, by golly!''
:::::: That you place those words in the mouths of your opponents is very far out of bounds, and betrays personal intent to disparage Christians and Christianity-- and attempting to silence others who you consider to be an opponent by diluting an article and so obfuscating the subject of that article is not going to be tolerated, and I cannot imagine why you expect it to be.  --[[User:Crews Giles|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;cregil&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Crews Giles|&lt;small&gt;(''talk'')&lt;/small&gt;]] 16:59, 29 April 2012 (UTC)

Personally I'm quite fond of the etymology section as it stands now.  The reason that we need an extensive etymology section is precisely due to these sectarian arguments about origins.  A section which is absent ignores origins altogether and opens the article up for Hyslop-type conspiracy theories.  A short etymology section makes Easter look clearly (Germmanic) pagan.  A longer one is necessary to convey the complexity of the situation. -[[User:Benwbrum|Ben]] ([[User talk:Benwbrum|talk]]) 01:20, 30 April 2012 (UTC) (Who thinks the origins of the parts of Easter he cares about are Jewish.)

::::::Crews, I suggest you re-read [[Ēostre]] (of which I am the primary author). Indeed, the modern English and modern German worlds are in a unique situation due to the placement of a goddess name over what is considered the most major of Christian holidays. The reasons for this have been much debated, but are obviously related to the observances associated with the goddess prior to the placement of the imported Christian event over it (&quot;Now they designate that Paschal season by her name...&quot;). We also have a very strong, extra-biblical series of customs that live on in the &quot;secular world&quot; recorded from an early date. Much discussion has occurred about this. And I'm talking about scholarly circles here. As I'm responsible for the addition of the Grimm passage in question, it seems that you could use some clarification; Grimm is here speculating on exactly ''why'' the church would allow the application of the name of the goddess this crucially important Christian holiday, his idea being that the population wouldn't give up their previous customs so easily, and so either the population (or, less likely, the church) ''intentionally'' applied the name to this new event (i.e., &quot;whose worship was so fully rooted&quot;) and that the church ''tolerated'' it (i.e., were not able to or decided against trying to stamp it out). The result would therefore be syncretism; a Christian event with the name of a native goddess. We can only guess to what level this syncretism extended at the time, but there has been a fair amount of discussion of absorption of Christian deities (Jesus, Yahweh, etc.) into the Anglo-Saxon pantheon during the Christianization process for a period. Anyway, Grimm additionally has much to say about Easter customs having essentially nothing to do with anything biblical, some of which continue today.

::::::Further, on ''Wikipedia'' etymologies are usually front and center, particularly in confusing situations such as this. As with confusion over terminology relating to the Sun or the Moon, it's inevitable that someone immediately asks why we are using ''Easter'' rather than ''Paschal season'' in English the English language. Of course, there's a lot more to it than the vague passage you're suggesting, which requires clarification to the reader. I agree with Ben here.

::::::As for my sarcastic response that you quote above, given your suggestion to shorten any discussion of the origins of the word ''Ēostre'' on this article to the extremely vague &quot;The term Easter is taken from the archaic name of the month used in a medieval Germanic calendar in which the feast fell&quot;, I must point you to the rest of the similar sarcastic comments attached to it. Or I can just sum it up with &quot;all secular and non-Christian elements must be purged from this page—or, if that fails, minimized as much at possible—at all cost!&quot;, an approach I've now seen more than a few times here. [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 06:21, 30 April 2012 (UTC)

&quot;Vague passage?&quot;--  ''Them's fightin' words!''  You want to engage me, because you enjoy the discussion?  Okay.  Let's discuss.

I had read before that you had stated you had responsibility for much of the [[Ēostre]] article, and so am surprised to find you seeking to go beyond your own scholarly work on this article.  In reading that fuller article with Grimm's comments summarized and quoted, it seems to me that if there was any celebration of the Goddess, it is unknown what that celebration included, unknown as to how any associated customs and rituals developed and how, why, and when they fell out of favor.  It is mere speculation. 

From that article-- well written by the way, and thank you-- what we have is speculation.  What we do not seem to have is documents or archeology contemporary to any goddess festivals of the distant past.  Example: 
:''Bonfires were lighted at Easter... ...Maidens clothed in white, who at Easter, at the season of returning spring, show themselves in clefts of the rock and on mountains, are suggestive of the ancient goddess.'' 
Grimm appears to write of anciently attested ''Christian'' custom of the catechumens dressed in white on Easter morning, for their Baptisms for which they prepared during Lent.  Grimm speculates that this (and along with sunrise bonfires) might be syncretism-- the Church taking on customs of the goddess rites.  He is wrong.

Here is why he is wrong:  The dressing in white is a Christian symbol lifted straight from Christian Scriptural imagery (&quot;washed in the blood of the Lamb&quot; and others).  The Bonfires at dawn are much more easily attributed to the non-synchenistic Christian liturgical custom of &quot;New Fire&quot; used by Anglican, Roman and Orthodox Easter Vigil rites. 

Grimm is looking at known Christian customs contemporary to himself, and seeking to glean hints of goddess customs to be assigned to syncretism-- but it is far removed from what can be known now-- and could have been known by Grimm two hundred years ago-- but he didn't seem to know it. 

Why that has not been discussed is, apparently that the details of the argument have not been brought forth by you or others in this present discussion.

'''Let me, let that hang there for a moment, in light of the other major (and more explicit) prong of the discussion:'''

Again and again, even before the RfC, your connecting the etymology and assuming synchretism (not to mention assuming nefarious intent of the Church) has been well met with the point that the etymology of the term does not bear the weight of an assumption of synchretism.

Many of us have read the [[Ēostre]] article and others on the topic (some verbatim from the Wiki or visa-verse, by the way) and since you wrote much of it, it is telling that we do not read the connection which you imply is made in it. 

Grimm's work is speculation-- it is an attempt to assume syncretism SO THAT, something of the goddess ritual practice, IF ANY, may be speculated upon.  It is all he had to go on.  It is not that we do not &quot;get it&quot; it is that we ''do get'' that it is assumptions for the sake of speculation.  Fun and intellectually stimulating, but not encyclopedic-- except as the thin and ONLY framework for imagining anything about hypothesized goddess customs. That is what Grim wanted to do, but he did it in a vacuum of evidence. 

Grimm suggests what we might look for as regards this long-lost and, except for Bede, forgotten goddess; but so far, it has yet to be found.  Or so the article has me believe.

Grimm admits that the etymology of the word may be a reference to the rising of the sun:
:''Grimm details that the Old High German adverb ôstar 'expresses movement towards the rising sun',''
but stops short of making the connection of that to the equinox, when the sun's &quot;power&quot; overcomes that of darkness (in primal thinking and symbolism-- but Grimm had not been able to read Carl G.Jung!), instead preferring to speculate on the one and only hint to go on, which is that Bede claimed the month was named after a goddess.  No other evidence exists.

Let me make that clear.  '''The only evidence that there is even a goddess named Ēostre is because Bede wrote that the month was named after a goddess.  Nothing else (zero, zed, zilch!) exists.'''

So, going even beyond that tenuous (spurious?) theory, your desires for this article seem to be heading toward an &quot;original research&quot; violation (specifically, that Christian practices derived from goddess worship) and stepping to, but not crossing the line, the reader is to be led to jump to that conclusion. It has no place on this article.

You are free to jump to that unproven and presently unprovable (more likely, ''easily deniable'') conclusion, but endeavoring to lead the reader to it is a POV violation-- and especially so on this article-- inexcusably so, in the lede and in the first main section.

'''Now back, as promised, to Grimm:'''
The study which Grimm lacks in his speculation, is liturgical.  He needed to step back and take into account global Christian custom and rites, and point to those which might only have developed in and when any goddess worship was contemporary to that development.  He had not done this.  It ought to be done, but his failure to do it places his speculation on a foundation of clay.  That may have been excusable, because he may not have intended such weight to be placed upon is modest speculation.

Note, for example, that Grimm provides no evidence for goddess worshipers wearing ritual garments, or lighting ritual bonfires-- only that he knows the Christians were doing these things.  But evidence that Christians have long done so (at least by the earliest part of the fourth century and THAT attestation to the Easter Vigil practice in ''Jerusalem'')-- throughout Christianity (not just in regions of Germanic root language) abounds.  Talking about hiding evidence and scholarship, were you?  Let me see you put that in the [[Ēostre]] article, and I'll give you due credit for both objectivity and scholarship.

Finally, your implicit concept that no Christian believes in the faith of the Church except by having more organic beliefs &quot;stamped out&quot; is not going to do you any good as a starting place for your edits-- it is a dead end, historically unlikely, personally false, and a token common to that of a closed mind-- not to mention a POV violation.

'''POV checking time:'''

Mind you, the Christian faith and practice was horribly persecuted for its first 300 years-- everywhere-- and pretty much by all, probably including at the hands of goddess worshipers.  Welcome to the real world where we are not surprised that people acted like people whether Christian, Jewish, Muslim, pagan, atheist, pantheist, panentheist, animist or anything else-- so you can stop your demonizing-- beginning with taking back your statement that what I write is &quot;vague.&quot;  I am ''vague'' in my writing like a two-by-four to the side of the head is ''subtle''.

In this case, &quot;Easter&quot; is wholly equivocal to &quot;Pascha.&quot;  Why the term Easter is used in English and not Pascha is an etymological footnote, nothing more than a reference to the calendar in use at one time; but has nothing at all to do with the faith and practice-- or even the meaning of the word in English.  No change in custom, creed, dating, observance, ritual, or prayer, of the Christian Festival has been (or can be, it would seem) linked to any goddess worship.  The whole discussion begins and ends there.

If I began editing articles so that those on Muslim rites and practices were led by a discussion of Christian rites and practices-- do you not think I would find my edits reverted?  I have, in fact, read scholarly speculation that Muslim faith and practice borrows largely from a syncretism of animist and Christian thought to which Mohammed was exposed, and yet rejecting both-- so I have a valid point, but know it is not appropriate to use such speculation to derail the main content of the article for something which cannot be proved to begin with.  What is the difference?

Hear that sound?  That was the thud of a two-by-four. --[[User:Crews Giles|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;cregil&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Crews Giles|&lt;small&gt;(''talk'')&lt;/small&gt;]] 21:03, 30 April 2012 (UTC)

:Crews, you've only made it further clear that you're in dire need of basic research on this subject. You haven't absorbed much of the Ēostre article. First of all, Grimm's work has been picked up on and expanded on by numerous scholars since (which the article makes perfectly clear). An example of this is linguist Philip A. Shaw's recent work on the subject (Shaw, Philip A. (2011). ''Pagan Goddesses in the Early Germanic Goddess: Eostre, Hreda and the Cult of Matrons''. Bristol Classical Press. ISBN 978-0-7156-3797-5), where he discusses further evidence that has come to light since Grimm's time, such as the ''matronae Austriahenea'' (discovered in 1958), toponyms, personal names, etc., all further &quot;evidence&quot; for the goddess beyond Bede's attestation and beyond Grimm's reconstructions. Then there's the strong Indo-European dawn goddess reconstruction that continues to be developed. Essentially the Anglo-Saxon extension could be reconstructed without Bede's attestation at this point. Please get a basic grip on this material before continuing.

:As you do so, you need to understand that Grimm was both a polyglot and by most definitions a polymath; he knew his material extremely well and made major innovations in his field(s). He has been repeatedly compared to Darwin for good reason. Before producing a rambling original research essay, you need to go back and figure out ''why'' he said rather than run with my quotes. Grimm very frequently cites extremely obscure church records in numerous languages, and was by no means ignorant of church custom or history. The man knew his material perhaps better than anyone alive today, and his records are frequently referred back to in their respective fields. While his research has in many areas been built on since, he remains vital. On the other hand, you've clearly got a long way to go yet.

:As for your personal rant about Christianity and paganism, I'm not interested in getting in to that with you (or anyone else on Wikipedia). [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 02:22, 1 May 2012 (UTC)

:: Your quick answers along the lines of &quot;you are in dire need of more research&quot; and &quot;you haven't absorbed much&quot; lack any force.  Instead, you may have responding to the analysis of the scholarship-- which I took the trouble to provide.  (I am an uninvolved editor-- why am I the one doing this?)

:: 1) In your..., well, ''rant'', you provided two orts:

::: (a) ''Grimm's work has been picked up on and expanded on by numerous scholars since''
:: Expanding on speculation is irrelevant without conclusions.  Perhaps you simply forgot to mention the necessary part where we learn of the specific rites and customs of [[Ēostre]] worshipers which were adopted by the Church as syncretism?  I am all ears.

:::(b) ''Philip A. Shaw... discusses further evidence.. such as such as the ''matronae Austriahenea'', toponyms, personal names, etc.
:: And how does any of that tell us of the rites and customs of the goddess named Ēostre? 

::2) From that recently updated section in the [[Ēostre]] article:
:::''A cluster of place names in England contain and a variety of English and continental Germanic names include the element*ēoster, an early Old English word reconstructed by linguists and potentially an earlier form of the goddess name Ēostre. These locations include Eastry (Eastrgena, 788 CE) in Kent, Eastrea (Estrey, 966 CE) in Cambridgeshire, and Eastrington (Eastringatun, 959 CE) in East Riding of Yorkshire.'''

:: I hate use the term, yet again, but that is a ''non sequitur''.  Look at map.  All the places mentioned are on the eastern edge of England-- EASTERN.  How many places names in England are named after the also forgotten goddesses of Middle, South, North, and the evil twin of Ēostre, known as &quot;West&quot;?  What allows me to see the data without forcing an interpretation is called &quot;objectivity&quot; -- it is not unfamiliarity, it is not ignorance.

:: 3) The facts and the analysis I provided previous to this post are accurate and you have not provided a contrary argument other than empty contradictions and insults.  What you provided (i.e., ''matronae Austriahenea'') is no evidence of the rites and customs involving the goddess [[Ēostre]].

:: Here is how the analysis goes:

:: * We have a word which primarily etymology is related to &quot;the direction of the rising sun&quot; also known as the common word &quot;East.&quot;  Exactly the same usage as calling a storm from the north-east a &quot;Nor-Easter.&quot;  ([[Ēostre]]: &quot;Grimm details that the Old High German adverb ôstar &quot;expresses movement towards the rising sun&quot;)
:: * We have, 400 years ago, the Venerable Bede writing that the equivalent to April was once called by a variant of that word. ([[Ēostre]]: &quot;whose role as a goddess is attested solely by Bede&quot;)
:: * We have Bede write that the month was named after a long forgotten goddess in whose honor, feasts were once held.-- he tell us nothing more. (Bede: &quot;once called after a goddess of theirs named Eostre, in whose honour feasts were celebrated in that month.&quot;)
:: * We have mythology scholars search for, but fail to find (&quot;...solely by Bede&quot;), any lore referring to such a goddess, therefore...
:: * We have a scholarly debate ensue drawing Bede's accuracy into question ([[Ēostre]]: &quot;...have debated whether or not Eostre is an invention of Bede's&quot;); suggesting he was merely mistaken or confused-- perhaps assuming a goddess by an ASSUMED etymology rather than a more obvious etymological model that the name of the month refers to the direction rising of the sun-- perhaps due to the equinox, and more to the point-- the word &quot;East.&quot;
:: * We have, 200 years later, Grimm and others defending Bede with SPECULATION-- but no evidence.  Nature abhors a vacuum... so does scholarship. ([[Ēostre]]: &quot;Grimm additionally ''speculates'' on the nature of the goddess and surviving folk customs ''that may have been'' &quot;)

::4) The debate concerning syncretism -- and thus, ANY connection to the Christian festival-- is at an impasse for lack of specific evidence one way or the other.

:: So, it is a dawn on or about the six hundred years ago somewhere in Europe and Ēostre goddess worshipers have gathered for a feast.  '''What were they doing?''' and '''How do we know?'''

:: Unless we can answer that, the syncretism theory rests in a logical reverse presumption; that is, in attempting to discover what Ēostre worshipers might have done by what the Christians were doing at the time.  That is extraordinarily presumptive, don't you think?

:: 5) Also, this entire discussion of the [[Ēostre]] article belongs on that articles talk page-- underscoring, I think, the misplacement of your edits on this article.  An example of that, is that to respond to my part in this discussion, you first had to go add material to the other article.

--[[User:Crews Giles|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;cregil&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Crews Giles|&lt;small&gt;(''talk'')&lt;/small&gt;]] 15:50, 2 May 2012 (UTC)

:::I went and added the Shaw references, which was cited throughout the article. I had added the material previous to this discussion. What's your point? Anyway, like I said before, you clearly have a poor grip on what we're talking about; as Shaw (2011) discusses at length, comparative linguistics, personal names, a cluster of toponyms, and the discovery of earlier matronae all provide evidence for the goddess that must be considered. These are all factors in the discussion. And, as I said before, due to the well attested Indo-European cognates (Ushas, Eos, Aurora, etc., etc.), Eostre could likely be [[Linguistic reconstruction|reconstructed]] without any of that evidence. You're going to great lengths to produce original research here (&quot;you may have responding to the analysis of the scholarship-- which I took the trouble to provide&quot;) to defend your position, when what you should be doing is finding scholarship backing your position. Good luck with that. In the mean time, I'm not interested in reading your (or anyone else's) confused original research on Wikipedia, whether or not you want to call it an &quot;analysis of the scholarship&quot;. [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 18:02, 2 May 2012 (UTC)

:::: What is my point?

:::: And you accuse me (well, most everyone, really) of having a poor grasp of what I/we read? 

::::The point was that this discussion belongs on the [[Ēostre]] article.  I must have had made that too vague for you when I used the words,&quot;Also, this entire discussion of the [[Ēostre]] article belongs on that articles talk page.&quot;

::::Good grief!

::::: ''Anyway, like I said before, you clearly have a poor grip on what we're talking about''

:::: You have used that and similar slaps to so many in this discussion. You realize that indicates a character flaw, right?  It is also a violation. 

::::There have been several opportunities to respond to known facts and objections counter to your argument, but insults is the best you have managed-- insults followed by merely repeating your original ''non sequitur'' as if repeating it will suddenly make your conclusion logical.  It won't.

:::: BECAUSE the name of several towns can be traced to the root word for &quot;shine&quot; 
:::: THEREFORE IT FOLLOWS THAT
:::: Christians named their practices from Bede's Ēostre goddess worship.

:::: NO!  It does not follow.  No matter how many times you write it or how you word it-- no matter what scholar you have making such a statement-- you cannot fix the broken logic.  What about &quot;No!&quot; do you not understand?

:::: As for your claim of my &quot;original research&quot; I have provided no original research.  I simply read with comprehension, and because you claimed &quot;original research&quot; last time I paraphrased your own arguments, this most recent time I cited your own article after paraphrasing what you wrote-- directly quoting. 

:::: I don't blame you for not wishing to have your own words used to cut the legs out from under your own argument-- but you cannot call quoting your edits and looking at a map &quot;original research&quot;-- in my world-- that is called simple reasoning.--[[User:Crews Giles|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;cregil&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Crews Giles|&lt;small&gt;(''talk'')&lt;/small&gt;]] 21:11, 2 May 2012 (UTC)

:::::Okay, after &quot;BECAUSE the name of several towns can be traced to the root word for &quot;shine&quot; THEREFORE IT FOLLOWS THAT Christians named their practices from Bede's Ēostre goddess worship. NO!  It does not follow.  No matter how many times you write it or how you word it-- no matter what scholar you have making such a statement-- you cannot fix the broken logic.  What about &quot;No!&quot; do you not understand?&quot;, I do not think I need to respond further. This statement, with its head-scratching inaccuracies combined with an open disdain for scholarship, says it all. [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 21:44, 2 May 2012 (UTC)

== No history section? ==

This article is laughable; it almost reads like a Hallmark marketing promo. Well done wiki-elites for letting this one article slide.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/66.229.248.119|66.229.248.119]] ([[User talk:66.229.248.119|talk]]) 18:50, 7 April 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:You're not alone with this criticism, as the talk page makes it clear. However, under threat of being blocked, it has been made clear that not even a &lt;nowiki&gt;{{NPOV}}&lt;/nowiki&gt; tag is to be allowed on the article space until Easter is over, regardless of the various threads here discussing how un-neutral the article is. [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 19:54, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
::User:Bloodofox, you are trying to fuse the ''[[Ēostre]]'' with the ancient Christian celebration of Pascha, as it is known by most non-English speaking Christians. That term itself is derived from ''[[Passover]]''. If history is to be added it should focus on this ([http://www.churchyear.net/easter.html see reference]). The source states: {{quotation|The English word for the feast of the resurrection, Easter, differs from the feast's name in other regions. In other regions the term is &quot;Pascha,&quot; which is derived from the word for &quot;Passover.&quot; The word &quot;Easter&quot; might come from an Anglo-Saxon spring goddess. This is probably because the festival of Easter overlapped some pagan holiday in ancient England. While some have used this fact to say celebrating Easter is pagan, the fact is that only the name comes from a pagan source, probably stemming from popular usage.}} 
::The source also indicates that Easter/Pascha was celebrated by the [[Early Church]], long before Christianity even arrived in Europe. Thanks, [[User:Anupam|Anupam]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Anupam|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 20:15, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
:::First, I am trying to do no such thing. Secondly, your source is not a reliable source and not acceptable here. Please stick to academic works. To be sure, indeed, the history of Pascha needs to be covered just as much as its importation and synthesis with Eostre-monath, as modern Easter is in fact the combination of the two as much as Yule and Christmas came to intermingle in the English-speaking world. [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 20:19, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
::::Is it your contention that members of the Greek Orthodox Archdiocese of the USA do not exist?[[User:Dogface|Dogface]] ([[User talk:Dogface|talk]]) 22:32, 7 April 2012 (UTC)
:::::What? [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 23:33, 7 April 2012 (UTC)

== No NPOV Tag Allowed on Article on Threat of Block ==

Administrator {{user|Kim Dent-Brown}} has been very vocal on this talk page that he will block users who add an &lt;nowiki&gt;{{npov}}&lt;/nowiki&gt; tag to this article before Easter is over. Seriously. However, just about every user on this talk page has expressed concern that this article does not reflect the secular element of this holiday.  In fact, the word &quot;secular&quot; (i.e. non-religious) appears only a single time on this article. Consensus that this article is therefore not neutral is strong, and Kim above even acknowledges this. I have previously presented some quality academic references covering this very subject, and there many others out there to be handled in turn. A few of these references:
* Duchak, Alicia (1999). ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=qWkoF8eJ07kC&amp;pg=PA99&amp;dq=secular+easter+customs&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=2k5-T-CJBZOW8gTe6qWLDg&amp;ved=0CEUQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=secular%20easter%20customs&amp;f=false A-Z of Modern America]''. Psychology Press.
* Watts, Linda S. (2007). ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=2dce6_CA76MC&amp;pg=PA122&amp;dq=secular+easter+customs&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=Ok9-T__nCob-9QTYutHjDg&amp;ved=0CDsQ6AEwADgK#v=onepage&amp;q=secular%20easter%20customs&amp;f=false Encyclopedia of American Folklore]''. Infobase Publishing.
Now, I ask, is it this acceptable administrator conduct—to decide that they will block users who add a tag to the article reflecting the state of the talk page? This is the first time I've ever seen an administrator decide that they have this ability—to block users for adding an appropriate tag because they have decided that it is inappropriate to have on the article on the day of the holiday—and I think it requires some discussion here. [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 12:03, 8 April 2012 (UTC)
:This article will not be improved by an NPOV template, still less by spending ages deciding whether or not one should be added. Divert this energy to improving the article and to discussing a compromise so that both sides of this can contribute to an improved article. That means stopping trying to prove others wrong, and starting trying to devise text on which you can all agree. If you insist on an NPOV template and really think it will help the article, slap one on after the main page link has gone in less than 24 hours. [[User:Kim Dent-Brown|&lt;font face=&quot;century gothic&quot;  color=&quot;#0E6E2D&quot;&gt;Kim Dent-Brown&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Kim Dent-Brown|&lt;font face=&quot;century gothic&quot; size=&quot;1&quot; color=&quot;#0E6E2D&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;(Talk)&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 12:09, 8 April 2012 (UTC)
::Sweeping the neutrality issues that this article has under the carpet (on threat of block no less) on the day that it gets the most visibility only hinders it from attracting more collaborating editors outside of the usual suspects on this talk page. You are hindering the collaborative process of this page and attempting to make the article look as if it has less problems than it does. [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 12:29, 8 April 2012 (UTC)
:::You [[WP:BATTLEGROUND]] attitude is not helping one whit. '''No-one''' objects to adding more material on secular aspects of celebrations and their history - preferably giving a world wide view of various traditions. But you should not confuse omissions with POV issues. Weakness in certain areas does not necessarily imply that the article is slanted to a POV. If there were no information on - say - Russian traditions, this would not make the article &quot;anti-Russian&quot;. That would only be the case if they had been deliberately excluded for some ideological reason. If they are not there just because no-one's added them yet, ''there is no POV issue''; and there is no point in creating drama by adding POV tags. What other editors have objected to is your attempt to argue that Easter was somehow originally a Germanic pagan festivity, or that neo-pagans have &quot;revived&quot; this &quot;original&quot; celebration. That's a fringe POV, and it is you who brought it to the article. By saying now that you just want to add material on secular celebrations, you are changing your story. That's ''not'' a POV issue, it's about filling gaps and adding useful content. BTW, I don't think generic popular encyclopedias of folklore are &quot;quality&quot; academic sources. Such general literature often repeats out of date material. [[User:Paul Barlow|Paul B]] ([[User talk:Paul Barlow|talk]]) 12:43, 8 April 2012 (UTC)
::::Here we go again. Paul, I've quite clearly commented on Germanic paganism on this article for years now. In fact, at some point I even remember adding the English and German etymology (mostly) as it still stands to this article. Indeed, I am the primary author of [[Ēostre]] and around 50 GA articles on related subject matter. I've said absolutely nothing &quot;fringe&quot; on the subject matter, and I challenge you to ''find it'' if I have (but I suggest you prepare yourself). ''Easter'' or its ancestral word ''Ēostre'', as in the heathen deity and subsequent festivals in honor thereof from which the German and English Christian Paschal season takes its name, did indeed originate in the pre-Christian stratum, and much debate has waged since the 19th century as to whether or not various customs now considered ''secular'' or ''cultural'' originate from pre-Christian practices or not (of which I am generally skeptical, but there's much to say here). You're surely well aware of this by now.

::::As to how to approach the revival of pre-Christian veneration of the goddess from which the current Christian and secular holiday takes its name in English and German is yet another matter, and remains pretty thorny due to evidently spotty academic coverage and the semantics of ''Easter'' and ''Ēostre'' in modern and Old English. The secular issue is a third separate issue. The issue of this this article not reflecting the major secular aspects in favor of an entirely Christian approach is obviously not neutral. Further, I'll note that I am simply one of numerous editors over the years to raise these issues, and it has been discussed here previously how there are a variety of &quot;Easters&quot; due to this; Christian, secular, and the pre-Christian. How to handle these three &quot;Easters&quot; has been a constant thorn in the side of this article. But, as another editor has noted above, it seems that this article has swung way in the direction of the Christian at the expense of all else.

::::Further, specialized academic handbooks and encyclopedias are perfectly acceptable sources and often the best way to get an opinion of &quot;general&quot; approaches in their fields. As my time is now up on this (much of it was spent yesterday on an inappropriate block made by Kim above and subsequently quickly lifted) I'll leave you to decided what to do with these aspects of the article. This is exactly why such tags are necessary; some of us have very limited time on Wikipedia, often just enough time to the attention of others to issues or to improve specifically targeted articles. [[User:Bloodofox|&amp;#58;bloodofox:]] ([[User talk:Bloodofox|talk]]) 13:04, 8 April 2012 (UTC)
:Wow... why can't we just change the name to Pascha as it is a more accurate term, then Bloodofox can better learn the subject![[Special:Contributions/75.73.114.111|75.73.114.111]] ([[User talk:75.73.114.111|talk]]) 22:30, 27 June 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>42wdi85tzbfcka9dhrsq70brrvf7axw</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
