<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Covenant</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1272653</id>
    <revision>
      <id>477616894</id>
      <parentid>423033018</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-02-18T22:43:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pastaguy12</username>
        <id>14761293</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Disambiguation */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11597">{{DisambigProject}}
{{WikiProject Law|class=C|importance=High}}
{{talkheader}}

{{todo|6}}
==Inexplicably deleted==
[[User:Ihcoyc|Ihcoyc]], the religious info regarding Covenant wasn't &quot;inexplicably deleted&quot; &amp;mdash; it was moved to its own page at [[covenant (theological term)]].  Your restore has removed all references to the new [[covenant (disambiguation)|disambiguation page]], all pages linked from that disambiguation page that were not mentioned in the original article, ''and'' all edits to the new theological-term page since the split.  The split happened because there were simply too many senses being referred to at once; if you came to the link from another article expecting to find the theological info, the proper thing to do was correct the inbound links &amp;mdash; and ''not'' to revert.  I'm reverting your revert. - [[User:Korpios|Korpios]] 17:34, 6 Jul 2004 (UTC)

:Update &amp;mdash; actually, it was [[User:Stevertigo|Stevertigo]]'s fault in removing the link to the disambiguation page.  Sorry to blame you for that part, but the page still needs to be reverted. - [[User:Korpios|Korpios]] 17:38, 6 Jul 2004 (UTC)

::I gathered that something of the sort had happened, but I couldn't figure out what it was from the history or the comments, so it struck me as odd.  No problem; I just didn't want there not to be a page on the theology part.  [[User:Ihcoyc|Smerdis of Tlön]] 18:26, 6 Jul 2004 (UTC)

:::Understandable; again, sorry to blame you, but I at first couldn't understand why you did what you did, until I went back through the revisions one-by-one and realized that you were seeing a page without the {alternateuses} link. - [[User:Korpios|Korpios]] 18:45, 6 Jul 2004 (UTC)

::I would like to put up a request to clean up the covenant page and the covenant disambiguation page by merging them and shortening the descriptions that accompany newly merged page.  Since i am new, I hesitate to add the /attention/ flag at the top of the directly linking [[covenant|covenant]] page

::: adendum to previous post [[User:Ramius|Ramius V. Schweitzer]] 21:48, Nov 25, 2004 (UTC)

==Southern states==
Aren't there also a few of the Southern US states that have created a second type of marriage called a covenant marriage? A quick Google search find that there are currently three states (Arkansas, Arizona and Louisiana) that currently have covenant marriage laws, and a few other states where they have been proposed. There is also non-governmental movement for a form of covenant marriage. (see [http://www.divorcereform.org/cov.html]) [[User:GK|gK [[User talk:GK|&amp;iquest;?]]]] 12:04, 13 Dec 2004 (UTC)

==Categories?==
What categories should this article be under? --[[User:Randolph|Randolph]] 00:10, 3 May 2005 (UTC)

it should stay as is

==Hate group==
Can someone find a referance for Covenant, as a hate group? [[User:Gflores|Gflor]][[User:Gflores/Esperanza|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;e&lt;/font&gt;]][[User:Gflores|s]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[User Talk:Gflores|Talk]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 00:40, 3 April 2006 (UTC)

==Halo==
&quot;The Covenant&quot; shouldn't automatically forward to the Halo article. The 2006 movie generates far more hits on Google and is more widely-known in general.&lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[User:71.35.125.183|71.35.125.183]] ([[User talk:71.35.125.183|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/71.35.125.183|contribs]]) {{{2|}}}.&lt;/small&gt;
:You do have to consider that Halo has been around a lot longer than the film.--[[User:Drat|Drat]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Drat|Talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 11:19, 31 August 2006 (UTC)

== Covenant definition need correcting ==

The definition of covenant listed here is fundamentally flawed.  Covenant relationships are most definitely two-way and are essentially contracts.  Both parties must agree to the terms of the covenant and be willing participants.  What makes covenantial relationships different from others is that they are unbreakable.  Many covenants were &quot;to the death&quot; in that the parties entering into covenant agreed that they would rather die than forsake the terms of the covenant.  Today, we see a growth in what's called Covenant Marriages (very much a two-way relationship) where the parties agree to make their vows intentially hard to break.  Both parties are most definitely bound by the terms of the covenant.  

Biblically, the word covenant comes from the Hebrew word &quot;Berith&quot;.  The greek word is &quot;diatheke&quot;.  It was the translation of &quot;diatheke&quot; as &quot;testament&quot; instead of covenant (I believe it was in the King James Verson of the Bible) that has caused many to believe that this is much like a &quot;Last Will and Testament&quot; or a one-way agreement.  Most translations today, correctly translate this word as &quot;covenant&quot; giving it an intirely different (and appropriate) conotation from testament.

I can go on since I find this subject fascinating, butt for now, let's update the definition to reflect correctly that covenant is two-way and is unique among other contracts in that it was binding.--[[User:Taratime|Taratime]] 02:27, 15 October 2006 (UTC)

: I changed &quot;a covenant can also be made could also refer to the unconditional promises made to humanity by God&quot; to &quot;covenants have been made by God with humanity&quot;.  [[User:Heptazane|Heptazane]] 20:04, 9 September 2007 (UTC)

::The current definition of covenant is just flat-out wrong.  This one-way idea is just bogus.  It's been a year and a half, and still no one defends it.  I'm changing it within the next few days.  &amp;nbsp;&lt;font style=&quot;background: lightblue&quot;  color=&quot;#000000&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;'''GUÐSÞEGN'''&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/font&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash;&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;[[User:Guðsþegn|U]][[User talk:Guðsþegn|T]][[Special:Emailuser/Guðsþegn|E]][[WP:X|X]]&lt;/small&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; 12:28, 1 April 2008 (UTC)

: I am trying to move the covenants legal section to an article [[Covenant (law)|covenant]] that can keep all the info in one place. I removed most of the information from this page seems it seems to be a random mishmosh of specific legal covenants, but got an automatic reversion. Not enterirely sure why? This information seems a little rough. I have also added [[Covenant (law)|covenant]] to the disambiguation page  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Ontheinternets|Ontheinternets]] ([[User talk:Ontheinternets|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Ontheinternets|contribs]]) 17:07, 3 May 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Definition of covenant, in the religious sense==

Should probably create a separate link for [[covenant theology]], as a specific [[hermeneutics|hermeneutical framework]] for interpreting the Bible, particularly popular among [[Presbyterianism|Presbyterians]] and other [[Calvinism|Reformed]].

Should also probably create a separate link for the concept of covenant expressed in such documents as the [[Solemn League and Covenant]], and for the concept of covenant in [[Judaism]]. &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[User:Edonovan|Edonovan]] ([[User talk:Edonovan|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Edonovan|contribs]]) 01:34, 14 December 2006 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;

==Dubious definition==
I see that almost 10 months later a dubious definition of religious covenant is still in place. Every text I've read does not limit the meaning the way this article does. [[User:24.6.65.83|24.6.65.83]] 23:11, 7 August 2007 (UTC)

::Agreed.  The definition of religious covenant is also wrong.  I'm changing it within the next few days, too.  &amp;nbsp;&lt;font style=&quot;background: lightblue&quot;  color=&quot;#000000&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;'''GUÐSÞEGN'''&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/font&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash;&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;[[User:Guðsþegn|U]][[User talk:Guðsþegn|T]][[Special:Emailuser/Guðsþegn|E]][[WP:X|X]]&lt;/small&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; 12:28, 1 April 2008 (UTC)

==What about patent covenants?==
Should we also put that into &quot;law and government&quot; section somewhere?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Jagy|Jagy]] ([[User talk:Jagy|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Jagy|contribs]]) 14:15, 12 December 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Dispute ==
The basic definition of [[covenant]] is disputed on its [[Talk:covenant|talk]] page. When that is resolved, this one-liner definition should be updated, if required. [[User:Markhurd|Mark Hurd]] ([[User talk:Markhurd|talk]]) 00:42, 18 December 2008 (UTC)

== Split this page ==
I think this page should be split. It currently discusses three largely distinct topics:
*Covenants, as a religious concept
*Covenants, as a legal concept
*Covenants, as a historical term for &quot;treaty&quot; or &quot;agreement&quot;
The only thing these three have in common is the dictionary definition of &quot;covenant&quot;.

I would propose:
* The section on in a religious context can be moved to [[Covenant (biblical)]]. The concept has a broader religious application than the Bible alone, since this article talks about its presence in Islam and Indo-Iranian religions such as Zoroastrianism, and it also exists in Bahaism (see [[Covenant of Bahá'u'lláh]]). But maybe we can cater for that still in one article, by renaming [[Covenant (biblical)]] to e.g. [[Covenant (religion)]]? Or else, a separate [[Covenant (religion)]] for the transreligious aspects, and then the specifically Judaeo-Christian in [[Covenant (biblical)]]? But, since this concept is much more important in Judaism and Christianity than in other religions, there is inevitably going to be much more meat in [[Covenant (biblical)]] than any [[Covenant (religion)]], so that argues for having just one article
* We already have [[Covenant (law)]], I don't see why the legal content of this page can't be merged into that
* There's not much more to Covenant in history than there is to [[Covenant (disambiguation)]]. Maybe this content could just be moved to this page?
* Finally, redirect this page to [[Covenant (disambiguation)]].

What do people think? --[[User:SJK|SJK]] ([[User talk:SJK|talk]]) 08:57, 6 July 2010 (UTC)
:OK, no one else responded, so I went ahead and did it. I have split the article into [[Covenant (law)]], [[Covenant (religion)]], and [[Covenant (historical)]]. I am not sure if the later two articles really should exist - maybe [[Covenant (religion)]] should merge with [[Covenant (biblical)]], and [[Covenant (historical)]] could just go away? But anyway, I have kept them for now. --[[User:SJK|SJK]] ([[User talk:SJK|talk]]) 00:27, 10 July 2010 (UTC)

== Old edit history ==

There are now 400+ deleted edits for this page. I was going to just merge them into the history of the disambiguation page, but I'm not sure if that would create a bigger mess. Anyone have more experience with the results of a split like the one done here? -- [[User:JHunterJ|JHunterJ]] ([[User talk:JHunterJ|talk]]) 13:19, 12 July 2010 (UTC)

:Why are they deleted? I see that some of my edits (the second and third paragraphs that I added at covenant (law)) are no longer reflected in this history, and I don't really like that. They should be restored to this page's history. 15:56, 12 July 2010 (UTC)

== Disambiguation ==

Should this page not instead be considering the religous sense of the word, and also have a disambiguation page linked at the beginning of the page? This instead of merely having an actual article as a disimbiguation page. [[User:Pastaguy12|Pastaguy12]] ([[User talk:Pastaguy12|talk]]) 22:42, 18 February 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>9m63yi6oy4c63l7o1o5cte1au1ej28d</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
