<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Second Great Awakening</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>101855</id>
    <revision>
      <id>510078069</id>
      <parentid>491474521</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-08-31T08:17:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Psychonaut</username>
        <id>28478</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Misleading graph */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18020">{{talk header}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
 {{WikiProject Christianity
  |class=B |importance=Low
  |charismatic-christianity=yes |charistmatic-christianity-importance=
  |latter-day-saint-movement=yes |latter-day-saint-movement-importance= Mid
 }}
 {{USHistoryTalk|class=B|importance=}}
}}

==Merge==
I'm not sure I'd agree with merging Old/New Lights with this article - they are usually associated with the First, not the Second Great Awakening.  Perhaps some disucussion of Old and New School Presbyterians would be helpful, though.  

-JFahler

: And the terms are more general than the use here.  I've expanded [[Old Lights]] as an example; if there are no objections, I'll eventually merge [[New Light]] into [[Old Lights]], and remove all the merge tags.
: -- [[User:TimNelson|TimNelson]] 10:16, 10 April 2007 (UTC)

:: Done -- [[User:TimNelson|TimNelson]] 12:01, 24 April 2007 (UTC)

==Copyvio?==
Blocks of this text show up in Google, at:

http://www.gmsys.net/teachers/english/background/history/us_history4.htm

http://odur.let.rug.nl/~usa/H/1994/ch4_p13.htm

Does it have copyright problems?

----
This article is copied in several places on the internet, and with each new copy I believe that an historical inaccuracy is perpetuated.  It claims that observers of the Second Awakening revivals in the East were &quot;awed by the respectful silence&quot; of those bearing witness to their faith.  This does not appear to be true &amp;mdash; however, I'll leave it there until I can find solid proof.  I used to have a quote, which I believed was the original source of this misquote, which I took to say almost precisely the opposite.  I'll see if I can find it. Otherwise, the article is dense with good information, IMO. &amp;mdash; [[User:Mkmcconn|Mkmcconn]]

Contrary to the paragraph:
:There was dancing, running and singing - all of which Stone said were manifestations of God's presence. The noise of the meetings was so great that some said &quot;the noise was like the roar of Niagara.&quot; 

Supporting the paragraph:
: &quot;In the east, Yale University experienced a revival of Biblical Christianity under President Timothy Dwight, Jonathan Edwards' grandson. Christianity was almost nonexistent then at Yale, the campus church almost extinct. For four years Dwight preached a series of weekly sermons on Christian belief; when he finished the series, he started over again. Finally, in 1801, after seven years of preaching, revival came to Yale. At least half of the student body was converted to Christianity under Dwight's Presidency. One college tutor wrote home to his mom, &quot;Yale College is a little temple; prayer and praise seem to be the delight of the greater part of the students while those who are still unfeeling are awed with respectful silence.&quot; [http://www.gospelcom.net/chi/GLIMPSEF/Glimpses/glmps040.shtml]

The contrast here is between the experience-centered revivals of Cane Ridge, and the college-centered revivals in the eastern states.  But even in this, does the quote really say what the entry has taken it to say?  Are the unbelieving students in awe of the respectful silence kept by those who testify to their faith?  Or isn't the reporter, in plainer English, writing to tell his mother that even those who are not part of the revival of religion at the college are not speaking out against it or mocking it, but respectfully keep their mouths shut.  I'm considering how to change the entry. &amp;mdash; [[User:Mkmcconn|Mkmcconn]]

: I've deleted the paragraph. [[User:Mkmcconn|Mkmcconn]] 19:39 May 7, 2003 (UTC)

== Second Great Awakening  ==

Can we put some dates on this? Is  ca, 1790- 1840 realistic?

: It depends on who's doing the telling.  The Cumberland Presbyterians date the revival from around 1795 (numerous presbyteries passed several resolutions to pray for revival, beginning around 1790, or so).  The Stone-Campbell people date it from 1800/1801 (Cane Ridge). The end is harder to point to. [[User:Mkmcconn|Mkmcconn]][[User Talk:Mkmcconn| &lt;small&gt;(Talk)&lt;/small&gt;]] 04:44, 11 July 2005 (UTC)

::Would it be reasonable to put the endpoint at 1844 with the [[Great Disappointment]]?? [[User:Ansell|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#0000FF;&quot;&gt;Ans&lt;/span&gt;]][[User:Ansell/Esperanza|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#009000;&quot;&gt;e&lt;/span&gt;]][[User talk:Ansell|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#0000FF;&quot;&gt;ll&lt;/span&gt;]] 08:51, 30 April 2006 (UTC)
:::yes but that only affected a small group of Millerites. the next awakening has to start 1857 so we better end this one in 1840s [[User:Rjensen|Rjensen]] 09:34, 30 April 2006 (UTC)

This article needs dates.

Suggested Revision:
The first sentence of this article states the dates as 1790-1840 and then claims that it &quot;was a period of great religious revival that extended into the antebellum period.&quot;  If you follow the link of antebellum period (&quot;the time period in America from after the birth of the United States to the start of the American Civil War&quot;) and use the provided definition, the Second Great Awakening didn't extend into the antebellum period, it took place entirely within that period. Just a thought.

== Causes? ==

Does anyone know why this happened? It would be hard to believe it's just a big coincidence... --[[User:Euyyn|euyyn]] 07:47, 7 June 2006 (UTC)

I've just found something about this [[Great Disappointment|here]] --[[User:Euyyn|euyyn]] 07:50, 7 June 2006 (UTC)

And this in History of the LDS:

:This &quot;awakening&quot; was a [[Christianity|Christian]] response to the [[secularism]] of the [[Age of Enlightenment]], and extended throughout the [[United States]], particularly the frontier areas of the west.

I hope to find something more scattered in other articles before I try to add it to the article. --[[User:Euyyn|euyyn]] 00:44, 25 June 2006 (UTC)

Louis P. Masur, 1831:  Year of Eclipse.  

&quot;But with this growth [referring to the expansion of the United States, Westward development, etc.]came discord.  The middle class divided on political and religious issues and united against the labouring classes on moral questions such as the consumprion of alcohol.  The story repeated itself in scores of other towns and cities.  With expansion and wealth came dissension and strife.  Only a revival of religion, many believed, could preserve the nation &quot;from our vast extent of territory, our numerous and increasing population, from diversity of local interests, the power of selfishness, and the fury of sectional jealousy and hate.&quot; page 66.  quoting from Lyman Beecher &quot;Necessity of Revivals.&quot;  

You should also look at Joyce Appleby's &quot;Inheriting the Revolution&quot; which talks about how the 2nd Great Awakening interacted with republican ideas of progress and self-development.  Both civic and religious reformers saw mankind as flawed, capable of being reformeed, and that that reform must start from the self.  This fit well with republican virtues, even if religious involvement with the state did not.
[[User:Cherbert18|Cherbert18]] 20:17, 15 January 2007 (UTC)
[[User:Aimzzz|Aimzzz]] ([[User talk:Aimzzz|talk]]) 21:18, 1 August 2009 (UTC)
Also, there are *no* citations in the last 3 sections:
Appalachian, 
Prominent figures, 
Political implications  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Aimzzz|Aimzzz]] ([[User talk:Aimzzz|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Aimzzz|contribs]]) 21:16, 1 August 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
I agree and have edited the Political Implications of the article. This article seems to be unfocused because it does not place the revival movement within a larger framework social experimentation. It completely ignores the great importance of marriage, conception and sexual control , that were more important practical matters, in all of these groups.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/98.217.7.202|98.217.7.202]] ([[User talk:98.217.7.202|talk]]) 13:41, 18 October 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Asahel Nettleton ==

Just observed that as yet there is no Wikipedia page for [[Asahel Nettleton]] ([[1783]]&amp;ndash;[[1844]]) who was one of the most influential figures during the Second Great Awakening.  This is a plea for someone to take up the task. [http://www.reformedreader.org/nettleton.htm] gives a cameo. [http://members.aol.com/intoutreach/NettletonBio.html] is a brief biographical sketch.  To prepare such an article, the user is directed to the invaluable book by [[Andrew A. Bonar]] and Bennet Tyler.  [[User:David Haslam|DFH]] 19:18, 20 July 2006 (UTC)

==Swedenborgianism==
Does anyone have information on whether [[Swedenborgianism]] was involved in the SGA?  The English church had missionaries in the United States about this time.  [[User:WBardwin|WBardwin]] 06:53, 20 May 2007 (UTC)

==Controversy and Generations==

I have a couple of questions/comments about this article

1.  Why is no mention made of the fact that the Second Great Awakening is a controversial term among historians?  Many feel lumping various 19th century religious movements under that term (and implicitly making a connection to the original &quot;Great Awakening&quot;) is a huge mistake.  I think this should be discussed, and I might try to work on this in the future.

2.  What is up with the &quot;generations&quot; box on the right?  I know the Strauss and Howe book and found it interesting, but implicitly tying the Second Great Awakening to some made-up list of American generations is completely bizarre and practically constitutes original research, since this was apparently not one of the &quot;generations&quot; which Strauss and Howe used.  Can we delete this from the article?  Historians of this period would, I think, shudder at its inclusion.--[[User:Bigtimepeace|Bigtimepeace]] &lt;small&gt;| [[User_talk:Bigtimepeace|talk]] |  [[Special:Contributions/Bigtimepeace|contribs]]&lt;/small&gt; 19:55, 27 June 2007 (UTC)

:No replies, and I have gone ahead and removed the generations template. I find the entire template to be bizarre and probably worthy of deletion, but it certainly does not belong here.  The Second Great Awakening is not a &quot;generation&quot; and is not even referred to as such by Strauss and Howe, nor anyone else as far as I am aware.  As I mentioned above, the very term &quot;Second Great Awakening&quot; is so controversial among historians that referring to it as a &quot;generation&quot; is even more ridiculous.  We're making stuff up out of whole cloth here. I'm theoretically open to arguments for including this template in the article, and I think such arguments need to be offered before the template is reinstated.  Arguments like &quot;it's a useful template&quot; or &quot;the Second Great Awakening is included in the template&quot; will obviously not be convincing.--[[User:Bigtimepeace|Bigtimepeace]] &lt;small&gt;| [[User_talk:Bigtimepeace|talk]] |  [[Special:Contributions/Bigtimepeace|contribs]]&lt;/small&gt; 19:20, 9 July 2007 (UTC)

::The [[Strauss and Howe]] fan club is really out of control. They behave as if anyone reads their books.  It's spread like a virus onto many pages on wikipedia and needs to be monitored. 
:::More importantly, WHO CAME UP WITH THE IDEA OF A SECOND GREAT AWAKENING????? This seems like a very biased, point of view, article, with little basis in reality.  I know of no US Historians who take the term seriously.  This article needs citations or it needs to die.  I'm sorry, but it's not fair to promote the idea of a &quot;Second Great Awakening&quot; as if it's a fact.  SAYS WHO?  Very unhappy with this article.  I'd like to see this article's fans come up with some firm backing.  --[[User:Dylanfly|Dylanfly]] 16:45, 28 July 2007 (UTC)
::::P.S. The citations which mention &quot;Great Awakening&quot; include articles from 1970, 1980.  The Hankins book sold so poorly that it never came out in paperback.  So does this &quot;great awakening&quot; exist?

== Vandalism ==

This page has been vandalised but I don't know enough about the topic to repair it.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Wayne Stewart|Wayne Stewart]] ([[User talk:Wayne Stewart|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Wayne Stewart|contribs]]) 04:06, 7 November 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Alexander Campbell ==

Alexander Campbell never affiliated with the Baptists, so I changed his denomination to Christian Church (Disciples of Christ) which is the denomination that he founded.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Copywriter2001|Copywriter2001]] ([[User talk:Copywriter2001|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Copywriter2001|contribs]]) 01:32, 13 July 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;


== Ellen White ==

Ellen White was described as a false prophet, which I have changed to not cause offense to Seventh-day Adventists ( including myself )! [[User:Verisate|Verisate]] ([[User talk:Verisate|talk]]) 10:47, 12 November 2008 (UTC)

== Mormonism and Seventh Day Adventist should be seperated out. ==

Firstly, since there was no Mormonism or Seventh Day Adventist belief during the first great awakening it stands to reason they were CREATED during the 2nd great awakening rather then part of the CAUSE.

Secondly, The great awakening is a reference to the return to basic traditional Christianity not new streams. That could be included in it's own topic. Mormonism includes &quot;new&quot; revelation only contained in The Book of Mormon and is rejected by tradition Christianity. Seventh Day Adventist also have beliefs that are not considered mainstream Christianity which is what the great awakenings were about; a return to not a divergence from.

[[User:Davf|Davf]] ([[User talk:Davf|talk]]) 05:09, 25 February 2009 (UTC)Davf

== Creedance Clearwater Revival Church? ==

The current article contains a reference to a &quot;Creedence Clearwater Revival&quot; Church.  That name coincides with the name of a [[Creedence Clearwater Revival|famous rock band]].  One might guess that maybe the band was named after the church, but the band's article says its name was invented in 1967 by combining &quot;Creedence&quot; from a person's name, &quot;Clearwater&quot; from a beer commercial, and &quot;Revival&quot; to symbolize the members' commitment.  No church of this name can be found via Google.  It seems quite surprising that a band name independently invented in 1967 would just happen to coincide with the name of a church from the 1800s, so I wonder if the presence of this name in the article might be the result of vandalism. [[Special:Contributions/216.59.249.45|216.59.249.45]] ([[User talk:216.59.249.45|talk]]) 03:02, 26 May 2009 (UTC)

:I also just noticed this change and reverted it.  The change was made in [[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Second_Great_Awakening&amp;diff=49994241&amp;oldid=49992715|this] edit from April 24, 2006. I reverted it back to the original which was Gasper River church. --[[User:Scottmsg|Scottmsg]] ([[User talk:Scottmsg|talk]]) 03:06, 26 May 2009 (UTC)

== [[Benevolent Empire]] ==

I'm currently trying to edit a page called [[Benevolent Empire]]. Just wanted to list it here in case there is someone interested in developing that page. I came to it to 'wikify', but it is in need of a lot of editing. More facts required, and a more neutral tone. I've added a photo and rewritten the intro for neutrality. However, I don't know enough about the subject to bring any more factual detail to it.  It seems to be focused on the social reforms developed or increased during the Second Awakening, but it's not written clearly, mostly just reiterating how wonderful it all was. [[User:Nihola|Nihola]] ([[User talk:Nihola|talk]]) 04:22, 5 February 2011 (UTC)

== Do Mormons &quot;proclaim their roots in the Second Great Awakening&quot;?? ==

The current text of the &quot;Church membership soars&quot; section of the article lists The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints as being ''&quot;Among the new denominations that were formed, and which in the first decade of the 21st century still proclaim their roots in the Second Great Awakening&quot;''.  I doubt many people (either Mormon or not) would agree with this; Mormons (of whom I happen to be one) would generally say that the LDS Church's links to the Second Great Awakening are of a distinctly secondary nature, and many non-Mormons would also object to the suggestion.  Is this really what the cited source says?  [[User:Richwales|&lt;u&gt;Rich&lt;/u&gt;wales]] ([[User talk:Richwales|talk]] · [[Special:Contributions/Richwales|contribs]]) 21:42, 21 July 2011 (UTC)
::the Mormons were not revivalists, but they did emerge from the same Burned-Over district of religious ferment and experimentation that supported other revivalists. Many recent scholars root the Mormons in the ferment of the 2nd Great  Awak. (Remini 2002; Hankins, 2004; Slaughter 2005; Nielson 2009, etc) [[User:Rjensen|Rjensen]] ([[User talk:Rjensen|talk]]) 22:47, 21 July 2011 (UTC)
:::I don't question that the origin and rise of Mormonism was intertwined with the Second Great Awakening.  I was just objecting to the idea that Mormons consider themselves to be a ''product'' of the S.G.A. in the same sense that revivalist denominations do.  I think the new text (with ''&quot;Among the new denominations that were rooted in the religious ferment of the Second Great Awakening&quot;'') is a definite improvement over the earlier version.  [[User:Richwales|&lt;u&gt;Rich&lt;/u&gt;wales]] ([[User talk:Richwales|talk]] · [[Special:Contributions/Richwales|contribs]]) 16:26, 22 July 2011 (UTC)

== Misleading graph ==

The graph here is possibly misleading, as it shows church membership in absolute numbers, and without reference to the general population, which I presume was also growing for the period in question.  This could be remedied by changing the data to show membership as a percentage of the population, or else adding the total general population as another data series. —[[User:Psychonaut|Psychonaut]] ([[User talk:Psychonaut|talk]]) 08:17, 31 August 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>dsrxsbech4qm5vpsmd4yud9c730wxer</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
