<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:List of Catholic priests</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1100842</id>
    <revision>
      <id>378120922</id>
      <parentid>378119937</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-08-10T04:03:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Frostandchill</username>
        <id>12695471</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Creator of this article and those who have updated it lack proper theological knowledge */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3899">Moved from [[List of Catholic Priests]] to correct capitalization. --[[User:Whosyourjudas|Whosyourjudas]] [[User talk:Whosyourjudas|(talk)]] 04:33, 25 Oct 2004 (UTC)

:Please don't make this into a link farm for the sex-abuse scandal. I already have Geoghan on the list and if you want to add more sex-abusers then look in [[:Category:Roman Catholic Church sex abuse scandal]]. In fact I'll head this off myself.--[[User:T. Anthony|T. Anthony]] 09:46, 22 January 2006 (UTC)

::On consideration this worked better as a category and doesn't work well as a list. Sorry, but you live you learn.--[[User:T. Anthony|T. Anthony]] 02:04, 24 January 2006 (UTC)

:::This list needs a lot of work.  When I say a lot, I mean a lot lot lot.  There are thousands upon thousands of notable priests.  What standard does this article use for inclusion?  There are so many notable priests missing from this list.  Why even have this list to begin with?  It needs to be more focused... much more focused. [[User:Frostandchill|Frostandchill]] ([[User talk:Frostandchill|talk]]) 03:40, 10 August 2010 (UTC)

== List of Criminals ==

I removed [[Dale Fushek]] from the &quot;Criminals&quot; section, since he's only been indicted and hasn't been tried.  Listing him as a criminal could be considered [[WP:libel]].  I also removed [[Tim Wilson]], since the person linked to is not a priest or convicted criminal. 

[[John Geoghan]] is a more interesting question, since technically his conviction was overturned.  Erring on the side of only label people convicted as criminals, I removed him as well, but this is probably a matter for wider discussion. -- [[User:Kaszeta|Kaszeta]] 03:06, 18 December 2006 (UTC)

*I deleted this section on &quot;criminals&quot;.  This article's own description states &quot;Catholic priests who are mostly known for their non-priestly work should be placed on other lists.&quot;  Being a criminal is not an intrinsic part of being a priest.  Being a criminal is &quot;non-priestly&quot; and the vast majority of priests are not criminals.  Inclusion of criminals in this manner would be non-scholarly and rather would be in bad faith and perhaps anti-Catholic bias.  There are so many Catholic priests in the world.  Thousands, perhaps millions throughout history.  Why highlight those who have committed crimes when there are so many who are saints and have contributed to this world.  I don't understand how this list is maintainable.  It lacks proper focus and honestly is all over the place.  It has typos, spelling errors.. totally unprofessional organization.  Maybe the whole list should be deleted?  It's worth some thought.  [[User:Frostandchill|Frostandchill]] ([[User talk:Frostandchill|talk]]) 03:54, 10 August 2010 (UTC)

== Creator of this article and those who have updated it lack proper theological knowledge ==

&quot;This is an annotated list of men primarily known for their work as Catholic priests. Catholic priests who are mostly known for their non-priestly work should be placed on other lists. Further men known for being bishops, archbishops, and other positions above the priesthood should be placed elsewhere. This is to avoid redundancy with the [[List of cardinals]], [[List of popes]], etc.&quot;

*Please note the following:
**Being a Catholic priest is not simply a job.  The Catholic priest is ordained as a priest through the sacrament of Holy Orders.  So being a priest is more than just doing some priestly work, but there is an ontological change.  The man ''is'' an ordained priest.
**''Newsflash'', bishops, archbishops, popes, cardinals, etc. are all priests.  They are not in positions &quot;above&quot; the priesthood.  They have received the episcopal ordination and the fullness of the priesthood... but they are still priests.  Breaking News: Pope Benedict XVI is still a priest even though he is Pope.
[[User:Frostandchill|Frostandchill]] ([[User talk:Frostandchill|talk]]) 04:03, 10 August 2010 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>b5w4nhkbqweuwc4llgcbiavtnzdknt8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
