<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Siddur</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>949875</id>
    <revision>
      <id>478209605</id>
      <parentid>477912418</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-02-22T06:54:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yehuda Falk</username>
        <id>1908310</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Hebrew spelling at top of article regarding yud and chirik malei */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5136">{{WikiProject Judaism | class= start | importance= high }}

==Its not what you think!==

Its not what you think!  :) I only removed the Artscroll siddur from the references as part of the removal of all siddurim. I was operating under the tentative classification of having this article be about the history of the siddur, while the article on [[Jewish services]] would be about services and siddurim as they exist (hence, the references on this page to liturgical history.) Yet see my note today the subject, on the WikiJudaism project page. This distinction is up for grabs.  Maybe all the content on Jewish services should be moved here, and a separate article be set up on the history of the liturgy? [[User:RK|RK]] 17:24, Sep 1, 2004 (UTC)

actually we are currently working on a newer version of the Singer's Prayer Book, so you might want to change your reference to the &quot;Centenary Edition of the Singer's Prayer Book&quot; since the new Singer's Prayer Book won't be out until Rosh HaShanna &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:80.74.118.130|80.74.118.130]] ([[User talk:80.74.118.130|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/80.74.118.130|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

I completely rewrote the section on the chabad siddur, as it was both untrue and poorly worded, and rewrote it as a reference to the general sefarad siddur.

i need a list of sefarad siddurim there. I only know the chabad ones.[[Special:Contributions/74.138.193.126|74.138.193.126]] ([[User talk:74.138.193.126|talk]]) 16:04, 8 June 2009 (UTC)

also i was unsure what version of the history to use, so i used a general compromise on all sides... anyone else who wants to look up the jewish encyclopedia and publish from that, or some other such thing, is welcome to do so.[[Special:Contributions/74.138.193.126|74.138.193.126]] ([[User talk:74.138.193.126|talk]]) 16:06, 8 June 2009 (UTC)

== Added daat.co.il ==

daat.co.il has a terriffic online siddur project that contains complete texts with vowels, and it's in actual text format unlike some other online siddurim. i added it to the links section.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Bluesdance|Bluesdance]] ([[User talk:Bluesdance|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Bluesdance|contribs]]) 22:29, 19 February 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Forward Article==
[http://www.forward.com/articles/112469/ Even a New Siddur Can’t Close ‘God Gap’] is a really interesting overview and history of English language translations.... [[User:Fintor|Fintor]] ([[User talk:Fintor|talk]]) 09:26, 14 September 2011 (UTC)

== Hebrew spelling at top of article regarding yud and chirik malei ==

The Hebrew for siddur is spelled [[samekh]], [[yodh]], [[daled]], [[vav (letter)|vav]], [[reish]].  However, this is incorrect, because the [[hiriq]] vowel on the samech is not a chirik malei.  Therefore, there should be no yud in between the samech and the daled.  Same goes for the plural.  I am editing the article unless anyone objects.  Alternatively, if anyone knows how to use Hebrew font on Wikipedia, they can make it look like it is on the [[vidui]] page.  The form for siddur and vidui is called the [http://he.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D7%93%D7%A7%D7%93%D7%95%D7%A7_%D7%A2%D7%91%D7%A8%D7%99#.D7.A9.D7.9D_.D7.A4.D7.A2.D7.95.D7.9C.D7.94 shem hape'ulah], or in english, the [[gerund]].

:Whether the spelling with the yud is correct or incorrect depends on what kind of Hebrew you are talking about. For modern Hebrew without nikud (or, if you prefer, niqud), the spelling with the yud is correct. The spelling is incorrect by the norms of Biblical Hebrew. I think the spelling in the article should be the modern spelling (as it is in the Hebrew Wikipedia). [[User:Yehuda Falk|Yehuda Falk]] ([[User talk:Yehuda Falk|talk]]) 09:15, 20 February 2012 (UTC)

::I disagree.  What you say is true of Israeli Hebrew, but untrue of rabbinic or any other variant of traditional or religious Hebrew till the present day: it's not just a question of remote Biblical Hebrew, when there was no such word anyway.  And as this article is about the Jewish religion and not about Israeli culture we should stick to that spelling (samech, dalet, vav, resh); which is the one you will find on the spine of any actual siddur! --[[User:Sirmylesnagopaleentheda|Sir Myles na Gopaleen (the da)]] ([[User talk:Sirmylesnagopaleentheda|talk]]) 17:22, 20 February 2012 (UTC)

:::I have &quot;actual siddurim&quot; that have the yud (including some editions of Rinat Yisrael), but I suppose that since they are Israeli siddurim they don't count. As for the spelling of Rabbinic Hebrew, it is actually pretty inconsistent, with a fair amount of mixture of &quot;ktiv male&quot; and &quot;ktiv haser&quot;. This hangup that there is one proper spelling is a modern obsession. (There are even inconsistencies of spelling in Biblical Hebrew, although I don't know off-hand about the specific mishkal in question.) [[User:Yehuda Falk|Yehuda Falk]] ([[User talk:Yehuda Falk|talk]]) 06:54, 22 February 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>ghtyn9vagavhdweekn1e778dc8uers4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
