<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Peace</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>239629</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517567571</id>
      <parentid>498279842</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-13T13:01:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Unimpeder</username>
        <id>11507170</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Religious beliefs and peace */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21371">{{ACIDnom}}
{{philosophy|class=c|importance=mid|ethics=yes|social=yes}}
{{WikiProject Anti-war|class=B|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=C|importance=Top}}
{{WP1.0|class=B|category=category|VA=yes}} 
{{Archive box|[[/Archive 1]]}}

== Countries at peace ==

It would be interesting, though I'm sure very difficult, to list the status of every country (ie. &quot;at war&quot; or &quot;peace&quot;) in a table.  Even better would be presenting it as a map!  [[user:violetriga|violet/riga]] [[User_talk:violetriga|(t)]] 19:22, 28 August 2007 (UTC)

:: It would be interesting but it would be POV. Whether a country is at peace or at war is entirely POV. So, NO you should not include it.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Dudeman1st|Dudeman1st]] ([[User talk:Dudeman1st|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Dudeman1st|contribs]]) 02:34, 20 December 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

See also [[War on Terrorism]]. LOL! [[User:Tschravic|Tschravic]] ([[User talk:Tschravic|talk]]) 08:11, 30 April 2009 (UTC)

== Been watching this page for more than a year.  ==

All stuff on this page needs cites. I don't care if it's your religious view or your group's view. There can be no original research or POV stuff on this page, especially without cites. I am now deleting stuff that has been on the page for more than a year without a cite, like &quot;Environmental Peace.&quot; I am reorganizing a little. I will trim down POV stuff. If you have beef with my changes, post here or to my talk page. [[User:Dudeman1st|Dudeman1st]] ([[User talk:Dudeman1st|talk]]) 02:56, 20 December 2007 (UTC)

:Please do not put symbols for peace in the main area. Whether you like it or not, there is no universally recognized symbol for peace. I believe the dove and the &quot;peace sign&quot; are sufficient, but I also believe that a [[swastika]] is a peace symbol. Better to let sleeping dogs lie.[[User:Dudeman1st|Dudeman1st]] ([[User talk:Dudeman1st|talk]]) 03:52, 20 December 2007 (UTC)

== international creed for peace / International Peace Institute ==

I have restored the International Creed for Peace please read to the disscusion page before deleting [[User:Motegole|Motegole]] ([[User talk:Motegole|talk]]) 23:39, 26 December 2007 (UTC)

you know i am not sure what user Jossi meant by &quot;..........., and we are not listing such orgs in this page&quot; please could someone clarify who he is refering to as we [[User:Motegole|Motegole]] ([[User talk:Motegole|talk]]) 23:53, 26 December 2007 (UTC)

see also [http://www.jmu.edu/jmuweb/fs/news/fs9375.shtml]  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Motegole|Motegole]] ([[User talk:Motegole|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Motegole|contribs]]) 00:09, 27 December 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

: This article is about Peace, not about Peace organizations. The material does not belong here. When I said &quot;we&quot; I meant Wikipedia. [[User:Jossi|≈ jossi ≈]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Jossi|(talk)]]&lt;/small&gt; 00:15, 27 December 2007 (UTC)
: Added a redlink to [[International Creed for Peace]], you are welcome to create an article about the subject, based on [[WP:V|verifiable]] sources. This article does not present other organizations related to peace either, so do not add a section about the International Creed for Peace as that will violate [[WP:UNDUE]] [[User:Jossi|≈ jossi ≈]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Jossi|(talk)]]&lt;/small&gt; 00:23, 27 December 2007 (UTC)

:: Why would you delete a redlink to that page? That is very strange behavior... [[User:Jossi|≈ jossi ≈]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Jossi|(talk)]]&lt;/small&gt; 00:25, 27 December 2007 (UTC)

:: Ah... I see that [[Peace Insititute]] was [[Wikipedia:Articles_for_deletion/International_Peace_Institute_%282nd_nomination%29||deleted]]. on the basis of lack of notability. If that is the case, a mention of this &quot;International Cree for Peace&quot; in this article is not warranted either. [[User:Jossi|≈ jossi ≈]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Jossi|(talk)]]&lt;/small&gt; 00:29, 27 December 2007 (UTC)

:::you see you dont take your time to investigate properly [[User:Motegole|Motegole]] ([[User talk:Motegole|talk]]) 00:36, 27 December 2007 (UTC)

:::: Sorry? If that was the case, why did you revert my deletion of the material? [[User:Jossi|≈ jossi ≈]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Jossi|(talk)]]&lt;/small&gt; 00:37, 27 December 2007 (UTC)

:::: In your edit summary you said: ''restored the International Creed for Peace was allowed on the page by consensus''. Where is that discussion? I do not see anything of the kind, on the contrary. [[User:Jossi|≈ jossi ≈]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Jossi|(talk)]]&lt;/small&gt; 00:40, 27 December 2007 (UTC)

please read the discussion page see

12 Recommend removal of &quot;International creed for peace&quot; and &quot;International Peace Institute&quot; and 
18 Reorganized different kinds of peace

you see one person is not wikipedia 

International creed for peace is not an organisation  and it well referenced that is why it survived the deletion on the basis of lack of notability 

i will restore the entry  so that we can allow others to contribute and we will definitly reach a consesus to delete or to keep 

please take is easy i appauld your zeal but let others have a say [[User:Motegole|Motegole]] ([[User talk:Motegole|talk]]) 01:03, 27 December 2007 (UTC)

: This is not about &quot;zeal&quot;, but about material that does not comply with our content policies. The related articles have been all deleted for lack of notability, so the material should stay out of the article. [[User:Jossi|≈ jossi ≈]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Jossi|(talk)]]&lt;/small&gt; 01:37, 27 December 2007 (UTC)
: In case you forgot [[International Creed for Peace]] was deleted in [[Wikipedia:Articles for deletion/International Peace Institute (2nd nomination)|this AfD]] alongside these related articles:
:: {{la|Peace Insititute}}
::{{la|Universal Peace Protocol}}
::{{la|Peace Conservation System}}
::{{la|ICP Campaign}}
::{{la|Post Philosophy}}
::{{la|Christian Post Philosophy}}, and
::{{la|Chika Sylva-Olejeme}}

:Re-adding ''any'' of that material is against community consensus, and will be regarded as [[WP:DE|disruption]] [[User:Jossi|≈ jossi ≈]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Jossi|(talk)]]&lt;/small&gt; 01:41, 27 December 2007 (UTC)

Re- adding? this entry has been on the peace page before and after  all the pages deleted
please investigate before making strong statements [[User:Motegole|Motegole]] ([[User talk:Motegole|talk]]) 01:51, 27 December 2007 (UTC)

: Yes, re-added by you after my deletion.  [[User:Jossi|≈ jossi ≈]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Jossi|(talk)]]&lt;/small&gt; 04:14, 27 December 2007 (UTC)

Dear Jossi, this is the peace page you know, what is the hurry to remove this entry, 1, the website has been cited 2, &quot;WAR AND PEACE: THE ETERNAL SWING&quot; CALL FOR PAPERS 2008 Conference JAMES MADISON UNIVERSITY: April 3-4, 2008 also, you may search the web for even more,
please no disrespect i will restore the entry and await administrative actions as you have suggested,  sometimes  others editors of wikipedia may have alternative opinions to yours in such cases what do you do? let allow other wikipedians  discuss this issue or do you simply take up you decision , i hope you understand i do want to upset you [[User:Motegole|Motegole]] ([[User talk:Motegole|talk]]) 08:47, 28 December 2007 (UTC)

: I have made the necessary points already, but you seem unable to understand them. What you are doing is not acceptable, as the material you are adding has failed several times to be included in Wikipedia due to lack of notability. [[User:Jossi|≈ jossi ≈]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Jossi|(talk)]]&lt;/small&gt; 17:31, 28 December 2007 (UTC)

the International Creed for Peace has been on the Peace page for more than one Year and has been edited by wikipedians  before and after the deletion of the other pages i think it is evident as it on 12 and 18 see the dates

Recommend removal of &quot;International creed for peace&quot; and &quot;International Peace Institute&quot;
The &quot;International Peace Institute&quot; page has been recommended for deletion AfD. There's no good references for these two terms, even if you Google them. I think they are probably fabrications. If there's no major objections, I am going to delete themDudeman1st 12:17, 3 October 2006 (UTC)

Refs have been added and the organization is listed by UNESCO. The AfD proposal is still pending, but even if the article is deleted, there is no reason why material from the organization can't be included here.--agr 16:17, 5 October 2006 (UTC) 
This is an article about Peace and shouldn't be an advertisement for IPI of Nigeria. An NPOV blourb is acceptable.Dudeman1st 14:31, 9 October 2006 (UTC) 
removed the link of IPI Kobrown 18:55, 9 October 2006 (UTC)

Reorganized different kinds of peace
Just cleaning up a little. The new heading is 'theories and versions of peace'Dudeman1st 00:43, 10 October 2006 (UTC) 
I also moved things from &quot;International Creed for Peace&quot; section to the International Creed for Peace page. If users want to read the creed's text and philosophy, they can follow the link. The ICP philosophy and text belong on the ICP page. There's no need to double post them. I added the intro sentence &quot;The International Creed for Peace(see link for creed's text), created by Chika Sylva-Olejeme and the International Peace Institute, sets forth an agenda and moral code for the advancement of peace for all humans and nations.&quot;Dudeman1st 02:33, 10 October 2006 (UTC) 
you clean up is good Kobrown 09:53, 10 October 2006 (UTC) 
Hate to even mention such a pragmatic thing amongst the heated discussion, but should there be a disambiguation link for &quot;peace&quot;? There's a play by Aristophanes by that name, listed under &quot;Peace (play)&quot;. Hierophany 01:48, 9 December 2006 (UTC)

i have cited this before please give another reason and we can reach a consensus to delete or to keep  i don't want to engage in an edit war i have also seen your report  [[User:Motegole|Motegole]] ([[User talk:Motegole|talk]]) 18:39, 28 December 2007 (UTC)

I have removed  &quot;written by Chika sylva-Olejeme&quot; and the website link to avoid the claim advertisment of the author and the website however the International Creed for Peace i still think is relevent in the discuss of Peace today i stand to be corrected [[User:Motegole|Motegole]] ([[User talk:Motegole|talk]]) 19:30, 28 December 2007 (UTC)

:I'm responding to the [[Wikipedia:Administrators%27_noticeboard/Incidents#User:Motegole|ANI report]]. I've [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Peace&amp;diff=180747997&amp;oldid=180663239 removed content] that clearly does not belong in this article.  It is not notable and has been deleted from Wikipedia on that basis.  This article is about peace, not peace organizations.  Do not re-add this material to the article.  [[User:Dreadstar|Dreadstar]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Dreadstar|&lt;span class=&quot;Unicode&quot;&gt;†&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/small&gt; 05:14, 29 December 2007 (UTC)

fine thanks [[User:Motegole|Motegole]] ([[User talk:Motegole|talk]]) 10:39, 29 December 2007 (UTC)

== Cleanup-rewrite ==

The current articel appears to be stuck somewhere between a disambiguation for various &quot;types&quot; of peace (&quot;plural&quot;, &quot;inner&quot;, etc.) and trying to explain what the concept is in general, with some extra directory like sections thrown in. If someone wants to rewrite or revise this, I suggest deciding what sort of a page this will be and then fixing or rewriting it. [[Special:Contributions/68.39.174.238|68.39.174.238]] ([[User talk:68.39.174.238|talk]]) 06:23, 3 January 2008 (UTC)

== too much &quot;clean up&quot; ==

i think the &quot;clean up&quot; is slowly reducing the article into a joke, i hope that the whole page will not soon be removed due to &quot;clean up&quot;,  it is unfortunate that those who do the &quot;clean up&quot; to not contribute to building up the page [[User:Motegole|Motegole]] ([[User talk:Motegole|talk]]) 09:02, 4 January 2008 (UTC)

== No edit wars, please. ==

Vandals, spammers and edit warriors, please keep yourselves from editing this page. Remember that this is not a battleground and this page is about peace. [[User:Alexius08|Alexius08]] [[User talk:Alexius08|is welcome to talk]] [[Special:Contributions/Alexius08|about his contributions]]. 22:17, 27 March 2008 (UTC)

== Peace Prize ==

Does anyone feel that the Nobel Peace Prize section is placed a bit too early in the article?  I don't think the Nobels are a central concept of 'peace', worthy of being in the first paragraph after the lead.  comments? [[User:Pedant|User:Pedant]] ([[User talk:Pedant|talk]]) 17:36, 22 April 2008 (UTC)



== Criticism ==

I dont see why there is no criticism section. There can never be &quot;true&quot; peace. One organism much consume/kill another to survive. One human must have some type of hegemony (even on the most minute scale). Any one can add anything to it or make some type of criticism.

Survival has nothing to do with peace.--[[Special:Contributions/108.20.189.221|108.20.189.221]] ([[User talk:108.20.189.221|talk]]) 03:07, 19 June 2012 (UTC)

== Picture ==
u shuld hve a pcture of lke john lennon of that guy on my shirt. thy is heaps more peacefull. or doves  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/121.0.0.162|121.0.0.162]] ([[User talk:121.0.0.162|talk]]) 04:39, 7 May 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

I hope you don't mean Che, because communism ain't peaceful. Besides that, symbols of peace are cultural and don't fit in it directly.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/87.210.119.109|87.210.119.109]] ([[User talk:87.210.119.109|talk]]) 11:20, 15 April 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== [[Pacification]] ==
Redirects here, while its meaning is quite different.--&lt;sub&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus]]|[[User_talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt; talk &lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; 17:11, 26 June 2008 (UTC)

:I've added a section on [[peace#Peace in the presence of injustice|Peace in the presence of injustice]] which covers the perspective of those on the receiving end of a pacification policy. --[[User:Philip Baird Shearer|Philip Baird Shearer]] ([[User talk:Philip Baird Shearer|talk]]) 11:27, 29 June 2008 (UTC)

==Rewrites/Clean-up==
I re-wrote the first section of the article. It was very sloppily done, and from the moment I saw it I knew it needed re-writing. The very first sentence said something about peace being either a positive and negative condition, and that peace is a negative condition when associated with an unwillingness to engage in armed conflict????? I don't know. Didn't really make sense/sound good. The other sections look just as bad. Lots of work needs to be done on those sections. It looks like some biased trolls have been valdalizing this article, probably for a long time now. [[Special:Contributions/204.254.175.249|204.254.175.249]] ([[User talk:204.254.175.249|talk]]) 18:07, 1 December 2008 (UTC)

== Most of the stuff in this section should be moved to peace studies. ==

Peace is a general term, Please move the details of peace studies items to peace studies.  [[User:Geo8rge|Geo8rge]] ([[User talk:Geo8rge|talk]]) 16:54, 25 May 2009 (UTC)

== Active Peace Theory ==

Active Peace Theory has very few google hits if any, and no references.  I think it should be deleted as it is original research.  Or moved to peace and conflict studies. [[User:Geo8rge|Geo8rge]] ([[User talk:Geo8rge|talk]]) 17:29, 25 May 2009 (UTC)

== Please move these sections to peace and conflict studies, create a  new WP article to contain them, or delete them ==

These articles seem are too detailed for a general article like peace.
*Active Peace Theory- few if any google hits
*Plural peaces - few if any google hits
[[User:Geo8rge|Geo8rge]] ([[User talk:Geo8rge|talk]]) 17:58, 25 May 2009 (UTC)

==Redesign==

Okay so I just reviewed the article, a dreadful mess. What I do is repair articles. So I am going to do some major work on this article. I think the basic structure is there but needs clarification. There is a need for more sources which is the force thing I am going to do. [[User:Empireheart|Empireheart]] ([[User talk:Empireheart|talk]]) 08:02, 8 July 2009 (UTC)

==Definition==
&quot;Peace&quot; can mean a variety of things; this is not well explained in the article's definition. I suggest that the article is made a disambugation page stating that it may refer to
- a type of social relationship (aka 2 entities &quot;[[being in peace]]&quot; or &quot;at peace with&quot; )
- the duration of absence of conflict; aka a [[period of peace]] or period of absence of conflict

Finally, it should be mentioned that the opposite of peace isn't war (the latter being essantially a [[period of conflict]]), rather the opposite of a period of absence of conflict is a period of conflict

The opposite of [[Being in conflict]] (aka &quot;Being at war&quot;) is &quot;finding practical solutions to ensure that no conflicts can arise&quot; (see http://gracetopia.wordpress.com/2009/07/19/the-opposite-of-war-isnt-peace-its-creation/)  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/81.245.66.161|81.245.66.161]] ([[User talk:81.245.66.161|talk]]) 08:17, 27 July 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== '''Homogenizing Theory''' ==

=='''Homogenizing Theory'''==  

Mr. Inderias Dominic Bhatti, a role model peace hero from Pakistan ;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.findahero.com/HeroDetailsPrinterFriendly.cfm?SearchValue=351&lt;/ref&gt; added his peace theory with a title '''Homogenizing Theory''' with these words below:

''' “Peace is a cycle of contentment starts from the very SELF of individual and regulates one’s consciousness and thinking patterns in such a way that homogenize ones individual liberty with collective and public good” '''  &lt;ref&gt;http://www.wiserearth.org/forum/view/56edc5a65c231e3c306e63c29527f96d&lt;/ref&gt;

== dove ==

the dove is a sign of peace. --[[User:WhiteInKnights|WhiteInKnights]] ([[User talk:WhiteInKnights|talk]]) 16:33, 4 January 2010 (UTC)

== Democratic peace theory ==

Democratic peace theory is simply a calque from Marxist peace theory which claims that in a socialist society there is no reason for war.--[[Special:Contributions/79.111.107.10|79.111.107.10]] ([[User talk:79.111.107.10|talk]]) 17:55, 6 May 2010 (UTC)

==Image==
Perhaps [[File:People_in_peace_and_at_war.png|thumb|right|150px|this image]] can be integrated to the article ?
[[Special:Contributions/91.182.232.33|91.182.232.33]] ([[User talk:91.182.232.33|talk]]) 14:10, 28 September 2010 (UTC)

==Peace as a code word?==
*Peace has been thrown around often. During the Cold War, Soviet dictators claimed they were &quot;always in the interests of peace&quot;. Of course, their definition of &quot;peace&quot; was world communism. On that note, how is Islam a &quot;religion of peace&quot;? [[Special:Contributions/69.143.107.112|69.143.107.112]] ([[User talk:69.143.107.112|talk]]) 03:15, 16 February 2011 (UTC)

== Need more information about ways to achieve peace? ==

One should consider why people look at an article about peace. Are they simply interested in gathering more informaiton about the subject of peace in the same way that they would about, say, Lady Gaga? I don't think so. I believe that peace is what one could call a &quot;lifestyle subject,&quot; in that one is interested in it not in a casual way but in a deeper way that could affect one's lifesytle. I therefore feel that there is a need for the article to list more ways to achieve peace, which is, after all, one of life's essential questions. That is why I added the ways to achieve peace given by Buddhism and the spiritual teacher [[Meher Baba]]. Wikipedia's motto, I think, is &quot;the sum of all human knowledge,&quot; which is of course a tall order, but Wikipedia does seem to want to be rather inclusive.
[[User:Tentotwo55|Tentotwo55]] ([[User talk:Tentotwo55|talk]]) 17:24, 15 June 2011 (UTC)
: That's very subjective. See [[WP:COI]], [[WP:NPOV]], and [[WP:NOT#Wikipedia_is_not_a_manual.2C_guidebook.2C_textbook.2C_or_scientific_journal]]. &lt;b&gt;[[User:Ohnoitsjamie|OhNo&lt;font color=&quot;#D47C14&quot;&gt;itsJamie&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Ohnoitsjamie|&lt;sup&gt;Talk&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;/b&gt; 17:33, 15 June 2011 (UTC)

Ok, but at least add somewhere in the article that one definition of peace is the state of not wanting anything. It was taught by Krishna as &quot;renouncing the fruits of one's actions&quot; and by the Buddha as &quot;desire is the cause of all suffering.&quot; It is one of the oldest religious concepts related to peace and should be included. A concise article is great, but a complete article is even better.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Tentotwo55|Tentotwo55]] ([[User talk:Tentotwo55|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Tentotwo55|contribs]]) 17:58, 15 June 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Religious beliefs and peace ==

added interesting ref by Benedict XVI, connecting peace and ecology[[User:Unimpeder|Unimpeder]] ([[User talk:Unimpeder|talk]]) 13:01, 13 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>ndqw7gpz4bukn0tijyi3hs0qhctxys8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
