<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Unitarian Universalist Association</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>391451</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521553449</id>
      <parentid>492412488</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-05T19:36:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Nived 90</username>
        <id>2414472</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>{{talkheader}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13304">{{talkheader}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Organizations|class=B|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject United States|class=B|importance=Low|MA=yes|MA-importance=|auto=inherit}}
{{WikiProject Christianity|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=B|importance=Top|UnitarianUniversalism=yes|UnitarianUniversalismImp=Top}}
}}

==Untitled section==
One of these days I'll get around to adding pages for the UCA and AUA.... [[User:UtherSRG|UtherSRG]] 04:04, 7 Dec 2003 (UTC)

== CUC/UUA stuff ==
I have a CUC point of view which probably different than that of someone in the United States, but from a Canadian perspective, Canadian congregations have no ties to the UUA whatsoever, and this article states otherwise.  The only ties that exist from our perspective are through YRUU (Young Religious Unitarian Universalists) and C*UUYAN (Continental Unitarian Universalist Young Adult Network) which are affiliated with the UUA.  Perhaps when the CUC split from the UUA there was some agreement in between them about managing ministries, but it certainly is not happening.

:Agreed. I come from a UUA perspective (rather, a PCD UUA) perspective, and the only cooperation I've with the CUC is through YRUU. [[User:HellaNorCal|HellaNorCal]] 06:33, 15 July 2006 (UTC)

==Gun Org stuff==
If the Association is a member of a gun control special interest group, then why the problem identifying it as such?  It clearly is a gun control special interest association and hence an organization associated with gun control, along with, of course, other larger interests.  It can't be both ways. [[User:Yaf|Yaf]] 19:25, 17 February 2006 (UTC)
:It sn't primarily a gon control organization. It's a religion. There's no reason to tag religions as gun control organizations, especially when the religion has a significant number of issues it is working much more strongly on than this one issue. - [[User:UtherSRG|UtherSRG]] [[User_talk:UtherSRG|(talk)]] 19:38, 17 February 2006 (UTC)

::Except when they ''are'' also a gun control association, by their own public admissions and announcements.  Clearly, this is not a major issue within the religion, as you (and evidently others within the religion) don't think their position on gun rights is worth noting. (Am I reading your reason right?) Yet, if they were also against, say, the [[First Amendment of the United States Constitution]] and free speech to publish cartoons for example (ridiculous, I must admit), would it be noteworthy to state they were against one of the [[United States Bill of Rights|Bill of Rights]]? I would think so.  Similarly, by their position against the [[Second Amendment to the United States Constitution|Second Amendment]] by public announcements, which is also in the Bill of Rights, it is somehow not worth noting their position against another freedom that is also protected by the Bill of Rights.  OK.  This suppression does puzzle me, though, in keeping with the claim of respecting the beliefs of others and promoting tolerance.  It is somehow OK to trash certain freedoms in the name of religion, but not others.  Definitely reminds me of certain other religions that are in the news these days.  [[User:Yaf|Yaf]] 20:00, 17 February 2006 (UTC)

:::If you want to make a personal effort to hunt down all of the things which the UUA has publicly denounced, and maybe sections on other things which districts, congregations, Youth Groups and individuals have denounced, then you'll get no qualms from me. However, just mentioning one of them is POV. &lt;span style=&quot;background-color: #008000&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#ffffff&quot;&gt;[[User:Canaen|Canaen]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 06:30, 31 May 2006 (UTC)

:::: The UUA and many of its members has many positions, including opposition to racism, opposition to sexism, opposition to homophobia, generally friendly attitudes towards environmentalism, and more. Does this make it an anti-racist, anti-sexist, gay rights, environmentalist special interest group? No. The Catholic Church has social justice teachings, is opposed to gay marriage, is opposed to abortion. Does that make the Catholic Church a pro-social-justice, 'pro-family', pro-life special interest group? No. It's a religion. As others have pointed out, other Churches that support gun control aren't being targeted here. No other things the UUA supports are being targeted. We need to apply standards fairly, not single out the UUA to militant gun rights activists based on some overzealous wiki editor's vendetta. The UUA has already been targeted for and suffered from [[Knoxville Unitarian Universalist church shooting|political violence]] for their positions. --[[Special:Contributions/152.65.37.143|152.65.37.143]] ([[User talk:152.65.37.143|talk]]) 01:38, 9 September 2011 (UTC) 

Why stop there? Why not mention a lot of people think that Roe V Wade was decided incorrectly and they are willing to kill people who think differently. Why not start up slavery again, and decide who can vote? 

Oh, I forgot, we already do that.

--[[User:Lee Wells|Lee Wells]] 14:25, 9 July 2006 (UTC)

I would point you to all of the church organizations that are directly or indirectly supporters/funders of gun control.  I notice Yaf has not visited any of those churches' wikis and made this same complaint.  I see no reason to cherry pick which churches to attack on this issue.  What about the Baptists, Jesuits, Methodists, Holiness, Jews, and many other religions who all support the gun ban group &quot;Coalition to Stop Gun Violence&quot; (formerly known as &quot;National Coalition to Ban Handguns&quot;) on their wiki pages, for example?  
--Suntree

== Districts, Youth stuff, and more. ==

Hey y'all. I've decided to work on nothing but UU-related articles, and have created this account as such. I've created a few navigation boxes, and stubs for all the UUA districts. See [[Districts of the Unitarian Universalist Association]], [[YRUU]], and [[PCD YRUU]] and you'll see all the navigation boxes I've made. If anyone wants to help out, I have a sort of to-do list on my user page. Go in peace, [[User:HellaNorCal|HellaNorCal]] 06:36, 15 July 2006 (UTC)

== First Paragraph Issue  ==

Hi, I'm new here.  Wouldn't the opening paragraph be more balanced if the word &quot;wisdom&quot; was replaced with &quot;ideas&quot; or a similar word?  [[User:Macmelvino|Macmelvino]] 00:08, 14 September 2006 (UTC)
:Read the Principles and Purposes section, and you'll see why &quot;wisdom&quot; is appropriate. - [[User:UtherSRG|UtherSRG]] [[User_talk:UtherSRG|(talk)]] 02:48, 14 September 2006 (UTC)
::Hey, thanx for the welcome!  I do see your point, and this perhaps isn't the place for a debate, but I as a Christian feel that any actual wisdom that can be found in another religion is already covered in the Bible.  Many (um, not all) of the Principles and Purposes listed are indeed values that I hold.  I could be a minority of one here, but I still believe that in the interests of neutrality, &quot;ideas&quot; or maybe even &quot;doctrines&quot; would be a better word.  Peace. - [[User:Macmelvino|Macmelvino]] 18:03, 14 September 2006 (UTC)
:::But wisdom is just what they're looking for, not ideas and certainly not doctrines.  You may feel there is no wisdom outside the bible, but that is a point of view.  Many religions (Islam, Buddhism, Hinduism) feel they find wisdom from other sources. &amp;ndash;[[User:Shoaler|Shoaler]] ([[User talk:Shoaler|talk]]) 18:26, 14 September 2006 (UTC)
::::I think I've said my piece.  I'm done now.  Peace, [[User:Macmelvino|Macmelvino]] 16:18, 15 September 2006 (UTC)

== UUA is a denomination ==

I'm not quite sure why it makes sense to say that the UUA isn't a denomination, when many denominations have congregational polity like the UUA (as the article mentions).  &quot;Denomination&quot; literally means &quot;a collective name for a group of churches.&quot;  As long as it's possible for a church to belong to the UUA, the UUA is a denomination--but one with congregational polity.
[[User:Atterlep|Atterlep]] 04:51, 27 January 2007 (UTC)

:Some object to &quot;denomination&quot; because it implies a subgroup of a larger group (e.g. UU is not a Christian denomination because it is separate).  On the other hand, UUA has promoted the catchline &quot;The Uncommon Denomination&quot;. To me though, that begs the question &quot;denomination of what?&quot; [[User:Aleta|Aleta]] 05:22, 27 January 2007 (UTC)

::The [http://www.uua.org/administration/bylaws.html UUA self-definition] is &quot;a voluntary association of autonomous, self-governing local churches and fellowships&quot;, not a [[denomination]]. The &quot;Uncommon Denomination&quot; slogan is just part of a marketing campaign. --[[User:Jdemarcos|jofframes]] 14:30, 28 January 2007 (UTC)
==Fair use rationale for Image:UUA Logo.svg==
[[File:Nuvola apps important.svg|70px|left]]
'''[[:Image:UUA Logo.svg]]''' is being used on this article. I notice the image page specifies that the image is being used under [[Wikipedia:Fair use|fair use]] but there is no [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline|explanation or rationale]] as to why its use in '''this''' Wikipedia article constitutes fair use. In addition to the [[Wikipedia:Image copyright tags/Fair use|boilerplate fair use template]], you must also write out on the image description page a specific explanation or rationale for why using this image in each article is consistent with [[WP:FU|fair use]].

Please go to [[:Image:UUA Logo.svg|the image description page]] and edit it to include a [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline |fair use rationale]]. Using one of the templates at [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline]] is an easy way to insure that your image is in compliance with Wikipedia policy, but remember that you must complete the template. Do not simply insert a blank template on an image page.

If there is other other fair use media, consider checking that you have specified the fair use rationale on the other images used on this page.  Note that any fair use images uploaded after 4 May, 2006, and lacking such an explanation will be deleted one week after they have been uploaded, as described on [[Wikipedia:Criteria for speedy deletion#Images.2FMedia|criteria for speedy deletion]]. If you have any questions please ask them at the [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions|Media copyright questions page]]. Thank you.&lt;!-- Template:Missing rationale2 --&gt;[[User:BetacommandBot|BetacommandBot]] 04:24, 5 June 2007 (UTC)

:I went ahead and took a stab at providing a fair use rationale for the logo. I kind of copied from the text used on the Apple, Inc. logo but changed it to make it fit. If anyone wants to add to or correct what I did, go for it. For now, though, it should prevent speedy deletion. [[User:ThAtSo|ThAtSo]] 07:04, 5 June 2007 (UTC)

== Boy Scouts of America controversy ==

Do UUA congregations still sponsor BSA troops? Do UUA and BSA still have ties? --[[User:Jagz|Jagz]] 16:37, 30 September 2007 (UTC)

Here is an article named &quot;Scouting alternatives draw UU youth&quot;.[http://www.uuworld.org/news/articles/45487.shtml] --[[User:Jagz|Jagz]] 17:09, 30 September 2007 (UTC)

== Was this the article you were looking for? ==

I checked all of those listed as possibly being confused with Unitarian Universalist Association, and not one of them has this warning with lists of other churches at the bottom.  I fear this is yet another effort to advertise those religions when people view this article rather than helping viewers find the article they seek.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Suntree|Suntree]] ([[User talk:Suntree|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Suntree|contribs]]) 01:19, 12 October 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:I agree that this [[Template:Uni|template]] should be used on all the pages that are referenced on the template.  For example, [[United Church of Christ]] is listed on the template, but it doesn't use the template.  If the UUA could be confused with the UCC, can't the UCC also be confused with the UUA?  I've raised this concern on the [[Template talk:Uni#Concern about lack of universal use of template|talk page]] and will start making changes unless I hear any objections. [[User:Rickterp|Rickterp]] 19:02, 15 October 2007 (UTC)

::I didn't realize this page had ben singled out. I've just added the template to some of the other referenced articles, so it's now on all all the ones in the top line, and in the general article on uniting churches.  I haven't checked the remaining articles [[User:Aleta|Aleta]] 00:00, 16 October 2007 (UTC)

:::I just added the template to the articles listed on the bottom half of the template. Hope this helps. --[[User:Nived 90|Devin Murphy]] 07:59, 2 December 2007 (UTC)

==Unitarian Universalism work group?==
There has been a suggestion over on the [[Wikipedia talk:WikiProject Religion|WikiProject Religion talk page]] to create a work group consisting of folks interested in articles related to Unitarian Universalism. So would anyone here be interested in joining in such an effort. --[[User:Nived_90|Devin Murphy]] ([[User talk:Nived_90|talk]]) 07:45, 2 December 2007 (UTC)
:It’s now official there’s a [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Religion/Unitarian Universalism work group|Unitarian Universalism work group]]. --[[User:Nived_90|Devin Murphy]] ([[User talk:Nived_90|talk]]) 22:08, 13 January 2008 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>phwypz0val0q8xjc75lyav8eo3kwsuz</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
