<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Imperial cult</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2525421</id>
    <revision>
      <id>376751608</id>
      <parentid>376751564</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-08-02T13:01:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>72.228.177.92</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Horus Cult */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="4916">{{WPReligion|class=Start}}

== early smerdis ==
I'm afraid that this article is about the historical worship of Roman emperors and has nothing to do with anything your group is concerned about.  I am making the weblinks added here not autolinking, and I hope not to find dozens of them elsewhere on Wikipedia.  [[User:Ihcoyc|Smerdis of Tlön]] 04:45, 24 August 2005 (UTC)

==Rome==

I think I'll split off most of the 'Ancient Rome' section to [[Imperial cult of ancient Rome]] or something alike, as this article is heavily out of balance now. Any objections?--[[User:Hippalus|Hippalus]] 22:03, 23 January 2006 (UTC) 
:Done! [[Imperial cult (Ancient Rome)]]--[[User:Hippalus|Hippalus]] 08:54, 24 January 2006 (UTC)

== Modern practice ==

I have encountered several accounts in my readings of modern practitioners of this type of cult, including but certainly not limited to, the modern worship of Julius and Augustus Caesar.  My question is if this information should be added to this article, due to the fact that the purpose of the article as it currently reads seems to (perhaps inadvertently) focus on Ancient practices.  There is the Rastafari section, but before I attempt an edit (and recheck my sources) I wanted to be clear on the article's intention.  If modern practice should not be added to this article, what are your thoughts on creating a separate article entitled [[Modern Practices of Imperial Cults]] and moving the Rastafari and Japanese information to it.  I'm not sure it is necessary to create a seperate article, but I don't want to mangle the purpose of this one.  Additionally, do you think a new article as described is even worthy of creation, when a section within this one might suffice?  I noticed the creation of [[Imperial cult (Ancient Rome)]], but I wonder if that article should be expanded to include all Ancient practices and appropriately renamed?  However, the current [[Imperial cult (Ancient Rome)]] does seem to warrant its own article IMHO.  Perhaps this article would best be reorganized into two main sections, &quot;Ancient Practice&quot; and &quot;Modern Practice&quot;. [[User:Trippz|Trippz]] 08:29, 6 August 2007 (UTC)

== Euhemerus  ==

Should the Euhemerus reference be included?  The way it reads it suggests that Euhemerus himself was worshiped.  After reading the article on [[Euhemerus]], I see the point the entry is attempting to make, but it still seems unclear.  I almost changed the wording myself to euhemeristic, but I'm not sure that is a word.  The information about Euhemerus and his inclusion in the article seems helpful, but its presentation is a little clunky. [[User:Trippz|Trippz]] 08:44, 6 August 2007 (UTC)

:Euhemerisation is the substantive I believe. [[Special:Contributions/72.228.177.92|72.228.177.92]] ([[User talk:72.228.177.92|talk]]) 12:51, 2 August 2010 (UTC)

== Defining &quot;Imperial Cult&quot; ==

I just want to open a discussion on the agreed definition of Imperial Cult for purposes of this article.  My understanding is that the venerated figure(s) in question must be (or have been) the leader(s) of a politically or geographically recognized nation.  The nation in question may not necessarily fit the definition of being an Empire, thus making the use of the word &quot;Imperial&quot; somewhat misleading.  For example, Monarchs and Dictators may also have Imperial Cult followers.  In fact, it seems to be the autocratic nature of the venerated figure or dynasty which worshipers adhere to most.  I'm somewhat confused by the use of &quot;...supranational identity in the case of a multi-ethnic state ...&quot; as mentioned in the article, because this appears to be more like [[nationalism]].  Can someone clarify this to me?  The two terms seem closely related, but I don't specifically see the distinction.  Is it that the nationalistic beliefs are centered exclusively on the autocrat? [[User:Trippz|Trippz]] 09:12, 6 August 2007 (UTC)
== Horus Cult ==

Have provided references for this elsewhere and thought I had here but a quick look through older versions seems to indicate not. In any case the fact tagged stuff in that &amp;sect; is easily sourced. [[Special:Contributions/72.228.177.92|72.228.177.92]] ([[User talk:72.228.177.92|talk]]) 12:51, 2 August 2010 (UTC)

:Moved this here, apparent stray comment with unbalanced markup (corrected markup, left typos): &lt;b&gt; Egyptians Pharaohs were concered to be gods because they were the proctector the people &lt;/b&gt;

:: The last sentence did seem to be a counterfactual. The dead pharoahs joined the other gods, but the living king enjoyed the status of a god on earth as well. This is in contrast to deification in Rome, or the posthumous naming of Chinese Emperors but of course the religious practices of Egypt also occurred against the real world conditions upon which dynastic turnover was based. [[Special:Contributions/72.228.177.92|72.228.177.92]] ([[User talk:72.228.177.92|talk]]) 13:01, 2 August 2010 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>b5boebbwisk2k2hb4a5yg2o9ttf698e</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
