<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Aten</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>3038905</id>
    <revision>
      <id>496738030</id>
      <parentid>486878162</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-09T12:18:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>CharlieRCD</username>
        <id>5385738</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Dubious- First appearance of the Aten */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5829">{{AncientEgyptBanner
|class=start
|importance=top
|religion=yes
|religion-importance=top}}
{{WikiProject Religion |class=start |importance=high}}
{{WP Mythology|class=start|importance=high}}

== Style of Leader ==
On this page, &quot;[[Style_%28manner_of_address%29#In_religion]]&quot;, there is an entry for,

:''*The Most Reverend  (abbreviation'' The Most Rev.'', oral address'' Father'') &amp;mdash; The Leader of &quot;The People of the [[Aten]]&quot;''

Does this have anything to do with the [[Aten]] page? There is no reference to an extant People or their Leader.--[[User:Oxonian2006|Oxonian2006]] 03:43, 7 January 2007 (UTC)

== Aton and Athena ==
Is there a relation (etymological or else) between god [[Aton]] and goddess [[Athena]]?

--[[User:Ionn-Korr|IonnKorr]] 20:31, 30 October 2005 (UTC)
I do not believe so. [[User:Therealmikelvee|mikey]] 04:53, 4 September 2006 (UTC)

== Grammar and sources ==
This article makes some pretty wild claims, in bad English. This needs to be fixed. --[[User:OneTopJob6|OneTopJob6]] 15:30, 26 July 2006 (UTC)

== Organizing ==
I've done some preliminary reorganizing of the article, separating the Moses theory into its own section and for the time being removing the Adonis and Adonai links since neither of these articles reference the Aten in any way, and the relationship is only specific to this theory, not general knowledge of Aten.

I might add that the Moses entry is in definite need of better citations and writing. It uses unnecessary contractions and has no sources whatsoever. My guess is the author of the previous post who liked the Moses theory, decided to include it by simply throwing in a quickly written summary of it, which is negligible. I would call on someone better acquainted with the authors and concepts of the Moses books than myself to edit this section.

The titles of the Aten are also pitifully organized and written and especially need citations for those specific translations, as more than one author gives an alternate English meaning of the inscriptions.

The Aten's spherical likeness being more readily apparent in personal views of the stelae is a subjective opinion only, and I would advocate removing it if others agree. The Hugh Nibley reference is more preferable, although perhaps a citation would be helpful too. [[User:AtenRa|AtenRa]] 19:08, 26 August 2006 (UTC)


== Criticism ==

The general statement that &quot;traditional beliefs don't 'gel' with history&quot;, though common believed, is far from being a neutral statement. The entire paragraph in which it is contained is written in non-encyclopaedic language and the citation of another opinion as the major support of the statement rather than a proven fact (about Solomon, for instance, which automatically writes off the entire Kebra Nagast) about three Biblical characters throws the whole thing into question.

[[User:200.108.27.63|200.108.27.63]] 13:24, 18 December 2006 (UTC)

Well the site by which I get much of my Kemetic information totally eradicates all notions put forth in this totally opinionated article. The link I am providing here is the total opposite of what you have here. This needs to be reseached more to reach more accuracy[http://www.kemet.org/glossary/aten.html]. [[User:Churchofyinepu|Antoine L. Mason]]


This page displays Akhenatens worship of Aton as being monotheistic of monastic, while this is far from certain; it should be noted that many scientists consider his form of worshipping as belonging to a henotheistic tradition.

== Inaccurate, Incomplete ==

The entire article is inacurate and incomplete. '''Simple to refute by anyone with a book of pictures from Ancient Egypt'''. For instance, the Aten is a solar disc utilized by nearly every diety as represented in hieroglypics. Not merely Ra or the the cult of Aten. Pictures from Egyptian artifacts with Atens on top of many different deities are very easy to come by and can be provided.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Akutra|Akutra]] ([[User talk:Akutra|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Akutra|contribs]]) 22:17, 10 April 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== The Visible Disk of the Moon ==

If ''aten'' is the visible disk of the sun, and an aspect of Ra, is there an Egyptian word for the visible disk of the moon, perhaps an aspect of Khonsu (or is Khonsu an aspect of Thoth)?

If there is such a word, I feel it should be linked-to in the '''''aten''''' article, as the moon is somewhat a conjugate of the sun.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:AltiusBimm|AltiusBimm]] ([[User talk:AltiusBimm|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/AltiusBimm|contribs]]) 07:03, 6 December 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:There probably was no moon god really equivalent to the Aten. Perhaps the closest god to what you're asking about is [[Iah]], but he was represented as a human with the moon hieroglyph on his head rather than as an object or hieroglyph alone. I did add to the article the only slight connection that I know of between the Aten and the moon—namely, that the moon disk was sometimes called &quot;the silver Aten&quot; by analogy with the sun disk. [[User:A. Parrot|A. Parrot]] ([[User talk:A. Parrot|talk]]) 19:13, 6 December 2011 (UTC)

== Dubious- First appearance of the Aten ==

The statement that the Aten first appears in the 12th Dynasty should be clarified and given a proper citation - aten with the meaning 'disc' appears at least as early as the Vth Dynasty, and is also used to describe the seat of the sun god in certain passages from the Coffin Texts (e.g. CT V:335). [[User:CharlieRCD|CharlieRCD]] ([[User talk:CharlieRCD|talk]]) 12:18, 9 June 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>s27ih73ru2go5l02u1jjonuzs4nwgs7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
