<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Transcendentalism</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>311050</id>
    <revision>
      <id>459108662</id>
      <parentid>459108589</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-11-05T08:59:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SineBot</username>
        <id>4936590</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Dating comment by [[User:Kirkmc|Kirkmc]] - &quot;/* List */&quot;</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25685">{{Spirituality project|class=Start}}
{{philosophy|class=start|importance=mid|}}
{{NovelsWikiProject|class=C|importance=high|19thC-task-force=yes|19thC-importance=}}
{{WikiProject Literature}}
for prior comments, see [[Talk:Transcendentalism/Archive]]
{{Portal|Spirituality}}

== Self-transcendence ==

Why on earth does self-transcendence redirect to Transcendentalism? The former is a psychological experience or state, the latter is an artistic-philosophical movement. 

[[User:Dr. Peter Lankton|Dr. Peter Lankton]] ([[User talk:Dr. Peter Lankton|talk]]) 08:31, 12 January 2010 (UTC)

:I was wondering that, as there's no reference to self-transcendence in this article - where ''should'' [[self-transcendence]] point to? In [[Maslow's hierarchy of needs#Self-transcendence]] it's a piped link, &lt;tt&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Transcendence (philosophy)|Self-transcendence]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;, pointing to [[Transcendence (philosophy)]], which seems a bit better. (I've sharpened that, to point to the section [[Transcendence (philosophy)#Colloquial usage]], as this has the only direct to self-transcendence in that article.)

:As I can find no reasoning for the redirect (no reply here, no explanation in the [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Self-transcendence&amp;action=history history of the redirect]) I'm changing it to redirect to [[Transcendence (philosophy)#Colloquial usage]] for want of anything better (that I'm aware of). Feel free to improve on this. --[[User:Chriswaterguy|Chriswaterguy]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Chriswaterguy|talk]]&lt;/small&gt; 09:12, 26 October 2011 (UTC)

== Vandalism ==

Lots of foolish vandalism lately it looks like, propose a semi locked state or the like from a more experienced user.

[[User:Ryoutou|Ryoutou]] 17:57, 7 November 2007 (UTC)

== History and Philosophy ==
I think the article needs more on the history of Transcendentalism, and should be divided into sections, one of philosophy and one on the history itself. - [[User:Pingveno|Pingveno]] 20:37, 3 Jan 2004 (UTC)

What's the relavance of linking &quot;transcendental meditation&quot; from the article? They appear to have little in common besides a name.

There are many views on this topic and a lot of it started in the early to mid 19 century.

I think the link to Kant and other hard philosophers and philosophy should be de-emphisized.  Trancendetalism though having philosophical pretensions was primarily a literary movement.  It was not a product of german idealism so much as german romanticism and romanticism generally.  The idealist philosophers influenced a lot of romantics aside from just the New England crew.  This is a common tension in views of Emerson, and some others like Theraue, and Carlyle, they wrote in a tone that might be interpreted as philosophical but did not call themselves philosophers.  Emerson called himself always a poet.  He attacked philosophy in favor of the poetic outlook.  Some like Stanley Cavell have tried to say Emerson was a philosopher, but I think they are in the distinct minority, and change the meaning of philosopher to do so.  The way the article is now leaves the immpresion that these were just a bunch of ametuer, &quot;table top&quot; philosophers.  I think the reality is that they were a very dynamic literary movement that in many ways founded American culture.  By the way theirs a nice quote from Charles Dickens in his notes on America which was mostly a critical look, that talks about the Boston Trancendentalist, and ends with him saying  &quot;If I lived in Boston I would be a trancendentalist too.&quot;  Or something like that.  You could google it.--[[User:Casey Emerson|Case]] 21:16, 13 Sep 2004 (UTC)

: It seems to me that the narrow definition of philosophy which would include Kant as &quot;hard&quot; and exclude (e.g.) Emerson is a distinctively twentieth-century invention.  The standard anthology ''The Transcendentalists'', edited by the intellectual historian Perry Miller, is instructive on this topic, portraying Transcendentalism as primarily theological-philosophical rather than literary.  And the claim that Transcendentalism is a literary movement founders on the extremely thin literary production of the movement anyway (especially if we use &quot;literary&quot; in the way the 19th C. authors would have understood it, as referring to poetry and fiction), as compared to their prodigious and excellent criticism, scholarship, lectures and essays.  So I don't think it's out of place to characterize it as a theological and philosophical movement as much as, or more than, a literary one (and the Kant reference is primarily an explanation of the name, anyway).  But the article can certainly be improved in many ways, so feel free to make whatever changes seem appropriate. -- [[User:Rbellin|Rbellin]] 04:12, 14 Sep 2004 (UTC)

If I was unfamiliar with Transcendentalism and depended upon this article to enlighten me I would leave dissapointed. This article needs serious attention.
[[User:CWatchman|CWatchman]] ([[User talk:CWatchman|talk]]) 11:32, 4 March 2008 (UTC)

----

==Would like some help==

Does anyone know what kind of relation the Transcendentalists philosophy has with Nietzsche's? Are they antagonistic? As I'm not familiarized with the latter, I'd really much like to know.
Edited: The Individual 00:52 2/V/05

: Nietzsche read Emerson and was influenced by him to some degree.  Beyond that, matters are less settled, and there's not a whole lot of scholarship on the relationship.  There's a book called ''Nietzsche and Emerson: An Elective Affinity'', ISBN 0821410377, that you might look at for more on the relationship. -- [[User:Rbellin|Rbellin]]|[[User talk:Rbellin|Talk]] 00:41, 2 May 2005 (UTC)

== recent changes ==

I have reverted two recent changes to the article.  First, [[User:Euhlig]] [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Transcendentalism&amp;diff=68141289&amp;oldid=67643746 changed the lead paragraph] to the present tense, which is inappropriate in a historical article (and this article has occasionally attracted Transcendentalist-revival POV-pushers).  This article is about the early-to-mid-19th-century movement in American thought, not any current movement referring to it.  Second, [[User:Kenosis]] [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Transcendentalism&amp;diff=68142283&amp;oldid=68141289 deleted] a description of some of Transcendentalism's founding motivations (&quot;Transcendentalism originated as a protest against the general state of American culture and [[society]], and particularly the state of [[intellectualism]] at [[Harvard]] and the doctrine of the [[Unitarian]] church which was taught at [[Harvard Divinity School]].&quot;) and appended an edit comment describing this as &quot;erroneous stretch of imagination&quot;.  It's certainly not patently untrue, and in fact this is a generalization of a kind found in many scholarly works on Transcendentalism -- so I can see no justification for the deletion. -- [[User:Rbellin|Rbellin]]|[[User talk:Rbellin|Talk]] 14:56, 7 August 2006 (UTC)

==Unitarianism==

Do you have an outside source for the assertion that the transcendentalism was founded due to problems with Unitarianism?  I know little about transcendentalism, except for the fact that it and its founders are particularly revered by the Unitarian church, which I grew up in.  You can hardly visit one of them without finding an &quot;Emerson Hall&quot;, or something of the like.  And most of them are listed under categories like &quot;american unitarians&quot;.  My first urge was just to edit that part out, but I saw you'd reverted it before so I thought I'd ask.  [[User:JS Nelson|J.S. Nelson]] 09:45, 1 November 2006 (UTC)

: If you know little about Transcendentalism, it's good you resisted the urge to start deleting things from the article.  I'm not sure how you get to &quot;problems with Unitarianism&quot; from this sentence, but the fact that Transcendentalism originated partly as a protest against Unitarian theology is as virtually uncontested as historical assertaions get.  Take a look at any scholarly work on Transcendentalism (say, Perry Miller's ''The Transcendentalists'', or Barbara Packer's essay in the ''Cambridge History of American Literature'') for a source. -- [[User:Rbellin|Rbellin]]|[[User talk:Rbellin|Talk]] 15:13, 1 November 2006 (UTC)

Thanks. Just making sure; I thought it was perhaps a weirdly formatted sentence because the Unitarians are so fond of the transcendentalists (and learning more about the origins of Transcendentalism, I see to what great extent the Unitarian theology I grew up with has embraced the concerns of the transcendentalists.)  To clarify, I meant &quot;problems with Unitarianism&quot; as in &quot;problems they had with Unitarianism&quot; which I would assume lay behind their protest. [[User:JS Nelson|J.S. Nelson]] 06:49, 2 November 2006 (UTC)


Speaking of Unitarians, it's the article says that almost none of the leaders of the movement (all Unitarians) were familiar with original sources in other languages.  In fact, Margaret Fuller translated Goethe from the German;  he was a major influence on the thought of her and her peers, including Emerson.  If I am remembering my source correctly, she did the first direct translation of Goethe in America.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/68.106.110.14|68.106.110.14]] ([[User talk:68.106.110.14|talk]]) 17:30, 6 November 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Tense ==

Why is &quot;transcendentalism&quot; strictly historical?  My dictionaries define the word as &quot;a philosophy that emphasizes...&quot; and &quot;any philosophy based upon the doctrine that...&quot; &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Euhlig|Euhlig]] ([[User talk:Euhlig|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Euhlig|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

: First of all, [[Wikipedia:What Wikipedia is not|Wikipedia is not]] a dictionary.  The general philosophical sense of the word is, quite properly, noted in [[wiktionary:transcendentalism|Wiktionary]], and other uses of &quot;transcendentalism&quot; in philosophy are further described in the Wikipedia articles on [[transcendence (philosophy)]] and [[transcendental idealism]].  Those are not the subjects of this article.  As the second sentence of the article says, this article is about New England Transcendentalism.  -- [[User:Rbellin|Rbellin]]|[[User talk:Rbellin|Talk]] 22:50, 10 August 2006 (UTC)

: For the sake of clarity, I've also added a disambiguation header to the top of the article. -- [[User:Rbellin|Rbellin]]|[[User talk:Rbellin|Talk]] 17:10, 11 August 2006 (UTC)

== Walt Whitman ==

My AP U.S. History textbook ''The American Pageant: Thirteenth Edition'' lists the three &quot;Trumpeters of Transcendentalism&quot; to be Emerson, Thoreau, and Whitman, in that order. I noticed that Whitman is not listed on the page: does he belong there? [[User:JeffreyGomez|JeffreyGomez]] 02:10, 16 April 2007 (UTC)

: No.  Whitman was not a Transcendentalist.  He was from New York, not New England, and had nothing to do with Transcendentalism as a moral, religious, philosophical, or literary institution.  Sure, he corresponded with Emerson (famously using Emerson's letter about the first ''Leaves of Grass'' as a promotional device) and met him a few times, but that's all he had to do with Transcendentalism.  High-school textbooks are not the most trustworthy sources. -- [[User:Rbellin|Rbellin]]|[[User talk:Rbellin|Talk]] 02:47, 16 April 2007 (UTC)

yes he was a trascendentalist.  Song of myself is entirely about helping people cope with the changes of his time.  ... hello?!  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/130.156.46.252|130.156.46.252]] ([[User talk:130.156.46.252|talk]]) 19:00, 8 October 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;


See this article:
http://www.vcu.edu/engweb/transcendentalism/roots/legacy/whitman/index.html

Also, our own WP article on Whitman reinforces the view.  He may have not been part of the movement's genesis, but following the majority of its tenets - and certainly was under the wing of the leader of the movement.  I'd agree with his inclusion in this vein, but I'm not sure I'd list him at the top.

Cheers,
Ryo  [[User:Ryoutou|Ryoutou]] 16:12, 8 November 2007 (UTC)

: No, this should not be inserted in the article, because it is false.  Whitman was not directly affiliated with Transcendentalism in any way.  (Nor was he &quot;under the wing&quot; of Emerson in any sense, as the article you linked makes quite clear.)  The Wikipedia article on Whitman, like many others, is salted with dubious generalizations about literary history that have apparently been pulled out of introductory textbooks by people with little familiarity with the subject. -- [[User:Rbellin|Rbellin]]|[[User talk:Rbellin|Talk]] 19:30, 8 November 2007 (UTC)

::Emerson took issue with some approaches Whitman took, but the same could surely be said for his views of HDT's misanthropic nature.  A search shows many references of WW reviving the movement, of being within the spirit of the movement etc - and he knew Emerson on a personal basis.  Emerson wrote professional recommendations for him, which is certainly a closer relationship than some folks have &quot;within a movement&quot;.  You are saying perhaps that WW was a modernist?  Seriously, what category (with your implied academic erudition within this field) would you put him in?  [[User:Ryoutou|Ryoutou]] 21:28, 8 November 2007 (UTC)

::: I would categorize Whitman as a 19th-century poet.  He was ''sui generis'' in every way that mattered, not a member of any &quot;category.&quot;  (Also, you might want to read more about the story of that infamous letter from Emerson about ''Leaves of Grass'' before calling it a &quot;professional recommendation,&quot; and the two were not terribly close personal friends, though they did meet.) The Transcendentalists (that is, those who called themselves that and were called that by others at the time) were a clearly defined group of people who are enumerated in this article, not a grab-bag label for any contemporary author that we deem close to their &quot;tenets&quot; or &quot;spirit.&quot; -- [[User:Rbellin|Rbellin]]|[[User talk:Rbellin|Talk]] 22:25, 8 November 2007 (UTC)

:::: I wasn't speaking of Emerson's letter about Leaves, which Whitman used as a review and angered Emerson - but of Emerson's writing to the Dept of the Interior to argue for his job.  And yes, they met - a number of times.  Emerson visited Whitman and reviewed works in progress, Whitman visited Emerson, etc.  Whitman all of his professional life claimed Emerson as his primary inspiration, though I suspect you would say that was purely for commercial gain?  It seems pretty clear that had Whitman but spent a year at Walden he would be universally accepted as part of the movement, which is a trivial bit of micro-geography.  It isn't you or me that is claiming the allegiance to the &quot;tenets&quot; or &quot;spirit&quot;, but the author himself.  At the very least I would support his presence on this page as being on the periphery of the movement should another editor come along who agrees and can create consensus.  [[User:Ryoutou|Ryoutou]] 13:35, 9 November 2007 (UTC)

As far as I can tell, Whitman was not an active part of the transcendentalist movement.  That in mind, he was a speaker of transcendentalists cases and, regardless of what he called himself, is a shaping force of what we now call transcendentalism.  I do not agree that Whitman should be listed as a prominant transcendentalist but would move that he be mentioned in the article at some point for the unquestionably profound impact he had, not just on the movement itself, but on our particular views of it.  Long story short...who cares how he's categorized?  &quot;A rose by any other name...&quot;
-David S. Kadaris  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/132.235.45.247|132.235.45.247]] ([[User talk:132.235.45.247|talk]]) 18:51, 19 November 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

I agree with the above. I don't think that Whitman should be completely excluded from the article...nothing wrong with at least mentioning him.
[[Special:Contributions/66.32.226.140|66.32.226.140]] ([[User talk:66.32.226.140|talk]]) 22:43, 27 January 2008 (UTC)

Whitman may not have been an actual member of the Transcendentalist circle, but he was profoundly influenced by their ideas, and especially by Emerson, and its influence can be felt in Leaves of Grass. He was definitely a Transcendentalist in spirit, and most academics recognize this. I agree that he should at least be mentioned somewhere.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.8.130.192|24.8.130.192]] ([[User talk:24.8.130.192|talk]]) 23:12, 18 November 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Supposed Quote From &quot;The Transcendentalist&quot; ==

The paragraph beginning the section _History_ is very confusing, referring at once to Emerson's speech &quot;The Transcendentalist&quot; and his book _Nature_.  The boxed quote beginning &quot;So we shall come to look at the world&quot; is marked as being from &quot;The Transcendentalist,&quot; but is nowhere within the linked text of the speech.  Is it from _Nature_ instead?  If so, please change it. [[Special:Contributions/128.147.28.1|128.147.28.1]] ([[User talk:128.147.28.1|talk]]) 18:19, 24 December 2007 (UTC)

== Criticism and other expansion ==

Hello, folks! I started a &quot;Criticism&quot; section, which currently only includes a brief mention of Hawthorne and a fuller discussion of Poe - I will try to expand and, hopefully, others will jump in. I'm going to pick at this article here and there, adding references in-line. I would also suggest some further clean-up, possibly merging &quot;Origins&quot; into &quot;History&quot;, and possibly a separate section for &quot;Beliefs&quot; or &quot;Philosophy&quot; or something. Thoughts?  --[[User:Midnightdreary|Midnightdreary]] ([[User talk:Midnightdreary|talk]]) 14:20, 6 January 2008 (UTC)
:By the way, is there a solid way to determine if &quot;Transcendentalism&quot; and &quot;Transcendentalists&quot; should be capitalized? I've been seeing it both ways - should we just pick one? --[[User:Midnightdreary|Midnightdreary]] ([[User talk:Midnightdreary|talk]]) 20:31, 8 January 2008 (UTC)

It seems to me that when talking about Transcendentalism as a title for the Transcendentalist movement, as opposed to &quot;transcendentalism&quot;, which could refer to the general word, it is capitalized.  When talking about &quot;transcendentalists&quot; as individuals, however, it seems like it's NOT capitalized. Can anyone confirm or deny this?
[[Special:Contributions/66.32.151.112|66.32.151.112]] ([[User talk:66.32.151.112|talk]]) 20:13, 21 February 2008 (UTC)
:I think I see what you're saying, and it's as good an argument as I could come up with. Does anyone know any better? --[[User:Midnightdreary|Midnightdreary]] ([[User talk:Midnightdreary|talk]]) 20:40, 21 February 2008 (UTC)

== Transcendental Club ==

In my opinion, there should be more information on the Transcendental Club in this article. It is only mentioned, not described at all. While there is a separate article, I think at least a brief description should be added.
[[Special:Contributions/66.32.151.112|66.32.151.112]] ([[User talk:66.32.151.112|talk]]) 20:15, 21 February 2008 (UTC)
:The whole article could really use some help. Feel free to lend a hand yourself! --[[User:Midnightdreary|Midnightdreary]] ([[User talk:Midnightdreary|talk]]) 20:40, 21 February 2008 (UTC)

== Disambiguation page ==

Instead of having small section at the bottom for &quot;other uses of transcendentalism&quot; shouldn't someone make a disambiguation page?  Isn't that what they're for?[[User:Reaper Man|Reaper Man]] ([[User talk:Reaper Man|talk]])

==Spiritual intuitions==
In Kant's transcendental idealism, the word &quot;transcendental&quot; was used to describe a viewpoint from which the mind understands its own workings. It is somewhat as though the mind is seeing itself from above itself. From this, the Transcendentalists claim to achieve, according to the article, &quot;an ideal spiritual state that 'transcends' the physical and empirical and is only realized through the individual's intuition &amp;hellip;.&quot; Spiritual states and mystical intuition are the result of Kant's earnest and serious investigations. As the Latin saying goes: 
''corruptio optimi pessima'' (the worst is the corruption of the best). Is the Wiki article correct in its description?[[User:Lestrade|Lestrade]] ([[User talk:Lestrade|talk]]) 17:05, 3 November 2008 (UTC)Lestrade

==Definition==
Could we perhaps feature a clearer, more precise, and concise definition of the term &quot;Transcendentalism&quot;, top of the page and center? Right now there's a single sentence wedged in between a brief background on the history of transcendentalism and a list of prominent transcendentalists. It's nothing more than my opinion, but I think making sure the casual reader understands what transcendentalism ''is'' may be slightly more immediately relevant than a detailed account of the history of the movement and its proponents.--[[User:Althor Enchantor|Althor Enchantor]] ([[User talk:Althor Enchantor|talk]]) 20:39, 9 February 2009 (UTC)

: Trouble is, there is no such commonly agreed definition of American Transcendentalism in terms of the tenets of its ideas (rather than as a movement with identifiable constituents who differed as much as they agreed).  This is rather typical of intellectual-history topics, actually -- see [[Romanticism]] or [[Modernism]] for some even more difficult examples (some elements of which the Wikipedia articles handle quite poorly/simplistically at the moment).  The topic can't be handled responsibly by pretending that some oversimplified &quot;definition&quot; catches all or most of what has gone under the label Transcendentalism.  -- [[User:Rbellin|Rbellin]]|[[User talk:Rbellin|Talk]] 04:59, 10 February 2009 (UTC)

== Walt Whitman ==

what about walt whitman[[Special:Contributions/129.82.30.230|129.82.30.230]] ([[User talk:129.82.30.230|talk]]) 01:42, 11 March 2009 (UTC)

== Time Travelers ==

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Transcendentalism was a group of new ideas in literature, religion, culture, and philosophy that emerged in New England in the early to middle '''25th century'''.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

...wat? [[Special:Contributions/65.184.233.253|65.184.233.253]] ([[User talk:65.184.233.253|talk]]) 19:09, 8 October 2009 (UTC)

== Amos Bronson Alcott x2? ==

The intro paragraph reads:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Prominent transcendentalists included ... Amos Bronson Alcott, and Jones Very.[1]  Others included Amos Bronson Alcott and A.E. Waite.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
I don't know if he counts as &quot;prominent&quot; or &quot;other&quot; but someone with a little more knowledge may wish to edit that for clarity.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/64.149.37.230|64.149.37.230]] ([[User talk:64.149.37.230|talk]]) 05:51, 5 April 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

The link to George Putnam in the 'History' section leads to a disambiguation page. Can someone who knows which Putnam the page refers to replace it with a proper link? [[Special:Contributions/69.180.172.142|69.180.172.142]] ([[User talk:69.180.172.142|talk]]) 18:56, 19 September 2010 (UTC)

== Starting Date ==

the starting date cannot be 1488 at Harvard, because Europeans had not discovered the new world until 1492. [[User:Jed 20012|Captain Gamma]] ([[User talk:Jed 20012|talk]]) 00:14, 19 October 2010 (UTC)

== List ==

For the sake of avoiding argument, listcreep, or original research, I've confirmed the current list of Transcendentalists in the lede according to a reliable source, specifically Philip Gura's book. In two pages, he gives a laundry list of figures (most of whom have Wikipedia articles). I would not recommend anyone add to this list without a specific source, including page number. I've pulled out a few names that are, obviously, the leaders in the movement (Emerson, Thoreau, Alcott, et al) because I think they are worthy of being outside the laundry list. As it stands, it counts as original research, until a source is found which backs up my claim that they were the ''major'' figures. While I'm here, I'm wondering if anyone else thinks the article on the [[Transcendental Club]] should be merged here; the two can only be strengthened if put together. --[[User:Midnightdreary|Midnightdreary]] ([[User talk:Midnightdreary|talk]]) 17:04, 6 November 2010 (UTC)

I removed Dickinson, because, while she was influenced by the Transcendentalists, she certainlly was not part of the movement; she was only born in 1830, and never had direct contact with the movement. 

I also remove the &quot;New Thought&quot; info box, as its prominence suggests that Transcendentalist is subsumed under New Thought. I think that kind of info box has no place in an article that is not directly related to the subject, but I don't know the rules. If it were to be allowed, one could add a dozen others (Americen Liturature, Philosophy, etc.), which would just get in the way. New Thought gets its mention further down, and I think that's more than enough. [[User:Kirkmc|Kirkmc]] ([[User talk:Kirkmc|talk]])  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|undated]] comment added 08:58, 5 November 2011 (UTC).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!--Template:Undated--&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;</text>
      <sha1>8s3gj6rnxfjkmi5u78l3nv8mb2jywkt</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
