<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Demon</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>21378403</id>
    <revision>
      <id>513982280</id>
      <parentid>513968001</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-22T07:32:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ian.thomson</username>
        <id>2489738</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rv [[WP:NOTFORUM]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8708">{{Talk header|search=y}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|collapsed=yes|1=
{{WikiProject Occult|class=c|importance=}}
{{WikiProject Mythology|class=c|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=c|importance=Top}} 
{{WikiProject Christianity|class=c|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Cryptozoology|class=c|importance=mid}}
}}
{{findnotice}}

==scope==
The article should probably restrict itself to demons in Judeo-Christian (or &quot;Abrahamic&quot;, including Islam and Western occultism) tradition and delegate &quot;demons&quot; in other cultures (East Asia, South Asia, Shamanism, Sub-Saharan Africa, Americas, etc.) to disambiguation. 
What we need to expand upon and figure out how to present are the coverage of psychoanalytic aspects and comparative mythology. --[[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|(𒁳)]]&lt;/small&gt; 14:08, 25 December 2009 (UTC)

*There has been no support for splitting the article. However, developing the article in the manner indicated by Dbachmann seems feasible, and if the article is developed in such a way that there is a distinct section on Judeo-Christian and/or Shamanism, etc, which grows too large for the parent, then it can be split out per [[WP:Summary style]]. &lt;span style=&quot;border: 1px  #F10; background-color:cream;&quot;&gt;'''[[User:SilkTork|&lt;font face=&quot;Script MT&quot; color=&quot;#1111AA&quot; size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;SilkTork&lt;/font&gt;]]''' *[[User talk:SilkTork|&lt;sup&gt;YES!&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 10:27, 15 March 2011 (UTC)

== Nephilim as the origin of demons  ==

'''Before the Flood'''

Genesis 6:4
The Nephilim were on the earth in those days—and also afterward—when the sons of God went to the daughters of humans and had children by them. They were the heroes of old, men of renown.

'''After the Flood'''

Numbers 13:33
&quot;We saw the Nephilim there (the descendants of Anak come from the Nephilim). We seemed like grasshoppers in our own eyes, and we looked the same to them.”

It is my understanding that the early Christians believed that what we think of as demons are not fallen angels but are actually descendants of fallen angels, before and after the flood. According to those beliefs when Goliath the giant died his spirit would have no where to go.

After reading the above scriptures it would seem that Goliath the giant was not quite man and not quite fallen angel. So the contention is that those who were descendants of Anak would not have a place in Abraham's bosom or hell. So they would be force to wander the earth until the day of judgment. 

Looking from that perspective makes the behavior of demons in the new testament much more logical. Carnal spirits in search of a human host, then in turn looking to seek out sinful pleasures.

I'm not sure if their is source material for these ideas but it would be interesting to find out where they come from. I am fairly certain that this is an old idea that dates back to early church. I do know that there are some pastors that believe it but I'm not really interested in the new stuff. If some one could have some old source material on it i would love to look at it.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Peter.s.mcintyre|Peter.s.mcintyre]] ([[User talk:Peter.s.mcintyre|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Peter.s.mcintyre|contribs]]) 21:14, 23 February 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:You may want to look at our guidelines [[WP:NOR|restricting original research]], [[WP:RS|identifying reliable source]], and [[WP:NPOV|writing in a neutral fashion]].  The connection between demons and Nephilim is one idea among many, but also requires specific secondary sources to attest to this being a historical idea.  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 21:38, 23 February 2011 (UTC)
Right That was the point of discussions. I hope that someone may be able to make that connection.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Peter.s.mcintyre|Peter.s.mcintyre]] ([[User talk:Peter.s.mcintyre|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Peter.s.mcintyre|contribs]]) 03:53, 24 February 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Questionable Reference to DSM IV ==

This citation is not actually of the DSM IV, but rather a news article which makes a passing reference to the DSM IV, with no immediately apparent attribution. Furthermore, I'm not sure that the assertion using this reference is accurately portraying the article's meaning, or intent. The source material says this:

&quot;It is hardly novel for ideologues to press alleged demonic phenomena into service, beginning in the late Middle Ages and reaching a climax in the witchcraft trials of the 17th century that claimed the lives of hundreds of thousands of innocents. The trials and executions at Salem, Mass., in 1692 still provide an instructive case in point. Dr. Peck seems oblivious, on the other hand, to the persuasive role played by suggestion and especially hypnosis in inducing dissociative states. In his enthusiasm to enter the lists as an exorcist, he too easily dismisses dissociative identity disorder (formerly known as multiple personality disorder) as a simpler explanation and more easily treated condition. '''Far from being discredited, moreover, it is still listed in the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (IV) of the American Psychiatric Association.'''&quot;

In this context, the article seems to be suggesting that it is the theory of ''&quot;dissociative identity disorder (formerly known as multiple personality disorder)&quot;'' that is listed within the DSM IV of the APA--not Dr.  Peck's studies on the subject, much less his theories on the psychology of demonic possession. As a result, I think the citation as used in the Wikipedia article is misusing/misinterpreting the source material's assertion.

But even then, since the source material is itself a business news article (not a peer-reviewed psychology/psychiatry journal), and only makes a passing, unsourced reference to the DSM IV, it seems like a questionable citation no matter which way you interpret it.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Dkamouflage|Dkamouflage]] ([[User talk:Dkamouflage|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Dkamouflage|contribs]]) 18:58, 9 February 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:The article is from (and probably copyvio) National Catholic Reporter / 										April 29, 2005. Having said that, it isn't referring to Peck but as you say, disassociative identity disorder, and I've removed it. In fact it's a criticism of him, and we could use it for that but give the source as the NCR. Well spotted. [[User:Dougweller|Dougweller]] ([[User talk:Dougweller|talk]]) 19:13, 9 February 2012 (UTC)
==File:The Army of Super Creatures.jpg Nominated for Deletion==
{|
|-
| [[File:Image-x-generic.svg|100px]] 
| An image used in this article, [[commons:File:The Army of Super Creatures.jpg|File:The Army of Super Creatures.jpg]], has been nominated for deletion at [[Wikimedia Commons]] in the following category: ''Deletion requests April 2012'' 
;What should I do?
''Don't panic''; a discussion will now take place over on Commons about whether to remove the file. This gives you an opportunity to contest the deletion, although please review Commons guidelines before doing so.
* If the image is [[WP:NFCC|non-free]] then you may need to upload it to Wikipedia (Commons does not allow fair use)
* If the image isn't freely licensed and there is no [[WP:FUR|fair use rationale]] then it cannot be uploaded or used.
To take part in any discussion, or to review a more detailed deletion rationale please visit the relevant [[commons:File:The Army of Super Creatures.jpg|image page (File:The Army of Super Creatures.jpg)]]

''This is Bot placed notification, another user has nominated/tagged the image'' --[[User:CommonsNotificationBot|CommonsNotificationBot]] ([[User talk:CommonsNotificationBot|talk]]) 15:25, 11 April 2012 (UTC)
|}

== Demons in literature ==

While all demons are fictional, this article concentrates on religious or folkloric concepts. I've added a section where we can list explicitly fictional descriptions. [[User:Monado|Monado]] ([[User talk:Monado|talk]]) 05:48, 31 July 2012 (UTC)
:Claiming that all demons are fictional is an unfounded assertion. Unless you can prove that demons do not exist, it would be nice of you to show respect for the many contributors to this page who do believe in them. [[User:Dontreader|Dontreader]] ([[User talk:Dontreader|talk]]) 03:49, 31 August 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>1uua2hipvkzphrrcy5wde56nc57bzai</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
