<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Nontrinitarianism</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>407141</id>
    <revision>
      <id>502033793</id>
      <parentid>502027941</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-07-13T10:02:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bonadea</username>
        <id>2877947</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* July 13, 2012 edit to remove POV wording */ cmt</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="30209">{{talk header}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell |1= 
{{ChristianityWikiProject |class=C |importance=Top 
 |core-topics-work-group = yes |core-topics-importance=Top
 |jehovah's-witnesses=yes |jehovah's-witnesses-importance=Top
 |theology-work-group=yes |theology-importance=Top
 |latter-day-saint-movement=yes |latter-day-saint-movement-importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Religion |class=C |importance=Mid
 |UnitarianUniversalism=yes}}
}}
{{User:WildBot/m04|sect={{User:WildBot/m03|1|unitarianism#Impact and opposition|the related section}}|m04}}
{| class=&quot;messagebox standard-talk&quot;
|-

| style=&quot;text-align: center&quot; |
This article was nominated for '''''[[Wikipedia:Deletion policy|deletion]]''''' on 05/12/05.
The result of the discussion was keep. &lt;!-- please do not add bolding to keep here: this breaks many places where it is already specified --&gt;
An archived record of this discussion can be found [[Wikipedia:Articles for deletion/Nontrinitarianism|here]].
|}
{{calm talk|pink}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 4
|minthreadsleft = 5
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Nontrinitarianism/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Archives |bot=MiszaBot I |age=90 |search=yes }}

== Supporting scriptures: no proof! ==

The section '''Supporting scriptures''' provides a lot of Bible references that allegedly non-trinitarians use to prove this and that. But we don't need those lists of Bible references per se, because {{red|'''none of them prove anything at all'''}}, they're just a list of Bible references. We instead need a sourced explanation from non-trinitarians that explain why they should preferrably be interpreted against trinitarism, otherwise we ignorants (and everybody else, who are not anti-trinitarians) will not understand a beep. [[User:Rursus|Rursus]] dixit. ([[User talk:Rursus|&lt;span style=&quot;color: red; background: #FFFF80&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;m&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;u&gt;bork&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]]!) 13:46, 3 November 2011 (UTC)
:Almost all of those have references from Jehovah's Witnesses publications. I would add  it. --[[User:Fazilfazil|Fazilfazil]] ([[User talk:Fazilfazil|talk]]) 00:57, 5 January 2012 (UTC)


Just read '''John 8:42'''.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/101.160.154.83|101.160.154.83]] ([[User talk:101.160.154.83|talk]]) 01:35, 19 April 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Arian ==

Recent edits notwithstanding, the current article still uses &quot;[[Arian]]&quot; as a synonym for &quot;nontrinitarian&quot;. Few nontrinitarians actually are adherents of [[Arianism]], and editors should be careful to only use the latter term when it is appropriate and [[WP:V|verifiable]] to do so.--[[User:AuthorityTam|AuthorityTam]] ([[User talk:AuthorityTam|talk]]) 22:45, 7 March 2012 (UTC)
:Arianism is listed as ''one of'' the forms of nontrinitarianism in the section at the top. Improve other text as necessary.--[[User:Jeffro77|&lt;span style='color:#365F91'&gt;'''Jeffro'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style='color:#FFC000'&gt;''77''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Jeffro77|talk]]) 22:51, 7 March 2012 (UTC)



== MichaelJW ==

The article currently has a paragraph on Jehovah's Witnesses, eight sentences in all. Of the eight, ''four'' sentences discuss Jesus as [[Michael the archangel]]:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;small&gt;They identify Jesus as the archangel, Michael, mentioned in the Bible at Jude 9. They believe he left heaven to become Jesus Christ on earth, and that after his ascension to heaven he resumed his pre-human identity. This belief is partly based upon 1 Thessalonians 4:16, in which &quot;the voice of the resurrected Lord Jesus Christ is described as being that of an archangel&quot;. They also cite passages from the books of Daniel and Revelation in which Jesus and Michael take similar action and exercise similar authority, concluding these scriptures indicate them to be the same person.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
IMHO, that seems to be three or four sentences too many (at least for ''this article''). How did a discussion of ''nontrinitarianism'' get so Michael-centric? I'll likely look to edit it in the next couple of weeks.--[[User:AuthorityTam|AuthorityTam]] ([[User talk:AuthorityTam|talk]]) 22:40, 9 March 2012 (UTC)
:The focus on Michael was recently added by Willietell, and I did some subsequent cleanup on it. No objection to paring it down to a single sentence, or maybe removing it as out of scope.--[[User:Jeffro77|&lt;span style='color:#365F91'&gt;'''Jeffro'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style='color:#FFC000'&gt;''77''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Jeffro77|talk]]) 02:29, 10 March 2012 (UTC)


:I really think it is in scope and notable as a belief.  The belief is unique to Jehovah's Witnesses as far as I know and it is relevant to the theme of the article, in that it ''partially'' explains the biblical understanding of JW's as to why Jesus is not a part of a trinitarian godhead but rather an angel in heaven who both existed before the universe was created and continues to exist today as the foremost angel in heaven.  I would have actually liked to have expounded upon it a little and drawn attention to other scriptures found in Daniel, Proverbs, Psalms, and Revelation that Jehovah's Witnesses believe support this reasoning, but I concluded this would become rather lengthy, so I only made a short reference to Daniel and Revelation.  In any case, I included the information because I thought it both noteworthy and within the scope of the article. [[User:Willietell|Willietell]] ([[User talk:Willietell|talk]]) 05:55, 10 March 2012 (UTC)
::I don't think it is necessary to talk about Michael in order to establish the JW belief that Jesus is not part of a Trinity.
::There shouldn't be ''more'' about Michael or archangels here. This is covered at [[Archangel]] and [[Michael (archangel)]] (there were some redundancy and scope issues with the sections at those two articles, which I've attempted to clean up&amp;mdash;discuss any concerns at those Talk pages); both of those articles have sections discussing the JW belief.--[[User:Jeffro77|&lt;span style='color:#365F91'&gt;'''Jeffro'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style='color:#FFC000'&gt;''77''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Jeffro77|talk]]) 06:06, 10 March 2012 (UTC)
::I'd support the inclusion of Michael. If Michael, a mere angel, is just one of the many &quot;heavenly beings&quot; and &quot;godlike ones&quot; (see discussion above), then that makes clear the regard in which Jesus is held by JWs. On the spectrum from the mortal to the Almighty, it makes clear why the JW position is nontrinitarian. [[User:Laurel Lodged|Laurel Lodged]] ([[User talk:Laurel Lodged|talk]]) 09:41, 10 March 2012 (UTC)
:::One solid sentence is sufficient regarding the JW belief that Jesus is a created angel and the only archangel (and thus Michael). Editors should know that JWs are not entirely unique in their belief that Michael is Jesus, but regardless: that discussion is almost entirely unrelated to Trinitarianism or nontrinitarianism; it's better discussed at '[[Michael (archangel)#Jehovah's Witnesses]]' and/or '[[Jehovah's Witnesses beliefs#Jesus Christ]]'.--[[User:AuthorityTam|AuthorityTam]] ([[User talk:AuthorityTam|talk]]) 22:44, 16 March 2012 (UTC)
::::This isn't the lead, this a subheading in the article.  Brevity is not important here, it is more important to give a well rounded understanding to the reader, and the material regarding Michael goes towards helping the reader understand Jesus' position in heaven and that, as the archangel Michael, Jesus cannot be part of some trinitarian godhead. [[User:Willietell|Willietell]] ([[User talk:Willietell|talk]]) 03:19, 30 March 2012 (UTC)
:::::It seems sufficient to simply ''mention'' the JW belief that Jesus is Michael, and it seems unnecessary to devote half the current section ('[[Nontrinitarianism#Jehovah's Witnesses]]') to discussing the idea. The extra material is certainly not [[WP:UNDUE|unduly weighing]], but the Wikipedia community seems better-served by ''linking to'' (rather than ''including'') a more-thorough discussion of '[[JW beliefs#Jesus Christ]]' and/or '[[Michael (archangel)#Jehovah's Witnesses]]'.--[[User:AuthorityTam|AuthorityTam]] ([[User talk:AuthorityTam|talk]]) 21:47, 30 March 2012 (UTC)

== Large delete reverted ==

Earlier today, an editor deleted an entire section. I hadn't seen that previously discussed, so I reverted that delete pending discussion if needed. I left in place all the minor edits (see [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Nontrinitarianism&amp;diff=482270519&amp;oldid=481717106 here] and if you want, compare [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Nontrinitarianism&amp;diff=482254699&amp;oldid=481717106 the delete] with [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Nontrinitarianism&amp;diff=482270519&amp;oldid=482254699 my revert]).--[[User:AuthorityTam|AuthorityTam]] ([[User talk:AuthorityTam|talk]]) 22:44, 16 March 2012 (UTC)
:The action was a bit extreme but has been hinted at here by several editors. It's clear that it's just a collection of Scriptural verses. In and of themselves, they prove nothing. They are primary sources. Strictly speaking, secondary sources should be used to support a point. Wiki is not a debating shop. Either the position is verifiable from secondary sources or it is not. Something like this was long overdue. [[User:Laurel Lodged|Laurel Lodged]] ([[User talk:Laurel Lodged|talk]]) 23:59, 16 March 2012 (UTC)
::Tam, I performed the delete. The section, as summarized in the edit, is just a large collection of proof-texts, which is inherently unencyclopedic/un [[WP:V]]erifiable (it probably falls under [[WP:WEIGHT]] as well, although if the article on Trinitarianism has a list of proof-texts, I'll head over there and blank it out too) as it uses primary sources that are open to interpretation - as the template says, &quot;This section uses religious texts as primary sources in a way that is not encyclopedic&quot; [paraphrase] - the rest of the article seems to be in order when I read through it, but that section doesn't belong in an encyclopedia. As my edit summary said, &quot;Wikipedia is not a debating hall or apologetics testing ground&quot; (although I'm not sure if we actually have policies that say it in no few short words).
::If you wish, I believe you can re-write the section with specific references to antitrinitarian secondary or tertiary sources, such as, &quot;The Jehovah's Witness' book, ''Reasoning from the Scriptures'', presents an apologia for antitrinitarian beliefs, and it uses some of these verses [add verses and the interpretation given in the book]...&quot; or &quot;The ''Encyclopedia of Christianity'' says that ''Science and Health with Key to the Scriptures'' uses these verses, interpreted in X manner, to support contention Y&quot;. I will let this sit here for a couple of days to gain comments, or, if you wish, you may open an RfC on it. [[User:JohnChrysostom|St&amp;nbsp;'''John&amp;nbsp;Chrysostom''']]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:JohnChrysostom|Δόξα]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/JohnChrysostom|τω&lt;sup&gt;&amp;nbsp;Θεώ&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;/sub&gt; 01:20, 18 March 2012 (UTC)
:::Ah, except for labeling nontrinitarians as &quot;''anti''trinitarians, that seems entirely fine and I can agree with its removal ''on the basis described''. I have no plans to rewrite the section, but I also would not object to another editor's rewrite per secondary sources, so the &quot;couple of days&quot; makes sense before re-deleting the section and noting that here.--[[User:AuthorityTam|AuthorityTam]] ([[User talk:AuthorityTam|talk]]) 14:58, 19 March 2012 (UTC)
::::Sorry, I didn't realize one was preferred: &quot;nontrinitarians&quot; are &quot;antitrinitarians&quot;, as those who reject something are generally considered ''anti-'' it (as in [[antidisestablishmentarian]]s, not &quot;nondisestablishmentarians&quot;) and it's the term I'm familiar with from the sources I have used (I'd never seen &quot;non-&quot; before this article). Some group such as &quot;Hindus&quot; could be described as &quot;nontrinitarian&quot;, because they are not Trinitarian yet do not actively reject the dogma, whereas Mormons, Unitarians, Jehovah's Witnesses, Christian Scientists, Muslims, etc. are not Trinitarian, but also actively reject the dogma (making them &quot;antitrinitarian&quot;).
::::I was going to delete it today (three day wait), but I'll give it until tomorrow or the day after, if you wish. [[User:JohnChrysostom|St&amp;nbsp;'''John&amp;nbsp;Chrysostom''']]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:JohnChrysostom|Δόξα]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/JohnChrysostom|τω&lt;sup&gt;&amp;nbsp;Θεώ&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;/sub&gt; 11:00, 20 March 2012 (UTC)
:::::It would seem that nontrinitarians don't wish to be ''defined'' by their rejection of trinitarianism, though nontrinitarians are typically not shy to acknowledge and discuss it. It's been a while since the matter has been rehashed, but every time the merits of ''[[nontrinitarianism]]'' and ''[[antitrinitarianism]]'' are compared as titles, ''nontrinitarianism'' emerges as superior for Wikipedia's purposes (eg [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Nontrinitarianism/Archive_1#Non-_or_anti-_trinitarian this article's Talk]).--[[User:AuthorityTam|AuthorityTam]] ([[User talk:AuthorityTam|talk]]) 21:46, 20 March 2012 (UTC)
::::::I have no issue with the title of the article either way as long as the standard term is somewhere in the lead (as it is now). I have no desire of opening another debate on some pedantry, as often happens on many religion articles. It would seem that anti/nontrinitarians, even if they do not wish to be defined by their rejection of the Trinity, are defined as such by mainstream Christians, that dogma - the Nicene Creed - being the oldest and most dearly held of all (even those Christians who are so liberal as to be apostate by any objective criteria still hold to a pretense of Trinity, from what I've seen - it even permeates Spong's writings!): being whether in truth or in consequence (I think both) the main difference between the groups. As, everything hinges on Jesus' divinity - soteriology, theo-/anthropology, Christology, sacred and dogmatic theology, ecclesiology, even study or view of Biblical inspiration and continuing revelations. When one looks at the mainstream Christian tradition and non/antitrinitarianism, one can ask what do they have in common with each other? The Bible. Mostly. (As most that I've seen lay claim to some form of continuing public revelation, whether through Swedenborg, the Watchtower, the General Authorities, or The {{Sc|S|CIENCE}} God/El-Rashonaliddai, as the extinct Unitarians and Deists.) That's a pun on &quot;El-Shaddai&quot; if you didn't get it. [[User:JohnChrysostom|St&amp;nbsp;'''John&amp;nbsp;Chrysostom''']]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:JohnChrysostom|Δόξα]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/JohnChrysostom|τω&lt;sup&gt;&amp;nbsp;Θεώ&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;/sub&gt; 04:39, 21 March 2012 (UTC)
{{outdent}}
[https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Talk:Nontrinitarianism/Archive_1#Trinitarian_Sabotage It actually appears the list of verses was put in here in an edit war between an alleged Trinitarian and a clearly abusive now-banned sockpuppeteer] &quot;See your one verse? Look at the TWENTY ONE verses I put above it to contradict it! God-damned Trinitarian! (emphasis in the original). Four years ago, this article was clearly a POV-fork (not that it is now): were the standards that much laxer back then? I've edited as an IP since 2007, but never used the talk page or did anything other than add content and copyedit. [[User:JohnChrysostom|St&amp;nbsp;'''John&amp;nbsp;Chrysostom''']]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:JohnChrysostom|Δόξα]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/JohnChrysostom|τω&lt;sup&gt;&amp;nbsp;Θεώ&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;/sub&gt; 04:57, 21 March 2012 (UTC)

:I am deleting now, after five days' wait. If any man stumbleth upon this and wisheth to re-write the section in an encyclopedic manner through the interpretations of secondary sources, feel welcome to. [[User:JohnChrysostom|St&amp;nbsp;'''John&amp;nbsp;Chrysostom''']]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:JohnChrysostom|Δόξα]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/JohnChrysostom|τω&lt;sup&gt;&amp;nbsp;Θεώ&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;/sub&gt; 23:26, 21 March 2012 (UTC)
{{RPA}}

:::Nothing was really settled here in Talk, and I put everything back, per common sense.   If Johnny keeps doing this because of obvious Trinatarian and chronic ''bias'', with the weak front excuse of &quot;not sourced&quot;, then he will probably ALWAYS be reverted.  His wholesale removals are arguable vandalism.  And should not really be tolerated, unless the matter is truly really settled in the discussion here, and real solid clear and copious consensus is established.  Which hasn't happened.  Cheers. [[User:Hashem sfarim|Hashem sfarim]] ([[User talk:Hashem sfarim|talk]]) 01:52, 22 March 2012 (UTC)

:::Addendum - as for the name of this article, it's fine...but I do agree that &quot;anti-trinitarianism&quot; should be somewhere in the article.  But the more loaded term of &quot;anti&quot; is not the main point (per AuthorityTam's good point) of what nontrinitarian professed Christians adhere to or dwell on necessarily.  Dawn Bible Students and JWs don't necessarily go around saying or thinking what Jesus is ''not'' more than they deal with who they believe Jesus ''is''.  Which, according to their view, just happens to be the First Son and Creation, who happens to be less than the Uncreated Father.  And Modalists don't necessarily define themselves as being ''against'' Trinitarianism more than they define themselves as being ''for'' Jesus Only as the Only Name and actual Only Person of God. Regards. [[User:Hashem sfarim|Hashem sfarim]] ([[User talk:Hashem sfarim|talk]]) 02:06, 22 March 2012 (UTC)


::::I agree that the section should stand, if you feel the section is poorly written then undertake re-writing it, do the research and provide the secondary sources you seek.  I will help as my time permits, but I have arrived at a busy time of year for me and my time at present is limited, but I will do what I can to help. [[User:Willietell|Willietell]] ([[User talk:Willietell|talk]]) 03:04, 22 March 2012 (UTC)

:::::The section is original research and the deletion should have stood. In any case it is far, far too long, which is why [[WP:UNDUE]] was mentioned. There is no vandalism here and religious arguments aren't a reason to delete or keep and Hashem's comments are personal attacks. Consensus isn't relevant where policy is concerned. I've taken this to [[WP:NORN#Nontrinitarianism#Scriptural verses employed by nontrinitarians]]. [[User:Dougweller|Dougweller]] ([[User talk:Dougweller|talk]]) 06:18, 22 March 2012 (UTC)
::::::Just want to second (or third) Doug's action here. This doesn't however preclude (1) finding WP:RS sources that clearly state that x verse is used by x nontrinitarian commentator (or better historically notable Arians/Socinians/Unitarians or notable modern church) to restore the mention of x verse as properly sourced. (2) checking other articles - I haven't looked at [[Trinitarianism]] - to ensure the same WP standard is being applied. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 08:26, 22 March 2012 (UTC)
::::::It should indeed be deleted. The purpose of the article is not to try to ''convince'' readers of a particular theological position. It is not necessary to provide a long list of scriptures in order to present the relevant beliefs of notable nontrinitarian groups.--[[User:Jeffro77|&lt;span style='color:#365F91'&gt;'''Jeffro'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style='color:#FFC000'&gt;''77''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Jeffro77|talk]]) 08:28, 22 March 2012 (UTC)

:::::::I am deleting it again. Common sense doesn't an encyclopedia write, nor does it policy override. It should not be here (it is a primary source, a list/directory, and open to interpretation: that is evidenced enough by the fact that Trinitarians use the very same verses to argue their position). Whether or not you personally think it should be here, policy states that it can not. Open an RfC if you want to. And, Hashem, [[Wikipedia:Articles_for_deletion/Holy_Catholic_and_Apostolic_Church_of_Arian_Catholicism|make sure you're not just angered at my AfD]], alright? You're coming across as writing polemics against &quot;Trinitarian bias&quot; and asserting that a personal &quot;Trinitarian bias&quot; of mine is what is urging the deletes (see above comment about Trinitarians using the same sources), not an adherence to policy and an attempt to build a better [[WP:ENCYCLOPEDIA]] instead of directory or apologetics test-ground, and further, that &quot;they could be considered [[WP:VANDALISM]]&quot;. I'm, surely through misinterpretation on my part, sensing that they seem aimed at me. You seem to skirt the edge of [[WP:CIVILITY]], and I would appreciate it if you would [[WP:NPA|tone it down a bit]], even if it is due to my own oversensitivity.
:::::::Furthermore, I do not know enough about the topic to write about it, and do not believe I could do it justice without bias; I do not have access to non/antitrinitarian sources. However, one does not have to be able to write something in order to apply policy to it. Also, if something is &quot;not sourced&quot;, that is a valid reason to remove it as well as place &lt;nowiki&gt;{{fact}} or {{cn}}&lt;/nowiki&gt; tags on it (and either the deletion stands or it is rewritten in accordance with policy) even if there is no other factor at play. [[User:JohnChrysostom|St&amp;nbsp;'''John&amp;nbsp;Chrysostom''']]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:JohnChrysostom|Δόξα]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/JohnChrysostom|τω&lt;sup&gt;&amp;nbsp;Θεώ&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;/sub&gt; 09:08, 22 March 2012 (UTC)
::::::::I just saw the IP editor: [[WP:NPA|no personal attacks]] is a policy here (I suppose I'm doing something right - I've been in a few '''very''' contentious and heated debates but have never seen PA before) and violating it is severely frowned upon - especially when insinuating genocide. And, I also just saw Doug's link. I'm going to follow it and see everyone over there in a minute. [[User:JohnChrysostom|St&amp;nbsp;'''John&amp;nbsp;Chrysostom''']]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:JohnChrysostom|Δόξα]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/JohnChrysostom|τω&lt;sup&gt;&amp;nbsp;Θεώ&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;/sub&gt; 09:13, 22 March 2012 (UTC)

:::::::::To Dougweller above.  I was merely stating my opinion that there seems to be some personal BIAS ''as well'' as &quot;not enough sources and &quot;OR&quot;&quot; arguments, from John.   I'm not the only one who has felt that way. Or noticed things.  Even if there's a kernel of truth to what he's saying, sorry, I doubt that that's the only reason for his motivation.   I barely said anything about that though in my comments above.   I was not the IP address that personally attacked John.  The IP's comment was removed by John for some reason.   I was making the point that consensus was never reached, and if anything, up until you showed up, had actually been going in the direction of retaining the sections.  So it was not only presumptuous for John to remove entire sections like that, it was also just plain premature.  One of his edit comments mentioned the Talk, but the problem is the &quot;Talk&quot; up until that point was no consensus to do anything that drastic.  There was no agreement yet for that.  And in fact, the opposite in a way.  Also, another point is that there were plenty of sources and refs, in a lot of those sections, but apparently not enough.  And some of it could have been modified, instead of entirely deleted. [[User:Hashem sfarim|Hashem sfarim]] ([[User talk:Hashem sfarim|talk]]) 19:30, 22 March 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::As I stated above, I can agree with the section's removal ''on the basis described'' here. Any point or points could be reinstated ''if they are properly sourced'' (which would be relatively easy but time-consuming for an interested editor to do).--[[User:AuthorityTam|AuthorityTam]] ([[User talk:AuthorityTam|talk]]) 19:38, 22 March 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::::Even if there was personal bias, it would still be correct to delete for all the objective reasons written above. Is that being right for the wrong reason? [[User:Laurel Lodged|Laurel Lodged]] ([[User talk:Laurel Lodged|talk]]) 19:45, 22 March 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::::True, because we all have leanings and positions, so that's no big problem all the time necessarily, but when it becomes a situation where there might be a combination of reasons or motives to remove entire sections that were established for a long time in an article, sections that had some refs at least, then it makes one wonder if at least some of the reason to remove said sections was not entirely valid, but maybe only semi-valid, and maybe more modifying than out-right deleting could have been more considered.  Regards. [[User:Hashem sfarim|Hashem sfarim]] ([[User talk:Hashem sfarim|talk]]) 03:27, 23 March 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::::::Hashem: I ask again that you refrain from [[WP:NPA|personal attacks]]. Accusing another editor of personal bias in absence of evidence (and, indeed, in evidence of adherence to policy) is a personal attack. [[User:JohnChrysostom|St&amp;nbsp;'''John&amp;nbsp;Chrysostom''']]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:JohnChrysostom|Δόξα]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/JohnChrysostom|τω&lt;sup&gt;&amp;nbsp;Θεώ&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;/sub&gt; 21:25, 23 March 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::::::::There were plenty of sources and refs, in a lot of those sections, but apparently not enough. And some of it could have been modified, instead of entirely deleted. [[User:Hashem sfarim|Hashem sfarim]] ([[User talk:Hashem sfarim|talk]]) 08:59, 24 March 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::::::::JWs publications have pioneered in convincing people to expose the non-scriptural theory of Trinity. So in case somebody need references for each scripture they can get it from their publications. [http://www.watchtower.org/e/ti/index.htm I found a Sample is here]. --[[User:Fazilfazil|Fazilfazil]] ([[User talk:Fazilfazil|talk]]) 22:47, 30 March 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::::::::I have saved the 'Ontological difference' section in my sandbox page. I saw that in Trinity article scriptures are referred to support arguments. When I get time I would try to write in a similar manner with proper references.--[[User:Fazilfazil|Fazilfazil]] ([[User talk:Fazilfazil|talk]]) 01:38, 31 March 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::::::::::If the &quot;theory of Trinity&quot; is &quot;non-scriptural&quot;, then how can recourse to scrpture disprove. Wouldn't such a proof consist &quot;there it isn't, like I told you so&quot;. At best, would this not amount to absence of evidence to support the theory as opposed to proof to absence? [[User:Laurel Lodged|Laurel Lodged]] ([[User talk:Laurel Lodged|talk]]) 12:15, 31 March 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::::::::::It is a Universally known truth that the theory of trinity in not scriptural but are based on the teachings of church fathers. As quoted in this article several reputed encyclopedias explicitly support the fact. However people who say that church is infallible (though the church have done the most number of sins throughout the history), do all kinds of search in the Bible to find scriptures that could be construed as a fitting to their predefined beliefs. But that was not the point I was talking about. So I don't want to move forward with a vague conversation. I just wanted to compare the writing Style of this article with the trinity article--[[User:Fazilfazil|Fazilfazil]] ([[User talk:Fazilfazil|talk]]) 15:06, 31 March 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::::::::::::Editor [[User:Laurel Lodged|Laurel Lodged]] seems to be mildly teasing regarding the term &quot;non-scriptural&quot;; by contrast, editor [[User:Fazilfazil|Fazilfazil]] seems to use the term &quot;non-scriptural&quot; to seriously indicate that which he believes ''contradicts'' Scripture. Of course Wikipedia is ''not'' the place for Nontrinitarian or Trinitarian advocacy. Furthermore, Wikipedia is uninterested in whether a particular belief is or isn't &quot;Scriptural&quot;. Wikipedia is interested in effectively discussing what [[WP:V|verifiable references]] have to say about a notable topic in a balanced, encyclopedic format. The article on Nontrinitarianism should be ''informed by'' (that is, influenced by) the article at Trinitarianism, but the two topics are ''not'' directly comparable. As [[User:Fazilfazil|Fazilfazil]] notes, an editor interested in a &quot;refresh&quot; [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Nontrinitarianism&amp;oldid=483332762#Scriptural_verses_employed_by_nontrinitarians of the former &quot;Scriptures&quot; section here] ''could'' source from Watch Tower publications (including Watchtower.org), but Wikipedia will prefer that other sources ''also'' be included (perhaps by other editors familiar with those other sources).--[[User:AuthorityTam|AuthorityTam]] ([[User talk:AuthorityTam|talk]]) 20:34, 2 April 2012 (UTC)

== Jesus Christ is God only ==

Is page about nontrinitarians (including people who believe in Jesus only) or is it about Father Unitarians (and jewish variations) if so could rename the page. Instead please include Jesus nontrinitarians on the page in future.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/82.22.79.206|82.22.79.206]] ([[User talk:82.22.79.206|talk]]) 13:20, 7 May 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== July 13, 2012 edit to remove POV wording ==

The [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Nontrinitarianism&amp;diff=502000620&amp;oldid=502000224 recent edits] to reduce POV wording have improved the tone of the article. The removal of the often pejorative term &quot;cult&quot; seems to be the basic action taken. Within the broad Christian realm, some trinitarian groups consider non-trinitarians to be less than Christian and thus are labeled &quot;cult&quot;. Exchanging &quot;cult&quot; for &quot;group&quot;, etc. moves the article closer to NPOV wording. [[User:DonaldRichardSands|DonaldRichardSands]] ([[User talk:DonaldRichardSands|talk]]) 09:06, 13 July 2012 (UTC)

:You are definitely right about the POV wording - that edit was, however, a reversal of one editor's very recent insertion of POV verbiage, rather than a removal of phrasing that had been in the article previously. The POV editor also removed all mention of nontrinitarianism from various Christianity related articles and templates (which has also been reverted). --''[[User:Bonadea|bonadea]]'' &lt;small&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Bonadea|contributions]] [[User talk:Bonadea|talk]]&lt;/small&gt; 10:02, 13 July 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>q3jb6j2yayycdwnkwguneecy5mi4spy</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
