<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Faith</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>11066</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520937745</id>
      <parentid>512294880</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-01T19:08:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>HuPi</username>
        <id>7327467</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>revise the definition</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10380">{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{talkarchivenav}}
|maxarchivesize = 45K
|counter = 3
|minthreadsleft = 5
|algo = old(30d)
|archive = Talk:Faith/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{talkheader}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell |blp= no|1=
{{WPREL|class=start|importance=Top}}
{{Spirituality project|class=Start|importance=high}}
{{philosophy|importance=mid|class=start|ethics=yes|religion=yes}}
}}
{{archivebox |auto=yes}}

== Atheist contributions are heavily biased in this attempt for an fact based article about faith ==

This &quot;talk&quot; section was titled &quot;11 million Mormons, one third of which is active, and they get the bulk of this article?&quot; and it contained this content: &quot;This page has obviously been run over with Mormon content. Not proportionally representative of the varying views. It appears we have some zealous Mormon editors.&quot; The above editor should substantiate her claims, they come across as personal attacks.  

In my opinion there is an obvious lack of LDS content in this article (no mention that a correct understanding of Christ is necessary to have faith, no mention in regard to faith that God is no respecter of persons, etc.); however, it is very heavy with atheist content. 

Atheistic Substantiations: Heavy emphasis on transcendence in the summary; Usefulness of faith in the here and now (present) is deleted (eg., any reference to self-help authors are deleted: Think and Grow Rich or Psycho-Cybernetics); Any description that &quot;faith&quot; is based on &quot;evidence&quot; is summarily deleted (never improved upon, just deleted with inaccurate comments); Heavy emphasis on Fideism; Clumsily forcing in William James, Bertrand Russell, Richard Dawkins; Ending the article with the &quot;CRITICISM&quot; instead of the &quot;REBUTTAL.&quot;

Shouldn't a religious definition sit aside a non-religious one ESPECIALLY for an article that is supposedly part of a Wikipedia &quot;project&quot; on &quot;religion?&quot;  Why won't the atheist editors allow Wikipedia articles to contain religious definitions that describe religion from the point of view of the religious?  Doesn't it make sense that the religious should be able to explain their religious experience? Why look to the CRITIC for a description of how it FEELS to be on stage?  

== Sections that NEED to be written ==

The following sections are missing from this article: 
1) Non-religious Faith: Faith and it's usefulness now and in the future [quote self-consistency and self-help authors and psychologists], 
2) Changing Faith: How faith decreases or grows based on life experiences [quote human development and self-help psychologists and authors], 
3) Rebuttal to the criticism of faith: Faith provides an individual with the joy and other benefits that come from acting as if something is true while the facts are still being resolved [quote theists and self-help psychologists].

References and Further Reading: Add relevant writings of Self-help psychologists and authors such as Jean Piaget (eg.: &quot;Genetic Epistemology&quot;), Prescott Lecky (eg. The Concept of Self in Medicine and Health Care), Napoleon Hill, Maxwell Maltz, Tony Robbins, etc.

[[User:Rhenrie|Rhenrie]] ([[User talk:Rhenrie|talk]]) 18:57, 27 December 2011 (UTC)

== Faith as commitment ==

Removed the section &quot;Faith as commitment&quot; because as it stands it is not well written section. If someone wants to re-write it, get the text from history.

(reasoning in italics):
Sometimes, faith means a belief in a relationship with a [[deity]]. ''redundant.''

In this case, &quot;faith&quot; is used in the sense of &quot;fidelity.&quot; ''not explained'' 

For many Jews, the [[Hebrew Bible]] and [[Talmud]] depict a committed but contentious relationship between their God and the Children of Israel. ''This is covered in &quot;Judaism&quot; with a link to &quot;Main article: Jewish principles of faith&quot;''

For a lot of people, faith or the lack thereof, is an important part of their [[Identity (social science)|identity]], for example a person who identifies himself or herself as a [[Muslim]] or a [[skeptic]]. ''way to generic for an article that goes into so much detail elsewhere, maybe add to intro?''

According to [[Michael Green (theologian)]] faith is &quot;Self-commitment on the basis of evidence&quot;. ''unreferenced, if included it needs expanding and explanation.''

== Sikh Faith ==

With reference to this article on Faith &quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Faith&quot;, you forgot to include the Sikh Faith. Kindly reseach and include that to this section, because like Hindu, Christianity, Buddhu, and Islam faiths, Sikh faith is a major world religion. Thanks. Good work on the article!

== Definition ==
I think that the opening line seriously misrepresents the nature of faith. I would suggest a statement like &quot;A (religious) faith is a world-view and life-style associated with a particular set of beliefs, and usually with particular practices and a community.&quot; More simply and more generally, faith (religious or secular) implies trust and committment. In William Blake's poem 'Jerusalem', the first half muses quietly on four historically improbable propositions. The second explodes with the confidence and determination typical of a strong faith.[[User:HuPi|HuPi]] ([[User talk:HuPi|talk]]) 19:08, 1 November 2012 (UTC)

(There have recently been some revisions to the long-standing definition of faith on this page, sourced to multiple dictionaries.  For some reason, an editor deleted multiple sources (check earlier versions of the page, e.g. March 2011).  Definition issues also arose previously, and are clarified by referring to the disambiguation page (linked at the top).  Although I previously favored including &quot;lack of proof&quot;, on closer consideration this article is specifically about religious faith, and it is a matter of controversy whether the separate definition referring to &quot;lack of proof&quot; is appropriate in this context or not.  &quot;Lack of proof&quot; is one of at least 8, and up to 10 possible definitions of faith directly sourced, and several of those definitions (e.g. &quot;sincere intentions&quot;) are peripheral to the subject of this article.  Scientific evidence is one exceedingly strong form of proof, and most agree that religious faith is not scientific.  Mathematical proofs are not based upon science, but are proofs nonetheless.  Scholars continue to debate whether or not religious faith can ever be based on deductive proof, and it is presumptuous to ignore these debates.  Because this article is 1) specifically about religious faith, 2) is not a completely general definition page, and 3) controversy remains about the question of proof in the context of religious faith, it seems most appropriate to focus on the clearly applicable definition of faith as trust.[[User:Jj1236|Jj1236]] ([[User talk:Jj1236|talk]]) 08:03, 28 December 2011 (UTC)

Then there is the biblical definition of faith which certainly doesn't carry with it the &quot;lack of proof&quot; as part of it's definition. For while it states, &quot;Hebrews 11:1 Now faith is the substance of things hoped for, the evidence of things not seen.&quot; it also states &quot;Hebrews 11:29 By faith they passed through the Red sea as by dry [land]: which the Egyptians assaying to do were drowned.&quot; and &quot;Hebrews 11:33 Who through faith subdued kingdoms, wrought righteousness, obtained promises, stopped the mouths of lions,...&quot;. The difference between the proof of biblical faith and science is that the outcome of biblical faith rests in the object, God, a person, while the outcome of science rests in the predictable behavior of nature. As such, biblical faith cannot be verified by a repeatable experiment any more than one can expect a free person to behave the same way on a whim. Further, biblical faith is always obedience to something the object of the faith has stated or commanded. Science does not deal with substances that command a certain behavior in order for them to behave a certain way. Biblical faith is then obedience to what the object of faith, God, has said and is proven by the outcome. It is therefore not repeatable in the sense that 2H2 + O2 = 2H2O is repeatable. 
[[User:Kellnerp|Kellnerp]] ([[User talk:Kellnerp|talk]]) 13:50, 29 March 2012 (UTC)

:Don't forget the assumption made by most scientists that nature's behavior predictable. 

:Moreover, an argument against God's existence made by atheists is that [[God]]'s behavior (if he existed) would not be predictable. Compare this to the belief (or notion or &quot;observation&quot;) that human behavior is often predictable, especially in the aggregate. Economics, sociology and political science study human behavior. --[[User:Ed Poor|Uncle Ed]] ([[User talk:Ed Poor|talk]]) 14:40, 4 August 2012 (UTC)

==Restrictive page move==

[[Religious faith]] is not the only kind of faith; most scientists have 'faith' that physical laws are pervasive and persistent. There is also &quot;full faith and credence&quot; and &quot;good faith&quot;. 

The notion that only religious people have &quot;faith&quot; but that scientists (and/or materialists and atheists) do not have faith, is a POV. It should not be swept under the table by changing an article title. 

In any case, a general article on [[faith]] should include secular kinds of faith, such as the following:
* the physical laws of nature (physics, chemistry and biology) guide everything within the universe, including mankind! Our lives are completely dominated by the laws of inertia and gravity (and all the other laws of nature). [http://www.novan.com/god.htm Donald L. Hamilton, Separating God from Religion]

--[[User:Ed Poor|Uncle Ed]] ([[User talk:Ed Poor|talk]]) 14:36, 4 August 2012 (UTC)

Disagree. This is not a POV issue, it is derived from definitions. In formal usage Faith is used as a companion word to talk about religious viewpoints. The poster above actually reinforced that view with their use of scare quotes whenever talking about faith in the non-religious sense.

Regarding the uniformity of nature, firstly this is a universal stance, and secondly assuming it isn't a faith position it is the only available rational coping strategy. One cannot hold any other view and be able to function. One cannot plan or make decisions around the assumption that the physical laws are not persistent or may radically change at any time without warning.

Expanding faith beyond religious faith is equivocation.

[[Special:Contributions/86.17.224.17|86.17.224.17]] ([[User talk:86.17.224.17|talk]]) 01:43, 14 September 2012 (UTC)Rich</text>
      <sha1>ljgtl3ff03wz1e5tei48kv7tbvm64q0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
