<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Abraham</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>17949934</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522408063</id>
      <parentid>522260302</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-11T00:41:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MiszaBot I</username>
        <id>3797869</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot: Archiving 1 thread (older than 100d) to [[Talk:Abraham/Archive 6]].</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="52682">{{Talk header|search=yes}}
{{Not a forum}}
{{calmtalk}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|collapsed=yes|1=
{{WikiProject Iraq|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Christianity|class=B|importance=High|saints=yes|saints-importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Judaism|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Bible|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Islam|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Biography
|living= no
|class = B
|priority= Top
|listas = Abraham
}}
{{WP1.0|v0.7=pass|class=B|category=Philrelig}}
}}
{{Auto archiving notice|bot=MiszaBot|age=100|dounreplied=yes}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=Talk:Abraham/Archive index
|mask=Talk:Abraham/Archive &lt;#&gt;
|leading_zeros=0
|indexhere=yes}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 6
|minthreadsleft = 4
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|algo = old(100d)
|archive = Talk:Abraham/Archive %(counter)d
}}

== The &quot;Historicity and origins&quot; section is massively biased, and even self-contradictory. ==

&quot;none of the kings mentioned are known&quot;
Known? Known by who?
Known by anyone? [[User:Almufasa|Almufasa]] ([[User talk:Almufasa|talk]])

&quot;Abimelech could not have been a Philistine (they did not arrive until centuries later)&quot;
Completely false. Is the writer believing that no kings existed in this area?

&quot;Urwould not become known as &quot;Ur of the Chaldeans&quot;&quot;
Questionable, and possibly irrelevant, if it was written down later.

&quot;Laban could not have been an Aramean, as the Arameans did not become an identifiable political entity until the 12th century&quot;
Utterly irrelevant, even if true. Aram was an area, not just a political entity.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Sloppyjoes7|Sloppyjoes7]] ([[User talk:Sloppyjoes7|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Sloppyjoes7|contribs]]) 17:11, 4 July 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:The edits you made to &quot;fix&quot; this plagiarized from the source used.  Copyright violation is never right.
:[[WP:NOR|This site does not take original research]], your assessment of the sources does not matter.
:When McNutt says &quot;none of the kings mentioned are known,&quot; it is followed by &quot;from other sources.&quot;  You have completely taken this part out of context, which is only either dishonest or incompetent.
:The argument &quot;Is the writer believing that no kings existed in this area?&quot; is both a non-sequitor and a straw man argument.  It demonstrates that you're not properly reading the source used.  The author stated that Palestinian kings of that time and place are known, and that the records of that time and place do not match those in the Bible.  The author also states that a king of the Philistines is given as being in Palestine in the Bible, when there is no evidence that the Philistines had arrived in Palestine yet.
:The author points out that ''Babylon'' was not known as ''Chaldea'' until a later date.  This does show that the text was written at a much much later date, which does drastically decrease the possibility that it was history and not legend.
:Your reading comprehension is questionable at best.  Quit attempting to push your misunderstanding bias of the source into the article.  Your misunderstanding bias is not bias on part of the article.  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 17:51, 4 July 2012 (UTC)

::&quot;The edits you made to &quot;fix&quot; this plagiarized from the source used.&quot;
::I did no such thing. That's a pure lie.
::&quot;your assessment of the sources does not matter.&quot;
::Well, the article is massively biased, and that violates the guidelines.
::&quot;When McNutt says &quot;none of the kings mentioned are known,&quot; it is followed by &quot;from other sources.&quot;
::Oh, really? Because the Wikipedia article said no such thing.
::&quot;Your misunderstanding bias is not bias on part of the article.&quot;
::I'm afraid this refers to you far more than it does me.
::&quot;do not delete sources.&quot;
::With this false accusation, you undid my edits. You are fighting to keep the article from being neutral.
::[[User:Sloppyjoes7|Sloppyjoes7]] ([[User talk:Sloppyjoes7|talk]]) 08:24, 13 August 2012 (UTC)
:::I think there is a misunderstanding here between the two of you. I hope that my new revisions to the [[Abraham#Origins]] will clear some of this madness up. Thanks, &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 10:19, 13 August 2012 (UTC)

:: Jewish tradition holds that [[Ezra]] edited Genesis, adding contemporary place names.  [[Special:Contributions/124.198.202.25|124.198.202.25]] ([[User talk:124.198.202.25|talk]]) 14:27, 4 August 2012 (UTC)
:::Even with a [[WP:RS|reliable source]] for that assertion, you would also need a source applying it to this stuff, as applying it otherwise would go against [[WP:SYNTH]]. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 14:43, 4 August 2012 (UTC)

Surely there is no evidence for any of this so the whole article should start with &quot;According to Jewish and Christian mythology...&quot; [[User:Almufasa|Almufasa]] ([[User talk:Almufasa|talk]])
:That is just an ignorant comment when the lede already makes it clear that &quot;he plays a prominent role in Judaism, Christianity and Islam.&quot; and the first section of the article delves into the [[Biblical criticism]] of the narrative using secular sources. Thanks, &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 20:30, 13 August 2012 (UTC)
:He may play a prominent role in Judaism, Christianity, Islam etc. all of which are mythologies hence my suggestion that the article should be prefixed as such. [[User:Almufasa|Almufasa]] ([[User talk:Almufasa|talk]]) 19:07, 16 August 2012 (UTC)

== No oral tradition? ==

I find this modern claim that little or no oral tradition is incorporated in the story of Abraham a bit odd.  Here is just one example of an older tale that was recast, obviously in the oral stage, into a story involving Abraham: Jud 19 &gt; Gen 19.  Especially cf. Gen 19:5-8 with Jud 19:22-24:

Gen 19:5 And they called unto Lot, and said unto him, Where are the men which came in to thee this night? bring them out unto us, that we may know them.
6 And Lot went out at the door unto them, and shut the door after him,
7 And said, I pray you, brethren, do not so wickedly.
8 Behold now, I have two daughters which have not known man; let me, I pray you, bring them out unto you, and do ye to them as is good in your eyes: only unto these men do nothing; for therefore came they under the shadow of my roof.

Jud 19:22 Now as they were making their hearts merry, behold, the men of the city, certain sons of Belial, beset the house round about, and beat at the door, and spake to the master of the house, the old man, saying, Bring forth the man that came into thine house, that we may know him.
23 And the man, the master of the house, went out unto them, and said unto them, Nay, my brethren, nay, I pray you, do not so wickedly; seeing that this man is come into mine house, do not this folly.
24 Behold, here is my daughter a maiden, and his concubine; them I will bring out now, and humble ye them, and do with them what seemeth good unto you: but unto this man do not so vile a thing.

The multiple parallels and near equivalence of dialogue are not likely to be due to chance, nor is such invention or confusion on the part of the story tellers easily attributed to post-exilic scribal activity.  The fact that Ezekiel's triad (Noah, Job, and Daniel) differs from that of J-E-D-P (Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob) does not mean that the Abrahamic tradition was not already old in more limited circles (Judah or Benjamin?), if only in oral form. We could give many more examples of evolution in the oral stage, e.g., the variant traditions of a patriarch's wife being taken by a pharoah or Philistine king.   --AGF  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/67.128.133.10|67.128.133.10]] ([[User talk:67.128.133.10|talk]]) 15:40, 1 August 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Wikipedia uses [[WP:RS|reliable sources]], preferably [[WP:PSTS|secondary sources]], not [[WP:NOR|original research]].  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 15:45, 1 August 2012 (UTC)

Rest assured, no original research is involved with my statement above.  Such discussion may be read in any good commentary of Genesis or Judges.  --AGF  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/67.128.133.10|67.128.133.10]] ([[User talk:67.128.133.10|talk]]) 15:53, 1 August 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:You do not need to make a new section for each new statement, and please sign your posts with four tildes (&lt;nowiki&gt;~~~~&lt;/nowiki&gt;).  If it is not original research, please provide [[WP:RS|sources]] for your statements, or we cannot add them. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 15:56, 1 August 2012 (UTC)

I see nothing directing me how to respond other than adding a new section.  I don't care whether or not you change anything, and I feel no need to provide a bibliography of higher criticism to respond to such a spurious claim as that attributed to Blenkinsopp to the effect that the &quot;Genesis story of Abraham was not transmitted by oral traditions, but originated from literary circles of the 6th and 5th centuries BCE.&quot;  This is utter nonsense.  What is it doing in an encyclopedia article?  [[Special:Contributions/67.128.133.10|67.128.133.10]] ([[User talk:67.128.133.10|talk]]) 16:05, 1 August 2012 (UTC)AGF
:There's a button right next to new section saying &quot;edit.&quot;  You can also look to the right of any section title, and click the edit button there to edit only that section.  [[WP:CITE]] is one of the cornerstones of this site.  Nothing goes into articles without sources, and [[WP:BURDEN|the burden lies on you to provide those sources]].  It's no different than any college.  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 16:15, 1 August 2012 (UTC)

The &quot;edit&quot; function provided no cursor--can't work with it.

Rather than respond to your insistence on sources I'll simply show how the article text itself contradicts the spurious claim that no oral tradition is involved:

&quot;There is basic agreement that his connection with Haran, Shechem and Bethel is secondary and originated when he became identified as the father of Jacob and ancestor of the northern tribes; his association with Mamre and Hebron, on the other hand (in the south, in the territory of Jerusalem and Judah), suggest that this region was the original home of his religion.&quot;

Do you not understand that this &quot;secondary&quot; connection entails a later historical period and a change in tradition in response to this period?  That is, the tradition evolves over time in accord with an evolving historical setting.  And this &quot;sitz in lebn&quot; is of course pre-exilic.  So your &quot;basic agreement&quot; here flies in the face of Blenkinsopp's claim and the article seems oblivious to the fact that it is presenting conflicting viewpoints.  I am merely pointing out that Blenkinsopp's is untenable and should be deleted.  At the very least the article should note the different viewpoints, rather than present an incongruent picture.  --AGF [[Special:Contributions/67.128.133.10|67.128.133.10]] ([[User talk:67.128.133.10|talk]]) 16:35, 1 August 2012 (UTC)agf
:I'm having trouble understanding how you could create a new section if you can't edit: it's just variations of the same function.  Again, we do not take original research.  If you do not wish to provide sources for any assertions, Wikipedia is not the place for you.  Editor understanding does not matter here.  The basic agreement part does not say that the secondary connection was the same as the literary inventions discussed by Blenkinsopp or that the Mamre and Hebron connection was part of any oral tradition.  It could just as easily be read to mean that that the literary tradition changed over time.  If you can provide evidence that the sources being cited are contradictory, and that the two sections need to be clarified as competing theories, then you'd be on to something.  Otherwise, any relationship between the two sections is totally being read into the article.
:If you do not wish to provide sources, all your assertions will be treated as unsourced original research.  One fact of life in any academic field is &quot;cite your sources,&quot; and Wikipedia goes to an extreme to exclude anything that is not cited to a source.  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 17:02, 1 August 2012 (UTC)

::Just in case [[User talk:67.128.133.10|talk]] is still around: Anyone can edit a wikipedia article, including you. Just experiment a bit to get the hang of the mechanics. Read what Blenkinsopp says (there should be a link to the book in the bibliography section), and correct any mistakes the article makes regarding what he says - but don't correct the man himself. (For example, I think he talks about Abraham's &quot;cult&quot;, not his &quot;religion&quot;). Get other books too by all means. I think, by the way, that what Blenkinsopp means is that the Abraham story in Genesis is a literary creation, not a written version of an existing oral tradition. There was an earlier tradition, but Genesis is a late work, c.500BC, and the authors were out to create a foundation myth that tied the traditional ancestors to the Exodus, and they had no qualms about making things up. [[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 03:09, 8 August 2012 (UTC)

== Abraham is real. ==

According to a Wikipedia page on Babylonia, Abraham has been known since the reign of Hammurabi. He is referred to in Babylonian scripts as Abi-ramu.

[[Special:Contributions/71.164.209.66|71.164.209.66]] ([[User talk:71.164.209.66|talk]]) 05:41, 7 August 2012 (UTC)Anonymous

:The existence of someone with the same name doesn't prove anything, how could it? [[User:Dougweller|Dougweller]] ([[User talk:Dougweller|talk]]) 11:57, 13 August 2012 (UTC)

== Narrative in the Qur'an ==

I've moved the Narrative in the Qur'an section to [[Islamic views on Abraham#Narrative in the Qur'an]] out of respect for the hard work that was put into preparing such material... because, the alternative was delete that section since it did not have [[WP:THIRDPARTY]] sources, and could be viewed as borderline [[WP:ORIGINAL]] work. Thanks, &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 08:11, 13 August 2012 (UTC)

== Sources for &quot;it is widely believed&quot; - pretty rubbish ==

Ok the first source is the website of Grace Communion International which says it &quot;is a denomination with 42000 members&quot;.

Second source is from &quot;The Ensign Message, identifying the Anglo-Saxons, Celts and kindred peoples as the present day descendants of  the Israel of the Old Testament.&quot;

Third source is the Kjos ministry, a family ministry which is um, what can I say, a bit unusual?[http://www.crossroad.to/articles2/006/pd-deception.htm][http://www.crossroad.to/articles2/006/pd-deception.htm].

Fourth is to something called &quot;Judaism 101&quot;, a page on a personal website[http://www.jewfaq.org/author.htm] (author claims no qualifications).

There 4 sites are considered enough to back the statement &quot;It is currently widely believed by Christians, Jews, and other scholars that Abraham was a true historical figure.&quot;? Seriously? An very very small Christian denomination, two groups which might kindly be considered fringe and are even much tinier, and one Jew's website? Clearly none of them are scholars, none of them represent their faiths in any significant way, and in fact at least for the 3 Christian sources are clearly represent a miniscule minority.

Then we have: &quot; For example, the Catholic church takes the stance that Abraham was more than a mere myth, and that archaeology supports this position&quot; with the New Advent Encyclopedia as a source. A couple of problems - what the Church says officially can be reported, but we can't use the article to suggest it's the view of most Catholics. It probably is, but we'd need a better source. But in any case, what does this article represent? Certainly not any modern view, its sources are long dead, eg [[Theophilus Pinches]] and [[Archibald Sayce]]. So, we are using the century old [[New Advent]] encyclopedia to back this claim? Does anyone think that maybe readers might think that where it says &quot;archaeology supports this position&quot; readers might think that means something a bit more modern?

Seriously, this is all rubbish. For the moment, I'm removing the sources and replacing them with fact tags. But unless you can have some good research which would have to be mainstream, not fringe, I think this section needs to be removed or heavily rewritten. [[User:Dougweller|Dougweller]] ([[User talk:Dougweller|talk]]) 13:05, 13 August 2012 (UTC)

:I added those, and they aren't &quot;all rubbish.&quot; In fact, you just proved one of Wikipedia's main problems. Earlier in this very talk page, I questioned this section and made some edits. I received the reply &quot;This site does not take original research, your assessment of the sources does not matter.&quot; So, I ask, Dougweller, who are you to remove that sourced material? You had no right.[[User:Sloppyjoes7|Sloppyjoes7]] ([[User talk:Sloppyjoes7|talk]]) 23:08, 1 September 2012 (UTC)
::Church websites and newsletters are not academic peer-reviewed works and therefore do not meet [[WP:RS|our reliable sourcing guidelines]].  &quot;The Ensign Message&quot; is a white supremacist site, which makes it so unreliable a source that you have no choice but to admit you made a mistake.  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 23:21, 1 September 2012 (UTC)

:I apologize for not catching these bad sources when I moved the said material.&amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 13:28, 13 August 2012 (UTC)

::Apology not accepted. Why would you so quickly assume that Dougweller's analysis is accurate?[[User:Sloppyjoes7|Sloppyjoes7]] ([[User talk:Sloppyjoes7|talk]]) 23:12, 1 September 2012 (UTC)
:::The apology wasn't directed to you, and Dougweller's analysis is not assumed to be accurate, he is simply repeating observable facts. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 23:21, 1 September 2012 (UTC)

::Apology accepted. I note that the [[The Harvard Crimson]] is also used as a source (it is clearly inferior to the Yale Daily News of course).
::As your penance, you might want to note that the first 3 sources are used in a number of articles.[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Special%3ALinkSearch&amp;target=http%3A%2F%2F*.crossroad.to], [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Special%3ALinkSearch&amp;target=http%3A%2F%2F*.ensignmessage.com], [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Special%3ALinkSearch&amp;target=http%3A%2F%2F*.gci.org](ok to use Grace in its own article of course). [[User:Dougweller|Dougweller]] ([[User talk:Dougweller|talk]]) 14:11, 13 August 2012 (UTC)
:I would just remove said content altogether if you ask me.&amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 14:13, 13 August 2012 (UTC)
::Done --[[User:Steven J. Anderson|Steven J. Anderson]] ([[User talk:Steven J. Anderson|talk]]) 23:53, 1 September 2012 (UTC)

== So who wrote the Torah? ==

This section worries me (headed Form):

''{{also|Form criticism}}''

''Scholarship for more than two centuries have agreed that the [[Torah]], in which the Patriarchal stories are found, was drawn together from different literary sources. However, any particular identification or dating of the textual sources have been strongly debated.{{sfn|Alter|2008|p=x}}''

''It is widely held by modern biblical scholarship that the Patriarchs, including Abraham, are not clearly and unambiguously attested in the [[Hebrew Bible]] earlier than the [[Babylonian exile]]. This has led modern scholars to propose that the entire ''Torah'', which include the stories of Abraham, all originated from literary circles either during the Persian period of the late 6th century BCE, to the 5th century Babylonian rule,{{sfn|Blenkinsopp|2009|p=38-39}} or as late as [[Hellenistic]] times.{{sfn|Alter|2008|p=x}} Under these dominions, the Patriarchal stories are seen as ''hope'' for the Jewish people when Jerusalem, the Temple, and the Davidic kingship were all but destroyed. [[YHWH]]'s dealings with their ancestors provided hope for a future in which an ancestral foundation could be built.&lt;ref name=&quot;Xx9YzJq2B9wC 2003 p.246&quot;&gt;[http://books.google.com.au/books?id=Xx9YzJq2B9wC&amp;dq=Rainer+Albertz,+%22Israel+in+exile%22&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=bn&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=HtlsTK7mFpO8sAPKzYmgCw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CCcQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Albertz, R, &quot;Israel in exile: the history and literature of the sixth century B.C.E.&quot; (Society of Biblical Literature, 2003)] p.246&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, Abraham served as a model for those who would return to [[Judah]].{{sfn|Blenkinsopp|2009|p=38-39}}''

''There are however, modern supporters for an earlier dating. [[Robert Alter]] interjects that the [[Hebrew language]] evolved over nine centuries of biblical literary activity, from the ''First Commonwealth'' (1000 BCE to 586 BCE) to the late Persian/Hellenistic periods.{{sfn|Alter|2008|p=x}} Both Alter and [[Ronald Hendel]] argue that there is very little Hebrew in the Torah that could bare a late dating to the 6th-4th century BCE eras, due to their linguistic differences.{{sfn|Alter|2008|p=xi}}''

Well for a start, this is source criticism, not form criticism. More importantly, it relies rather heavily on Robert Alter's ''Five Books''. Alter is a great scholar, but here he's arguing his personal convictions, not setting out the position of the scholarly community as a whole. Despite what Alter says, there's a growing consensus that sees the five books getting their first version in the late 7th century and reaching final form in the early Persian period. And the argument that the forms of Hebrew are pre-Exilic isn't Alter's, he's just repeating it. Anyway, I'd prefer to see a more generalist book used for mthis - and it can be done in a single sentence, not a whole subsection. [[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 12:17, 14 August 2012 (UTC)

:;Form Criticism part of Source Crticism
:Before you start ranting about &quot;dangerous&quot; and &quot;worrisome&quot; things... you should know what you are talking about first. The first section [[Abraham#Form]] is very much [[Form criticism]]. 

::&quot;Form criticism is a method of biblical criticism that classifies units of scripture by '''literary pattern''' and that attempts to trace each type to its period of '''oral transmission'''. Form criticism '''seeks to determine a unit's original form and the historical context''' of the '''literary tradition'''.&quot;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;

:All of these points are covered within that section. Also note that... 

::&quot;It is used to supplement the [[documentary hypothesis]] explaining the origin of the Pentateuch.&quot;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;

:Which means that Form Criticism is a sub-part of [[Source criticism]] (documentary hypothesis). If you [[User:PiCo]] understood this, you would save yourself from getting all worked up again. Thanks, &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 20:52, 14 August 2012 (UTC)

:&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt; ''Quotes taken from [[Form criticism]] referencing (&quot;form criticism.&quot; Encyclopædia Britannica. 2007. Encyclopædia Britannica Online. 2 Dec. 2007  [http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9125589 read online])''

:;Supporting citations
:If you had verified all of the supporting citations, you would find that the lede sentence is a neutral statement from Alter, Robert (2008). In the 2nd paragraph, Alter only reiterates what Blenkinsopp, Joseph (2009) says about how modern scholars believe the texual sources were rooted from the late 6th-4th century BCE eras. The last paragraph is the only paragraph used to show Alter's alternative view of an earlier dating. Thus the [[wp:weight]] of the article is balanced enough not to push either view too hard. Thanks, &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 21:05, 14 August 2012 (UTC)
::Jason you like to have it both ways, when there is too much stuff in an article about a Bible topic ''you'' don't like, you try demolishing it with arguments about too much &quot;weight&quot; and &quot;undue&quot; etc, BUT when you are left to your own devices and no one opposes you, you insert voluminous reams of material that are primarily from Christian and evangelical POVs. I can back up all these claims with a careful look at your recent editing history. Please stop the charade and stop chopping up and attacking long-standing articles just so you can get your way. You need to learn how to proceed with more CAUTION and build [[WP:CONSENSUS]] CAREFULLY and not come in with guns blazing and then put on the innocent act when you are called on it. By the way, have you considered that this title &quot;So who wrote the Torah?&quot; is outright offensive to many editors and could lead to uncalled for edit warring? Like asking &quot;[[Who wrote the New Testamant?]]&quot; or &quot;[[Who wrote the Koran?]]&quot; would be HIGHLY offensive to many Christianity and Islam editors given ''your'' tone here and the dismissive stance you take citing liberally from latter-day secular (university? pop? pulp? ghost?) writers but ignoring what those ancient religions and their scholars would have to say on those topics and not even caring to hear them out. Kindly note '''Wikipedia is not [[iconoclasm]]''' either!! Or do you miss that as well? Thanks a lot. [[User:IZAK|IZAK]] ([[User talk:IZAK|talk]]) 00:36, 16 August 2012 (UTC)
::#You [[User talk:IZAK]] state: &quot;you ([[User:Jasonasosa]]) insert voluminous reams of material that are primarily from Christian and evangelical POVs. I can back up all these claims with a careful look at your recent editing history.&quot; - So are you saying that the [[Abraham#Scholarly criticism]] section, that I edited, is all Christian POV? 
::#Did you even take a look at the edit history to see who wrote the title, [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:Abraham&amp;diff=507364114&amp;oldid=507265405 So who wrote the Torah?]
::Before you start ranting, why don't you deliver? It's apparent that you don't check your information, which makes me question your abilities to edit as a wikieditor. Thanks, &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 19:27, 16 August 2012 (UTC)
:::PiCo wrote it, and it is demeaning. Minor typo on my part. [[WP:AGF]]. I am not ranting and you are not reading what I have to say. Pity. You just want to have it all your way, and call anyone who disagrees with you as &quot;ranting&quot; or what? [[User:IZAK|IZAK]] ([[User talk:IZAK|talk]]) 19:37, 16 August 2012 (UTC)
::::There is no indication of a typo here, as it is read...
:::::&quot;You ([[User:Jasonasosa]]) need to learn how to proceed with more CAUTION and build [[WP:CONSENSUS]] CAREFULLY and not come in with guns blazing and then put on the innocent act when you are called on it. By the way, have you considered that this title &quot;So who wrote the Torah?&quot;... 
::::So, as you can see... the two thoughts in your brain were put together spilling through your fingers faster than you can keep up with. You just need to slow down and pay attention to what and who you are writing to, backing up your comments with solid evidence, just as I had done in my [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:Abraham&amp;diff=507441439&amp;oldid=507435604 retort to User:PiCo]. Thanks, &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 19:58, 16 August 2012 (UTC)
:::::Jason, you are deliberately ignoring what I am referring to, not just the comments here, but to your recent spate of rash editing all over the place when it comes to [[Hebrew Bible]] topics, such as when you rushed to chop down the [[Genesis 1:1]] article ''after'' it survived a recent [[Wikipedia:Articles for deletion/Genesis 1:1 (2nd nomination)|AfD]] and you were [[User talk:Jasonasosa#Genesis 1:1|called on it and retracted]]; when you were ready to &quot;hack away&quot; (your phrase) as you put it at [[Talk:Noach (parsha)#Scope proposals]] that contributed to the massive downhill slide of a discussion that degenerated into squabbling. While for a while now you have edited these kind of religion topics wherein Judaism/Christianity/Islam intersect and overlap with little opposition, you seem to have now reached a point where you are running into headwinds where you need to slow down your efforts to become the almost sole editor and final voice-over for more and more Bible topics in what can only be described as a form of creeping annexation of these topics to reflect your POV as you merrily &quot;hack away&quot; to carve things up the way you want them to appear. I have long ago ceased that type of editorial style that was more suitable to WP's early days when articles where first appearing and all content was welcome, the more the merrier and there were relatively few alternative views, whereas today there are many layers of content submitted by waves of editors over many years that cannot be simply hacked away and what you are seeing is a reaction to your zealous approach, especially as you veer into more topics that directly interface with core subjects in Judaism that you do not display a strong grasp of. Just slow down and cool it and try to win over allies. [[User:IZAK|IZAK]] ([[User talk:IZAK|talk]]) 21:59, 16 August 2012 (UTC)
::::::[[WP:BOLD]]. Thanks, &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 22:13, 16 August 2012 (UTC)
::::::Analysis of [[User:IZAK]]'s statement, &quot;...and try to win over allies&quot; seems to suggest habitual [[WP:EDITWARRING]]. - &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 22:13, 16 August 2012 (UTC)
:::::::Wrong again. You just don't get the message, no matter which way I send it. You have obviously not heard of [[WP:CONSENSUS]] and taking heed when you are up against [[WP:CONTROVERSIAL]] see it, WP has a list of [[Wikipedia:List of controversial issues]] and RELIGION is one of them. In almost ten years of editing on WP I have not been known to edit war in religion topics, and you have probably never noticed the {{tl|Controversial}} warning template (even when it's implied) and many others like it that warn you to proceed with CAUTION. [[User:IZAK|IZAK]] ([[User talk:IZAK|talk]]) 22:21, 16 August 2012 (UTC)
::::::::Yeah, because you argue about ''Talk page titles'' rather than Main page content within [[wp:scope]]. I can see how you've skirted from getting caught from edit warring as you spend most of your time ranting on talk pages rather than contributing content within [[wp:scope]] to the main page.&amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 22:35, 16 August 2012 (UTC)
{{od}}
Wrong again. You don't know my history. In the early part of my ten years on WP I wrote many articles relating to rabbis and Judaism. Then when the categorization system came in I created the entire framework of categories for the huge [[:Category:Jews and Judaism]], I spend a lot of time improving almost all articles with [[:Category:Jewish history]]. I used to spend more time on Israel-related articles but I don't have the time and there is too much controversy there that I avoid like the plague. The Hebrew Bible-related articles are a TOTAL mess because they try to blend opposing views in a maddening way so that they all suffer from severe multiple [[split personality]] disorders as they cannot make up their minds what to communicate, and many good Judaic editors have lost interest and confidence in them precisely because you have Christian and secular editors telling them what they should think and say and convey about a subject which rightly commenced with Judaism and was then conveyed to Christianity and which latter-day secular scholars have converged upon to tear to shreds. I spend time trying to IMPROVE non-Biblical articles relating to religious Jews and Judaism that could need help. I keep track of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Deletion sorting/Judaism]], and I ''very'' seldom nominate articles for AfDs. There is just so much one person can do, as you well know. [[User:IZAK|IZAK]] ([[User talk:IZAK|talk]]) 23:10, 16 August 2012 (UTC)

===Focusing on latter day Bible critics and secular professors while ignoring what classical Judaism maintains puts the cart way before the horse===  

Why is this not mentioned when it is such an obvious point, accepted by Judaism for 3000+ years: 

#Classical Judaism, meaning [[Rabbinic Judaism]] not just &quot;believes&quot; but accepts it axiomatically that the [[Torah]] was ''written down'' by '''Moses''' (no link to WP article because it's a total shambles) as dictated from God based on ''nevu'ah'' which means &quot;prophecy&quot; -- a divine phenomenon whereby God communicates with select men and women that the secular mind cannot grasp. This is called &quot;Torah from Sinai&quot; or &quot;Torah min hashamayim&quot; and that it came in stages: 
#The [[Decalogue]] when God ''spoke'' the Ten Commandments to the Children of Israel gathered at Mount Sinai; 
#then the [[Ten Commandments]] were given carved on stone by God (first set) and Moses (second set); 
#then during the forty years the Israelites spent in the wilderness the [[Five Books of Moses]] ([[Chumash (Judaism)|Chumash]] or [[Pentateuch]]) was dictated by God and written down by Moses who then handed it to Joshua and the Seventy Elders (forerunners of the Great [[Sanhedrin]]). 
#The rest of the [[Tanakh]] was written by the successive leaders and prophets ending with the [[Men of the Great Assembly]] who then &quot;sealed&quot; and closed the epoch of the [[Written Torah]]. 
#Judaism also holds that the [[Oral Torah]] (Torah shebe'al peh) was transmitted at the same time as the Written Torah. 
#The Oral Torah was written down by later sages and does ''not'' have the same status as the Written Torah but it was reliably transmitted through the [[Mishnah]]; [[Talmud]] and various [[Midrash]]im. 
#Drawing from both the Written Torah and the Oral Torah and based on their great Torah scholarship and piety in Judaism the most competent and greatest Jewish sages (meaning rabbis, not university professors and pop writers) have written further works of Jewish Law ([[Halakha]]), and commentaries. 
#[[Posek|Deciders]] of Jewish Law, have published later works based on the Written and Oral Torah such as [[Maimonides]]' [[Mishneh Torah]] and Rabbi [[Joseph Karo]]'s [[Shulkhan Arukh]] the Code of Jewish Law that is the basis of ''all'' Jewish Law today. 
#Mystical, moral and homiletical commentaries on the Written and Oral Torah based on the [[Midrashim]] are a different but related field of knowledge with their own great works, such as the [[Sefer Yetzira]] and [[Zohar]], and with its scholars specializing in Jewish mysticism and the [[Kabbalah]] such as [[Isaac Luria]], [[Moses ben Jacob Cordovero|Moses Cordovero]] and the early great rabbis of [[Hasidic Judaism]].

This is Judaism 101 yet look how so few even know this much. [[User:IZAK|IZAK]] ([[User talk:IZAK|talk]]) 15:34, 15 August 2012 (UTC)
:The time it took you to prepare these points could be better spent improving the article [[Lech-Lecha]]. A lot of the points you bring up here are not within [[wp:scope]] of this article anyway. Further, Jewish 101 would be [[wp:undo]] weight here. Thanks, &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 16:10, 15 August 2012 (UTC)
::Agreed. I think [[WP:SOAPBOX]] might be relevant to this thread. It is also worth pointing out that [[Rabbinic Judaism]] is itself a rather late arriver on the seen, dating to after the destruction of the Temple, and it is not necessarily proven that its beliefs are necessarily identical to those of earlier Jews. One thing that might be useful is to compare and contrast the content of this article to that of other reference sources. Going to the Highbeam Research site, I found articles on this subject in four reference works, the ''New Catholic Encyclopedia,'' ''Dictionary of the Israeli-Palestinian Conflict,'' ''Encyclopedia Judaica,'' and ''World Religions Reference Library.'' There is also one in the Lindsay Jones ''Encyclopedia of Religion,'' and presumably several others as well. I haven't checked on their lengths, but if anyone wanted copies of them e-mailed to them, just drop me an e-mail and I will forward them the articles I have online access to. Some of the other databanks which are currently offering free subscriptions here may well contain additional articles, as well as other subscription databanks elsewhere. I am on the candidates lists for the other free subscriptions as well, and should know by the end of the month. That being the case, if editors to this article are not themselves given access to those databanks or services, it might make sense to file a request for copies of those reference articles after the first of next month, when I should have access to those other databanks as well. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 19:40, 15 August 2012 (UTC)
:::John, too bad you reject the occasional [[reality check]] from the real world, and it's nice to know you live in your own academic [[ivory tower]] that has nothing to do with the real world where Judaism exists. Are you now an authority on Judaism and its beliefs and origins as well? Wow! You see, this is precisely the ongoing problem, that WP has become a &quot;world unto itself&quot; creating one huge mish-mash that would in its own language violate [[WP:NOR]], [[WP:SYNTH]], [[WP:NPOV]], [[WP:NOTMADEUP]], [[WP:NEO]] and even [[WP:HOAX]] that is often a reflection of some editors acting like [[WP:SPIDERMAN]]. Someone asks who wrote the Bible/Torah, and the correct WP way to answer would be: According to XYX group it is ____; According to ABC group it is ___; According to modern secular scholars it is ____; and instead everyone mixes up all the views, no one knows how anything starts, discredits the religion's own set of axioms, with half-baked, zany and dishonest citations that are sham and discredit the purpose of [[WP:RS]] and [[WP:V]] with personal views from a mish-mash of zeros, and walla, WP has produced a new religion, or definition for a religion, that no one ever heard of or practices. This is disgraceful and does not become an encyclopedia. Think it over. [[User:IZAK|IZAK]] ([[User talk:IZAK|talk]]) 23:33, 15 August 2012 (UTC)
::::If you don't like it, walk away. This is a secular site. Thanks, &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 03:55, 16 August 2012 (UTC)
:::::Wrong! WP is neither secular nor religious, because this is ONLY an '''[[encyclopedia]]''' (look that up) that draws on ALL bodies of knowledge and welcomes editors from all areas of expertise and incorporates all points of view as long as they adhere to WP policies of [[WP:NPOV]] and the [[WP:FIVEPILLARS]] and all other long-standing WP policies. [[User:IZAK|IZAK]] ([[User talk:IZAK|talk]]) 18:13, 16 August 2012 (UTC)
::::::[[WP:SCHOLARSHIP]]. Thanks, &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 19:08, 16 August 2012 (UTC)

Jason, are you claiming that 2000+ years of traditional Jewish scholarship should be disregarded in favor of 200 years of secular scholarship? There are over two millenia of published works, by scholars accepted in their field, and of whom secondary sources certainly exist that compile their collective opinions. I completely agree that modern secular opinion deserves its place here, but not exclusively. In an article which is core to [[Judaism]], I believe it selbstverständlich that the traditional Jewish view, as brought down through, at the very least, 1500 years of commentary, exegesis, gloss, and discussion from the [[Midrash]] to [[Rashi]] and the [[Ramban]] (two name two undeniably notable and seminal figures, who remain accepted as authoritative to this very day) need be discussed. Wikipedia is certainly not a religious project; but it is not anti-religious either. A good encyclopedia will bring both perspectives, as they are both necessary in understanding the topic, its context, its reach, and its effect on people. -- [[User:Avraham|Avi]] ([[User talk:Avraham|talk]]) 19:22, 16 August 2012 (UTC)
:The [[Abraham#Judaism]] section is (+3,322)‎ bytes; The [[Abraham#Scholarly criticism]] is (+5,897)‎ bytes... a difference of 2,575 bytes. My contributions to the Scholarly criticism section totals: 1,251 bytes. There is also a wonderful page called [[Lech-Lecha]] which is roughly (80,949 bytes) with about (+44,120)‎ bytes worth of &quot;2000+ years of traditional Jewish scholarship&quot;, which dwarfs my contribution of a mere 1,251 bytes of scholarly criticism. So, feel free to contribute 2,575 more bytes to the ''Judaism'' section of this article if its really eating away at you.&amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 20:31, 16 August 2012 (UTC)

::Dear Jason, look up the meaning of '''[[primary source]]s''' in [[wikt:real world|real world]] scholarship, as well as of '''[[secondary source]]s'''. Besides, when posing a question such as &quot;So who wrote the Torah?&quot; (sticking in the word &quot;So&quot; by anyone in any case, it is oh, SO demeaning) you then have to face the irrefutable fact that the Torah is the '''[[primary document]]''' of Judaism, and therefore also realize that Judaism has had and has its own field of [[Torah study|Torah scholarship]] and [[Talmid Chacham|Torah scholars]], namely those that are relied upon today, the [[Talmud]]ists (Judaism's teachers of the Torah), [[Rishonim]] (medieval scholars), [[Acharonim]] (latter scholars), and [[meforshim]] or ''parshanim'', see {{tl|Rabbinical Literature}} and {{tl|Eras of the Halakha}} as introductions. If these terms mean nothing to you, you need to brush up on them when taking on questions about Judaism's most important text/s, such as 'So, who wrote the Torah?&quot;. Thanks, [[User:IZAK|IZAK]] ([[User talk:IZAK|talk]]) 19:31, 16 August 2012 (UTC)
:::Dear [[User:IZAK]], your reply to my inquiry was: &quot;PiCo wrote it, and it is demeaning. Minor typo on my part. [[WP:AGF]].&quot; By this statement and you addressing me &quot;Dear Jason&quot; in your above comment bashing me for &quot;So who wrote the Torah?&quot; means that you back peddled and lied to me. From here on out, I having nothing more to say to you.&amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 20:06, 16 August 2012 (UTC)
::::You and PiCo worked under that heading and at ''no point'' disputed it as it's a demeaning heading. [[User:IZAK|IZAK]] ([[User talk:IZAK|talk]]) 22:07, 16 August 2012 (UTC)
:::::Are you serious? You need to chill out. This does not improve the main page at all! &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 22:15, 16 August 2012 (UTC)
::::::Good idea, but it's hard to ignore you when you are zooming around and busy with so many Hebrew Bible topics lately, bringing up a number AfDs, moving material around all over the place, that's just nerve racking. I will look into the article with greater depth to see what can be done, if anything. [[User:IZAK|IZAK]] ([[User talk:IZAK|talk]]) 22:31, 16 August 2012 (UTC)
:::::::Oh, just a little FYI... you might want to get an update on my contributions to [[Genesis 1:1]] from an admin at [[User talk:Jasonasosa#Genesis 1:1]]. Thanks, &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 22:40, 16 August 2012 (UTC)
{{od}}Here we go for Abraham [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Abraham&amp;diff=507753400&amp;oldid=507666015] this makes sense, following the chronological and historical order. First you describe and explain the subject in its own terms, then feel free to supply all the Criticisms in the world. First comes the case then comes the analysis. [[User:IZAK|IZAK]] ([[User talk:IZAK|talk]]) 22:44, 16 August 2012 (UTC)
:P.S. User {{user|StAnselm}} is ''not'' an admin, and yes, you do improve things many times, but by the same token you also are overly quick to make mass changes when more incremental change would work a lot better and not get people so nervous. There are so many ways to improve articles and WP content without getting into massive editorial changes of content. One can create useful [[Wikipedia:Template messages|templates]], navigational [[Wikipedia:Categorization|categories]], basic [[Wikipedia:Cleanup|clean up]] without massive changes in core articles and panic being induced. [[User:IZAK|IZAK]] ([[User talk:IZAK|talk]]) 22:57, 16 August 2012 (UTC)
::{{user|StAnselm}} projects himself with such etiquette, even when he is obliged to relay criticism, that I mistook him for an admin. Maybe we could all learn something from him. Thanks, &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 05:31, 17 August 2012 (UTC)
:::Agreed, but for better or worse God/Nature/Evolution (take your pick) created human beings who all have different faces and different personalities, characters, temperaments, and even different souls/spiritual and psychological make-ups. There are seven '''B'''illion+ humans on Earth today and they are all different to each other. But yes, there are rules of the road and we all need to aspire to them. Mastering [[WP:CIVIL]] is not the same for all people, everyone can improve all the time. [[User:IZAK|IZAK]] ([[User talk:IZAK|talk]]) 22:28, 17 August 2012 (UTC)
::::Unfortunately, the fact that people &quot;can&quot; improve over time does not necessarily mean that they &quot;will&quot;, although we can assume good faith that some people might. It is I think the sincerest hope of all of us that no one has cause to raise concerns regarding such matters in the future. However, if reason for such concerns do continue to be raised, then it is not unreasonable for others to take whatever action they might deem necessary and appropriate. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 19:11, 19 August 2012 (UTC)

== Arguments for a pre-exilic tradition of Abraham ==

May I take the liberty of providing a link to arguments for a pre-exilic Abrahamic tradition:
http://agfosterjr.wordpress.com/2012/08/27/the-case-for-a/  [[Special:Contributions/67.169.241.205|67.169.241.205]] ([[User talk:67.169.241.205|talk]])agf  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|undated]] comment added 03:14, 27 August 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!--Template:Undated--&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Blogs are not RS. [[User:Carl.bunderson|carl bunderson]] [[User talk:Carl.bunderson|(talk)]] [[Special:Contributions/Carl.bunderson|(contributions)]] 03:59, 27 August 2012 (UTC)

== A Case for a Pre-exilic Abraham ==

Tried to edit, got no cursor as before. Tried to add descript, format demolished.  Here's a 'non-blog' (since such names mean all) with addenda, making a brief case for a pre-exilic Abrahamic tradition: https://docs.google.com/document/d/1NsAhw4e7ifBWQeXi4xTUenFAbDBHOKSgdruVmUkK7q0/edit
[[Special:Contributions/67.128.133.10|67.128.133.10]] ([[User talk:67.128.133.10|talk]])agf  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|undated]] comment added 21:11, 27 August 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!--Template:Undated--&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:That's still a self-published source.  We have no idea who it's by, if it's been reviewed, and the paper doesn't even give sources (which means it didn't even get a good grade, I'm sure, not that we cite student's papers).  [[WP:RS|Here are the reliable sourcing guidelines]].  Many editors have repeatedly linked to them for you for a reason.  Please read them.  Here is a summary of the reliable sourcing guidelines:
:*[[WP:RS|Reliable sources typically include]]: articles from magazines or newspapers (particularly scholarly journals), or books by recognized authors (basically, books by respected publishers).  Online versions of these are usually accepted, provided they're held to the same standards.  User generated sources (like Wikipedia) are to be avoided.  Self-published sources should be avoided except for information by and about the subject that is not self-serving (for example, citing a company's website to establish something like year of establishment).
:Please read the [[WP:RS|reliable sourcing guidelines]] anyway, even though I have summarized it. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 21:20, 27 August 2012 (UTC)

== Abraham is a fictional charecter ==

Abraham is a fictional character, however the article reads like there's some sort of proof that he has ever existed (which there is not). This should be corrected or at least acknowledged.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/216.149.187.98|216.149.187.98]] ([[User talk:216.149.187.98|talk]]) 19:11, 7 September 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Seeing how there's also complaints from religious fundamentalists about the article portraying him as fictional, with your complaints I'm fairly convinced that the article is neutral.  If it wasn't for those complaints, I would only point to [[Abraham#historicity|this section of the article]] to demonstrate that you haven't really read what the page says. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 22:24, 7 September 2012 (UTC)

== Spelling ==

This article alternates between &quot;Abraham&quot; and &quot;Abram&quot;. Is there any objection to sticking with one spelling or the other throughout the article? (As the title is &quot;Abraham&quot;, that seems like the logical choice, IMHO.) [[User:Joefromrandb|Joefromrandb]] ([[User talk:Joefromrandb|talk]]) 15:15, 19 September 2012 (UTC)
:If you'll take a close look at the book of Genesis, you'll see that the name of the person concerned changes from &quot;Abram&quot; to &quot;Abraham&quot; at a certain point in the story. I believe this accounts for the discrepancy you note. --[[User:Steven J. Anderson|Steven J. Anderson]] ([[User talk:Steven J. Anderson|talk]]) 20:37, 19 September 2012 (UTC)
:::I'm aware of it. What I meant to say is that with most people who undergo a change of name, the article usually explains it in the lede, while generally sticking to the name by whom the person was best known throughout the article. As Abraham is known mononomously, this seems even more important. [[User:Joefromrandb|Joefromrandb]] ([[User talk:Joefromrandb|talk]]) 22:08, 19 September 2012 (UTC)
:::: It is not to complex to follow and it is considered pivotal. Though I believe most modern sources use Abraham throughout the entire narrative up until the name change when a reminder is made. Religious studies would prefer otherwise, but for the general masses, we should keep it simple. [[User:ChrisGualtieri|ChrisGualtieri]] ([[User talk:ChrisGualtieri|talk]]) 15:17, 30 September 2012 (UTC)
:::::I agree, and &quot;using Abraham throughout the entire narrative until the name change when a reminder is made&quot; seems to be the ideal way to do that. [[User:Joefromrandb|Joefromrandb]] ([[User talk:Joefromrandb|talk]]) 12:13, 13 October 2012 (UTC)

== Urfa ==

Is there any common opinion about Abraham's birth place? Turk's believe that he was born in [[Urfa]] (Edessa).--[[User:Ollios|Ollios]] ([[User talk:Ollios|talk]]) 12:09, 27 October 2012 (UTC)

:You may find the article [[Ur Kaśdim]] interesting. In short: there is no consensus about what place Abraham was born, there have historically been various views and scholars are still divided in their opinions. The most common view among modern scholars is that Ur Kaśdim is [[Ur]], an ancient Sumerian city located in modern-day Iraq. ([http://books.google.com/books?id=3hQ6b5Fv0NsC&amp;pg=PA20 source]). - [[User:Lindert|Lindert]] ([[User talk:Lindert|talk]]) 13:05, 27 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>e3wxf5i5fdijc4rb43lgyqhtevhag46</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
