<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Jainism</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>239616</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522232347</id>
      <parentid>522224012</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T20:45:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Narssarssuaq</username>
        <id>1726257</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Deletion of unrefrenced and unsourced section. */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7459">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Jainism|class=B|importance=top}}
{{WPReligion|class=B|importance=top}}
{{philosophy|importance=High|class=B|religion=yes|eastern=yes|ethics=yes}}
{{WP1.0|class=B|category=category|VA=yes}}
{{WikiProject Timeline Tracer}}
{{WP India|class=B|importance=top}}
}}
{{Archives |bot=MiszaBot I |age=90 }}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 2
|minthreadsleft = 5
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Jainism/Archive %(counter)d
}}

== Few Correction Required ==

One is Bahubali is not a Arihant. He is able overcome all 8 karmas. That I think need to be updated.
Another issue is: Terapanth are worship Idols they are not against it. So I think this point should also be corrected.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/122.167.96.34|122.167.96.34]] ([[User talk:122.167.96.34|talk]]) 15:53, 28 September 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;


Also the mark: &quot;According to Jainism, there are sixteen heavens in total.[39]&quot; and its statement is wrong. There are seven heavens and not sixteen. Total fourteen levels, seven heavens and seven hells.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/122.169.101.246|122.169.101.246]] ([[User talk:122.169.101.246|talk]]) 10:48, 11 October 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

It is a debatable but jain cosmology shows, 16 Devlok ( Heavens)+ 5 Anudins + 9 Graiveyaks + 5 Anuttar = All considered as upper world ( urdhva lok). And 7 Hells (Narak) as a lower world. &lt;ref&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jain_cosmology&lt;/ref&gt;
--[[User:Nizil Shah|Nizil]] ([[User talk:Nizil Shah|talk]]) 23:19, 4 October 2012 (UTC)

== References ==

{{reflist}}

== Prose tag ==

The prose tag I added to the &quot;Core beliefs&quot; section was removed. I did not add the tag to detract from the article. I added the tag so that someone would ''improve'' the article. According to [[WP:PROSE]], &quot;Prose is preferred in articles as prose allows the presentation of detail and clarification of context, in a way that a simple list may not. Prose flows, like one person speaking to another, and is best suited to articles, because their purpose is to explain.&quot; There are some exceptions, but I don't see how this falls into any of them. 

I've seen how a bullet list like can be improved by turning it into prose—even after initial reluctance from editors to undertake the project. Also, if this article were nominated as a [[Wikipedia:Good articles|Good Article]] or [[Wikipedia:Featured articles|Featured Article]], it would not pass. For example, it would fail Featured Article [[Wikipedia:Featured article criteria|Criterion 1a]]. 

Why should this list not be turned into prose IAW Wikipedia's Manual of Style and the criterions we expect of our best work here? --[[User:Airborne84|Airborne84]] ([[User talk:Airborne84|talk]]) 15:52, 6 October 2012 (UTC)
:Since there has been no response for nearly a week, I will reinstate the tag, inviting an interested editor to transform the list into prose. --[[User:Airborne84|Airborne84]] ([[User talk:Airborne84|talk]]) 15:49, 12 October 2012 (UTC)

Hi Airborne84, I just came online after a gap, and noticed that the tag has been reinstated. You have pointed out that there are exceptions to the prose rule - and rightly should be.  I trust that this section is better presented in point form so as to highight the important bits of information to the reader with clarity.

[[User:Suresh Elangovan|Suresh Elangovan]] ([[User talk:Suresh Elangovan|talk]]) 09:47, 19 October 2012 (UTC)
::I looked at the listed exceptions in [[WP:PROSE]] before I posted the above and this section didn't seem to fall under any of them. I considered reworking the section into prose, but haven't had the time. Why don't we try this: I should be able to work on it in the next week or two. I'll rework the bullets into prose and we can discuss then. There's a lot of good material in this article and it could easily become a Good Article or Featured Article, but future edits need to align the existing material in the article with the GA and FA criterions. I hope this proposal is reasonable. Thanks. --[[User:Airborne84|Airborne84]] ([[User talk:Airborne84|talk]]) 17:46, 21 October 2012 (UTC)

Thanks for your efforts.  Your proposal is more than reasonable. I will be happy to contribute from my end, once the first draft is available. 
[[User:Suresh Elangovan|Suresh Elangovan]] ([[User talk:Suresh Elangovan|talk]]) 08:25, 22 October 2012 (UTC)
:First draft complete. I hope you find it acceptable and a general improvement. I'm sure you can improve it further since I am not an expert in Jainism—just an interested observer. Best, --[[User:Airborne84|Airborne84]] ([[User talk:Airborne84|talk]]) 18:06, 3 November 2012 (UTC)

== Jainism is not pantheistic ==

Jainism is not a pantheistic religion. I am changing it to '[[Transtheism|transtheistic]]' which better suits it. [[User:Rahuljain2307|Rahuljain2307]] ([[User talk:Rahuljain2307|talk]]) 09:10, 3 November 2012 (UTC)

== Article improvement ==

There are some areas that will need to be addressed in this article to improve it in the future. 

:1. It's too long at over 100,000 bytes. That creates problems for mobile users and those with slower connections. Consider breaking more lengthy sections into main article and summarizing them here according to [[WP:SUMMARY]]. Consider also summarizing the current sections to be more concise. [[Wikipedia:Article size|This page]] gives guidelines.
:2. Its lede does not adequately summarize the article. See [[WP:Lede]] for details. 
:3. It uses lists where prose ([[WP:PROSE]]) may be more appropriate. The section on meditation is an example. 
:4. The sources are inconsistent. In some cases, only URLs are provided. Complete sources should be used. 
:5. It is not adequately sourced. Some sections with main articles are unsourced or have one or two sources. The sources from the main article should be used here as well so readers can reference them. There are also many lengthy sections with none or very few citations. Rather than placing &quot;ref improve section&quot; in many of these sections, I'll place that tag on the article. I encourage the editors here who have put a lot of work in the article to not see that as a detractor. It is intended to improve the article by inviting interested editors to provide the references which are necessary for a reader to take an article seriously and not question its reliability throughout. --[[User:Airborne84|Airborne84]] ([[User talk:Airborne84|talk]]) 13:55, 7 November 2012 (UTC)

== Deletion of unrefrenced and unsourced section. ==

The sections which contains next to no sources or references should not be there in the article. I am deleting those sections. I request the editors to provide adequate reliable resources if they wish to undo it.
[[User:Rahuljain2307|Rahuljain2307]] ([[User talk:Rahuljain2307|talk]]) 19:43, 9 November 2012 (UTC)

:Apparently, you removed 35,000 bytes from the original article. Perhaps we could paste the deleted text in here and see if anything can be done with it? [[User:Narssarssuaq|Narssarssuaq]] ([[User talk:Narssarssuaq|talk]]) 20:45, 9 November 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>4bcf7q8z6lllx36fq7c75ib7h6q4j1k</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
