<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Articles of Faith</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>285961</id>
    <revision>
      <id>429130450</id>
      <parentid>366992514</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-05-14T20:05:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>William M. Connolley</username>
        <id>8072</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Caps? */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3824">{{ChristianityWikiProject|class=start|importance=low|latter-day-saint-movement=yes|latter-day-saint-movement-importance=low}}

== Copyright ==
Is including the full text a copyright violation, or is ''The Pearl of Great Price'' in the public domain? [[User:Wesley|Wesley]]
:I believe it is safe to assume that the ''Articles of Faith'', which is merely an excerpt from a letter that Joseph Smith wrote in his later life, is in the public domain. [[User:BoNoMoJo|B]] 20:13, 1 Aug 2003 (UTC)

Are the words &quot;(the New Jerusalem)&quot; original to the Wentworth letter, or are they a recent addition?  They weren't in the version I learned in 1976.  [[User:Hawstom|Tom Haws]] 16:34, Jun 1, 2005 (UTC)

== Move source material ==
Shouldn't the LDS Articles of Faith be copied to Wikisource and referred to from an article on that specific subject?  — [[User:Mkmcconn|Mark]] &lt;small&gt;([[User_Talk:Mkmcconn|Mkmcconn]])&lt;/small&gt; [[Special:Contributions/Mkmcconn|**]] 00:34, 25 August 2005 (UTC)

:I've made the new article you suggested, but I think the articles are short enough that they can be quoted. [[User:COGDEN|''CO&lt;small&gt;GDEN&lt;/small&gt;'']] 23:21, 21 September 2005 (UTC)

The term &quot;Protestant&quot; is not derived from Martin Luther protesting against the Roman Catholic Church.  The &quot;Pro&quot; means positive as pro and con.  Protestari – to confess profess – confess your faith.

Under &quot;zoroastrianism&quot; there is a link to &quot;articles of faith&quot; but then there is no back-reference. From that page comes the following:
Basic beliefs 
There is one universal and transcendental God, Ahura Mazda, the one uncreated creator and to whom all worship is ultimately directed. 
Ahura Mazda's creation — evident as asha, truth and order — is the antithesis of chaos, evident as druj, falsehood and disorder. The resulting conflict involves the entire universe, including humanity, which has an active role to play in the conflict. 
Active participation in life through good thoughts, good words and good deeds is necessary to ensure happiness and to keep the chaos at bay. This active participation is a central element in Zoroaster's concept of free will, and Zoroastrianism rejects all forms of monasticism. 
Ahura Mazda will ultimately prevail, at which point the universe will undergo a cosmic renovation and time will end (cf: Zoroastrian eschatology). In the final renovation, all of creation — even the souls of the dead that were initially banished to &quot;darkness&quot; — will be reunited in Ahura Mazda. 
In Zoroastrian tradition, the malevolent is represented by Angra Mainyu, the &quot;Destructive Principle&quot;, while the benevolent is represented through Ahura Mazda's Spenta Mainyu, the instrument or &quot;Bounteous Principle&quot; of the act of creation. It is through Spenta Mainyu that Ahura Mazda is immanent in humankind, and through which the Creator interacts with the world. According to Zoroastrian cosmology, in articulating the Ahuna Vairya formula, Ahura Mazda made His ultimate triumph evident to Angra Mainyu. 
As expressions and aspects of Creation, Ahura Mazda emanated seven &quot;sparks&quot;, the Amesha Spentas, &quot;Bounteous Immortals&quot; that are each the hypostasis and representative of one aspect of that Creation. These Amesha Spenta are in turn assisted by a league of lesser principles, the Yazatas, each &quot;Worthy of Worship&quot; and each again a hypostasis of a moral or physical aspect of creation.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/75.162.137.242|75.162.137.242]] ([[User talk:75.162.137.242|talk]]) 08:49, 1 March 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Caps? ==

Why is this &quot;Articles of Faith&quot; not &quot;articles of faith&quot;? [[User:William M. Connolley|William M. Connolley]] ([[User talk:William M. Connolley|talk]]) 20:05, 14 May 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>4z5283pqvmske0z68ihbp3gk2r694cf</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
