<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:College of Cardinals</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>441514</id>
    <revision>
      <id>462560960</id>
      <parentid>444334664</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-11-26T12:30:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dcheney</username>
        <id>419922</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Premature Updates (turning 80) */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8776">{{talkheader}}
{{WikiProject Christianity|class=B|importance=|catholicism=yes|catholicism-importance=Top}}

==Wikipedia's [[list of notable cardinals]] does exist==

Why is someone putting this extensive list of links to articles about cardinals without adding them to the [[list of notable cardinals]]?  &quot;Notable&quot; in this context seems to be construed as meaning &quot;the subject of a Wikipedia article&quot;.  I've found within the last few minutes that some of the cardinals listed here who do have Wikipedia articles about them are not on that list. [[User:Michael Hardy|Michael Hardy]] 20:21, 11 Jan 2005 (UTC)

== Cardinal in pectore ==

pope died, but
In 2003 the Pope announced he was also creating one cardinal secretly (in pectore), which would have taken effect if the appointment had been announced before the Pope's death. This prelate is believed to reside in the People's Republic of China.The Pope turned 80 yester day.
who is him? --????Pope Benidict the 16th. 
:The point of &quot;in pectore&quot; is that it's secret. No one apart from the pope who named him and himself knows who it was. Cardinal in pectore means cardinal in the pope's heart, don't enjoy the privileges etc. of a normal cardinal. The only thing is if a cardinal in pectore were later to become a full cardinal, his seniority (time as a cardinal) would start counting from when he was named as a cardinal in pectore. On a related note, the rumour about being in China's was I think referring to the Archbishop of Hong Kong. -- [[User:KTC|KTC]] 21:35, Apr 3 2005 (UTC)

==What has happened?==

Is it just me - or has this page changed dramatically.  It used to list the currently alive cardinals - now it seems to list the whole lot created since the time of Paul VI.  Personally I preferred the currently alive cardinals, those being over 80 and therefore non-voting in a conclave duly asterisked.  If there is need to mention other cardinals they should be in articles about the individual or about the diocese or dicastery  or curial office to which they belong. It is my hope that someone will tidy this up and revert it to the alive cardinals again. My belief is that the College of Cardinals is a living organ of the Church and should only contain the living members of the College. [[User:Kiddo54|Kiddo54]] 04:19, 28 January 2007 (UTC)


The idea of the College being a &quot;living organ&quot; of the Church is more in the realm of devoitional theology than an encyclopedia article. However, I agree with Kiddo on different grounds: it is defensible to either list only current cardinals (as this is a reference 'book&quot;) or ALL cardinals in history for the sake of completeness (this is impossible, as it wopuld require vast amounts of space for little benefit, and one can link to other sites that do have this information, or something close to it). Listing all cardinals appointed in -- what? the lifetime of a particular contributor? -- doesn't make any logical sense. Let's reduce this to the current members, with an asterisk for non-voters, as suggested.[[User:HarvardOxon|HarvardOxon]] 04:36, 28 January 2007 (UTC)

If there is a desire to maintain a more complete list of Cardinals in history one might adopt the rough structure used in this article but have separate articles for each pope. In other words, &quot;Cardinals Created by Pope John Paul II&quot;, &quot;Cardinals Created by Pope Leo XIII&quot;, etc. And those articles could then split the list by the various consistories held by that pope and would include links to both living and deceased. (And no, I'm not volunteering for this project - there are already several websites that provide the information in a useable format.)--[[User:Dcheney|Dcheney]] 00:14, 20 September 2007 (UTC)

====Cardinal Bishops====
The current Cardinal Priests and Cardinal Deacons are listed under the Pope who appointed them a cardinal. Why was this removed from the Cardinal Bishops section (I'm assuming it was for page length reasons). [[User:GoodDay|GoodDay]] 16:02, 18 October 2007 (UTC)

== The New Pope Turned 80 Years of Age on April 16,2008 ==

Pope Benidict the 16th turn 80 years old in his pillgrimage to the United States.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/66.219.158.123|66.219.158.123]] ([[User talk:66.219.158.123|talk]]) 00:54, 18 April 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Proposed split ==

I propose that the list of current cardinals be split into a list article so free up space for the history, function, traditions, and significance of the College. Something like [[List of current Roman Catholic cardinals]]. Discuss. [[User:Savidan|Savidan]] 00:01, 5 June 2008 (UTC)

==Latin title==
The page currently states &quot;(formal: Sacred College of the Holy Roman Church, ''Sancta Romana Ecclesia, S.R.E.'')&quot; but ''S.R.E.'' is simply the abbreviation for the ''Sancta Romana Ecclesia'', which is the Latin title for the Roman Catholic church, not the College of Cardinals. Is the article trying to note that Cardinals append S.R.E. after their names in Europe? -[[Special:Contributions/114.91.67.127|114.91.67.127]] ([[User talk:114.91.67.127|talk]]) 13:59, 19 April 2009 (UTC)
:Checking the Vatican City's official website, I couldn't find the &quot;formal&quot; title here given anywhere. The formal title appears to be ''sacrum cardinalium collegium'' (Sacred College of Cardinals), with the informal simply omitting the &quot;sacred.&quot; If anyone restores the &quot;Sacred College of the Holy Roman Church,&quot; please give a source. -[[Special:Contributions/114.91.67.127|114.91.67.127]] ([[User talk:114.91.67.127|talk]]) 14:20, 19 April 2009 (UTC)
:This anonymous editor did right in pointing to and correcting this mistake. It is true that, since cardinals are regularly described as &quot;Cardinals of Holy Roman Church&quot;, you will sometimes meet, as in [http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/speeches/1993/april/documents/hf_jp-ii_spe_19930405_concistoro_lt.html this 1993 speech] by Pope John Paul II, the phrase &quot;Collegium Cardinalium Sanctae Romanae Ecclesiae&quot;, but it is not a constantly used phrase.
:In addition, &quot;''Sacred'' College of Cardinals&quot; is no longer used.  The adjective seems to have been dropped at the same time as it was for the Congregations of the Roman Curia, which until then were referred to as Sacred Congregations, but which appear for the first time simply as Congregations in the 1985 Annuario Pontificio. By force of habit and because no decree was issued about the matter, they continued for some time after 1985 to be referred to sometimes with the adjective &quot;Sacred&quot;, which has by now disappeared completely. The latest document that adds the adjective &quot;Sacred&quot; to the name of the College of Cardinals is the 25 September 1988 [http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/apost_letters/1988/documents/hf_jp-ii_apl_19880925_evangelicae-caritatis_lt.html Decree of Beatification of Joseph Benedict Dusmet.] And a 1989 [http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/speeches/1989/june/documents/hf_jp-ii_spe_19890623_assemblea-africa_it.html speech] by [[Pope John Paul II]] ''quotes'' a 1973 speech that used the adjective. [[User:Soidi|Soidi]] ([[User talk:Soidi|talk]]) 17:51, 19 April 2009 (UTC)

== 2010 consistory ==

I believe there were 24 bishops elevated to cardinal. [[User:GoodDay|GoodDay]] ([[User talk:GoodDay|talk]]) 01:22, 21 November 2010 (UTC)
: No, that's wrong! As of 20th of October, 22 of them were bishops, two only priests. Walter Brandmüller was consecrated bishop on 13th of November (Titular Archbishop of Cesarea in Mauretania), so that in fact 23 bishops and one priest (Domenico Bartolucci) have been elevated to cardinals. --[[User:Heraklitcnl|Heraklitcnl]] ([[User talk:Heraklitcnl|talk]]) 22:25, 22 November 2010 (UTC)

== 195 cardinals? ==

What is our basis for saying there are 195 Cardinals at the moment? When I count the list, it comes up short. [[Special:Contributions/82.24.248.137|82.24.248.137]] ([[User talk:82.24.248.137|talk]]) 20:40, 11 August 2011 (UTC)
: So you've to recount the list. In fact there are 195 persons listed here (as of today ;-)) --[[User:Heraklitcnl|Heraklitcnl]] ([[User talk:Heraklitcnl|talk]]) 21:10, 11 August 2011 (UTC)
:I also come up with exactly 195 Cardinals.--[[User:Dcheney|Dcheney]] ([[User talk:Dcheney|talk]]) 21:20, 11 August 2011 (UTC)

== Premature Updates (turning 80) ==

Please note that cardinals do not lose the right to vote in a conclave (under current law) until the end of the day that they turn 80. So if a cardinal turns 80 on 26 November, they don't lose their vote until that day is complete (aka, 27 November). (Source: ''Universi Dominici Gregis'', 33).--[[User:Dcheney|Dcheney]] ([[User talk:Dcheney|talk]]) 12:30, 26 November 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>1o7co6ovpcy27x72y9vqsxar2ajssdy</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
