<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Gog and Magog</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>310060</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520081291</id>
      <parentid>496936769</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-27T07:25:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>94.168.67.169</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Russia &amp; Indo-Europeans?? */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="75730">{{talk header}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Bible|class=Start|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Islam|class=B|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Religious texts|class=|attention=yes|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Middle Ages|class=start}}
{{WikiProject Dacia|class=|importance=}}
}}
{{archive box|[[Talk:Gog and Magog/Archive 1|Archive #1]]}}

__TOC__

== wikipedia is neutral concerning religious material ==

Why is Mohamed being honored by stating(peace be with him) in the islamic explanation? This isn´t a religious website, it´s a neutral site. 
I believe this should be altered.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Toothfairy72|Toothfairy72]] ([[User talk:Toothfairy72|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Toothfairy72|contribs]]) 11:30, 21 January 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:added by an IP this morning. Removed. &lt;small&gt;[[User:Redvers/SN|⇦]]'''[[User talk:Redvers|REDVERS]]'''[[User:Redvers/SN|⇨]]&lt;/small&gt; 11:32, 21 January 2010 (UTC)

== evidencefortorah.com ==

In no way does this source meet our criteria at [[evidencefortorah.com]]. If any of this material is to be added it should be reliably sourced and with consensus. [[User:Dougweller|Dougweller]] ([[User talk:Dougweller|talk]]) 12:23, 5 May 2010 (UTC)

Why is http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/source/khazars1.html not a good source?   Its a legitimate university, and brings down an exact quote of the letter, where Khazarian king gives his genealogy.  If the www.evidenceForTorah.comxa.com is bothering you, fine, I can remove it. The reason I've added this source, was because they are the ones that brought this issue up.  King Joseph gives his genealogy, which contradicts the view that Khazars are Magogites. To not add this fact to the article, i think is an intellectual crime.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/67.253.158.55|67.253.158.55]] ([[User talk:67.253.158.55|talk]]) 14:28, 6 May 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Fordham.edu is a fine source, but that text is a [[WP:PRIMARY|primary source]], and editors can't insert their own interpretations of primary sources into articles. That's what your edit was doing.--[[User:Cuchullain|Cúchullain]] [[User talk:Cuchullain|&lt;sup&gt;t&lt;/sup&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/Cuchullain|&lt;small&gt;c&lt;/small&gt;]] 15:07, 6 May 2010 (UTC)

OK, so what if i just write this. &quot;However, according to the Khazar correspondence (Forham.edu), 'Know this, we are...'&quot;   I completely leave out any opinion, and just use the quote.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/67.253.158.55|67.253.158.55]] ([[User talk:67.253.158.55|talk]]) 11:16, 7 May 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:No, because it's not relevant. The Khazar source doesn't mention Gog and Magog at all, so it doesn't belong on this article.--[[User:Cuchullain|Cúchullain]] [[User talk:Cuchullain|&lt;sup&gt;t&lt;/sup&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/Cuchullain|&lt;small&gt;c&lt;/small&gt;]] 12:35, 7 May 2010 (UTC)

Why do you feel its not relevant? The Khazar source mentions its ancestor as, &quot;Togarmah&quot;. According to the bible, Togarmah was the nephew of Magog.  Is that not relevant?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/67.253.158.55|67.253.158.55]] ([[User talk:67.253.158.55|talk]]) 17:25, 7 May 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

: I don't get your point.  There is already a section of the article explaining what the traditional Jewish interpretation of Gog and Magog is, and anyone can see that it isn't Khazars.  I don't see any justification for putting in an argument against other interpretations.  Almost all the sources arguing for one interpretation include reasons against other interpretations; should we include them all?  It is better to just list the interpretations that have been made.  Actually there is a very important one missing: the theory that Gog and Magog were entirely mythological.  [[User:Zero0000|Zero]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Zero0000|talk]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 03:22, 8 May 2010 (UTC)

My point is not to include the Jewish view.  My point is to include the Khazar's own point of view.  Since, we are talking about Khazar's, shouldnt we include their point of view (on this issue)?  If their view is documented somewhere, why not include it?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/67.253.158.55|67.253.158.55]] ([[User talk:67.253.158.55|talk]]) 01:32, 9 May 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Standing on the shoulders of giants==
I have removed the paragraph relating &quot;[[Standing on the shoulders of giants]]&quot; on the UK £2 Coin with Gog and Magog and the City of London. It is not referenced and is directly contradicted by the [[Royal Mint]][http://www.royalmint.com/Corporate/facts/coins/TwoPoundCoin.aspx]. [[User:Alansplodge|Alansplodge]] ([[User talk:Alansplodge|talk]]) 16:30, 1 October 2010 (UTC)

== New edits by [[User:Koakhtzvigad]] and the need for consensus ==

[[User:Koakhtzvigad]] has indicated, through edit summaries and notes on my own talkpage, that he scorns the consensus process; he feels there is no need for consensus because he feels this is a topic &quot;belonging&quot; to Jews and therefore only the Jewish Bible (complete with &quot;Hashem&quot;) shall be used on wikipedia.  He also denies edit warring, despite his having reinstated this version four times today.
Even more alarmingly, the significant fact that the phrase &quot;Gog and Magog&quot; (the subjects of this article) appears for the first time anywhere in the New Testament, has been repeatedly removed by this user, who is new to the article. 
I am all out of 3RR reverts now, but I have warned him, and I also appeal for anyone who is paying attention to rollback these unwarranted and undiscussed unilateral changes. [[User:Til Eulenspiegel|Til Eulenspiegel]] ([[User talk:Til Eulenspiegel|talk]]) 16:01, 13 March 2011 (UTC)

(moving discussion - Gog and Magog what consensus?)

What possible consensus are you talking about? Are you telling me that the modern Christian NIV translation from KJV into English is better than two Jewish sources with a dozen rabbis signing in them? Next you will be telling the Chinese how to read the I Ching? [[WP:Bold]] is one thing, but this is not it. Do you even know where NIV comes from? Its a commercial cite that sells bibles! Should not even be used in Wikipedia. And how many clicks does one need to find out the translators? Try here http://www.niv-cbt.org/translators/ Half the people are ''New Testament'' specialists, with a couple of Greek language specialists. I see four people with PhD from the Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning, which seems to be &quot;the&quot; prerequisite for teaching Hebrew in Christian education institutions. And this despite saying &quot;The NIV is founded on the belief that if hearing God’s Word the way it was written and understanding it the way it was meant were the hallmarks of the original reading experience, then accuracy in translation demands that neither one of these two criteria be prioritized above the other.&quot; But it is better in the original, right? Compare that with studying Hebrew from 7, Mishnaic Hebrew and Aramaic from 10, full time, for life. [[User:Koakhtzvigad|Koakhtzvigad]] ([[User talk:Koakhtzvigad|talk]]) 15:34, 13 March 2011 (UTC)

:Stop this. I am not edit-warring, but editing. All you had there is the wrong translation, and unreferenced. There is no call for consensus where consensus is explicit in the sources provided. I don't need to seek consensus on the translation of the Hebrew Bible by Jews....its their Bible! If you want to say that the Christians translate the Hebrew Bible differently, you are welcome to it. However, if you persist to remove my edits and their accompanying references, you will be reported [[User:Koakhtzvigad|Koakhtzvigad]] ([[User talk:Koakhtzvigad|talk]]) 15:40, 13 March 2011 (UTC)

::You do know what the word &quot;consensus&quot; means, right? It's how we operate on wikipedia. You don't make UNILATERAL changes against policy, like determine which Bible translation is &quot;acceptable&quot;, without consuting other editors. There is no such policy saying your favorite translation only shall be used because it is the best or whatever. As for &quot;Gog and Magog&quot;, the article should point out clearly the fact that the exact phrase &quot;Gog and Magog&quot; originally occurs in the Christian New Testament book of Revelations for the first time anywhere -- but your edit has the effect of obscuring this point. Revelation should certainly be listed prominently along with all the other books where these names are mentioned, and attempting to censor it on whatever pretext isn't going to get very far. [[User:Til Eulenspiegel|Til Eulenspiegel]] ([[User talk:Til Eulenspiegel#top|talk]]) 15:41, 13 March 2011 (UTC)

:::Firstly don't give me the 3RR. You completely failed to see I was &lt;u&gt;editing&lt;/u&gt;. Did you see the now words with new references? Thats editing, not reverting, which is what you did.
:::[[WP:CONSENSUS]] - ''Consensus is a decision that takes account of all the legitimate concerns raised.'' So, what is your legitimate concern, that Jews don't know how to read the Hebrew Bible? Or is it your insistence of the ''one'' mention of Gog and Magog in Revelations be displayed more prominently then the three sources in the above-mentioned Hebrew Bible from which it is derived? If this is not [[WP:POV]], I don't know what is. 
:::My editing was not &quot;unilateral&quot;, I usually edit alone! I didn't see you editing there, and in fact you hadn't edited since '''03:26, 23 January 2011''', so what is your problem? How far back should I go, and how many editors should I consult before I press EDIT?
:::Censor what? I merely repositioned the reference to Revelations in its chronological order, that is after the Hebrew Bible. What is the problem with that? It originates from Ezekiel, so why would you &quot;put the horse before the cart&quot;? [[User:Koakhtzvigad|Koakhtzvigad]] ([[User talk:Koakhtzvigad|talk]]) 16:10, 13 March 2011 (UTC)

::::Do you have a habit of just making up your own policy as you go along?  Once again, THERE IS NO SUCH POLICY that says because your POV is that this is an exclusively Jewish topic, we have to use a &quot;Jewish&quot; translation.  You are making this stuff up. Now if you do it once, it could be overlooked, but hitting the revert button FOUR TIMES is called &quot;edit warring&quot; on wikipedia, regardless of what you may call it.  The article formerly mentioned that the phrase &quot;Gog and Magog&quot; (as a pair) was first originated in the Christian New Testament.  Now it doesn't mention that any more.  Don't you think that ought to be made clear?  Please answer on the discussion page, since discussing the topic here isn't fair to editors on that page. [[User:Til Eulenspiegel|Til Eulenspiegel]] ([[User talk:Til Eulenspiegel#top|talk]]) 16:17, 13 March 2011 (UTC)

:::::Are you serious? Did you even read ANY sources on the subject? Even Wikipedia says that the [[Book of Revelations]] is derived from Tanakh, so how can you possibly claim it originated with New Testament? So the answer is no, I don't think we ought to mention in Wikipedia something that is untrue and would constitute [[WP:OR]].
:::::The policy is to edit using reliable references. I have. Before then there were no reliable, or even unreliable references. The only thing that was there was a link to the verse on a Christian Bible selling site.
:::::Also, do '''not''' misrepresent what I said. I did '''not'' a)feel this is a topic &quot;belonging&quot; to Jews and b)therefore only the Jewish Bible (complete with &quot;Hashem&quot;) should be used. What I said is that these sources, that are Jewish, seem to be reliable so far as translation goes. As for using ''Hashem'', its a direct &quot;quote&quot;! However, I see nothing wrong with using the Jewish edition of a Jewish Bible as a source, do you? [[User:Koakhtzvigad|Koakhtzvigad]] ([[User talk:Koakhtzvigad|talk]]) 16:46, 13 March 2011 (UTC)

::::::No, I don't see anything wrong with using a Jewish translation provided there is discussion and consensus among editors to do so.  I do see a problem when one editor keeps ram-rodding it in there, and is so convinced of his own correctness in doing so, that he scorns the need for consensus, denies he is edit warring, and abusively tells me to &quot;get a grip&quot; for not seeing things his way. [[User:Til Eulenspiegel|Til Eulenspiegel]] ([[User talk:Til Eulenspiegel|talk]]) 16:51, 13 March 2011 (UTC)

::::::And regardless of your personal theories about the origin of Revelation being in the Tanakh, the well-known fact remains that the phrase &quot;Gog and Magog&quot; never appeared in print until the New Testament.   Don't beat your head into a brick wall.  [[User:Til Eulenspiegel|Til Eulenspiegel]] ([[User talk:Til Eulenspiegel|talk]]) 16:54, 13 March 2011 (UTC)

:::::::If you don't see a problem with my sources, what are you seeking consensus on?
:::::::I don't have personal theories about the origins of the [[Book of Revelations]]. Those are referenced in the article on it. :::::::The first ''print'' appeared in the 16th century :) &quot;Gog and Magog&quot; are used by ''John'' as a reference to a well known set of verses in Hebrew. Hence no need to translate word for word (unless, see below). 
:::::::What is the significance of them being &quot;together&quot;? Can you add a source that highlights this significance and say why it is significant? 
:::::::The fact that it is the first time it appears as such is mute since it is the ''only'' time it appears as such, and in Greek. Remember, most Jews at the time were either bi, or tri-lingual, and learned texts by heart since scrolls were expensive and highly perishable. Greek texts written on papiraii even more so. If ''John's'' mother tongue was Aramaic, he may have had less command of Greek, so translation word for word would have been tasking. On the other hand if he was a Hellinized Jew, he may have only head a general knowledge of the verse, or had seen it in the Greek translation, and so could not have had it translated from Hebrew even if he had the manuscript. 
:::::::In general only scholars (rabbis) were fully conversant with Biblical Hebrew (hence Mishnaic variety). However, this is speculation on my part that I remembered seeing somewhere. If you think this should be included, I'm sure sources can be found since there is no shortage of publications on this subject [[User:KoakhtzvigadMobile|KoakhtzvigadMobile]] ([[User talk:KoakhtzvigadMobile|talk]]) 06:11, 14 March 2011 (UTC)

== Continued edit-warring by [[User:Koakhtzvigad]] ==

Once again, [[User:Koakhtzvigad]] is opting for unilateral edit-warring his POV in lieu of discussion with other editors on this article. I implore you to be patient and wait for consensus in accordance with policy, rather than take this approach of reverting everything you don't like.  The name of the article is &quot;Gog and Magog&quot;.  It is of the utmost significance to most scholarly sources that this exact phrase &quot;Gog and Magog&quot; first occurs in the New Testament, but '''not in the Old Testament, where one is a prince and the other is a land'''.  Indeed, this fact was sourced in an entire book written on the subject (the one by Sverre Boe), which stands as a definitive scholarly and exhaustive work on every single known allusion to Gog and/or Magog in all of historiography.  However, because you seemingly wish to suppress this unassailable and sourced fact on the pretext that you find it too trivial to the subject &quot;Gog and Magog&quot; to mention where the source first occurs (or possibly because your theology is uncomfortable with acknowledging this sourced fact?) you have placed your own opinion above the source, and removed the source on the origin of the phrase &quot;Gog and Magog&quot;.  In addition you stated that I know nothing of the subject.  You have already reverted '''four times''' in the last 24 hours.  Once again, I implore you to stop being a one man revert machine, and reach some consensus here on the discussion page first, before summarily reverting references on the subject just because you don't like what they say.  [[User:Til Eulenspiegel|Til Eulenspiegel]] ([[User talk:Til Eulenspiegel|talk]]) 01:42, 14 March 2011 (UTC)

== Continued problems with [[User:Koakhtzvigad]]'s view of this topic ==

&quot;Gog and Magog&quot; in folklore is a concept unto itself.  That is the main scope of this article, hence the title, &quot;Gog and Magog&quot;.  It occurs in folk beliefs of people around the world, like it or not.  Like many related folk beliefs (eg &quot;Armageddon&quot;), the beliefs often do not square exactly with their Biblical origin, but they have taken on an extra-biblical life of their own. They are what they are, and we have to describe them as they are.  

For example, in more than a few cases the name has actually fused in the popular imagination into one, &quot;Gogmagog&quot;.  I can tell you from personal experience that in Ethiopia, a country that has known of the Bible longer than many countries have, there is a derived political expression &quot;Gugmangug&quot; meaning roughly autocrat or misguided dictator, e.g. &quot;Gaddafi is a Gugmangug&quot;.  (I haven't looked for a source for this yet, so I'm not about to add it to the article) 

Back on topic - just about every book or study ever written on the subject, or encyclopedia article written on the subject, will mention the significance of the fact that the original phrase &quot;Gog and Magog&quot; makes its first definite appearance in the New Testament Book of Revelation.  In the Book of Ezekiel, when it mentions &quot;Prince Gog of the land of Magog&quot; this is invariably seen as a sort of obvious ancestor or prototype of the later concept &quot;Gog and Magog&quot;, but not precisely the same.  Every other study, article or source outside of wikipedia on the subject, sees fit to preserve this precision in detailing the origin of the concept, but here we now have a user Koakhtzigad who feels it is &quot;UNDUE&quot; if wikipedia contains the same information as is available everywhere else. And feels so quite strongly, gauging from the amount of pillorying he has subjected me to for opposing his unilateral overhauls of the topic.  The fact that the prototypical Ezekiel concepts took its current form in the New Testament apparently doesn't sit well with him. He also has indicated that it is so important to him to sweep this fact under the rug, that he sees no need for things like &quot;consensus&quot; because it would seem the correctness of his own views on the subject trump all consensus.  As a result, the article is rapidly becoming distorted, particularly the part on REVELATION.

It looks like the familiar situation whenever someone is uncomfortable with the truth, so: first they accuse you of &quot;OR&quot;. Then they cry it is &quot;UNDUE&quot;.  Then they come to fight you, yelling you don't know the first thing about it... and then... ?  [[User:Til Eulenspiegel|Til Eulenspiegel]] ([[User talk:Til Eulenspiegel|talk]]) 11:28, 14 March 2011 (UTC)

:...and then you get a reply.
:Its very simple. The Greek form &quot;Gog and Magog&quot; is derived from the Hebrew form &quot;Prince Gog of the land of Magog&quot;. No source can change that Ezekiel lived 500 years before Christianity begun. After 500 years there was nothing ''original'' about &quot;Gog and Magog&quot; which probably became a [[euphemism|euphimistic]] [[allusion]] for the entire 38th chapter. 
:Rather what you want to say is that, &quot;The Greek rendering paved the way for the later view{{who}}, according to which Gog and Magog were the names of ''two'' persons{{why}} (see Rev 20:8). The LXX rendering of Ezek 39:6 as Gog for MT's (Masoretic Text) Magog. This also seems to confirm that the names Gog and Magog were interchangeable.&quot; (J. Lust, Dictionary of deities and demons in the Bible,pp.536-537), however, this would be a huge leap-of-a-theory. Firstly what is the source of interpreting them &lt;u&gt;both&lt;/u&gt; as ''personal names''? Secondly, what is the proof that the extant LXX MS is not corrupted? Finally, as one of my sources points out, the use of just two words instead of quoting the entire passage by the author of ''Revelations'' clearly suggests that he was using it as a reference for the reader, rather than trying to confuse the future reader of his writing. Who were these potential readers? Not Greeks, and not Romans, nor any other local pagans, but fellow (though perhaps Hellenised) Jews who were just as familiar with the Tanakh. This is the importance of dating the Revelations. However, even the most recent date is still within a generation of the destruction of the Temple. There was no Christian community to speak of just yet. 
:What you need to find therefore is some reliable source that plausibly argues for abandonment of the exegesis of Hebrew Ezekiel for the Greek Revelations reference you are so adamant to give prominence in the article.
:You do of course have a wide choice of literature since there is no shortage of suggestions for this exegesis ranging from &quot;sublime to ridiculous&quot;. 
:However, when you do, you can be assured I won't be reverting or removing anything. Just make it as rational as possible please [[User:Koakhtzvigad|Koakhtzvigad]] ([[User talk:Koakhtzvigad|talk]]) 13:55, 14 March 2011 (UTC)
::No, we still don't seem to be communicating on the same wavelength. I am not arguing any unusual origin theory, please don't complicate the issue.  My position could not be simpler.  Either we mention, as every other source does, where the phrase 'Gog and Magog' makes its first appearance in that form, or else this basic fact is, as you say, UNDUE and insignificant to wikipedia (though it would seem significant enough to all the sources one can easily find elsewhere.) Since its relative significance could be more of a subjective point, it is proper to solicit opinions and consensus from other editors per [[WP:BRD]], since we never have been, and never will be, governed by the fiat of any one editor. [[User:Til Eulenspiegel|Til Eulenspiegel]] ([[User talk:Til Eulenspiegel|talk]]) 14:43, 14 March 2011 (UTC)
:::Didn't say its unusual, the Greek texts are replete with paraphrased excerpts from Tanakh.
:::It says in the article now where 'Gog and Magog' makes its first appearance in that form
:::&quot;it would seem significant enough to all the sources one can easily find elsewhere&quot;, so you shouldn't have any problems finding one?
:::&quot;it is proper to solicit opinions and consensus from other editors&quot; - Well, I am giving you my opinion that its significance is only within the realm of those commentators which choose to interpret it as such in isolation from the Ezekiel text. I'm happy to hear from other editors who may differ. 
:::I edited that the same form is found in Hebrew from the Dead Sea scrolls [[User:Koakhtzvigad|Koakhtzvigad]] ([[User talk:Koakhtzvigad|talk]]) 03:10, 15 March 2011 (UTC)
::::Does your source really use the word &quot;proves&quot;?  Would you mind putting the exact quote here? I fail to see how the existence of the Hebrew Qumran fragment can be taken as &quot;proof&quot; ( a very strong word) that Greek Revelation borrowed from it, and I do know most competent scholars tend to be far too cautious, to recklessly throw around claims of &quot;proof&quot;. I suspect that the &quot;proof&quot; part is more of your editorialising / pov pushing. But even if that source does call it &quot;proof&quot;, we cannot ignore another prominent scholar (Boe)'s treatment of that same Qumran Scroll. Boe, who wrote a scholarly book specifically about the phrase &quot;Gog and Magog&quot;, does not even seem certain that the tiny scrap allegedly bearing the isolated words &quot;Gog and Magog&quot; really say that at all. And he does give that scroll an in-depth treatment too -- so I fear it may be a bit premature for us yet to go about endorsing any strong claims of &quot;proof&quot; of the original inspiration of the Book of Revelation. [[User:Til Eulenspiegel|Til Eulenspiegel]] ([[User talk:Til Eulenspiegel|talk]]) 11:29, 15 March 2011 (UTC)
:::::Is there a reason why you can't look up the reference yourself? [[User:Koakhtzvigad|Koakhtzvigad]] ([[User talk:Koakhtzvigad|talk]]) 02:56, 20 March 2011 (UTC)

===4Q523 Qumran reference===
This is in reference to 4Q523, a Qumran fragment published by E Puech in 1996. His translation of line 5 included the only legible letters “Gwg u Mgwg” (Gog and Magog) but no surrounding context.  This is described in the source that you brought to the table, despite obliging me to do the hunt for your source.

“It is possible that 4Q523 contained an eschatological prophecy, but this cannot 
be inferred from the remaining lines. Therefore, 4Q523 cannot be used as an 
early witness to the existence of an eschatological Gog and Magog tradition. Nevertheless, 4Q523 is still important for our present purpose, since it contains the earliest known reference to 'Gog and Magog' instead of 'Gog of the land of Magog'. Moreover, it is the only occurence of the combination of Gog and Magog in the 
Dead Sea Scrolls. In commentaries on the book of Revelation, it has been argued 
that the expression 'Gog and Magog' depends on the LXX of Ezek 38:2, 'Gog and the land of Magog' instead of the Masoretic 'Gog from the land of Magog'. The discovery of 4Q523, however, has demonstrated that the phrase and Magog' originated in Hebrew, not in Greek. It may be that [Gwg u mgwg] came into being as a short formula for 'Gog and (his people) Magog’. [...] Perhaps the combination ‘Gog and Magog’ stems from a tradition consisting of an abbreviated version of Ezekiel’s prophecy about Gog and  Magog. Unfortunately, 4Q523 is too damaged to draw any conclusion in that respect...”

The other source, Boe, says very much the same thing in a section beginning on 177 of his book on “Gog and Magog”. [http://books.google.com/books?id=vettpBoVOX4C&amp;pg=PA177&amp;dq=%22one+of+these+contains+a+reference%22&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q=%22one%20of%20these%20contains%20a%20reference%22&amp;f=false here’s a link for your convenience].  He tentatively speculates these are “negatively loaded terms for contemporary political enemies.” but concedes “The very fragmentary nature of these texts makes it impossible to interpret the Gog and Magog reference meaningfully. Still it is very interesting to find both names together with only a conjunction between them.” 

Based on what both these two sources tell us, I am still not happy with the info in the article in general, especially the much rasher language (compared to these scholarly sources) in the current  section on Revelation (and why does it have to be named ‘Christian tradition’ when the only one mentioned there is the Book of Revelation, it should rather be titled by the name of the book on a par with the sections for Hebrew Bible books.) 

The mention of &quot;Gog and Magog&quot; in Revelation  '''''is invariably treated as central to this topic in secondary sources''''', yet curiously, you want that necessarily treated as &quot;undue weight&quot; without really establishing why this is not just some subjective POV on your part. [[User:Til Eulenspiegel|Til Eulenspiegel]] ([[User talk:Til Eulenspiegel|talk]]) 14:06, 20 March 2011 (UTC)

:I try to provide sources available online (but not always), in the first instance through GoogleBooks. However, they do not stay there forever in preview mode.
:There is no need to quote the entire page. The point is that this fragment shows use of Gog and Magog as a pair in earlier Jewish tradition in Hebrew. Not much else can be derived from the texts, either Hebrew or Greek for the purpose of an encyclopaedia article.
:Actually Gog and Magog are found in the Torah (Bible in Hebrew), Neviim (Prophets) and Ketuvim (Writings). This is why they are listed separately. It is also found in the Talmud.
:Revelations is not something unique to Christianity, hence ''Christian tradition''. Other uses can come from titles like:
*The Book of Revelations: A Sourcebook of Themes from the Holy [[Qur'an]]
*Book of Revelations: A Collection of [[Poetry]]
*The Book of Revelations: A Year's Worth of [[Facebook]] Wisdom
*A Little Book of Revelations (This book is a radical reappraisal of the Christian life-style.)
*The Book of Revelations about the Sacred Company of the Virgins of Cologne (in Elisabeth of Schonau, p.213)
:Yes, it is not central to the Book of Revelations, but many (most!) secondary sources are (particularly Christian) focused on working out the future based on two words. However, when this discussion begun there were no secondary sources mentioned. As you have seen, in the more scholarly sources, even where they devote space exclusively to &quot;Gog and Magog&quot; it is a section in a chapter, so not really ''central''. The book that Doug would say is not reliable (self-published in lulu) is like that. [[User:Koakhtzvigad|Koakhtzvigad]] ([[User talk:Koakhtzvigad|talk]]) 10:55, 21 March 2011 (UTC)
::Really? What about &quot;Book of Revelation&quot;? (Note, no S on Revelation - the actual title in question)... And what exactly is all that supposed to prove in logical terms anyway?  We use ''real'' logic here, not hermeneutics.  And in real logic, pointing at a bunch of off topic books with the word &quot;Revelations&quot; in the title, as if that were somehow meaningful to the question, would be called a &quot;fallacy&quot;. [[User:Til Eulenspiegel|Til Eulenspiegel]] ([[User talk:Til Eulenspiegel|talk]]) 11:48, 21 March 2011 (UTC)

== Koakhtzvigad and sources ==

I've just reverted an edit by Koakhtzvigad which uses a blog and a self-published lulu.com book. [[WP:RS]] makes it clear we shouldn't be using such sources. It also added a claim &quot;no further etymological meaning can be derived.&quot; which had no source at all. [[User:Dougweller|Dougweller]] ([[User talk:Dougweller|talk]]) 06:27, 20 March 2011 (UTC)
:Actually you reverted the entire edit, and not only those that you refer to in the edit summary as ''we don't use blogs or self=published works as sources, statement &quot;no further etymological meaning can be derived.&quot; is unsourced''. Would you then please care to undo your revert and remove only those portions that you consider as not being supported by reliable sources.[[User:Koakhtzvigad|Koakhtzvigad]] ([[User talk:Koakhtzvigad|talk]]) 06:49, 20 March 2011 (UTC)

::Your 'not very well considered' explanation doesn't explain why you added the stuff about &quot; why they did not specifically appear together as a pair until that book was composed before any formal separation of Christianity and Judaism.&quot; which had no reference. I'm not putting anything back without a good reason. [[User:Dougweller|Dougweller]] ([[User talk:Dougweller|talk]]) 09:40, 20 March 2011 (UTC)
:::Til ''insisted'' on including that the phrase appears in Revelations once and once only.
:::There is indeed no other record before appearance of Christianity where the phrase appears in Greek
:::There is an example of the same phrase appearing in a Qumran fragment in Hebrew, but dated clearly to well before appearance of Christianity. 
:::This established, as I wrote in preceding text (referenced) that it was a well known form of reference that was used as much by the Essene sect in Hebrew as by the Christian sect in Greek
:::The sentence you quote is simply a closing for the paragraph, and doesn't need a reference. 
:::However, if you can find a reference where someone proves that something didn't exist, i.e. Greek reference to Gog and Magog before appearance of Christianity, be my guest 
:::However, what you did is to perform a wholesale revert without offering adequate explanation, indeed you were selective 
:::My editing restored a number of edits that PiCo removed due to what I would politically call bad judgment
:::It seems to me that there are guidelines about what one describes in edit summaries, and they ought to describe as closely as possible what editing you had performed, which in your case they did not.
:::I'm happy to describe why PiCo's prior editing was 'not very well considered', but I'm not here to cause embarassment to other editors [[User:Koakhtzvigad|Koakhtzvigad]] ([[User talk:Koakhtzvigad|talk]]) 11:56, 20 March 2011 (UTC)
::::If you can find a reference in a reliable sources saying there is no such record, fine. Without such a source, we can say nothing about it. I'm surprised you think my edit summary less clear or explicit than yours. [[User:Dougweller|Dougweller]] ([[User talk:Dougweller|talk]]) 13:11, 20 March 2011 (UTC)
:::::If I started undoing all of PiCo's bad editing one at a time it would take too long. The problem is that he removed content that should not be removed, but merely ''improved'', usually through better referencing. Having badly referenced content which is essentially valid is better than having none, which conflicts with PiCo's philosophy of editing. It is very much more difficult to re-reference content while having to look for it in the revision history. In PiCo's editing history of over 17,000 entries, only a couple of dozen are edits accompanied by references. These are unfortunately offset by removal of references that PiCo thought were 'old', and removal of content because it had no references, but was in fact viable. Hence I was content to leave the (as you pointed out) less good references (though still acceptable despite your assertion to the contrary), because it left a clue as to what to look for while providing continuity in the content, rather than leaving an [[Wikipedia:INTEGRITY#Text-source_integrity|integrity gap]] that arbitrary removal creates, and which is often evident in very many Wikipedia articles.
:::::However, I'll humour you. Below is the content as I edited it which you removed. Please Specifically point to what you have a problem with.
&lt;blockquote&gt;The term &quot;Gog and Magog&quot;, as distinct from Ezekiel's &quot;Gog of the land of Magog&quot;, first appears in the [[Christian]] [[New Testament]]'s ''Book of Revelation''.&lt;ref name=&quot;BelyeuIrene&quot; /&gt; The discovery of the 4Q523 [[Dead Sea scrolls]] fragment proves that the expression in Greek is derived from Hebrew which is the earliest record of 'Gog ''and'' Magog' rather than 'Gog of the land of Magog'.&lt;ref&gt;Buitenwerf, Rieuwerd, The Gog and Magog Tradition in Revelation 20:8, in, H. J. de Jonge, Johannes Tromp, eds., ''The book of Ezekiel and its influence'', Ashgate Publishing, Ltd., 2007, p.172&lt;/ref&gt; Gog and Magog appear in only one verse of the [[Book of Revelation]] (Rev. 20:8), and are equated in the vision with &quot;the nations in the four quarters of the earth&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;BelyeuIrene&quot; /&gt; The more recent interpretation of the prophecy in the received Christian text that suggests a battle waged by the Satan's forces, &quot;god of this world&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;BelyeuIrene&quot; /&gt; at the close of the Messianic kingdom is based on the [[Strong's Concordance]] entries #01463 ''Gog'', #04031 ''Magog'', #04902 Meshech, and #08422 ''Tuval''.&lt;ref name=&quot;BelyeuIrene&quot; /&gt;

The abbreviated Greek form of the Hebrew borrowing by ''John'' may have been because the passage was well known to him&lt;ref&gt;Berner, Douglas C., ''The Silence Is Broken! God Hooks Ezekiel's Gog &amp; Magog'', www.lulu.com, 2006, p.282&lt;/ref&gt;, and in the Jewish community where this Ezekiel passage precedes those read on [[Shabbat]] Chol Hamoed (intermediate) of [[Sukkot]] festival, the Ezekiel 38:18 - 39:16 [[haftarah]].&lt;ref&gt;Scherman Nosson &amp; Zlotowitz, Meir, eds., TANACH: The Torah, Prophets, Writings, The Twenty-Four Books of the Bible Newly Translated and Annotated, Mesorah Publications, Ltd., Brooklyn, 1996, p.x&lt;/ref&gt;
The tradition is difficult to date due to the protracted period of Hellenization in Judea.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

:::::You then replace it with the following 
&lt;blockquote&gt;While &quot;Gog and Magog&quot; are closely associated with one another in the Ezekiel passage, they are used only as a reference in the [[Christian]] [[New Testament]] ''Book of Revelation'', and not as a complete translation from Ezekiel, which is why they did not specifically appear together as a pair until that book was composed before any formal separation of Christianity and Judaism.&lt;/blockquote&gt; 
:::::The part &quot;and not as a complete translation from Ezekiel, which is why they did not specifically appear together as a pair until that book was composed before any formal separation of Christianity and Judaism.&quot; was added by me before I found that in fact the pair '''did''' appear together before the book of Revelations was composed, and the dating of the Qumran fragment '''is''' dated before separation of Christianity and Judaism, hence the part is edited out and replaced with information on the ''4Q523''.
:::::The blog reference is good because it provided English translations of Hebrew (but not linked) which are referenced. However, I can find more acceptable sources for the same material. The self-published (lilu.com) book is not authoritative, but is typical of its genre, and has references for what it says. I haven't looked, but I'm sure it will not be difficult to find similar statements in other books by similar-minded Christian authors.[[User:Koakhtzvigad|Koakhtzvigad]] ([[User talk:Koakhtzvigad|talk]]) 13:54, 20 March 2011 (UTC)

== Islamic tradition ==

I believe Islamic tradition of Gog and Magog should have its own sections, just like Christians and jews. 
Why its in other traditional in the first place ?? [[Special:Contributions/188.66.153.95|188.66.153.95]] ([[User talk:188.66.153.95|talk]]) 02:33, 28 March 2011 (UTC)

== Are they the anderthals? ==

Are they the anderthals? the same discription as in quran? has anybody thought of this?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:MasriDefend|MasriDefend]] ([[User talk:MasriDefend|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/MasriDefend|contribs]]) 01:51, 17 August 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Wikipedia is not an appropriate place for this sort of discussion, you need to find a forum somewhere else. [[User:Dougweller|Dougweller]] ([[User talk:Dougweller|talk]]) 16:07, 17 August 2011 (UTC)

== Dispensationalist View ==

As a newcomer to Wikipedia, I am hesitating to post anything myself,
but I would submit that, in various re-edits, the Dispensationalist view 
(which was once presented in this article) has disappeared and should be restored.

In short, most Dispensationalists view Gog and Magog as a reference to Russia (and, usually to a Russian leader), citing Josephus and similar ancient sources.

Citations of authority:  &quot;The Book of Revelation: A Commentary on the Greek Text&quot; by Gregory Beale (1999), at page 1025;

&quot;The Man of Sin: Uncovering The Truth About the Anti-Christ&quot; by Kim Riddlebarger (2006) at page 57.

Thoughts?

[[User:AVERHOES|AVERHOES]] ([[User talk:AVERHOES|talk]]) 18:23, 19 November 2011 (UTC)
:The view that Gog/Magog is Russia is in the article, though I guess your point is that it should be more detailed. I rather doubt that myself - a simple mention is enough, surely. [[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 10:28, 15 December 2011 (UTC)

Pico - You are correct that there is a reference to Russia being identified as Gog and Magog in a couple of contexts (a) ancient Jewish scholars such as Josephus associated Gog and Magog with the Scythians; and (b) &quot;during the Cold War&quot;, Russia was identified as Gog and Magog.  The Dispensationalist view predates the Cold War, and continues to be held to this day - that Biblical references to Gog and Magog refer to Russia.  My point is that there was once a statement in the text affirming that a modern theological movement still views Russia in this light, but that such a statement disappeared from the text about 6-8 months ago.  As currently written, a reader could assume that no one in the post Cold War period subscribes to the belief that Russia is viewed as Gog and Magog, which is demonstrably incorrect.  I would also respectfully point out that several paragraphs are included on legends (not having any scriptural basis and not embraced by any segment of modern Judaism, Christianity, or Islam) that Gog and Magog references either Ireland or England.  If this theory is worth several paragraphs, surely a single sentence could be devoted to Gog and Magog as Russia?  

Averhoes  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:AVERHOES|AVERHOES]] ([[User talk:AVERHOES|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/AVERHOES|contribs]]) 19:33, 21 December 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== bavel v magog ==

I think what this phrase &quot;by turning BBL (&quot;Babylon&quot; in Hebrew script, which originally had no vowel-signs) into MGG (Magog), but this account, like the others, has problems.&quot; is really trying to describe the following:  In Hebrew Bavel is spelt bbl.  The relationship to magog (mgg) is to advance each letter by 1 so that b&gt;g b&gt;g l&gt;m and then spelling it backward.  I find this interesting, but... not very likely.  Most obscure things would normally be encoded in a variant of an atbash cypher.  However, ad hoc, this would be yyo - which doesn't help.  It is interesting to note that &quot;gog&quot; in hebrew means &quot;ceiling&quot;.  Persia at the time of the prophecy was pretty much at the top of the known world and Russia could be considered as descended from &quot;the roof of the world&quot; or &quot;magog&quot; (as opposed to Europe which is generally considered as being descended from Eisav via Troy&gt;Italy).  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Weedmic|Weedmic]] ([[User talk:Weedmic|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Weedmic|contribs]]) 11:57, 9 April 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Sorry, this page is not a blog for engaging in speculation and conjecture by wikipedians. We can't 'decide' anything here. We can only use speculations that already appear in 3rd party sources. [[User:Til Eulenspiegel|Til Eulenspiegel]] ([[User talk:Til Eulenspiegel|talk]]) 13:02, 9 April 2012 (UTC)

== Gog and Magog in the Islamic sources Qur'an, Hadith ==

lot of information but need to translation
{{hide|Ya jūj Wama jūj|
'''ياجوج وماجوج''' اسم لشعب يظهر في اخر الزمان، عند خروجهم من تحت الردم يقومون بأبادة جميع الشعوب التي تكون في طريقهم حسب المصادر الإسلامية.   

ويكون اشتقاق الأسم من أجت النار أجيجا : إذا التهبت . و  من الأجاج : وهو الماء الشديد الملوحة ، المحرق من ملوحته ، وعن الأج : وهو سرعة العدو. و مأجوج من ماج إذا اضطرب، ويؤيد هذا الاشتقاق قوله تعالى ( وتركنا بعضهم يومئذ يموج في بعض ) ، وهما على وزن يفعول في ( يأجوج ) ، ومفعول في ( مأجوج ) أو على وزن فاعول فيهما [http://www.khayma.com/albayan/majoj.html].

'''من القرآن  '''

جاء ذكرهما في كل من [[سورة الكهف]] و[[سورة الأنبياء]].
* سورة الكهف
:(وَيَسْأَلُونَكَ عَن ذِي الْقَرْنَيْنِ قُلْ سَأَتْلُو عَلَيْكُم مِّنْهُ ذِكْراً (83)‏ إِنَّا مَكَّنَّا لَهُ فِي الْأَرْضِ وَآتَيْنَاهُ مِن كُلِّ شَيْءٍ سَبَباً (84) فَأَتْبَعَ سَبَباً (85) حَتَّى إِذَا بَلَغَ مَغْرِبَ الشَّمْسِ وَجَدَهَا تَغْرُبُ فِي عَيْنٍ حَمِئَةٍ وَوَجَدَ عِندَهَا قَوْماً قُلْنَا يَا ذَا الْقَرْنَيْنِ إِمَّا أَن تُعَذِّبَ وَإِمَّا أَن تَتَّخِذَ فِيهِمْ حُسْناً (86) قَالَ أَمَّا مَن ظَلَمَ فَسَوْفَ نُعَذِّبُهُ ثُمَّ يُرَدُّ إِلَى رَبِّهِ فَيُعَذِّبُهُ عَذَأباً نُّكْراً (87) وَأَمَّا مَنْ آمَنَ وَعَمِلَ صَالِحاً فَلَهُ جَزَاء الْحُسْنَى وَسَنَقُولُ لَهُ مِنْ أَمْرِنَا يُسْراً (88) ثُمَّ أَتْبَعَ سَبَباً (89) حَتَّى إِذَا بَلَغَ مَطْلِعَ الشَّمْسِ وَجَدَهَا تَطْلُعُ عَلَى قَوْمٍ لَّمْ نَجْعَل لَّهُم مِّن دُونِهَا سِتْراً (90) كَذَلِكَ وَقَدْ أَحَطْنَا بِمَا لَدَيْهِ خُبْراً (91) ثُمَّ أَتْبَعَ سَبَباً (92) حَتَّى إِذَا بَلَغَ بَيْنَ السَّدَّيْنِ وَجَدَ مِن دُونِهِمَا قَوْماً لَّا يَكَادُونَ يَفْقَهُونَ قَوْلاً (93) قَالُوا يَا ذَا الْقَرْنَيْنِ إِنَّ يَأْجُوجَ وَمَأْجُوجَ مُفْسِدُونَ فِي الْأَرْضِ فَهَلْ نَجْعَلُ لَكَ خَرْجاً عَلَى أَن تَجْعَلَ بَيْنَنَا وَبَيْنَهُمْ سَدّاً (94) قَالَ مَا مَكَّنِّي فِيهِ رَبِّي خَيْرٌ فَأَعِينُونِي بِقُوَّةٍ أَجْعَلْ بَيْنَكُمْ وَبَيْنَهُمْ رَدْماً (95) آتُونِي زُبَرَ الْحَدِيدِ حَتَّى إِذَا سَاوَى بَيْنَ الصَّدَفَيْنِ قَالَ انفُخُوا حَتَّى إِذَا جَعَلَهُ نَاراً قَالَ آتُونِي أُفْرِغْ عَلَيْهِ قِطْراً (96) فَمَا اسْطَاعُوا أَن يَظْهَرُوهُ وَمَا اسْتَطَاعُوا لَهُ نَقْباً (97)‏ قَالَ هَذَا رَحْمَةٌ مِّن رَّبِّي فَإِذَا جَاء وَعْدُ رَبِّي جَعَلَهُ دَكَّاء وَكَانَ وَعْدُ رَبِّي حَقّاً (98)) 

* سورة الأنبياء
: (حَتَّى إِذَا فُتِحَتْ يَأْجُوجُ وَمَأْجُوجُ وَهُمْ مِنْ كُلِّ حَدَبٍ يَنْسِلُونَ)(الأنبياء: 96) 

تكلم [[القرآن]] عن [[ذو القرنين|ذي القرنين]] وجعله قدوة ومثلا رائعا للملك المحسن وعن تمكينة في الأرض ورحلاته الثلاث:
* رحلته الأولى حتى بلغ مغرب الشمس
* ثم رحلته الثانية حتى بلغ مطلع الشمس (القطب الشمالي وشمال شرقي سيبريا)
* ثم رحلته الثالثة حتى بلغ السدين

'''تفسير الآيات'''

تفسير الآيات الكريمة [[يأجوج ومأجوج#مصدر|[1]]] 

((ويسألونك عن ذي القرنين)) 

يقول تعالى لنبيّه صلى اللّه عليه وسلم ‏{‏ويسالونك‏}‏ يا محمد ‏{‏عن ذي القرنين‏}‏ أي عن خبره، نزلت بعد سؤالهم ((أي اليهود))، إن السؤال لم يكن عن ذات ذي القرنين، بل عن شأنه، فكأنه قيل: ويسألونك عن شأن ذي القرنين. 

(قل): لهم في الجواب 

(سأتلو عليكم منه ذكرا): الخطاب للسائلين، سأقص عليكم منه خبرا. 

((إنا مكنّا له في الأرض)): أي اعطيناه ملكاً عظيماً، ممكناً فيه من جميع ما يؤتى الملوك من التمكين والجنود وآلات الحرب والحضارات، ودانت له البلاد وخضعت له ملوك العباد. 

((وآتيناه من كل شئ سببا)): أي اعطيناه من كل شيء ‏{‏ سبباً ‏}‏ طريقاً يوصله إلى مراده ‏.‏ 

(فأتبع سببا): سلك طريقاً 

((حتى إذا بلغ مغرب الشمس)) ومغرب الشمس هو المكان الذي يرى الرائي أن الشمس تغرب عنده وراء الأفق. 

&quot;وجدها&quot;: أي الشمس. 

(تغرب في عين حمئة): أي راى الشمس في منظره تغرب في البحر وهذا شان كل من انتهى إلى ساحله، يراها كانها تغرب فيه، والحمئة مشتقة على إحدى القراءتين من الحماة وهو الطين، كما قال تعالى ‏{‏اني خالق بشراً من صلصال من حما مسنون‏}‏‏:‏ أي من طين املس، وقد تقدم بيانه‏.‏ وقال ابن جرير‏:‏ كان ابن عباس يقول ‏{‏في عين حماة‏}‏ ثم فسرها ذات حماة، قال نافع‏:‏ وسئل عنها كعب الاحبار فقال‏:‏ انتم اعلم بالقران مني لكني اجدها في الكتاب تغيب في طينة سوداء‏.‏ وبه قال مجاهد وغير واحد‏.‏ وعن اُبي بن كعب ان النبي صلى اللّه عليه وسلم اقراه حمئة، وقال علي بن ابي طلحة، عن ابن عباس وجدها تغرب في عين حامية يعني حارة‏.‏ وكذا قال الحسن البصري، وقال ابن جرير‏:‏ والصواب انهما قراءتان مشهورتان، وايهما قرا القارئ فهو مصيب، ولا منافاة بين معنييهما إذ قد تكون حارة لمجاورتها وهج الشمس عند غروبها وملاقاتها الشعاع بلا حائل، وحمئة في ماء وطين أسود كما قال كعب الاحبار وغيره‏.‏ 

والظاهر من النص أن ذا القرنين غرب حتى وصل إلى نقطة على شاطئ البحر ويظن أن اليابسة تنتهى عنده – فرأى الشمس تغرب فيه. والارجح أنه كان عند مصب أحد الأنهار، حيث تكثر الأعشاب ويتجمع حولها طين لزج هو الحمأ. وتوجد البرك وكأنها عيون الماء. فرأى الشمس تغرب هناك و(وجدها تغرب في عين حمئة). 

(ووجد عندها): أي عند تلك العين على الساحل المتصل بها (قوما) أي أمة من الأمم. 

(قلنا ياذا القرنين إما أن تعذب وإما أن تتخذ فيهم حسنا) أي ليكن شأنك معهم إما التعذيب وإما الإحسان، فالأول لمن بقي على حاله، والثاني لمن تاب. 

(قال أما من ظلم): نفسه ولم يقبل دعوة التوحيد والمنهج الرباني واستمر على شركة وكفره وعناده. 

(فسوف نعذبه): بالقتل. 

(ثم يرد إلى ربه): في الآخرة. 

(فيعذبه): فيها. 

(عذابا نكرا): أي شديداً بلغياً وجيعاً اليماً، وهو العذاب في نار جهنم. 

(وأما من آمن): أي تابعنا على ما ندعوه إليه من عبادة الله وحده. 

(وعمل صالحا فله جزاء الحسنى): أي المثوبة الحسنة أو الفعلة الحسنى أو الجنة. 

(وسنقول له من أمرنا يسرا): معروفاً. 

(ثم أتبع سببا): أي سلك طريقاً.

(حتى إذا بلغ مطلع الشمس): أي مطلعها من الأفق الشرقي في عين الرائي. 

(وجدها): أي الشمس. 

(تطلع على قوم لم نجعل لهم من دونها سترا): إشارة تدلنا على أن ذا القرنين قد وصل إلى القطب الذي تكون فيه الشمس ستة شهور لا تغيب، وطوال هذه الشهور لا يوجد ظلام يستر الشمس في هذه الأماكن.وهذا إعجاز من القرآن الكريم. 

(كذلك وقد أحطنا بما لديه خبرا): أي أن الله سبحانه كان عالما بأحوال ذي القرنين، مطلعا على حركاته، محيطا بأخباره وأخبار جيشه، فما يسيرون خطوة إلا بإذن الله، ولا يتحركون حركة إلا بمشيئة الله، ولا يكسبون معركة أو يحتلون بلدا إلا والله عالم بهم، مطلع عليهم، خبير بهم. 

(ثم أتبع سببا): أي طريقا ثالثا معترضا بين المشرق والمغرب، آخذا من مطلع الشمس إلى الشمال. 

(حتى إذا بلغ بين السدين): أي الجبلين. 

(وجد من دونهما): أي السدين: قال ابن كثير: (هما جبلان متناوحان (متقابلان) بينهما ثغرة يخرج منهما يأجوج ومأجوج على بلاد الترك، فيعيثون فيهم فسادا ويهلكون الحرث والنسل). 

(قوما لا يكادون يفقهون قولا): أي أمة من الناس لا يفقهون أقوال أتباع ذي القرنين لقلة فطنتهم وبعدهم عن لغات غيرهم. 

(قالوا ياذا القرنين إن يأجوج ومأجوج مفسدون في الأرض): أي اشتكوا إلى ذي القرنين من ظلم (يأجوج ومأجوج) الذين أفسدوا أرضنا بالقتل والتخريب. 

(فهل نجعل لك خرجا على أن تجعل بيننا وبينهم سدا) أي يجمعون له من بينهم مالاً يعطونه اياه بغرض أن تبني لنا سدا بيننا وبينهم.. لقد تأدبوا في عرضهم المال على ذي القرنين ولذلك استخدموا أسلوب الاستفهام. 

والسد: أي حاجزا يمنعهم من الوصول إلينا. 

فقال ذو القرنين بعفة وديانة وصلاح وقصد للخير: 

(قال ما مكني فيه ربي خير): أي إن الذي أعطاني الله من الملك والتمكين خير لي من الذي تجمعونه. 

(فأعينوني بقوة): أي ساعدوني بالأيدي العاملة. 

(أجعل بينكم وبينهم ردما): أي حاجزا حصينا منيعا.  (الردم للحفرة)

(آتوني زبر الحديد): أي قطع الحديد الكبيرة. 

(حتى اذا ساوى بين الصدفين): أي وصل الحديد وضع بعضه على بعض من الأساس، حتى حاذى به رؤوس الجبلين طولاً وعرضاً. 

(قال انفخوا) : أي اشعلوا النار تحت الحديد. 

(حتى إذا جعله نارا قال أتوني أفرغ عليه قطرا): أي من الذين يشرفون على أمر النحاس، لاضع فوق الحديد المصهور نحاسا مذابا ليختلط به. 

(فما اسطاعوا أن يظهروه): أي ياجوج وماجوج عجزوا على صعود على ظهر السد. 

(وما استطاعوا له نقبا): أي عجزوا عن نقضه وخرقه. 

(قال): أي ذو القرنين لمن عنده من أهل تلك الديار وغيرهم. 

(هذا): إشارة إلى السد. 

(رحمة من ربي): حيث جعله بينهم وبين ياجوج وماجوج حائلاً يمنعهم من العيث في الأرض والفساد. 

(فإذا جاء وعد ربي): أي اذا اقترب الوعد الحق. 

(جعله دكاء) أي ساواه بالأرض، وتقول العرب‏:‏ ناقة دكاء اذا كان ظهرها مستوياً لا سنام لها. 

(وكان وعد ربي حقا): أي كائناً لا محالة‏.

''' من الأحاديث النبوية '''

* عن ‏ ‏زينب بنت جحش - رضي الله عنها – قالت: دخل الرسول صلى الله عليه وسلم فزعاً وهو يقول: لا إله إلا الله، ويل للعرب من شر قد اقترب، فتح اليوم من سدِّ &quot;يأجوج ومأجوج&quot; مثل هذه، وحلق بإصبعه الإبهام والتي تليها، قالت له زينب: يا رسول الله أنهلك وفينا الصالحون ؟ قال: نعم إذا كثر الخبث، رواه البخاري.

‏ان يأجوج ومأجوج ‏ ‏ليحفرون ‏ ‏السد كل يوم حتى إذا كادوا يرون شعاع الشمس قال الذي عليهم ارجعوا فستحفرونه غدا فيعودون إليه كأشد ما كان حتى إذا بلغت مدتهم وأراد ‏ ‏الله عز وجل أن يبعثهم إلى الناس حفروا حتى إذا كادوا يرون شعاع الشمس قال الذي عليهم ارجعوا فستحفرونه غدا إن شاء الله ‏ ‏ويستثني ‏ ‏فيعودون إليه وهو كهيئته حين تركوه فيحفرونه ويخرجون على الناس فينشفون المياه ويتحصن الناس منهم في حصونهم فيرمون بسهامهم إلى السماء فترجع وعليها كهيئة الدم فيقولون قهرنا أهل الأرض وعلونا أهل السماء فيبعث الله عليهم ‏ ‏نغفا ‏ ‏في أقفائهم فيقتلهم بها فقال رسول الله ‏ ‏صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏ ‏والذي نفس ‏ ‏محمد ‏ ‏بيده إن دواب الأرض لتسمن شكرا من لحومهم ودمائهم)، رواه أحمد.

* عن ‏ ‏ابن حرملة ‏ ‏عن ‏ ‏خالته ‏ ‏قالت ‏ خطب رسول الله ‏ ‏صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏ ‏وهو عاصب إصبعه من لدغة عقرب فقال: (‏ ‏إنكم تقولون لا عدو وإنكم لا تزالون تقاتلون عدوا حتى يأتي ‏يأجوج ومأجوج ‏ ‏عراض الوجوه صغار العيون ‏ ‏شهب ‏ ‏الشعاف ‏ ‏من كل ‏ ‏حدب ‏ ‏ينسلون كأن وجوههم ‏ ‏المجان ‏ ‏المطرقة)، رواه أحمد.

* عن ‏ ‏حذيفة بن أسيد الغفاري ‏ ‏قال ‏ كنا قعودا نتحدث في ظل غرفة لرسول الله ‏ ‏صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏ ‏فذكرنا الساعة فارتفعت أصواتنا فقال رسول الله ‏ ‏صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏: (‏لن تكون ‏ ‏أو لن تقوم ‏ ‏الساعة حتى يكون قبلها عشر آيات طلوع الشمس من مغربها وخروج الدابة وخروج ‏ يأجوج ‏ ومأجوج ‏ ‏والدجال ‏ ‏وعيسى ابن مريم ‏ ‏والدخان وثلاثة خسوف خسف بالمغرب وخسف بالمشرق وخسف بجزيرة ‏ ‏العرب ‏ ‏وآخر ذلك تخرج نار من ‏ ‏اليمن ‏ ‏من ‏ ‏قعر ‏ ‏عدن ‏ ‏تسوق الناس إلى ‏ ‏المحشر)، رواه أبو داود.

* عن ‏ ‏أبي سعيد الخدري ‏ ‏قال ‏ قال رسول الله ‏ ‏صلى الله عليه وسلم: (‏ ‏يقول الله عز وجل يوم القيامة ‏ ‏يا ‏ ‏آدم ‏ ‏قم فابعث بعث النار فيقول لبيك وسعديك والخير في يديك يا رب ‏ ‏وما بعث النار قال من كل ألف تسع مائة وتسعة وتسعين قال فحينئذ يشيب المولود وتضع كل ذات حمل حملها ‏ ‏وترى الناس سكارى وما هم بسكارى ولكن عذاب الله شديد قال فيقولون فأينا ذلك الواحد قال فقال رسول الله ‏ ‏صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏ ‏تسع مائة وتسعة وتسعين من يأجوج ‏ ومأجوج ‏ ‏ومنكم واحد قال فقال الناس الله أكبر فقال رسول الله ‏ ‏صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏ ‏أفلا ترضون أن تكونوا ربع أهل الجنة والله إني لأرجو أن تكونوا ربع أهل الجنة والله إني لأرجو أن تكونوا ثلث أهل الجنة والله إني لأرجو أن تكونوا نصف أهل الجنة قال فكبر الناس قال فقال رسول الله ‏ ‏صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏ ‏ما أنتم يومئذ في الناس إلا كالشعرة البيضاء في الثور الأسود ‏ ‏أو كالشعرة السوداء في الثور الأبيض)، رواه أحمد.

* (يأتي نبي الله ‏ ‏عيسى ‏ ‏قوما قد عصمهم الله فيمسح وجوههم ويحدثهم بدرجاتهم في الجنة فبينما هم كذلك إذ أوحى الله إليه يا ‏ ‏عيسى ‏ ‏إني قد أخرجت عبادا لي لا ‏ ‏يدان ‏ ‏لأحد بقتالهم ‏ ‏وأحرز ‏ ‏عبادي إلى ‏ ‏الطور ‏ ‏ويبعث الله ‏ ‏ يأجوج ‏ ‏ ومأجوج ‏ ‏وهم كما قال الله من كل ‏ ‏حدب ‏ ‏ينسلون فيمر أوائلهم على ‏ ‏بحيرة الطبرية ‏ ‏فيشربون ما فيها ثم يمر آخرهم فيقولون لقد كان في هذا ماء مرة ويحضر نبي الله وأصحابه حتى يكون رأس الثور لأحدهم خيرا من مائة دينار لأحدكم اليوم فيرغب نبي الله ‏ ‏عيسى ‏ ‏وأصحابه إلى الله فيرسل الله عليهم ‏ ‏النغف ‏ ‏في رقابهم فيصبحون ‏ ‏فرسى ‏ ‏كموت نفس واحدة ويهبط نبي الله ‏ ‏عيسى ‏ ‏وأصحابه فلا يجدون موضع شبر إلا قد ملأه ‏ ‏زهمهم ‏ ‏ونتنهم ودماؤهم فيرغبون إلى الله فيرسل عليهم طيرا كأعناق ‏ ‏البخت ‏ ‏فتحملهم فتطرحهم حيث شاء الله ثم يرسل الله عليهم مطرا لا يكن منه بيت ‏ ‏مدر ‏ ‏ولا وبر فيغسله حتى يتركه كالزلقة ثم يقال للأرض أنبتي ثمرتك وردي بركتك فيومئذ تأكل ‏ ‏العصابة ‏ ‏من الرمانة فتشبعهم ويستظلون ‏ ‏بقحفها ‏ ‏ويبارك الله في الرسل حتى إن ‏ ‏اللقحة ‏ ‏من الإبل ‏ ‏تكفي ‏ ‏الفئام ‏ ‏من الناس ‏ ‏واللقحة ‏ ‏من البقر ‏ ‏تكفي القبيلة ‏ ‏واللقحة ‏ ‏من الغنم ‏ ‏تكفي الفخذ فبينما هم كذلك إذ بعث الله عليهم ريحا طيبة فتأخذ تحت آباطهم فتقبض ‏ ‏روح ‏ ‏كل مسلم ويبقى سائر الناس ‏ ‏يتهارجون ‏ ‏كما ‏ ‏تتهارج ‏ ‏الحمر فعليهم تقوم الساعة)، رواه ابن ماجة.

* عن ‏ ‏أبي سعيد الخدري ‏ عن النبي ‏ ‏صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏ ‏قال: (‏ليحجن ‏ ‏البيت ‏ ‏وليعتمرن بعد خروج‏ يأجوج ومأجوج)، رواه أحمد.

* قال رسول الله ‏ ‏صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏: (‏سيوقد المسلمون من قسي‏ يأجوج ومأجوج ونشابهم ‏ ‏وأترستهم سبع سنين)، رواه ابن ماجة.

3170 - حدثني إسحاق بن نصر: حدثنا أبو أسامة، عن الأعمش: حدثنا أبو صالح، عن أبي سعيد الخدري رضي الله عنه، عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال: (يقول الله تعالى: يا آدم، فيقول: لبيك وسعديك، والخير في يديك، فيقول: أخرج بعث النار، قال: وما بعث النار؟ قال: من كل ألف تسعمائة وتسعة وتسعين، فعنده يشيب الصغير، وتضع كل ذات حمل حملها، وترى الناس سكارى وما هم بسكارى، ولكن عذاب الله شديد). قالوا: يا رسول الله، وأينا ذلك الواحد؟ قال: (أبشروا، فإن منكم رجلا ومن يأجوج ومأجوج ألفا. ثم قال: والذي نفسي بيده، إني أرجو أن تكونوا ربع أهل الجنة). فكبرنا، فقال: (أرجو أن تكونوا ثلث أهل الجنة). فكبرنا، فقال: (أرجو أن تكونوا نصف أهل الجنة). فكبرنا، فقال: (ما أنتم في الناس إلا كالشعرة السوداء في جلد ثور أبيض، أو كشعرة بيضاء في جلد ثور أسود)

من هنا نستدل على أن عدد قوم يأجوج ومأجوج تقريبا يساوي 1000 ضعف عدد العرب. إذا فهم قوم لايعدوا من كثرتهم. لهم نفس وصف الترك [[المغول]] 
(عراض الوجوه، صغار الأعين، سواد الشعر مائل إلى البياض وكأن وجوههم المجان المطرقة، أي ذوي رؤوس مستديرة). كما وصفهم الرسول محمد

''' أحاديث عن يأجوج وماجوج  '''

رسمت الأحاديث النبوية المنسوبة [[محمد بن عبد الله|للرسول محمد صلى الله عليه وسلم]] ملامح أكثر وضوحاً عن عالم &quot;يأجوج&quot; و&quot;مأجوج&quot; وكشفت عن كثير من نواحي الغموض فيهم. فبنيت أن لديهم نظاماً وقائداً يحتكمون لرأيه، وأن السد الذي حصرهم به [[ذو القرنين]] ما زال قائماً، وأنه يمنعهم من تحقيق مطامعهم في غزو الأرض وإفسادها، ولذا فمن حرصهم على هدمه يخرجون كل صباح لحفر هذا السد، حتى إذا قاربوا هدمه أخروا الحفر إلى اليوم التالي، فيأتون إليه وقد أعاده الله أقوى مما كان، فإذا أذن الله بخروجهم حفروا حتى إذا قاربوا على الانتهاء قال لهم أميرهم: ارجعوا إليه غدا فستحفرونه - إن شاء الله - فيرجعون إليه وهو على حاله حين تركوه، فيحفرونه ويخرجون على الناس فيشربون مياه الأنهار، ويمرون على [[بحيرة طبريا|بحيرة طبرية]] فيشربها أولهم، فيأتي آخرهم فيقول: لقد كان هنا ماء !! ويتحصن الناس خوفاً منهم، وعندئذ يزداد غرورهم ويرمون بسهامهم إلى السماء فترجع وعليها آثار الدم فتنةً من الله وبلاءً، فيقولون: قهرنا أهل الأرض وغلبنا أهل السماء، فيرسل الله عليهم دوداً يخرج من خلف رؤوسهم فيقتلهم، فيصبحون طعاماً لدواب الأرض حتى تسمن من كثرة لحومهم. كما روى ذلك [[ابن ماجة]] في سننه.

وقد دلت الأحاديث على أن الزمان الذي يخرجون فيه يملكون أسباب القوة ويتفوقون فيها على سائر الناس، وذلك إما لكونهم متقدمين عسكرياً ووصلوا إلى تقنيات تمكنهم من إبادة غيرهم والسيطرة على بلادهم، وإما لأن زمن خروجهم يكون بعد زوال هذه الحضارة المادية، ورجوع الناس إلى القتال بالوسائل البدائية والتقليدية، ويؤكد ذلك ما ورد عند [[ابن ماجة]]، وورد في بعض الروايات من أن المسلمين سيوقدون من أقواس وسهام وتروس &quot;يأجوج ومأجوج&quot; سبع سنين. كما عند [[ابن ماجة]] وغيره. كما بينت الأحاديث بعض صفاتهم الخلْقية وأنهم عراض الوجوه، صغار العيون، شقر الشعور، وجوهم مدورة كالتروس. رواه أحمد.

وبينت أيضاً مدى كفرهم، وعنادهم وأنهم أكثر أهل النار، 
ففي الحديث أن الله عز وجل يقول لآدم يوم القيامة: أخرج بعث النار، فيقول: وما بعث النار ؟ فيقول الله: من كل ألف تسعمائة وتسعة وتسعين، ففزع الصحابة – رضي الله عنهم – وقالوا: يا رسول الله وأينا ذلك الواحد ؟ فقال – عليه الصلاة والسلام: أبشروا فإن منكم رجلاً ومن يأجوج ومأجوج ألفاً - رواه [[البخاري]].

وبينت الأحاديث كذلك أن خروجهم سيكون في آخر الزمان قرب قيام الساعة، وفي وقت يغلب على أهله الشر والفساد، 

قال - صلى الله عليه وسلم -: لن تقوم الساعة حتى يكون قبلها عشر آيات؛ طلوع الشمس من مغربها، وخروج الدابة، وخروج يأجوج ومأجوج.. - رواه [[أبو داود]]. 

وعندما دخل – صلى الله عليه وسلم – على زوجته زينب بنت جحش - رضي الله عنها – فزعاً وهو يقول: لا إله إلا الله، ويل للعرب من شر قد اقترب، فتح اليوم من سدِّ &quot;يأجوج ومأجوج&quot; مثل هذه، وحلق بإصبعه الإبهام والتي تليها، قالت له زينب: يا رسول الله أنهلك وفينا الصالحون ؟ قال: نعم إذا كثر الخبث - رواه [[البخاري]].

أما ترتيب خروجهم ضمن أشراط الساعة الكبرى فقد دلت الأحاديث على أن الدجال عندما يخرج، ينزل المسيح  بعده، ثم يخرج يأجوج ومأجوج، فيأمر الله عيسى -  - ألا يقاتلهم، بل يتوجه بمن معه من المؤمنين إلى جبل الطور، فيحصرون هناك، ويبلغ بهم الجوع مبلغا عظيماً، فيدعون الله حينئذ أن يدفع عنهم شرهم فيرسل الله عليهم الدود في رقابهم فيصبحون قتلى كموت نفس واحدة، وتمتلئ الأرض من نتن ريحهم، فيرسل الله طيراً كأعناق الإبل فتحملهم وتطرحهم حيث شاء الله. ويأمن الناس وتخرج الأرض بركتها وثمرتها، حتى تأكل الجماعة من الناس الرمانة الواحدة، ويكفي أهل القرية ما يحلبونه من الناقة في المرة الواحدة.

ويحج المسلمون إلى البيت بعد هلاكهم، كما في الحديث: 
ليحجن البيت وليعتمرن بعد خروج يأجوج ومأجوج - رواه [[البخاري]]

''' خروجهم (ياجوج وماجوج) '''

مما سبق فإن ياجوج وماجوج محبوسون خلف ردم من قطع الحديد والنحاس المصهور بين جبلين يوجد هذا الردم السد كما ذكر [[ابن عباس]] في (بلاد الترك) مما يلي [[أرمينيا]] و[[أذربيجان]]. أي في منطقة [[سيبيريا]] الكبيرة. ولم يستطيع أحد الوصول إليهم أو الظهور على موقعهم حتى الآن.

تخرج هذه الأقوام في عهد [[عيسى بن مريم|النبي عيسى بن مريم]] والذي سيعود إلى الأرض حيث يقوم [[عيسى بن مريم|النبي عيسى المسيح]] بقتل [[الدجال (إسلام)|المسيح الدجال]]. مما سيؤدي إلى ظهور ياجوج وماجوج وستكون لهم فتنة عامة وشر مستطير لايملك أحد دفعهم وسيحاصر [[عيسى بن مريم|نبي الله عيسى]] ومن معه في طور [[سيناء]] بأرض [[مصر]]. فيدعون الله فيسلط على ياجوج وماجوج [[دودة|دود]] يخرج في أعناقهم فيقتلهم كميتة رجل واحد وتنت الأرض بجيفهم وروائحم فيدعي [[عيسى بن مريم|نبى الله عيسى]] ومن معه فيرسل الله طيرا تحملهم وتقذف بهم في البحر ثم تهطل الأمطار فتغسل الأرض.

جاء شرحهم مفصل في الحديث التالي في زيادة الجامع الصغير:

تفتح يأجوج ومأجوج فيخرجون على الناس كما قال الله عز وجل من كل حدب ينسلون فيغشون الناس وينحاز المسلمون عنهم إلى مدائنهم وحصونهم ويضمون إليهم مواشيهم ويشربون مياه الأرض حتى إن بعضهم ليمر بالنهر فيشربون ما فيه حتى يتركوه يبسا حتى إن من يمر من بعدهم ليمر بذلك النهر فيقول: قد كان ههنا ماء مرة حتى إذا لم يبق من الناس أحد إلا أحد في حصن أو مدينة قال قائلهم: هؤلاء أهل الأرض قد فرغنا منهم بقي أهل السماء ثم يهز أحدهم حربته ثم يرمي بها إلى السماء فترجع إليه مختضب دما للبلاء والفتنة فبينما هم على ذلك إذ بعث الله عز وجل دودا في أعناقهم كنغف الجراد الذي يخرج في أعناقه فيصبحون موتى لا يسمع لهم حس فيقول المسلمون: ألا رجل يشري لنا نفسه فينطر ما فعل هذا العدو فيتجرد رجل منهم محتسبا نفسه قد أوطنها على أنه مقتول فينزل فيجدهم موتى بعضهم على بعض فينادي يا معشر المسلمين ألا أبشروا إن الله عز وجل قد كفاكم عدوكم فيخرجون من مدائنهم وحصونهم ويسرحون مواشيهم فما يكون لهم مرعى إلا لحومهم فتشكر عنه كأحسن ما شكرت عن شيء من النبات أصابته قط.}}  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/84.229.90.198|84.229.90.198]] ([[User talk:84.229.90.198|talk]]) 04:22, 5 June 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/77.127.125.194|77.127.125.194]] ([[User talk:77.127.125.194|talk]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Russia &amp; Indo-Europeans?? ==

I need to find some links but any time I've ever heard recognized and respected Christian evangelists speak of Gog &amp; Magog, it has been accepted as a reference to Russia. Magog being the ancestor of the Indo-Europeans (scientifically supported with the Indo-European language group and the DNA Y-marker R haplogroup)

How come no-one has managed to include this? Arabs the Bible makes clear in Genesis descend from Abraham via Hagar (Ishmael) and the sons of Ketarah. Prior to this it was the land of Canaan and Ham.

I need to find links to some of the many sermons as this is the Christian world faith :)

[[Special:Contributions/94.168.67.169|94.168.67.169]] ([[User talk:94.168.67.169|talk]]) 07:25, 27 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>fwup6qq38m6rv68rbabam8obl06jonq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
