<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:List of monasteries dissolved by Henry VIII of England</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>147588</id>
    <revision>
      <id>507728089</id>
      <parentid>507728035</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-08-16T19:17:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marauder40</username>
        <id>7651504</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rated for Catholic wikiproject</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5159">{{Anglicanismproject|class=list|importance=low}}
{{Project Catholicism|class=List|importance=low}}

==Name==
How will this work when we come to monasteries that are not just place names - eg the London Charterhouse (or is it really St Someone?) or St Bartholomews' which I don't think can be called anything else i.e. it's not Smithfield Priory etc.?  It might be v v boring to have a huge load of them just going London:This and London:That.

And if we do list some by saint's name will it be St or Saint and which convention on alpha order will we follow?

Questions questions eh? :) [[User:Nevilley|Nevilley]]

:Yes, it's a difficult one, isn't it?  (And by the way, you can spell Guisborough with or without the 'u' - I just checked.)  I've only been using saints' names where there is a possibility of confusion, eg. St Augustine's Abbey in Canterbury isn't in the same place as the cathedral.  And I've been using the town name as the criterion for alphabetical order, because I think that's how people will search for them.  And I'm not really interested in London.  I just thought it might be nice to have a list. --[[User:Deb|Deb]]

Yep it's nice to have a list - I'm not quite sure why one would be &quot;not interested&quot; in London, in an active sort of way (?), in that we've got plenty of dissolved monasteries here too and some are quite interesting! I think your basic strategy is right. I still just don't know what I'm going to do if I do list the two nice ones near me! Maybe I will read up on it a bit more. 

I can't agree with you, with all due respect, about Gisborough, but thanks for checking. I did too, and lived there for many years, and I feel pretty clear that Gisborough is THE correct spelling for the Priory, the Lord, and the Hall, and Guisborough is correct for just about everything else. It was always regarded as a faux pas to respell one of the three as Gui... 

Oh and I like your putting the (m) order in too. Very handy. --[[User:Nevilley|Nevilley]]


:I just meant that I'm not interested in doing London myself, because I don't live there (and wouldn't want to).  Let's face it, there will always be lots of other people who are only too keen to take it on.  Never lived in Gisborough or whatever it's called, either, but I found the 'u' spelling used in a book on abbeys.  There seem to be web sites for both, actually, so I suppose we should have a redirect??? -- [[user:Deb|Deb]]

== Major? ==

What's the point in the adjective &quot;major&quot; in the first sentence, and, if it is going to be left in and observed (which it probably should not be), how is it to be defined? Thanks. [[User:Nevilley|Nevilley]] 08:33, 23 Feb 2004 (UTC)

:No response to this so I'm taking it out. Please feel free to argue. :) [[User:Nevilley|Nevilley]] 08:28, 9 Mar 2004 (UTC)

==Cornwall==
Henry VIII also closed establishments in Cornwall, two i think. At the time Cornwall was recognised as a Duchy and extraterritorial to the English throne a client state if you like. If you are going to recount history please tell all of it and not just some from an Anglo centric point of view.
I come from Penryn in Cornwall and can tell you of a Glassney College that was closed.
This college was a seat of learning using the Cornish language, many works in the Cornish language where produced at Glassney and it was a great blow to the language when it was closed.
:I have added [[Glasney College]] to the list.  However, I am not sure it should be there.  As far as I can see, Glasney was dissolved under [[Edward VI of England|Edward VI]], and not as part of [[Henry VIII of England|Henry VIII]]'s dissolution of the monasteries.  Anyone have any views on whether it should remain on the list? [[User:Skinsmoke|Skinsmoke]] ([[User talk:Skinsmoke|talk]]) 16:52, 3 August 2009 (UTC)
::Now removed from list.  Not dissolved by Henry VIII. [[User:Skinsmoke|Skinsmoke]] ([[User talk:Skinsmoke|talk]]) 00:38, 14 December 2009 (UTC)

== What's the dispute? ==

&quot;The neutrality of this article is disputed. Please see its talk page. 

&quot;These monasteries were dissolved by Henry VIII of England in the Dissolution of the Monasteries. The list is by no means exhaustive, since virtually every town of any size had at least one abbey, priory, convent or friary in it, and often many small houses of monks, nuns, canons or friars.&quot;

Unless there is reason to dispute that some of the identified institution were, in fact, dissolved by Henry VIII, there does not appear to be a basis on which to dispute the article.  If the comments go to an earlier version of the article, then is it appropriate to continue to identify it as disputed?

== Missing monasteries ==

I see that this is not supposed to be an exhaustive list, but what determines which monasteries are included and which are not?

I think Glastonbury Abbey should be included as it is one of only three in which the Abbot was executed for resisting (Henry and Cromwell got him for robbery)

[[User:203.97.107.139|203.97.107.139]] 09:34, 30 March 2007 (UTC)

No comments on this so I've added it in (it was me who made the above comment)

[[User:203.96.59.44|203.96.59.44]] 05:20, 17 July 2007 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>byk8sj6i2fa0rk5ig56ghd3senymjbj</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
