<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:List of Patriarchs of Antioch</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>271038</id>
    <revision>
      <id>412898713</id>
      <parentid>412404132</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-02-09T12:00:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>1ForTheMoney</username>
        <id>5932223</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Assessed as List</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3272">{{WikiProject Biography
|living=no
|class=List
|listas=List of Patriarchs of Antioch
}}
{{WikiProject Christianity|class=List|importance=low|eastern-orthodoxy=yes|eastern-orthodoxy-importance=low|syriac-work-group=yes}}

==Multiple Patriarchs?==
I have a question...when the list gets to the point where Antioch becomes a Crusader state, will there be a list of both Latin and Greek Patriarchs? Or should there be a separate article for the Latin ones? (On the other hand, it may not matter...I can't remember if there were two at the same time, or if they just kept alternating depending on the political situation...) [[User:Adam Bishop|Adam Bishop]]

:Adam, as I started on this article, I soon discovered that the lineage of this Patriachate is very much a mess. Only yesterday did I at last understand where the Syriac/Jacobite Church &amp; the Greek Orthodox churches forked in their lineage, &amp; my most recent edits reflect this. (Although there are still some points in this list where I've probably made the wrong decision in names &amp; dates.)

: My plan at present, is to list in this article the undesputed (well, more or less) line of this office, then link to the Syriac/Jacobite Church &amp; the Greek Orthodox lines, from which there will be linked the branches of the Marionite &amp; Latin lineages. If I can show this to be the cleanest &amp; simplest way to present this information, maybe it will be adopted in the articles on the patriarchs of Alexandria &amp; Jerusalem. (Or maybe I'll show that their way is the best.) -- [[User:Llywrch|llywrch]] 00:10 20 Jul 2003 (UTC)

I would like to add some clarification here, if I may. I think the lists are in good shape, but I think that anyone who is not aquainted with the church traditions of the Near East might just find it a bit awkward to work out who is who.
: [[User:Garzo|Gareth Hughes]] 17:24, 20 Dec 2004 (UTC)

----
Looking at this list after a long time away from it, the I'm finding it a bit hard to follow due to all of the notes that have since been added to it. And yet the notes help explain the history (&amp; politics) of this see. Does anyone else think that it would be more readable if we put this material into a table format? -- [[User:Llywrch|llywrch]] 15:57, 16 August 2006 (UTC)

==Chronology==
There appear to be problems with the dates on this page, for at least two entries that I looked at. These need to be checked with more rigor. In one case, the martyrdom was in the Decian persecution, and Decius died before the date listed here. The second case is the death Euphrasius, which is here dated 528. I noted the source I consulted; looking further shows that Emperor Justin died in 527. My addition of Nicephorus to the references needs formatting; please lend it the help it requires.
[[User:Mallonb|Mallonb]]  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|undated]] comment was added at 05:33, 25 December 2008 (UTC).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!--Template:Undated--&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:As far as Justin is concerned, it it the original historian quoted who was wrong not the 528 date. There is a footnote in the new reference explaining this. But thanks. Could be misleading.[[User:Student7|Student7]] ([[User talk:Student7|talk]]) 14:26, 28 December 2008 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>fxvbx0tx3o9fp246r1stijy4tqsuo9n</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
