<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Homosexuality</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>9594279</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521292374</id>
      <parentid>519121373</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-04T01:51:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MiszaBot I</username>
        <id>3797869</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot: Archiving 3 threads (older than 30d) to [[Talk:Homosexuality/Archive 22]].</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="94441">{{Skip to talk}}
{{Talk header|noarchive=yes}}

{{Not a forum}}
{{Round in circles|search=yes}}
{{ArticleHistory|action1=GAN
|action1date=5 August 2006
|action1link=Talk:Homosexuality/Archive 10#Good article promotion
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=67927549

| action2       = GAR
| action2date   = 19:01, 2 August 2008 (UTC)
| action2link   = Wikipedia:Good article reassessment/Homosexuality/1
| action2result = delisted
| action2oldid  = 229150335

| action3       = GAN
| action3date   = 13:11, 9 January 2010 (UTC)
| action3link   = Talk:Homosexuality/GA1
| action3result = failed
| action3oldid  = 336577694

| action4       = GAN
| action4date   = 08:52, 26 January 2011 (UTC)
| action4link   = Talk:Homosexuality/GA2
| action4result = failed
| action4oldid  = 410080956

|currentstatus=DGA
|topic=Socsci}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|collapsed=yes|1=
{{WikiProject LGBT studies|class=B |importance=top }}
{{WikiProject Philosophy|importance=mid |class=B |ethics=yes |social=yes }}
{{WikiProject Sociology|class=B |importance=High }}
{{WikiProject Sexuality|class=B |importance=Top }}
{{WikiProject Psychology|class=B|importance=top}}
}}
{{To do|small=yes}}
{{archives | auto=yes |search=yes|index=/Archive index 
|bot=MiszaBot I |age=1 |units=month }}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=Talk:Homosexuality/Archive index
|mask=Talk:Homosexuality/Archive &lt;#&gt;
|leading_zeros=0 |indexhere=yes
}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 250K
|counter = 22
|minthreadsleft = 4
|algo = old(30d)
|archive = Talk:Homosexuality/Archive %(counter)d
}}

__TOC__

== Causes of sexual orientation ==

Hey, everyone. Refer to the [[Talk:Sexual orientation#Causes of sexual orientation]] discussion for why I reverted [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Homosexuality&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=515654676 these edits] that were made to the lead. I started the discussion at the [[Sexual orientation]] talk page to keep the discussion, which concerns two other articles, in one place. [[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]] ([[User talk:Flyer22|talk]]) 18:28, 2 October 2012 (UTC)

:With regard to your edit:  ''Scientific and medical understanding is that sexual orientation is not a choice, but rather a complex interplay of biological and environmental factors, especially with regard to early uterine environment.''

:From the APA source:
{{quote box|align=center|width=90%|fontsize=100%|
Although much research has examined the possible genetic, hormonal, developmental, social, and cultural influences on sexual orientation, '''no findings have emerged that permit scientists to conclude that sexual orientation is determined by any particular factor or factors.''' Many think that nature and nurture both play complex roles; '''&lt;u&gt;most&lt;/u&gt; people experience little or no sense of choice about their sexual orientation.'''
}}
:From the AAP article:
{{quote box|align=center|width=90%|fontsize=100%|
Sexual orientation probably is not determined by any one factor but by a combination of genetic, hormonal, and environmental influences.2 In recent decades, '''biologically based theories have been favored by experts'''.
}}

:I assume that we're on the same page with regard to &quot;environmental factors&quot; referring to sociological factors, as opposed to &quot;early uterine environment&quot; referring to biological factors.

:Based on these, I believe that your edit gives excessive weight to the environmental theory, and does so by implicitly synthesizing a conclusion from two different meanings of environment/environmental.
:&amp;ndash; [[user: MrX|MrX]] 19:04, 2 October 2012 (UTC)

::Hello, MrX. I thank you for looking after this article as you so often do. It's always good to have more editors who keep things within appropriate perspective, as, from what I have seen, you have done so far with regard to LGBT topics. I don't entirely understand your above reasoning, though, or why you chose to discuss this here instead of keeping it in one place. But we are partially in agreement that, in the case of these authoritative sources, &quot;environmental factors&quot; refer to sociological factors as opposed to &quot;early uterine environment.&quot; I state &quot;partially&quot; because, as was made clear in the previous discussion about this, &quot;environmental factors&quot; with regard to sexual orientation can refer refer to &quot;uterine environment&quot; and &quot;sociological factors.&quot; Your argument about what &quot;environmental factors&quot; in these cases mean, however, is why I stated that it is explicitly clear that these researchers don't only mean &quot;uterine environment&quot; when they state &quot;environmental factors&quot; or &quot;environmental influences&quot;; they list &quot;hormonal&quot; and &quot;environmental&quot; separately because they state that all of these factors -- biology, hormones (which are considered biological by various reliable sources, including ones on sexual orientation) and social environment -- are involved in a complex interplay when it comes to forming sexual orientation. As noted by the [[American Psychological Association]], which is authoritative, and as you partially cited above, &quot;''There is no consensus among scientists about the exact reasons that an individual develops a heterosexual, bisexual, gay, or lesbian orientation. Although much research has examined the possible genetic, hormonal, developmental, social, and cultural influences on sexual orientation, no findings have emerged that permit scientists to conclude that sexual orientation is determined by any particular factor or factors. Many think that nature and nurture both play complex roles.''&quot; And as also shown above, while the second source you cite states &quot;''In recent decades, biologically based theories have been favored by experts'',&quot; it also states, &quot;''Sexual orientation probably is not determined by any one factor but by a combination of genetic, hormonal, and environmental influences.''&quot; The [[American Psychiatric Association]], which is also authoritative, [http://healthyminds.org/More-Info-For/GayLesbianBisexuals.aspx states]: &quot;''No one knows what causes heterosexuality, homosexuality, or bisexuality... ... Currently there is a renewed interest in searching for biological etiologies for homosexuality. However, to date there are no replicated scientific studies supporting any specific biological etiology for homosexuality. Similarly, no specific psychosocial or family dynamic cause for homosexuality has been identified, including histories of childhood sexual abuse. Sexual abuse does not appear to be more prevalent in children who grow up to identify as gay, lesbian, or bisexual, than in children who identify as heterosexual.''&quot; 

::So, because of all this, [[WP:Consensus]] here was that we should not state that sexual orientation is only biological/hormonal when no authoritative source on sexual orientation states that. The consensus wording was &quot;Scientific and medical understanding is that sexual orientation is not a choice, but rather a complex interplay of [[Biology|biological]] and environmental factors.&quot;, which is supported by the two sources backing that line. That is not [[WP:SYNTHESIS]] or giving [[WP:UNDUE]] to the environmental theory in the least. That is reporting what the authoritative sources on sexual orientation state. As I made clear in the extensive discussion about this, it is not up to us to determine what the researchers mean by &quot;environmental factors&quot; or &quot;environmental influences&quot;; they don't specify what they mean by it, but they do give weight to both &quot;uterine environment&quot; and &quot;sociological factors,&quot; while making it very clear that they don't definitively know what causes sexual orientation. Only recently was the &quot;especially&quot; text about early uterine environment [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Homosexuality&amp;diff=513149737&amp;oldid=510954336 added to the lead.] And this is what followed:[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Homosexuality&amp;diff=513149737&amp;oldid=510954336][http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Homosexuality&amp;diff=513149873&amp;oldid=513149737][http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Homosexuality&amp;diff=513151295&amp;oldid=513149873][http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Homosexuality&amp;diff=513381389&amp;oldid=513341188][http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Homosexuality&amp;diff=513429876&amp;oldid=513381389][http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Homosexuality&amp;diff=513430381&amp;oldid=513429876][http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Homosexuality&amp;diff=513437706&amp;oldid=513430381]

::I have no problem with including &quot;rather a complex interplay of biological, hormonal and environmental factors&quot;...since &quot;hormonal&quot; specifically addresses &quot;early uterine environment,&quot; but it was agreed that &quot;early uterine environment&quot; is covered by &quot;biological.&quot; The only thing I have problem with on this topic is relaying that scientific consensus is that sexual orientation is biological/hormonal only...when the authoritative sources state the opposite of that. [[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]] ([[User talk:Flyer22|talk]]) 20:47, 2 October 2012 (UTC)

:::Admittedly, I neglected to read the linked discussion at the other article, because I was confused. I agree that the possibility of environmental factors should be mentioned in the article, especially if consensus supports it. I propose this wording, based on your last paragraph above:

:::''Scientific and medical understanding of sexual orientation is that it is not a choice. Current theories suggest that sexual orientation may result from a complex interplay of biological, hormonal and environmental factors.''

:::This would address my concern about having two meanings of environment/environmental in the same sentence, and I believe it addresses your concerns as well. &amp;ndash; [[user: MrX|MrX]] 21:42, 2 October 2012 (UTC)
::::Yes, I am fine with that wording, MrX. Thank you. [[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]] ([[User talk:Flyer22|talk]]) 22:24, 2 October 2012 (UTC)

Regarding [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Homosexuality&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=515751852 this revert], I agree that we should discuss this at the Sexual orientation talk page. By that, I mean in one place instead of two. I have already explained there why I object to that revert by [[User:Scientiom|Scientiom]], and I mentioned you there as well, MrX. [[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]] ([[User talk:Flyer22|talk]]) 09:55, 3 October 2012 (UTC)

:I reverted Scientom's ''Temporarily revert to stable version before my edits on October 2nd'' without prejudice to the contents of the edit.  This is a completly inappropriate type of edit.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Little_green_rosetta|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;little&lt;/font&gt; &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;green rosetta&lt;/font&gt;]]{{SubSup||[[Special:Contributions/Little_green_rosetta|central scrutinizer]]|[[User talk:Little green rosetta|(talk)]]}} 15:08, 3 October 2012 (UTC)
::Continuing your stalking of me I see? I think you need to stop this groundless reverting and edit-warring through stalking editors. Per [[WP:BRD]], I returned the lead to the stable version ''before my own edits on October 2nd''. Per [[WP:STATUSQUO]], that is what should be maintained unless consensus says otherwise. --[[User:Scientiom|Scientiom]] ([[User talk:Scientiom|talk]]) 15:19, 3 October 2012 (UTC)
:::Scientiom and I have continued discussion at the Sexual orientation talk page. And like I [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:Sexual_orientation&amp;diff=515873183&amp;oldid=515815236 recently stated to him], the version that he reverted to actually isn't the consensus version. Unless we consider it consensus because no one had objected to it since its September 18, 2012‎ placement. [[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]] ([[User talk:Flyer22|talk]]) 16:12, 3 October 2012 (UTC)
Your claims of &quot;stalking&quot; are bullshit.  This article is on my watchlist.  If you don't want me to revert you, then stop making inappropriate edits.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Little_green_rosetta|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;little&lt;/font&gt; &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;green rosetta&lt;/font&gt;]]{{SubSup||[[Special:Contributions/Little_green_rosetta|central scrutinizer]]|[[User talk:Little green rosetta|(talk)]]}} 22:05, 3 October 2012 (UTC)
:The only one making inappropriate edits here seems to be you.  The change you're trying to edit-war in removes sourced information, and instead adds a redundant term “hormonal” (which is included in “biological”) as an inadequate substitute.  Furthermore, I suggest that it plays into the conservative agenda of casting science you don't like as “theories” in order to imply a negative connotation. —{{SubSup|[[User:Kerfuffler|Kerfuffler]]&amp;nbsp;|[[Special:Contributions/Kerfuffler|forcemeat]]|[[User talk:Kerfuffler|horsemeat]]}} 22:30, 3 October 2012 (UTC)
::I'm not even commenting on the content of the edit.  I don't even '''care''' about this term and the spat some editors are having.  I do care about abuse of process.  Scientom has an issue with following BRD only when it suits them.  This caught my eye when I saw it appear on my watchlist.  I was well within my rights to say that we don't do &quot;temporary reverts&quot;.  We improve articles.  And watch the personal attacks please.  You have no clue as to what my political leanings arre in any case.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Little_green_rosetta|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;little&lt;/font&gt; &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;green rosetta&lt;/font&gt;]]{{SubSup||[[Special:Contributions/Little_green_rosetta|central scrutinizer]]|[[User talk:Little green rosetta|(talk)]]}} 22:41, 3 October 2012 (UTC)
:::Did I misread that, or did you just say you decided to engage in an edit war without bothering to review the content?  Go away, troll. —{{SubSup|[[User:Kerfuffler|Kerfuffler]]&amp;nbsp;|[[Special:Contributions/Kerfuffler|forcemeat]]|[[User talk:Kerfuffler|horsemeat]]}} 22:47, 3 October 2012 (UTC)
::::No I read it. I disagree with Scientom's gaming.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Little_green_rosetta|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;little&lt;/font&gt; &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;green rosetta&lt;/font&gt;]]{{SubSup||[[Special:Contributions/Little_green_rosetta|central scrutinizer]]|[[User talk:Little green rosetta|(talk)]]}} 23:01, 3 October 2012 (UTC)

:::@lgr, I'm trying to understand why you thought it was a good idea to remove 10 sources, not to mention a very relevant piece of content. Do you really not see the significance of same sex relationships being recorded in censuses? &amp;ndash; [[user: MrX|MrX]] 22:52, 3 October 2012 (UTC)
::::No disagreement with the content, nor the sources.  I do disagree with the lead abuse that has been going on here and at many other articles.  If the content is not in the body, it doesn't belong in the lead.  Why is it that some editors feel their &quot;point&quot; must be raised in the lead?&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Little_green_rosetta|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;little&lt;/font&gt; &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;green rosetta&lt;/font&gt;]]{{SubSup||[[Special:Contributions/Little_green_rosetta|central scrutinizer]]|[[User talk:Little green rosetta|(talk)]]}} 23:01, 3 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::The content is in the body, but not in the neat, encapsulated form that you may expect. Keywords: 'census', 'same sex marriage', 'relationships' and 'political'. I can't address your concerns about the lede containing too much, because I just haven't experienced that issue in the ~5000 articles that I've touched. In an article with high visibility like this one, these things works themselves out, through BRD, consensus and other processes. &amp;ndash; [[user: MrX|MrX]] 23:45, 3 October 2012 (UTC)

:::::Yes, Kerfuffler, per what I stated to Scientiom, the reason that it was decided, in the consensus reached last year, not to use &quot;hormonal&quot; is because &quot;biological&quot; can cover &quot;hormonal.&quot; And the reason we didn't include &quot;biological&quot; and &quot;genetic&quot; is because genetics are an aspect of biology, and it is therefore redundant to include &quot;biological&quot; and &quot;genetic&quot;; the sources on this always use one term or the other, even if starting off using the word &quot;biological&quot; before going into specifically stating &quot;genetic,&quot; and we should use one or the other as well. Since the sources use &quot;genetic&quot; (typically anyway, as shown above) and since &quot;genetic&quot; is more specific than &quot;biological,&quot; we should use it in place of &quot;biological.&quot; Instead of adding MrX's wording which includes &quot;theories,&quot; if including &quot;theories&quot; is considered to carry a negative connotation, I feel that we should word it as &quot;rather a complex interplay of genetic, hormonal and environmental factors&quot; and drop &quot;especially with regard to early uterine environment&quot; per my and MrX's reasoning on that; the latter is WP:SYNTHESIS because the sources do not state it or even imply it -- that sexual orientation is especially due to early uterine environment. [[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]] ([[User talk:Flyer22|talk]]) 23:16, 3 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::Let's be clear here.  What the source cited for the “uterine environment” part says is:
::::::{{quote|Despite almost a century of psychoanalytic and psychological speculation, there is no substantive evidence to support the suggestion that the nature of parenting or early childhood experiences play any role in the formation of a person’s fundamental heterosexual or homosexual orientation. It would appear that sexual orientation is biological in nature, determined by a complex interplay of genetic factors and the  early uterine environment.}}
::::::So that actually says: environmental factors (in the sense implied by our text) don't apply at all.  Now, where are you arguing that the [[WP:SYNTH|synthesis]] is, again?  Because it appears to be in a different place. —{{SubSup|[[User:Kerfuffler|Kerfuffler]]&amp;nbsp;|[[Special:Contributions/Kerfuffler|forcemeat]]|[[User talk:Kerfuffler|horsemeat]]}} 23:32, 3 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::::Hello again, Kerfuffler. I have been clear here, very clear, as shown above and at the Sexual orientation talk page. But I'll also be clear that I am not some religious conservative that you have to protect this article from, as many at this site know, since I am getting that feeling from your response to me above. MrX clearly isn't either. I am, however, someone who usually defers to what [[scientific consensus]] states. Like I stated to Scientiom: After I explained to MrX that &quot;''The consensus wording was 'Scientific and medical understanding is that sexual orientation is not a choice, but rather a complex interplay of biological and environmental factors.', which is supported by the two sources backing that line. That is not WP:SYNTHESIS or giving WP:UNDUE to the environmental theory in the least. That is reporting what the authoritative sources on sexual orientation state.&quot;'', he agreed with me. It's all there above, what I stated to MrX and what MrX agreed with. Scientific consensus is not that sexual orientation is only biological/hormonal. [http://www.apa.org/helpcenter/sexual-orientation.aspx This source], [http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/content/113/6/1827.long this source] and [http://healthyminds.org/More-Info-For/GayLesbianBisexuals.aspx this source] above make this very clear. There is no true consensus among scientists on this topic, except that sexual orientation is not a choice. But what most scientists do believe on this topic is that sexual orientation is determined by a complex interplay of genetic, hormonal and environmental factors. The [[Royal College of Psychiatrists]] source stating that &quot;''It would appear that sexual orientation is biological in nature, determined by a complex interplay of genetic factors and the early uterine environment''&quot; does not trump what the other (or more) authoritative sources state on this subject. The Royal College of Psychiatrists source doesn't even state &quot;is&quot;; it states &quot;would appear.&quot; And while it states that &quot;''there is no substantive evidence to support the suggestion that the nature of parenting or early childhood experiences play any role in the formation of a person’s fundamental heterosexual or homosexual orientation,''&quot; the other sources acknowledge that there is no conclusive evidence that sexual orientation is only biological/hormonal. The American Psychiatric Association, for example, states, &quot;''to date there are no replicated scientific studies supporting any specific biological etiology for homosexuality.''&quot; So, in summary, the &quot;especially with regard to early uterine environment&quot; text is WP:SYNTHESIS because none of the sources state or even imply that sexual orientation is especially due to early uterine environment. The Royal College of Psychiatrists source that you cite states &quot;''determined by a complex interplay of genetic factors and the early uterine environment''&quot;; it uses &quot;and,&quot; not &quot;especially,&quot; and its tagged onto the consensus wording as though it supports the other two sources' position that environmental factors, which can be uterine environment or social experiences, are likely included. Again, the other sources report differently than that source, stressing that while biological models are favored by the scientific community, the scientific community does not definitively know what causes sexual orientation; they believe that genetic, hormonal and environmental factors (&quot;environmental&quot; as in covering &quot;social experiences&quot; when &quot;uterine environment&quot; is already covered by &quot;hormonal&quot;) all contribute to the cause of sexual orientation in complex ways. [[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]] ([[User talk:Flyer22|talk]]) 03:49, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
===Section break: Somewhat off-topic===

[[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]], could you explain why you think a discussion on another article justifies any changes to this article?--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 18:28, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
:As shown above, the editor whose edits I reverted -- Scientom -- made the same edits not only to this article, but to the Sexual orientation article and the [[Biology and sexual orientation]] article. It all has to do with reporting what scientists believe to be the causes of sexual orientation, which was part of an extensive discussion at this talk page last year. And instead of revisiting that discussion at three different articles, I chose to have it at one article. The Sexual orientation article seemed (and still seems) the most relevant, as it is the main article for the topic of sexual orientation. It makes no sense to be inconsistent across articles in reporting what scientists state they believe to be the causes of sexual orientation, which is why Scientom made the change to three different articles. A discussion at one article has justified changes at another article plenty of times here at Wikipedia, when the discussion concerns a topic that affects other articles in the way that this does. 

:As for this discussion, like I [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=User_talk:Dominus_Vobisdu&amp;diff=515975150&amp;oldid=515974857#Input_on_wording_for_causes_of_sexual_orientation.3F told] [[User:Dominus Vobisdu|Dominus Vobisdu]], I get the feeling that as soon as &quot;environmental factors&quot; is mentioned, a few editors get the impression that the person stating that is some religious conservative. I am far from that, and contribute to LGBT topics regularly. Above, I mentioned that I'm someone who usually defers to scientific consensus/what most scientists state. That is the case here. Stating that most scientists believe that sexual orientation is determined by a complex interplay of genetic, hormonal and environmental factors is not stating that sexual orientation is a choice or that it can be solely due to environmental (as in social) factors. The keywords are &quot;combination&quot; and &quot;complex interplay.&quot; The sources make clear that sexual orientation is not a choice, but they (two of them) also very clearly state that scientists believe that it is not determined by any one factor...but by a combination of all of these. And as also mentioned, it is not up to us to determine what the researchers mean by &quot;environmental factors&quot; or &quot;environmental influences&quot;; they don't specify what they mean by it, but they do give weight to both &quot;uterine environment&quot; and &quot;sociological factors,&quot; while making it very clear that they don't definitively know what causes sexual orientation. That is my point when it comes to the topic of reporting the causes of sexual orientation. The only problem with the current lead of this article that I have, aside from [[Wikipedia:Bombardment|the oversourcing]] of two lines, is the &quot;especially with regard to early uterine environment&quot; wording; this is because it is WP:SYNTHESIS for the reasons noted above. If the lead stays that way, I won't mind much...since it has been returned to its state of not reporting that sexual orientation is only caused by genetic/hormonal factors. But I did want to try to get others to see why that wording is not best. So far, MrX is the only one here who has acknowledged that; he brought up the WP:SYNTHESIS issue first. Although I saw that synthesis problem from the start, I decided not to remove it because I didn't want to get into a big debate about all of this again. As we can see, that happened anyway. [[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]] ([[User talk:Flyer22|talk]]) 04:32, 5 October 2012 (UTC)

::I am not making any assumptions of you Flyer. Just that, regardless of good intentions, this article and its consensus cannot be overridden by the consensus on the other articles regardless of how logical it may seem. It only creates more problems than it solves. I don't really like giving too much weight to a source because it is &quot;scientific&quot; in regards to sexual identity, preference and desires. My research doesn't differ too much from your own, except I just like to see a wider variety of sources as the scientific community has altered its stance on this in just the last twenty years...drasticly. Homosexuality is not a scientific field and needs the input of a lot of sources to make the claims you are making. Not that I would agree or disagree with it, just that this is so far from a consensus in even that community (scientific, that is) that I would hesitate to claim anything as absolute by that judgement alone.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 04:52, 5 October 2012 (UTC)

:::Amadscientist, I wasn't speaking about you with regard to the religious conservative part. And as for &quot;''this article and its consensus cannot be overridden by the consensus on the other articles'',&quot; I've stated that &quot;''A discussion at one article has justified changes at another article plenty of times here at Wikipedia, when the discussion concerns a topic that affects other articles in the way that this does.''&quot; and I stick by that, as I have seen it time and time again, including at administrative noticeboards. And this discussion is about this article, as is clear from above. It's not just about the Sexual orientation article. It's about three articles, like I stated, and I invited editors from these three articles to discuss this in one place. See above where I stated that the edits concern three different articles. I did not want to discuss the same edit, made to three different articles, in three different places. And I am sure that no one else would have wanted to either, as is clear by most of the discussion having taken place here. Taking a discussion (that concerns multiple articles) to one place is common practice on Wikipedia. I used that common practice in this regard. 

:::About the claims... The claims I made about scientists are claims made by authoritative sources on sexual orientation, and these sources are not from twenty or even ten years ago. They are up-to-date. Homosexuality is a scientific field, according to authoritative sources. What comes with &quot;a wider variety of sources&quot; is a wide variety of personal opinions about sexual orientation from whatever author. Editors would cherry-pick their favorite authors, or favorite lines from whatever book, to support any stance they have on sexual orientation. This is why we are supposed to defer to authoritative bodies for this information. You state that &quot;''this is so far from a consensus in even that community (scientific, that is) that I would hesitate to claim anything as absolute by that judgement alone.''&quot; If you are referring to sexual orientation not being a choice, in addition to it being believed to be a complex interplay of genetic, hormonal and environmental factors... I have to state that from what I have researched, most scientists studying sexual orientation do believe that. They state that sexual orientation is not a choice, that they don't definitively know what causes it...and that they believe that it is a combination of the aforementioned factors. So it does appear that your research differs much from mine. But I don't see this discussion between us as too related to my expressed concerns above, and would rather stay completely on-topic in that regard (that is why I added the &quot;somewhat off-topic&quot; heading). [[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]] ([[User talk:Flyer22|talk]]) 05:45, 5 October 2012 (UTC)

::::(Got this far and decided to comment) ''&quot;A discussion at one article has justified changes at another article plenty of times here at Wikipedia, when the discussion concerns a topic that affects other articles in the way that this does.&quot;'' You will have to demonstrate that and not just claim such and if it isn't to policy then we have a problem right there. (back to the rest of your reply)--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 05:48, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::It's demonstrated all the time on Wikipedia. That you have not experienced it is something I don't know how to reply to. But I certainly don't have to cite an example as though I am citing text in a Wikipedia article. I'm certainly not interested in digging up any one case. And not all practices on Wikipedia are based on policy, as I'm sure you know. [[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]] ([[User talk:Flyer22|talk]]) 05:55, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::If you cannot demonstrate the claims you are making by showing the consensus discussion or the guideline or policy it will, of course, be dismissed. Not out of hand but as a matter of local consensus. You don't get to take over this article with a consensus from somewhere else without justifying it to the satisfaction of the involved parties.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 06:01, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::::You can claim that &quot;Homosexuality is a scientific field, according to authoritative sources&quot; but as above if you can't demonstrate it, its just original research. There are many areas of academia that study sexuality and the scientific community is but one and, as I said, they are not all in agreement. If you don't show even the mainstream objections or opposing opinion of whatever validity it may have then you would be pushing POV. Not that you are, but you have to understand this is an encyclopedia (which I am sure you do understand, but...) and in such we don't use what we strongly believe in. We weigh the sources and lay out the best argument, discussion or explanation in prose. I don't think you are doing that by relying strictly on the one opinion of one part of the scientific community. And I actually believe I had no choice in being gay, but there are other people who may have had a different experiance than me and we cannot dismiss everyone but ourselves, as we cannot dismiss all other sorces but the ones we feel strongly about.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 06:09, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::::About the practice... You can dismiss it of course. But I've explained sufficiently above that this isn't about &quot;tak[ing] over this article with a consensus from somewhere else.&quot; It's about discussing, in one place, the same edits made to three articles; since I informed the editors of those articles of the discussion concerning the edits made to their respective articles, this means that people from all of those articles would be discussing and deciding on the wording for their respective articles. Discussions about an article's text do not always happen at the article's talk page. Sometimes...they happen at a related article's talk page, a noticeboard, or an editor's talk page. I'm not sure how you haven't experienced that, especially since it is often the case with dispute resolution. But anyway... What is also already clear is that WP:CONSENSUS at this article is for the wording that I was arguing for; wording that was decided last year. There was no consensus achieved for the current wording of &quot;especially with regard to early uterine environment&quot;; nor should consensus matter in a WP:SYNTHESIS case. 

::::::::As for claims again... The sources above this section show that homosexuality is a scientific field. Sexual orientation, which includes homosexuality, is a scientific field. I can demonstrate that easily, but it's not my job to supply you with sources. And I don't have to debate with them; I sometimes choose to, but it's certainly not an every-time thing. You can just as easily go to [[Google Books]] and [[Google Scholar]] yourself and see that homosexuality is discussed within a scientific context, even though that is already clear from the sources above this section and many in this article. Clearly, we are defining &quot;scientific field&quot; differently. And I never stated that scientists are all in agreement about the topic of sexual orientation, nor have I ever implied that. What I did state is what authoritative sources state. And mainstream objections? It's mainstream scientific belief that sexual orientation is a choice, for example? Not from what I've read, and I've read a lot on the topic. We don't give [[WP:UNDUE WEIGHT]] to minority views and certainly not to [[WP:FRINGE]] views. Going by authoritative sources has nothing to do with my personal POV or what I strongly believe in, other than my belief that authoritative sources are what we should defer to...per the reasons I've already gone over. [[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]] ([[User talk:Flyer22|talk]]) 06:47, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::You are really not doing anything but talking (or typing) and are so incorrect about Wikipedia guidelines. You really do want this article to state as indisputable fact what you feel regardless of other mainstream opinion and are indeed pushing POV if you refuse to allow other mainstream opinion with due weight. That doesn't mean it has to be the same weight, but then we also dont place romance before sexuality on an article about sexuality. And as for DR I will tell you this- if a discussion has not been made on the artcile that the dispute is about I would kick it back to the articles talk page as not having extensive discussion. As was mentioned before, editors on the article itself being altered should not be excluded for your own conveniance.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 07:20, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::::It's not an article on sexuality, it's an argument on homosexuality, which includes romantic attraction, not just sexual. [[User:StillStanding-247|I&amp;#39;m StillStanding (24/7)]] ([[User talk:StillStanding-247|talk]]) 07:27, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::::Amadscientist, I consider you to be doing nothing but talking (or typing) in this regard as well. At least I have pointed to reliable sources on this particular subject, authoritative ones at that. And I stated nothing of Wikipedia guidelines. I stated that &quot;''Discussions about an article's text do not always happen at the article's talk page. Sometimes...they happen at a related article's talk page, a noticeboard, or an editor's talk page.''&quot; And that statement is 100% correct, as many at this site know. Since you like visiting administrator [[User:Dennis Brown|Dennis Brown]]'s talk page, an editor I am acquaintances with, why don't you ask him about it? I am going by mainstream opinion with regard to what I stated above about scientists' beliefs. That is what is meant by &quot;authoritative sources&quot; in this respect. You have offered none that counter those beliefs. It does not bother me in the least that you attribute my deferring to authoritative sources to POV-pushing, because POV-pushing is not at all connected with me on this topic or any topic on Wikipedia. And as you can see, we do indeed &quot;place romance before sexuality on an article about sexuality.&quot; But if you want &quot;sexual&quot; to come before &quot;romantic,&quot; I wouldn't throw a fuss about it. As long as &quot;romantic&quot; stays...per the authoritative sources. You don't have to tell me anything about dispute resolution. I know all about it; I'm not a newbie. Yes, you would &quot;kick it back to the article['s] talk page as not having extensive discussion,&quot; but many at this site, including me at times, would not. Extensive discussion about an article's text can happen at places beside that's article talk page, as I've made very clear. That is what I have seen happen with many disputes, including at the [[Wikipedia:Dispute resolution noticeboard]]. No editors were excluded for my own convenience. I don't know what isn't clear about &quot;''since I informed the editors of those articles of the discussion concerning the edits made to their respective articles, this means that people from all of those articles would be discussing and deciding on the wording for their respective articles.''&quot; [[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]] ([[User talk:Flyer22|talk]]) 07:49, 5 October 2012 (UTC)

Seeing it happen does not mean it is the correct manner to work towards a collaborative consensus. You would seriously drag Dennis Brown into this? (And its getting really fucking annoying the way you discuss me and where I &quot;like visiting&quot; on Wikipedia. Discuss the contribution and not the contributer) If you want to canvass others go for it. You made what &quot;you believe&quot; clear, but actually do refuse to demonstrate it on this article and I really am not interested in what you believe or feel. Just show disputing editors where you are getting these &quot;accepted practices&quot; to form a consensus for multiple articles on one location, because DR is only referring to talkpages as in - if disputing editors are at least discussing on their own talkpages and even then we still could make the two discuss on the article's talkpage to allow editors on that page the opportunity to add to the discussion. We don't accept a consenus formed on one article across two or three other articles.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 08:12, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
:No, I would not like to drag Dennis Brown into this. I asked you why don't you ask him a question about what you so wrongly dispute. It wasn't meant to be a serious suggestion; it was meant to show that others have seen what I have seen. And it's quite rich of you to tell me to &quot;''Discuss the contribution and not the contribut[o]r''&quot;...when I was doing just that. You are the one who made this personal. And what I made clear is not only what &quot;[I] believe&quot; I made clear. Calling me a liar (and don't state that you didn't; implying it is strong enough), despite evidence all over Wikipedia concerning what I stated about talk page practices, including at the aforementioned Wikipedia:Dispute resolution noticeboard, is quite laughable. Pointing to that noticeboard is demonstrating that &quot;''[d]iscussions about an article's text do not always happen at the article's talk page,''&quot; despite the fact that whatever discussion was had at the article's talk page first. Discussions about the article's text do not always happen at the article's talk page or at the article's talk page first. And again, you are wrong on that last point. The consensus would be concerning their respective articles. It would not be a consensus about one article being applied to another. What you don't grasp about having a discussion about the same edits (made to multiple articles) in one place, I will never know. You state that you aren't interested in what I believe or feel, even though you clearly are, as evidenced above. But you know what? I'm not interested in what you believe or feel. I'd just rather not let your assertions go unchallenged. After this Homosexuality article drama you have started is over, do avoid me in the future. [[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]] ([[User talk:Flyer22|talk]]) 08:47, 5 October 2012 (UTC)

::What I see is this article veering a little off from the body. The  Etymology section states '''&quot;sexual attraction, activity, and orientation&quot;'''. What is wrong with that for the lede.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 08:33, 5 October 2012 (UTC)



:::A few comments... take them for what little they may be worth:

:::*On &quot;sexual attraction, activity and orientation&quot;, I can see that phrase being used in the lede, perhaps in such a fashion (if it can be made to fit): &quot;Homosexuality, which encompasses aspects of sexual attraction, activity and/or orientation...&quot; - with the &quot;and/or&quot; being in there based on the more expansive body's explanation.

:::*&quot;other articles not relevant/relevant&quot; - this is a rather silly argument. Facts are this, which fit within Wikipedia's Guidelines. If another article (or section thereof) discusses the *same* topic, and holds a different position, then the matter '''IS''' related. That may seem like something inexplicable to some, so let me explain. If &quot;Article A&quot; says &quot;X... Z...&quot; on a matter, and &quot;Article B&quot; says &quot;Y... Z...&quot;, '''and''' both articles are discussing the same subject, then what that shows is that editors have not done their due diligence on one or both articles (whether through not knowing about or caring about the other article - or whatever reason), and are presenting an incomplete account of the subject matter. Either Article A, or Article B or '''BOTH''' articles need to be modified to incorporate '''and/or''' remove information so that both articles/sections of articles are consistently showing a non-POV pushing, no OR, neutral representation of the subject matter. Since we are now aware there are differences in the portrayal of the subject matter, doesn't it behoove us to figure out (a) why, and (b) which article(s) need to be fixed?

::::Does that make sense? As a simple example, if two articles on the same subject say opposing things, then perhaps (a) they both should have content added that the other has to show a lack of bias in the presentation of the subject matter, and/or (b) they should both be reviewed for bias and due weight, and/or (c) a variety of other things. 

::::Back to the '''simple fact''' part - in this reality, it is '''not possible''' for &quot;Subject A&quot; to be one thing - but magically change to something else simply because someone went to a different page on Wikipedia - one or both articles should be properly reviewed to figure out why such is happening, and then work on fixing such. And of course, which I shouldn't have to say, all such changes I propose above should fit within guidelines, policies, etc, etc...

:::As for the rest, didn't we discuss the &quot;environmental&quot; part before? Also, as I believe we agreed upon before, in all such relevant sections, in some wording or another, &quot;complex interplay&quot; and each parameter, should be noted. 

:::&lt;small&gt;[[User:RobertMfromLI|R&lt;small&gt;OBERT&lt;/small&gt;M&lt;small&gt;FROM&lt;/small&gt;LI]] &lt;/small&gt;&amp;#124;&lt;small&gt;&lt;small&gt; &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:RobertMfromLI|TK]]&lt;/sup&gt;/&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/RobertMfromLI|CN]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 20:25, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
===Centralized discussions===
(edited for brevity as much as possible) Thank you for the reply as well as the above explanation which actually makes a great deal of sense as does the explanation given by Flyer, however, I don't believe Wikipedia guidelines allow this. Here are all the guidelines/policies in regards to using a centralized discussion. 

(The following are in no particular order and my have added emphasis not in the original)

1) [[WP:CONADMIN]] ''&quot;In some cases, disputes are personal or ideological rather than mere disagreements about content, and these '''may require the intervention of''' administrators or '''the community as a whole'''. Sysops will not rule on content, but may intervene to enforce policy (such as WP:BLP) or to impose sanctions on editors who are disrupting the consensus process inappropriately.&quot;''

2) [[WP:Canvassing|Canvassing]], [[Wikipedia:Sock puppetry|sock puppetry]], and [[WP:MEAT|meat puppetry]]. '''Any effort to gather participants to a community discussion that has the effect of biasing that discussion is unacceptable.''' While it is [[Wikipedia:Canvassing#Friendly notices|fine]]&amp;nbsp;– even encouraged&amp;nbsp;– to invite people into a discussion to obtain new insights and arguments, '''it is [[Wikipedia:Canvassing#Inappropriate notification|not acceptable]] to invite only people favorable to a particular point of view, or to invite people in a way that will prejudice their opinions on the matter.''' Using an alternative persona (&quot;sock puppet&quot;, or &quot;sock&quot;) to influence consensus is absolutely forbidden. '''Neutral, informative messages to Wikipedia noticeboards, WikiProjects, or editors are permitted; but actions that could reasonably be interpreted as an attempt to &quot;stuff the ballot box&quot; or otherwise compromise the consensus-building process are considered disruptive editing.'''

3) [[WP:CONLIMITED]] '''&quot;Consensus among a limited group of editors, at one place and time, cannot override community consensus on a wider scale.''' For instance, unless they can convince the broader community that such action is right, '''participants in a WikiProject cannot decide that some generally accepted policy or guideline does not apply to articles within its scope.&quot;'''

4) [[Wikipedia:Canvassing]] Vote-stacking: Posting messages to users selected based on their known opinions (which may be made known by a [[Wikipedia:Userboxes|userbox]], [[Wikipedia:User categories|user category]], or prior statement).&lt;ref&gt;See [[WP:False consensus]] for a series of finding by the Arbitration Committee concerning vote-stacking and improper CANVASS&lt;/ref&gt; '''[[Votebank|Vote-banking]] involves recruiting editors perceived as having a common viewpoint for a [[:Category:Wikipedia collaborations|group]], similar to a political party, in the expectation that notifying the group of any discussion related to that viewpoint will result in a numerical advantage, much as a form of prearranged vote stacking.'''

According to WP:Canvassing: &quot;An editor who may wish to draw a wider range of informed, but uninvolved, editors to a discussion might place a message at one of the following:
*The talk page of one or more [[Wikipedia:WikiProject|WikiProjects]] (or other [[Wikipedia:Collaborations|Wikipedia collaborations]]) directly related to the topic under discussion.
* A '''[[Wikipedia:Centralized discussion|central location]]''' (such as the [[Wikipedia:Village pump|Village pump]] or other relevant [[Wikipedia:Noticeboards|noticeboards]]) for discussions that have a wider impact such as [[Wikipedia:Policies and guidelines|policy or guideline]] discussions.&quot;

'''[[Wikipedia:Centralized discussion]]''' &quot;Cent is generally used to draw attention to discussions regarding policies, guidelines or other matters that have a wide impact and on which a broad consensus is needed. Announcements, such as for ArbCom elections, etc, are generally done via the Watchlist notice or the Sitenotice. Discussions related to content, including use of infoboxes and templates within a specific topic area, are usually best advertised within the appropriate WikiProjects.&quot; - &quot;Discussions listed on Cent are about matters that are significant enough to require a broad consensus. See Wikipedia:Canvassing for guidance on the appropriate way to gain attention. Some discussions may also be listed on Wikipedia:Requests for comment.&quot;

;Appropriate
*Discussions on existing policies, guidelines and procedures
*Discussions on proposed policies, guidelines and procedures
*Discussions on matters that have a wide impact

;Inappropriate
*Announcements – see [[Wikipedia:Community portal]], [[MediaWiki:Watchlist-details]], or [[MediaWiki:Sitenotice]]
*Content disputes – see [[Wikipedia:Dispute resolution requests]]
*Topic specific discussions – see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject]]
*Minor matters, housekeeping, article content discussions, or maintenance  – see [[WP:Bold]] or [[Wikipedia:Talk page guidelines]].
*General ideas or proposals, reviving dead Projects, technical issues, or any other matters that would be better suited to [[Wikipedia:Village pump]]

I realize this is long and many may not take the time to read, So I apologise for the length.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 06:02, 6 October 2012 (UTC)

:Using [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Council/Guide]] we may find some very useful information for &quot;topic coordination&quot;. ''&quot;If you just want to do a little bit of topic coordination because you want to co-ordinate across just a few pages, you might find the ideas in the following sections useful. (This is especially helpful when a task force is involved.)&quot;'' Create a WikiProject Task Force or Work Group if one has not already been started. Use the Task Force/Work Group page to list tasks and projects within Wikipedia Guidelines, but still very similar to a centralized discussion. There is even a template!

:'''Topic coordination on a talk page''' 

Here's one example of how to go about a topic coordination on a talk page. There are no doubt other ways; if you come across something else that works well for you, feel free to document it here. The example below uses Tulips.

# Post a note on the [[Talk:Tulip]] page (this being the primary page for the tulips articles), saying:
## Your goal: that you want to try to get at least a Start-class article on each of the different species of Tulip
## Your to-do list: list all the articles as intra-wiki links, and encourage people to put their name next to one that they're volunteering for, or have done. You will also want to see [[Wikipedia:To-do list]]
# Do a little networking: link from the other talk pages back to your section of the main one, using [[Template:Topic co-ordination link]]


{{Topic co-ordination link
|Tulip|
*[[Tulipa batalinii]]
*[[Tulipa turkestanica]]
|name = Tulip
}}

I note that the goal here is individual improvement of related articles and not to form a single consensus across articles. I would suggest contacting one of the main WikiProject Council editors such as [[User:John Carter]] who appears to be the most active.

&lt;sub&gt;(The above example may seem innappropriate. My apologies, however it is straight from the Project council guidelines and autogenerates this page name into the temple. No way to control that)&lt;/sub&gt; 
--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 06:19, 6 October 2012 (UTC)

:Ok, enough.  If you have an issue with Flyer22 then take it to dispute resolution, do not clog up the talk page here with accusations and policy quotes.  I assure you however you will not get very far as absolutely nothing has been done wrong.

:I don't want to dwell on the guidelines, this is just fyi, but I'm not entirely sure you get the point of the concepts you quote as there clearly has been no canvassing and the &quot;centralised discussion&quot; concept as well as the Wikiproject Guide discuss issues the are more high level than simple content disputes over a couple of pages, as the WP:CENT page states itself.   The most relevant thing above to content discussions is also a guideline you don't quote, the [[Wikipedia:Talk page guidelines|talk page guidelines]], and particularly,

::&quot;'''Avoid posting the same thread in multiple forums.''' ''This fragments discussion of the idea. Instead, start the discussion in one location, and, if needed, advertise that in other locations using a link. If you find a fragmented discussion, it may be desirable to move all posts to one location, and linking to it. Make sure you state clearly in edit summaries and on talk pages what you have done and why.''&quot;

:Besides all of this, the guidelines are not legal documents, they are there to provide guidance in building the encyclopaedia and resolving differences, not be used to start petty arguments.  Note particularly the page [[Wikipedia:Gaming_the_system|gaming the system]] and its linked concepts. While we're at it the :tldr walls of text are getting disruptive, lets keep things concise. I hope this will be the end of the issue and the page can be returned to discussion of improving the articles. [[User:ChiZeroOne|ChiZeroOne]] ([[User talk:ChiZeroOne|talk]]) 09:51, 6 October 2012 (UTC)
::Besides not realizing that this discussion is about improving the article (actually several of them) you also just made an accusation of gaming the system? Was that really needed? A wall of text is meant to be just that...a wall. This was not, nor do I believe Flyers were. Some of us have no problem writing and reading extensive discussion....which is, by the way, pretty much required for collaboration and consensus, not to mention if an editor were to want to request help to resolve any dispute that may have arisen. Also...you can't ignore a rule to improve the article unless you know what it is. I assume that was your point about not being a &quot;legal documents&quot;.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 13:22, 6 October 2012 (UTC)
:::.*Sigh*.  No I did not accuse you of anything, I referred you to a page discussing how not to use policy and guidelines.  But fine, if you want to continue I'm sure the admins will love you... [[User:ChiZeroOne|ChiZeroOne]] ([[User talk:ChiZeroOne|talk]]) 13:36, 6 October 2012 (UTC)
::::While it is great that you attempted to help, you failed to check either mine or Flyers talkpages to see that we do not have a problem with each other. The above post is in regards to another user's comment and was an attempt to help find the actual guidelines so that if there was an onging interest in topic coordination, a suggestion of a Task force or work group through the project seems to be the best route. Perhaps not, but it is a good suggestion. You actually did accuse me of a few things and just an FYI the canvassing guidelines are part of the overall issue of cross posting and relate to the others as being what policy and guidelines we have on the subject being discussed. You are not AGF. Your directing an editor to [[Wikipedia:Gaming_the_system|gaming the system]] may certainly be taken in the same light. Also, if you feel admin should be concerned please file at AN/I.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 22:53, 6 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::Yes, as shown in the [[#Is romance dead?!]] section below, Amadscientist and I made a truce. Amadscientist, what ChiZeroOne pointed to about &quot;Avoid posting the same thread in multiple forums.&quot; is exactly what I was doing. While I appreciate your pointing to other avenues that can be taken, I believe that I acted appropriately per what ChiZeroOne pointed to in that regard. But if you want to discuss this further, you are welcome to comment on my talk page about it as to not keep this mostly off-topic aspect of the discussion going on here. [[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]] ([[User talk:Flyer22|talk]]) 17:06, 7 October 2012 (UTC)

::::::No worries Flyer. I have no idea where you have been posting and don't want you to assume I was referring to any behavior, just the things we were discussing. I am not at all worried about you.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 17:27, 7 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::::Yeah, I know that you were speaking of the &quot;Causes of sexual orientation&quot; postings, not my behavior in general, LOL. It's not often that I have to tackle centralizing discussions. [[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]] ([[User talk:Flyer22|talk]]) 17:43, 7 October 2012 (UTC)

== Research is research, especially when cherry-picking ==

From the article: &quot;research has shown that homosexuality is an example of normal variation in human sexuality and is not in and of itself a source of negative psychological effects&quot;

Always good to let people know how to think about an article right off the bat - saves the need for critical thinking. I'm guessing that ALL research says this; otherwise why would be in the summary part of the article - the part that should be the most balanced? 

LOL wikipedia, the standards of your guardians are so very low. The same people who always wants to know who funds a study they don't like, are the first to be completely oblivious to the fact that almost all &quot;unbiased&quot; sex research is performed by people who severely diverge from the norm in their own sexuality and are desperate to change what is considered normal to include themselves. 

All you have to do is look - will the person who erases this look into this? No, because that person both already knows the truth of this, but they don't want it to be, so they change words. But facts and the world never changes, whatever the perceptions of the proles. This place is run by our modern day Mr. Charrington's.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/184.59.74.196|184.59.74.196]] ([[User talk:184.59.74.196|talk]]) 01:00, 3 October 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:How do I become a Wikipedia Guardian? It sounds like a cool title. [[User:HiLo48|HiLo48]] ([[User talk:HiLo48|talk]]) 02:22, 3 October 2012 (UTC)

:&quot;''...are the first to be completely oblivious to the fact that almost all &quot;unbiased&quot; sex research is performed by people who severely diverge from the norm in their own sexuality and are desperate to change what is considered normal to include themselves.''&quot; {{cn}}

:Funnily enough I actually agree with your main point though, Wikipedia should let the sources talk. [[User:ChiZeroOne|ChiZeroOne]] ([[User talk:ChiZeroOne|talk]]) 10:53, 3 October 2012 (UTC)

::Any constructive proposals or did you just feel the need for bickering? By the way, the sources are in agreement with the statement you criticize.--[[User:Dvd-junkie|DVD-junkie]] | [[User talk:Dvd-junkie|talk]] | 15:05, 3 October 2012 (UTC)

:::Why must other people come up with &quot;constructive proposals&quot;, but not yourself? I was just pointing out the hypocrisy in what the editor was saying. And quote the sources providing evidence that sex researchers are all lgbt, thanks. [[User:ChiZeroOne|ChiZeroOne]] ([[User talk:ChiZeroOne|talk]]) 15:24, 3 October 2012 (UTC)

::::The text quotes the APA stating that &quot;research consistently failed to produce any empirical or scientific basis for regarding homosexuality as a disorder or abnormality, rather than a normal and healthy sexual orientation&quot; and that that &quot;homosexuality per se implies no impairment in judgment, stability, reliability, or general social or vocational capabilities.&quot; Since the text already corresponds to the sources why should I propose a change? By the way, I never stated that sex researchers are lgbt.--[[User:Dvd-junkie|DVD-junkie]] | [[User talk:Dvd-junkie|talk]] | 19:06, 5 October 2012 (UTC)

== Is romance dead?! ==

A recent edit removed the part about homosexuality involving a ''romantic'' as well as sexual attraction. I have no idea why this was done. It's quite easy to find reliable sources, particularly high-quality academic ones, which include romance and affection. [http://books.google.com/books?id=vbu2gis26C0C&amp;pg=PA450&amp;lpg=PA450&amp;dq=homosexuality+romantic+attraction&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=GYiNgsJMEl#v=onepage&amp;q=homosexuality%20romantic%20attraction&amp;f=false] Does anyone oppose restoring it? [[User:StillStanding-247|I&amp;#39;m StillStanding (24/7)]] ([[User talk:StillStanding-247|talk]]) 20:48, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
:I restored it. It's a completely unjustified removal with no need to discuss. [[User:Teammm|&lt;span style=&quot;color:black;font-family: fantasy&quot;&gt; '''''Teammm'''''&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Teammm|'''&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;T&lt;/font&gt;''']][[Special:EmailUser/Teammm|'''&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;M&lt;/font&gt;''']]&lt;/sup&gt; 21:41, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
::That seems reasonable. [[User:StillStanding-247|I&amp;#39;m StillStanding (24/7)]] ([[User talk:StillStanding-247|talk]]) 21:42, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
:::There is nothing on Wikipedia involving removal or addition of content &quot;with no need to discuss&quot;. I have provided a clear reasoning and if there are sources, provide them. At the moment this is undue weight and original research.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 21:52, 4 October 2012 (UTC)

::::This has once again been re-added without discussion and therefore I feel inclined to use another revert as no explanation has been offered or anything to demonstrate that romance should be used as an encyclopedic manner in describing sexuality. I do feel that there may well be some sources that can be found and its use in the article may be useful, but not in this manner.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 22:12, 4 October 2012 (UTC)

:::::There's no such thing as a &quot;last revert&quot;.  I'm perfectly willing to block someone for edit warring if they make less than 4 reverts. --[[User:Floquenbeam|Floquenbeam]] ([[User talk:Floquenbeam|talk]]) 22:14, 4 October 2012 (UTC)

Just going to note that I've made a total of 0 reverts. It would be interesting to see a block for that! [[User:StillStanding-247|I&amp;#39;m StillStanding (24/7)]] ([[User talk:StillStanding-247|talk]]) 22:16, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
:Well, yes, I would generally require at least one. But in case I wasn't clear, that wasn't directed at you. --[[User:Floquenbeam|Floquenbeam]] ([[User talk:Floquenbeam|talk]]) 22:18, 4 October 2012 (UTC)

:::::I am really mystified as to why Amadscientist insists that homosexuality excludes &quot;romantic attraction&quot;. Isn't this incontrovertible? &amp;ndash; [[user: MrX|MrX]] 22:21, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::Of course its not. One small mention from one web source[http://www.apa.org/helpcenter/sexual-orientation.aspx] does not mean we add it to the lede. Sexuality is an erotic desire. [http://books.google.com/books?id=DYTcx7FFSpMC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Homosexuality&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=ELhE5ERPKw&amp;sig=n7j_63y2oVPA1PzlVBByuaP9DpA&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=_gpuUOvvF4SoiALD4IGgBA&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Homosexuality&amp;f=false] Introduction page ten.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 22:26, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::::Love, not romance is better used here. [http://books.google.com/books?id=5042PWHyp9gC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Homosexuality&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=uUTRE9i8EN&amp;sig=S_u_EJortUfh8ntd4MQr1r2pdvY&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=Jg1uUM3IJ4bwiwKR2IH4CQ&amp;ved=0CDwQ6AEwAg] Pg 10.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 22:30, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::::I'm thinking maybe that the [[American Psychological Association]] might be somewhat authoritative in this matter. By the way, citing a book written 45 years ago really doesn't lend much credence to your argument. &amp;ndash; [[user: MrX|MrX]]
:::::::::OK, true about the older reference, but that was only one. And no, the American Psychological Association is not the ONLY authority and should not be held as such.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 22:44, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
{{od}}Correct, it's not the only authority. However, it's more reliable than most, so we should follow [[WP:UNDUE]] by favoring it. [[User:StillStanding-247|I&amp;#39;m StillStanding (24/7)]] ([[User talk:StillStanding-247|talk]]) 22:45, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::I am unfamiliar with this interpretation of the guideline. Could you explain how you arrived at that?--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 23:15, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
{{od}}[[WP:UNDUE]] talks about the need to put reliable mainstream sources in the forefront, with some mention of minority sources and little to no mention of fringe sources. Later on that page[[Wikipedia:UNDUE#Good_research]], it explicitly talks about scientific articles being more reliable. [[User:StillStanding-247|I&amp;#39;m StillStanding (24/7)]] ([[User talk:StillStanding-247|talk]]) 23:21, 4 October 2012 (UTC)

:Nothing about favoring a source, just balance between mainsteam academic sources and lesser counter argument sources that should only be given due weight to their own main stream opinion, not whether one source is better than another and therefore should be favored. Strength of RS is based on a number of things and that source is not as strong as many that are available and may not have the same definition.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 23:29, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
::Amadscientist, authoritative sources on sexual orientation, such as the American Psychological Association (noted above) and the [[American Psychiatric Association]] (see [http://healthyminds.org/More-Info-For/GayLesbianBisexuals.aspx here]), include &quot;romantic&quot; when it comes to defining sexual orientation. Sexual orientation is discussed this way -- including romantic and/or sexual attraction -- in many academic sources. [[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]] ([[User talk:Flyer22|talk]]) 04:46, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
:::So then we just default to a definition supplied by the American Psychological Association's website and the American Psychiatric Association because they decided to include something that may or may not even be a sexual, erotic asscoation, desire or attraction? No...we don't. This is clearly undue weight just by adding the single descripter of Romantic. I even made the mistake of mentioning love, but that is still not an actual homosexual feeling men can love men and women can love women and not be at all homosexual. Look, the fact is romance has a meaning that is being id not being correctly applied in this manner and I do dispute that this is mainstream academic perception. That is what is important. Not whether or not one community within academia thinks this.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 05:09, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
::::We default to authoritative sources. Like I told you at [[#Section break: Somewhat off-topic]], &quot;''What comes with 'a wider variety of sources' is a wide variety of personal opinions about sexual orientation from whatever author. Editors would cherry-pick their favorite authors, or favorite lines from whatever book, to support any stance they have on sexual orientation. This is why we are supposed to defer to authoritative bodies for this information.''&quot; Adding the descriptor &quot;romantic&quot; is not undue in the least, per above. And as for romance being connected to sexual feelings... A lot of people report them as connected. When a person says they are &quot;in love&quot; with someone, it usually carries a sexual connotation with it. Otherwise, they'd just state that they love the person...as in &quot;I love my mother.&quot; Most people don't state that they are &quot;in love&quot; with their mothers. [[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]] ([[User talk:Flyer22|talk]]) 06:05, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::::Sorry, but you are simply incorrect. We do not default to any single opinion. That is a little outrageous for Wikipedia. We have to balance the information IF there is indeed varying opinion and give it the weight it deserves in mainstream sources. But, again all we are discussing is one web source and a mention of another supposed source without a reference.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 07:05, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::::Nope, you are incorrect. We go by authoritative sources when it comes to initially defining a topic that has varying views. Other views can be included, as long as they are given due weight. If it was a little outrageous for Wikipedia, WP:UNDUE and [[WP:FRINGE]] wouldn't exist. [[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]] ([[User talk:Flyer22|talk]]) 08:04, 5 October 2012 (UTC)   
::::::Amadscientist, it seems like you have studied etymology. If so I'm sure you know that etymology is not always accurate. There are things called misnomers that suggest they mean one thing and mean something else or mean what you think it means plus something else. A great example is antisemitism. Antisemitism literally means anti (against) semitic (middle eastern and sometimes asian origins). The word means discrimination, prejudice or hatred of Jewish people but you would thing it would include all semitic peoples. Homosexuality does include romantic attraction and I'm sure that there are hundreds of sources that could be found to support that. Homosexuality is not only an action (some debate it as an action at all) its a biological based predisposition towards a romantic or sexual attraction to members of one's own sex or gender.-[[User:Rainbowofpeace|Rainbowofpeace]] ([[User talk:Rainbowofpeace|talk]]) 06:44, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::::I am not convinced that the scientific community agrees with that. In fact I am sure they do not agree with it. I know it is the case with me...but I also know it is not the case with many I have known. We are seriously overlooking the information about bisexuality and how environment does effect such behavior and desire and the are hundreds of sources that discuss this and how even bisexuality can lead some (perhaps not a mjority, but some) bisexuals into a homosexual relationship.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 07:11, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::::Thank you for the reply. I do not doubt that there are some that believe romanticism is indeed a part of homosexuality, however...I do doubt that this is mainstream in even the scientific community. This is really the first time I am seeing it weighted like this - literally ''before'' sexual behavior, erotic desire and attraction. I strongly feel, to even use it in the lede is undue weight to one portion of the scientific community. I am familiar with Byron, Shelly and whole issue of &quot;Greek love' as a literary trope. I am familiar with the Ancient Greek society where the men would commonly write romantic poetry about the beauty of the Olympic athletes. But I would not be for stating this as the basis for use as a term in the lede on this article for a modern interpretaion. I also feel that more sources would certainly be needed to in the body of the article to strengthen such a claim as well as adding some balance to mainstream academic opinion which disgrees, which is lacking here.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 07:00, 5 October 2012 (UTC)

::::::::Belief dosn't matter. If you go around asking 2,000 scientists &quot;What it is called when 2 women or 2 men are romantically attracted to each other?&quot; I guarantee you the VAST majority of them would say homosexuality. Homosexuality and Heterosexuality and for that matter all other sexual orientations (which is a misnomer) actually are not strictly about sex. They are about attraction and have nothing to do with sex.-[[User:Rainbowofpeace|Rainbowofpeace]] ([[User talk:Rainbowofpeace|talk]]) 07:12, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::Exactly. Belief doesn't matter, sources do. Attraction is not sex. Agreed, but then romance is not either, but attraction is more an issue to be a homosexual than a &quot;romantic&quot; feeling. Romance is idealized...attraction is raw.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 07:26, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::Well the problem is that if you remove romance which you say has no relevance than you have to remove sex as well since as I said before sex despite the etymology is not what homosexuality is about. Are you advocating that stance?-[[User:Rainbowofpeace|Rainbowofpeace]] ([[User talk:Rainbowofpeace|talk]]) 07:37, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::::I did not say it has no relevance, I said it was undue weight in the lede. If you take sex out you would be writing about homosapien. As I said, romance is an idealized thought process. It is not actual desire or attraction it is simply a way of looking at something. Romantic is painting a pretty picture of a less beautiful subject. And that seems to be what is happening here. LOL!--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 09:50, 5 October 2012 (UTC) 

:::::::::::Amadscientist, this being &quot;really the first time [you are] seeing it weighted like this - literally ''before'' sexual behavior, erotic desire and attraction.&quot; tells me that you haven't read on this subject as much as you think you have. Romantic attraction is also attraction, by the way, and, as I've stated, is tied to sexual attraction for many people. Even if you aren't American, how are you not familiar with sources such as the American Psychological Association and the American Psychiatric Association...or rather none of their statements on sexual orientation? [[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]] ([[User talk:Flyer22|talk]]) 08:11, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::::Did you really just presume to state what level of research or experiance I myself believe to have? That takes a lot of nerve to be so incivil and then to assume or imply I am not American. Please discuss the contribution and not the contributer. That seems to be a major problem for you. You just cannot stop.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 08:40, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::::::Yes, I did presume it. And I asked you about it. It's not [[WP:UNCIVIL]] in the least. And going by the &quot;Section break: Somewhat off-topic&quot; discussion higher up, discussing the contributor instead of the contribution seems to be a major problem with you. Not me. You are the one who initially did it, and can't seem  to stop doing it, and now can't handle that it was turned on you. Oh well. [[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]] ([[User talk:Flyer22|talk]]) 09:01, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::::::No I didn't. That is not accurate at all. The posts I am reading seem very much to be just parroting back a lot of what I say to filibuster.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 09:43, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::::::::Yes, you did (stating that is quite accurate), and I'm sure that others here would agree that you did. To state that you didn't is ludicrous. You started in about potential POV and motives that I may have (which I don't, by the way), and then went into asserting what you believe to be my POV/motives. You did that before I focused on your visiting [[User:Dennis Brown|Dennis Brown]]'s talk page or questioned your level of knowledge on sexual orientation topics.  Nothing to do with parroting or filibuster whatsoever. [[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]] ([[User talk:Flyer22|talk]]) 09:56, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::::::::You are obviously not able to comprehend the discussion since what I said was ''&quot;If you don't show even the mainstream objections or opposing opinion of whatever validity it may have then you would be pushing POV. Not that you are...&quot;'' But now, I am having a hard time assuming good faith. At some point innacuracy begins to look like something with a purpose.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 10:23, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::::::::::The only one who isn't comprehending what transpired between us is you. Like I stated, you went from implying that I may have potential POV and motives and then went into asserting what you believe to be my POV/motives. You stated, &quot;''You really do want this article to state as indisputable fact what you feel regardless of other mainstream opinion and are indeed pushing POV if you refuse to allow other mainstream opinion with due weight.&quot; Just because you added &quot;if&quot; does not change what you were clearly asserting about me. And it certainly does not negate that you were most assuredly focusing on the editor -- me -- not on any particular contribution. And you made yet another personal attack, this time about comprehension. So cut the crap and stop replying to me already. [[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]] ([[User talk:Flyer22|talk]]) 10:36, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::::::::::::Pushing a POV is a contribution issue. Every contribution has an editor behind it. I have not singled you out by name to attack you. However you have used personal information gained by checking &quot;contribution history&quot; to cherry pick information to literally attack me with. I don't think you comprehend the discussion. I don't. If you do not wish me to reply to you, then stop posting things for me to reply to!--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 10:53, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::::::::::::&lt;Strike&gt;And you had no reason to think that I was/am pushing a personal POV. I've told you that we are supposed to defer to authoritative sources first and foremost when it comes to defining sexual orientation and why that is, and that doing so is not pushing a POV...except for pushing the POV of deferring to authoritative sources. This is done all the time at scientific articles, and other type of articles, which is why WP:UNDUE and WP:FRINGE exist. With a username with &quot;scientist&quot; in it, one would think you'd know that. The topic of sexual orientation is a scientific topic. You speak of comprehension, but all of this is something you clearly do not comprehend. And make no mistake about it, you attacked me first. You focused on the contributor due to your personal opinion that POV editing may be behind the editor's insistence of deferring to authoritative sources, which would need to go for others here as well, since they are also deferring to the authoritative sources while you are not. So stating that you didn't single me out by name is silliness. Implying that an editor has a specific POV just because you disagree with deferring to the authoritative sources that are being used is equally silly. Stating that I attacked you by stating that you should ask Dennis Brown a question is sillier. It's funny that you are so sure that I looked at your contribution history when I've already made it known that Dennis Brown and I are acquaintances. As you know, there is a such thing as a watchlist or just checking in on another Wikipedian's talk page from time to time, or often, without one. You don't think I comprehend the discussion. I don't think you do, as well as some other aspects of this topic. Goody. As for replying, keep it coming if you must. [[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]] ([[User talk:Flyer22|talk]]) 11:23, 5 October 2012 (UTC)&lt;/Strike&gt;
:::::::::::::::::::::I struck my above comment out. Not because I don't still stand by most of it, especially the authoritative sources/non-POV aspect, but as part of a [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User_talk:Amadscientist#Start_over.3F truce attempt] with Amadscientist. [[User:Flyer22|Flyer22]] ([[User talk:Flyer22|talk]]) 17:15, 5 October 2012 (UTC)

TL;DR… seriously.  [[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]], you're assuming way too much based on the etymology.  “Homosexual” is widely used to discuss same-sex relationships regardless of whether or not they have sex.  (And then there's the whole debate about what “sex” is….)  Even massresistance.org has the phrase “homosexual romance” on their web site.  BTW, that interpretation of the word is also wrong; the Latin “sexus” refers to gender, not intercourse. —{{SubSup|[[User:Kerfuffler|Kerfuffler]]&amp;nbsp;|[[Special:Contributions/Kerfuffler|forcemeat]]|[[User talk:Kerfuffler|horsemeat]]}} 02:39, 6 October 2012 (UTC)

== Removal of sourced content from &quot;Etimology&quot; section ==

[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Homosexuality&amp;diff=516019444&amp;oldid=515895160 This edit] removed the following sourced content from the page:

The word ''homosexual'' is a [[Ancient Greek|Greek]] and [[Latin]] hybrid with the first element derived from Greek ''ὁμός'' ''homos'', 'same' (not related to the Latin ''homo'', 'man', as in ''Homo sapiens''), thus connoting sexual acts and affections between members of the same sex, including lesbianism.[1] ''Gay'' generally refers to male homosexuality, but may be used in a broader sense to refer to all [[LGBT]] people. In the context of sexuality, ''lesbian'' refers only to female homosexuality. The word &quot;lesbian&quot; is derived from the name of the Greek island [[Lesbos]], where the poet [[Sappho]] wrote largely about her emotional relationships with young women.[2][3]

#{{citation |title=Etymology of Homosexuality |accessdate=2007-09-07 |url=http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=homosexual&amp;allowed_in_frame=0 |periodical=University of Waterloo}}
#Marguerite Johnson, Terry Ryan: ''Sexuality in Greek and Roman society and literature: a sourcebook'' p.4
#{{cite web|url=http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/lesbian |title=Lesbian &amp;#124; Define Lesbian at Dictionary.com |publisher=Dictionary.reference.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-24}}

The edit summary was: &quot;Removing some information '''with no references'''. Some '''dead links''' to disputed content and moved some to talkpage for discussion. Some rearranging and '''some deletion of content without references'''&quot; (emphasis mine)

Is this vandalism?--''&lt;font face=&quot;bold&quot;&gt;[[User:Wikiwind|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#633B7E;color:#FFD550;padding:0 2px&quot;&gt;В и к и&lt;/span&gt;]][[User talk:Wikiwind|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#FFD666;padding:0 2px;color:#0000;&quot;&gt; T &lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/font&gt; 22:36, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
:It would not be civil to answer that. Instead, I will suggest that it was a nonconstructive edit that should be undone. [[User:StillStanding-247|I&amp;#39;m StillStanding (24/7)]] ([[User talk:StillStanding-247|talk]]) 22:40, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
::The sourced information was merely moved to a more appropriate location. The deleted information was not RS. I wouldn't start edit warring at the suggestion of others.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 22:42, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
:::No, a quick search confirms that information was lost. In particular, the Greek/Latin hybrid thing is gone, even though there is absolutely no controversy or doubt about it. [[User:StillStanding-247|I&amp;#39;m StillStanding (24/7)]] ([[User talk:StillStanding-247|talk]]) 22:44, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
::::The Sappho and lesbian information is still there. Yes the Greek/Latin hybrid &quot;thing&quot; requires a source that is RS and the true origin is in the section.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 22:48, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::That's very, very easily sourced, to the point where it would have been better to find a citation instead of removing it. Here's a citation: http://books.google.com/books?id=WcyqvWfJnyYC&amp;pg=PA172&amp;lpg=PA172&amp;dq=homosexuality+greek+latin+hybrid&amp;#v=onepage&amp;q=homosexuality%20greek%20latin%20hybrid&amp;f=false [[User:StillStanding-247|I&amp;#39;m StillStanding (24/7)]] ([[User talk:StillStanding-247|talk]]) 23:14, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::Perhaps it is best to read what the sources actually say about that...even in the source you just provided it makes it clear this is controversial and is a modern invention. It is not a true etymology. For one thing, it's original use was in German.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 23:18, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
{{od}}The term came to English from the original German, but the German was itself from a hybrid of Greek and Latin. We can mention the German part, but we don't need to. It serves to explain the awkward composite word (normal for German) but says nothing about the Greek and Latin roots. [[User:StillStanding-247|I&amp;#39;m StillStanding (24/7)]] ([[User talk:StillStanding-247|talk]]) 23:23, 4 October 2012 (UTC)

:That's OR. We do need to mention the german part. The point is that if you state that the word is derived from Greek and Latin terms it gives the impression that the term has ancient origins like most words with such roots. The implication is innaccurate. And I am not even sure it can really be said that is how the term was derived by the German author.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 23:26, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
::That's neither OR nor does it follow. Like &quot;television&quot;, it's a modern word that weirdly combines Latin and Greek. This very combination shows its modernity. I don't particularly object to mentioning that it was first coined in German, but it's not particularly necessary, either. [[User:StillStanding-247|I&amp;#39;m StillStanding (24/7)]] ([[User talk:StillStanding-247|talk]]) 23:39, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
:::It is necessary as it was the first use and it was not an english expression or term. We know how the word is derived and Wikipedia should not be used to make innaccurate claims. The controversy about the Latin/Greek origin is precisely why it is best not to use.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 23:51, 4 October 2012 (UTC)

Seeing as this is of no consequence to the article at hand, I recommend removing the section entirely and leaving this to Wiktionary. —{{SubSup|[[User:Kerfuffler|Kerfuffler]]&amp;nbsp;|[[Special:Contributions/Kerfuffler|forcemeat]]|[[User talk:Kerfuffler|horsemeat]]}} 23:30, 4 October 2012 (UTC)

:I wouldn't object to that if others agree.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 23:32, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
::I have to disagree, based on the precedent of [[Television]]. [[User:StillStanding-247|I&amp;#39;m StillStanding (24/7)]] ([[User talk:StillStanding-247|talk]]) 23:39, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
:::As always, one bad example does not justify another one.  But in the case of television, the etymology is at least non-obvious and not directly descriptive. —{{SubSup|[[User:Kerfuffler|Kerfuffler]]&amp;nbsp;|[[Special:Contributions/Kerfuffler|forcemeat]]|[[User talk:Kerfuffler|horsemeat]]}} 23:48, 4 October 2012 (UTC)
::::I don't know why you'd propose deleting the section when the information contained is proper and sourced. The only part in question here is the passage at the top of this discussion. All of that information is cited as well with sufficient sources, including the [http://books.google.com/books?id=WcyqvWfJnyYC&amp;pg=PA172&amp;lpg=PA172&amp;dq=homosexuality+greek+latin+hybrid&amp;#v=onepage&amp;q=homosexuality%20greek%20latin%20hybrid&amp;f=false one added] by [[User:StillStanding-247|I&amp;#39;m StillStanding (24/7)]]. There's no controversy about the Latin/Greek origin besides what you've invented here and its original use in German is already explained in detail within the section. So, I'm not seeing where anything you two said is contentious material or left out. [[User:Teammm|&lt;span style=&quot;color:black;font-family: fantasy&quot;&gt; '''''Teammm'''''&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Teammm|'''&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;T&lt;/font&gt;''']][[Special:EmailUser/Teammm|'''&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;M&lt;/font&gt;''']]&lt;/sup&gt; 05:08, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::It was a suggested compromise. Its probably not going to happen but the source provided by the other editor shows a controversy. Did you read it? The fact is, the term is &quot;Notorious&quot; because it is a Greek/Latin modern hybrid with no actual Greek or Latin equivalent. Now...if we actally worded it in that manner along with the German origin I would be all for it, but the other editor wants to make this cut and dry when it is not.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 05:18, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
{{od}}The term &quot;television&quot; is well-known for being a Greek/Latin hybrid, but that doesn't mean there were TV's in ancient Rome. In short, your argument is based on a false premise and hold no weight. [[User:StillStanding-247|I&amp;#39;m StillStanding (24/7)]] ([[User talk:StillStanding-247|talk]]) 07:29, 5 October 2012 (UTC)

::Not based on a false premise. Actually based on the very source you provided.

::{{quotation|The word homosexuality (notoriously a Greek/Latin hybrid of modern invention) has no Greek or Latin equivalent. &lt;sub&gt;Marriage and Family in the Biblical World edited by Ken M. Campbell&lt;/sub&gt;}}

::And there is a reason for that. Homosexuality is not a concept the ancient Greek or Romans knew or understood, but that is another subject.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 08:16, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
:::There sure were a lot of things they didn't understand. In any case, your interpretation of this source is fringe and is attacking a straw man. [[User:StillStanding-247|I&amp;#39;m StillStanding (24/7)]] ([[User talk:StillStanding-247|talk]]) 09:22, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
::::Uhm, that isn't an interpretation. Its actually paraphrased, and probably a little too closely to the source.--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 09:34, 5 October 2012 (UTC)

:::::Article does not imply that ancient Greek or Romans used the term &quot;Homosexuality&quot;. It only says uncontroversial fact that the word &quot;Homosexuality&quot; is derived from Greek &quot;homos&quot; and Latin &quot;sexus&quot;. Do you dispute that?--''&lt;font face=&quot;bold&quot;&gt;[[User:Wikiwind|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#633B7E;color:#FFD550;padding:0 2px&quot;&gt;В и к и&lt;/span&gt;]][[User talk:Wikiwind|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#FFD666;padding:0 2px;color:#0000;&quot;&gt; T &lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/font&gt; 11:01, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::^Buku asked my next question. I don't see how you interpret a word's derivation as &quot;the word was used at that time&quot;. [[User:Teammm|&lt;span style=&quot;color:black;font-family: fantasy&quot;&gt; '''''Teammm'''''&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Teammm|'''&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;T&lt;/font&gt;''']][[Special:EmailUser/Teammm|'''&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;M&lt;/font&gt;''']]&lt;/sup&gt; 15:07, 5 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::Hi, I wanted to give myself some time away from the discussion to be sure others had time to chime in, but I am glad Teamm came to the table and I appreciate the question asked by Buku. The history of the term &quot;Homosexual&quot; should be described with accuracy. And, while it currently has a good deal of the proper context the term ''modern'' is missing as well as some indication of it's &quot;invention&quot; and does indeed give the impression that the word itself has roots in the ancient languages being ascribed to it. This is false of course, and we need to be sure and make it clear that the Greek and Romans did not actually have any such word. This detail is important to be sure and seperate other such historic terms that do have their roots in these languages. The fact that the article does not state the modern invention is misleading for no reason when all sources are clear, yet, for somereason we have chosen to omit it believing that the following text will clarify. It actually does not as the text is still a little ambiguous. The prose states &quot;The first known appearance..&quot;. This leads the reader to simply believe there may yet be earlier writings yet discovered. But we do know that the term was invented by a german author.[http://books.google.com/books?id=gA0yUP1ct9IC&amp;pg=PA46&amp;lpg=PA46&amp;dq=origin+of+the+word+homosexual&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=cqXwgKUubt&amp;sig=5QMCH0-qNACmlPuRgfD62P2WQr8&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=mqNvULqeL-LCigLbloHgDg&amp;ved=0CD4Q6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=origin%20of%20the%20word%20homosexual&amp;f=false][http://books.google.com/books?id=Bky73nUjhXAC&amp;pg=PA24&amp;lpg=PA24&amp;dq=origin+of+the+word+homosexual+Karl-Maria+Kertbeny&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=JYje7NwcJi&amp;sig=L72KnQvUTrEHTOU6eAd2y7PLnLY&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=e6dvUPuNNeSdiQKbl4C4BA&amp;ved=0CDcQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=origin%20of%20the%20word%20homosexual%20Karl-Maria%20Kertbeny&amp;f=false][http://books.google.com/books?id=lWHOI2s9JqQC&amp;pg=PA3&amp;lpg=PA3&amp;dq=origin+of+the+word+homosexual+Karl-Maria+Kertbeny&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Ei-3TDrxu1&amp;sig=LeZkjrpPc-MY42R4WNoBDW1QfBs&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=e6dvUPuNNeSdiQKbl4C4BA&amp;ved=0CEMQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=origin%20of%20the%20word%20homosexual%20Karl-Maria%20Kertbeny&amp;f=false][http://books.google.com/books?id=kEfZ1knAguMC&amp;pg=PT47&amp;lpg=PT47&amp;dq=origin+of+the+word+homosexual+Karl-Maria+Kertbeny&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Rp4iHjDBvZ&amp;sig=U2WqZoH-0YS7oFq4M8tX3qqnnns&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=e6dvUPuNNeSdiQKbl4C4BA&amp;ved=0CE0Q6AEwBg][http://books.google.com/books?id=4aCsv-E3joEC&amp;pg=PA130&amp;lpg=PA130&amp;dq=origin+of+the+word+homosexual+Karl-Maria+Kertbeny&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=jFPxqn9dr0&amp;sig=8k5fXlsDXQft5yQlaOJys96t_68&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=e6dvUPuNNeSdiQKbl4C4BA&amp;ved=0CFIQ6AEwBw#v=onepage&amp;q=origin%20of%20the%20word%20homosexual%20Karl-Maria%20Kertbeny&amp;f=false] There is indeed some controversy surrounding the term. For one, while we do know when the term was coined, many still argue that the concept has been around for some time.[http://books.google.com/books?id=0AMN4_xZJDsC&amp;pg=PA100&amp;lpg=PA100&amp;dq=origin+of+the+word+homosexual+Karl-Maria+Kertbeny&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=qZIB8rcTTz&amp;sig=lXahzVbeaTMAVspLAtPb1uFocRs&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=e6dvUPuNNeSdiQKbl4C4BA&amp;ved=0CFgQ6AEwCA#v=onepage&amp;q=origin%20of%20the%20word%20homosexual%20Karl-Maria%20Kertbeny&amp;f=false] While this is true from at least the renaissance period, writings of the period have dealt with the concept of same sex love and attraction by using the terms &quot;Greek love&quot;, &quot;Socratic love&quot; or &quot;Plutonic love&quot; as almost a code.[http://books.google.com/books?id=ao5Kg1Se3TIC&amp;pg=PA249&amp;lpg=PA249&amp;dq=renaissance+same+sex+love+socratic+love&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=NmxR5kvfDA&amp;sig=cODvXA8kiITNeYjLktRZA9A0XgY&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=-6pvUK6UJamujAKh1oGIBA&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=renaissance%20same%20sex%20love%20socratic%20love&amp;f=false] The importance of the developement of the modern term is an important part of LGBT studies and I feel we do a diservice by not including some portion of the accurate origins. I will leave this up to editors. Thanks!--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 03:57, 6 October 2012 (UTC)

== Bold rearrangement ==

A recent edit that rearranged the sections has been reverted as needing disussion and a formed consensus. What articles are these changes being based on and why. Why would etymology and history not be at the beginning?--[[User:Amadscientist|Amadscientist]] ([[User talk:Amadscientist|talk]]) 20:24, 10 October 2012 (UTC)
:Byelf2007 is always making [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Homosexuality&amp;diff=517064196&amp;oldid=517063764 those kinds of edits.] See [[User talk:Byelf2007#Your editing]], and other comments in other sections on his talk page about it. He almost always puts the etymology and history sections farther down. Perhaps you want to ask him to comment here about that? [[Special:Contributions/216.119.145.148|216.119.145.148]] ([[User talk:216.119.145.148|talk]]) 00:10, 11 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>c40shw2z8h1m9u13x102yjno2m8ydme</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
