<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Natural theology</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>10064637</id>
    <revision>
      <id>407455544</id>
      <parentid>407418257</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-01-12T11:02:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dave souza</username>
        <id>85186</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Radical morphology */ rads</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26666">{{notice|{{find}}}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{philosophy|class=start|importance=mid|religion=yes}}
{{WPReligion|class=start|importance=}}}}

==Eastern Orthodox==
Orthodox Christianity rejects Natural theology. Can someone add this in the article? Also contrast it to [[scholastic theology]]. --[[User:Kupirijo|Kupirijo]] 04:49, 15 March 2007 (UTC)

--Where is your evidence that the Orthodox reject natural theology? The Cappadocian Fathers were to a degree natural theologians.  Check out Pelikan's book, Christianity and Classical Culture.[[User:Grailknighthero|Grailknighthero]] ([[User talk:Grailknighthero|talk]]) 14:41, 20 September 2010 (UTC)

== Natural Theology vs. Deism ==

I see a lot of similarities between these two philosophies/theologies.  I understand Deism is a type of natural theology, but I was wondering what the differences are and what other types of natural theology there is besides Deism.  Thanks!!! [[User:Byronarnold|Byronarnold]] 22:26, 19 April 2007 (UTC)

:Well, Natural Theology was pretty clearly used in both [[Deism]] and [[Theism]], since it's beyond my expertise you'll have to look at these articles to work out the difference. However, [[William Paley]] was clearly a theist and his ''Natural Theology, or Evidences of the Existence and Attributes of the Deity collected from the Appearances of Nature'' followed on from his ''Evidences of Christianity'' and was similarly influential on the [[Church of England]] which was the church the authors of the ''Bridgewater Treatises'' such as [[William Whewell]]. However ideas such as Whewell's &quot;But with regard to the material world, we can at least go so far as this-we can perceive that events are brought about not by insulated interpositions of Divine power, exerted in each particular case, but by the establishment of general laws.&quot; which [[Charles Darwin]] cited at the start of [[The Origin of Species]] may be more deistic. Good luck with the quest, .. [[User:Dave souza|dave souza]], [[User talk:Dave souza|talk]] 08:53, 20 April 2007 (UTC)

::As of right now, I consider myself Deist.  But I want to learn as much as I can about &quot;Natural Theology&quot;.  Maybe I fit more under it than I do Deism.  Who knows?  Well, I'm going to google the term, see what all I can find!  Thanks for your reply!!! [[User:Byronarnold|Byronarnold]] 01:34, 25 April 2007 (UTC)


==== difference b/t natural theology and deism ... in the article?? ====

I find it very confusing the difference betwixt the two, and would be very grateful for someone expert in both to perhaps describe for us, the lay person, what the differences are, in the article text. thank you. [[User:Decora|Decora]] ([[User talk:Decora|talk]]) 15:08, 19 September 2009 (UTC)

== Potential additional content/definition for the page: Natural Theology ==



The term &quot;natural religion&quot; has been used to describe an 18th and 19th century notion of  &quot;natural theology&quot; that used reasoning and ordinary experience rather than supernatural beliefs, but did not deny beliefs. This is set out in [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dialogues_Concerning_Natural_Religion David Hume's Dialogues Concerning Natural Religion]. Seeing a god or gods in nature, or nature-worship, are also included in the term &quot;natural religion&quot;, as exemplified by Frank Lloyd Wright's quote: &quot;I believe in God, only I spell it Nature.&quot;. These religious directions were an offshoot of Christian culture and based on the western understanding of nature at that time.

In contrast, the ideas in [http://www.thenaturalreligion.org The Natural Religion] by the zoologist and philosopher, Dr Brendan Connolly, are based on what is now world-wide knowledge of the biological system as accepted by all of human kind, not just western or Christian cultures. It sees humans as one part of our biological system and points out that there are no indications that humans are also part of something else, such as a supernatural world. Much of our current knowledge of ourselves was not known during the 18th and 19th centuries, therefore the then small green shoots of natural religion that tentatively investigated if reasoning could answer religious questions, have now come of age in Dr Connolly's book The Natural Religion ISBN 978-0-9558313-0-0, which now benefits from much greater and up-to-date knowledge to underpin its ideas. Also, no trace of &quot;natural theology&quot; is found in [http://www.thenaturalreligion.org The Natural Religion], as it does not suggest any gods or any supernatural beliefs in or about nature, and takes an agnostic stance. 

The Natural Religion therefore does not define religion, see [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Religion_Explained Religion Explained], as found in English language dictionaries with having supernatural beliefs and deities as part of it, but as: &quot;A set of ideas about ourselves and the world around us&quot;. The reasoning employed in the book [http://www.amazon.co.uk/Natural-Religion-Brendan-Connolly/dp/0955831318 'The Natural Religion'], sees traditional religions using beliefs to guess the answers to questions which were as yet unsolved due to lack of information. What the concept of The Natural Religion has in common with other religions is that it examines the age-old questions about the [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Meaning_of_life&amp;oldid=356490866 Meaning of Life], but contends that we now know why human life, as well as life in general, exists, and that the boundaries of human knowledge are now drawn at our understanding of the nature of [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Energy&amp;oldid=355378050 Energy]. Dr Brendan Connolly was a speaker at the International Conference on Human Ecology, Manchester, UK, June 29th to July 3rd 2009

--[[User:Scrutineer1|Scrutineer1]] ([[User talk:Scrutineer1|talk]]) 15:11, 21 April 2010 (UTC)

== Resemblance to Intelligent Design ==

I can't help but notice that Natural Theology bears a striking resemblance to [[Intelligent Design]]. So striking is the resemblance, that I'm tempted to say that Intelligent Design is Natural Theology repackaged for the modern age. Should this article be expanded into that area or would that cause a redundancy? [[User:Wolf ODonnell|Wolf ODonnell]] 14:39, 5 September 2007 (UTC)
:A brief mention is appropriate, but detail belongs in the intelligent design articles – as you've probably noted, Behe explicitly refers back to [[William Paley]] as a predecessor of ID, though of course they tend to claim that ID's not religion. . .  [[User:Dave souza|dave souza]], [[User talk:Dave souza|talk]] 16:41, 13 September 2007 (UTC)

::ID can be either or both of two things: (1) an argument that naturalism is insufficient to explain evolution; (2) a P.R. campaign to make Creationism palatable to educators. If it's also a form of natural theology then it's three things and that would make my head spin. --[[User:Ed Poor|Uncle Ed]] 17:14, 8 November 2007 (UTC)

Natural theology is the theistic form of deistic natural philosophy. It does not reject the evolution of species into another or the slowly forming universe over billions of years. Intelligent design, defined by Britannica, rejects the evolution concept. It would probably be less confusing to just say that natural theology and natural philosophy are synonyms. In practice they aren't discernible. Both have been around for 3000+ years before the terms 'intelligent design' and 'biological evolution' were even coined and parroted by popular culture.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/209.105.184.93|209.105.184.93]] ([[User talk:209.105.184.93|talk]]) 09:11, 24 December 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:(i) You're commenting on a 3 year old thread. (ii) Paley's take on natural theology, and his [[watchmaker analogy]], is probably the most widely-known version of it these days -- and ''is'' the immediate philosophical antecedent of ID. &lt;font face=&quot;Antiqua, serif&quot;&gt;''[[User:Hrafn|Hrafn]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Hrafn|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Hrafn|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;''('''[[M:Precisionism|P]]''')&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 10:17, 24 December 2010 (UTC)

== Barth and Brunner ==

This article should at some point discuss the debate between [[Karl Barth]] and [[Emil Brunner]]. [[User:70.131.128.247|70.131.128.247]] 04:27, 13 September 2007 (UTC)

:Thank you for your suggestion{{{{#if:notsubsted||subst:}}#if:{{{1|}}}|&amp;#32;regarding [[:{{{1}}}]]}}. When you feel an article needs improvement, please feel free to make those changes.  Wikipedia is a [[wiki]], so anyone can edit almost any article by simply following the '''{{MediaWiki:edit}}''' link at the top. The Wikipedia community encourages you to [[Wikipedia:Be bold in updating pages|be bold in updating pages]]. Don't worry too much about making honest mistakes — they're likely to be found and corrected quickly. If you're not sure how editing works, check out [[Wikipedia:how to edit a page|''how to edit a page'']], or use the [[Wikipedia:Sandbox|sandbox]] to try out your editing skills.  [[Wikipedia:Welcome, newcomers|New contributors are always welcome]]. You don't even need to [[Special:Userlogin|log in]] (although there are [[Wikipedia:Why create an account?|many reasons why you might want to]]).  &lt;!-- Template:Sofixit --&gt;
:In my opinion the sentence you deleted actually provides useful clarification and links that are inappropriate in the title phrase to the article, so I've reinstated it. Mr Hippo does seem to be an early exponent of the idea, suitable references for this and other points will welcome. .. [[User:Dave souza|dave souza]], [[User talk:Dave souza|talk]] 16:36, 13 September 2007 (UTC)

== Potential source ==

The introductory chapter (p9-54) of ''Adaptation: Natural Selection in Evolution'', Michael R. Rose, George V. Lauder (available through Google books), contains considerable information on the movement of Natural Theology from a basis in astronomy ('Astrotheology') to a basis in biology ('Physicotheology'). Might prove useful in fleshing this article out. &lt;font face=&quot;Antiqua, serif&quot;&gt;''[[User:Hrafn|Hrafn]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Hrafn|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Hrafn|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt;''&lt;/font&gt; 09:47, 3 June 2008 (UTC)

== Lead problem ==

I noticed an editor recently alter the lead without any discussion here.  Of course the alteration miraculously benefits a content dispute this editor is having at [[Astrotheology]].  The basic definitions I've seen for natural theology seem to more or less follow this one: &quot;'Natural Theology' is the favorite term in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries designating the knowledge of God drawn from nature in distinction from the knowledge of God contained in revelation.&quot;  I'm not sure that this is specific to &quot;God's purpose&quot; as the new edit claims.  Also the edit in question claims that natural theology is theology &quot;on nature&quot; as opposed to a theology &quot;from nature&quot; or &quot;based upon the observation of nature&quot;.  Isn't that entirely reversed?  Can someone with expertise here please have a look at this.  I reverted it and asked the editor to bring the change to the talk page first. Thanks.[[User:PelleSmith|PelleSmith]] ([[User talk:PelleSmith|talk]]) 21:31, 4 June 2008 (UTC)

:Gifford basically establish Natural Theology to prove the existence of God, and he wanted it to be a natural science. It evolved and embraced many theologies over time. The quote I put there was based on Paley's Natural Theology, and the quote is taken almost exactly as it exists in Modern Predicament. I realize there was a better way to states it, but I wanted to make sure I would not be accused of exactly what you accused me about. [[WP:AGF]], and using &quot;editor&quot; to hide it doesn't help. Since you restored the text, it is now up to you to [[WP:PROVEIT]]. &amp;mdash; [[User:Dzonatas|&lt;b&gt;&lt;FONT COLOR=&quot;#0000FF&quot;&gt;Dz&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;FONT COLOR=&quot;#3F50FF&quot;&gt;on&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;FONT COLOR=&quot;#5F80FF&quot;&gt;at&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;FONT COLOR=&quot;#77B0FF&quot;&gt;as&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;/b&gt;]] 22:57, 4 June 2008 (UTC)
::I noted a suspicious circumstance I did not accuse you of bad faith.  By what authority do we alter the lead of an entry on a very broad ranging historical concept to fit the strict definition of one of many possible primary sources?  I will advise you once again to please familiarize yourself with our sourcing conventions.  [[WP:V]] and [[WP:RS]] are the places to start.  Anyway I've asked for outside opinions here at three Wikiprojects: Religion, Philosophy and Christianity.  Regards[[User:PelleSmith|PelleSmith]] ([[User talk:PelleSmith|talk]]) 23:28, 4 June 2008 (UTC)
:::&quot;By what authority do we alter the lead of an entry on a very broad ranging historical concept to fit the strict definition of one of many possible primary sources?&quot; There was nothing being cited in the lead, and wikipedia needs it to be verifiable. Hmmmmm, so you deleted one of the only verifiable statements in the lead section and was not ready to provide something better cited? At least, if you felt it did not reflect what the source says, then attempt to rewrite it. You've obvious taken such open rewrite position on [[astrotheology]] to suit your pov, but you don't apply the same spirit here? &amp;mdash; [[User:Dzonatas|&lt;b&gt;&lt;FONT COLOR=&quot;#0000FF&quot;&gt;Dz&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;FONT COLOR=&quot;#3F50FF&quot;&gt;on&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;FONT COLOR=&quot;#5F80FF&quot;&gt;at&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;FONT COLOR=&quot;#77B0FF&quot;&gt;as&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;/b&gt;]] 23:38, 4 June 2008 (UTC)
::::Look, I'm not the one who came here and altered the entry after getting into a content dispute at astrotheology.  I'm only returning it to its pre-altered state.  Lets not confuse events here.  I apply the same spirit here of course, and its actually that spirit I'm trying to impart on you.  The issues I have on the other entry also have to do with [[WP:V]] and [[WP:RS]].  Primary sources are not encouraged, particularly not when we dealing with a primary historical source in what is a much much larger concept.[[User:PelleSmith|PelleSmith]] ([[User talk:PelleSmith|talk]]) 23:46, 4 June 2008 (UTC)
:::::Your invite attempt looks suspicious to call more attention to the AfD. &amp;mdash; [[User:Dzonatas|&lt;b&gt;&lt;FONT COLOR=&quot;#0000FF&quot;&gt;Dz&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;FONT COLOR=&quot;#3F50FF&quot;&gt;on&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;FONT COLOR=&quot;#5F80FF&quot;&gt;at&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;FONT COLOR=&quot;#77B0FF&quot;&gt;as&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;/b&gt;]] 00:49, 5 June 2008 (UTC)
::::::If I wanted to just mention the AfD I would have, and there would be nothing inappropriate about it.  Of course I didn't do that, I asked for people with expertise here to please take a look at the disputes.  These Wikiprojects are relevant to the topic at hand.  Please do post this at other relevant Wikiprojects I might have missed.[[User:PelleSmith|PelleSmith]] ([[User talk:PelleSmith|talk]]) 00:54, 5 June 2008 (UTC)

== Relevance of Hindu sacred texts ==

I've {{tl|irrel}} tagged the Hindu material as it presents no evidence that this material is &quot;based on reason and ordinary experience&quot; -- it appears rather 'based upon sacred texts and mataphysical speculations'. &lt;font face=&quot;Antiqua, serif&quot;&gt;''[[User:Hrafn|Hrafn]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Hrafn|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Hrafn|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;''('''[[M:Precisionism|P]]''')&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 06:06, 9 August 2009 (UTC)

== Marcus Terentius Varro ==

I would point out that:
#The previously-tagged material on [[Marcus Terentius Varro]] does not establish that he is one of the &quot;Key proponents&quot; of Natural Theology (or even that he is a proponent at all). Meaning that this material should have been deleted regardless of sourcing.
#That a citation to the German-language ''Die Theologie der frühen griechischen Denker'', lacks even page numbers, is ''completely useless'' for [[WP:Verification]].
#That the citation to Shanks only appears to verify the &quot;three kinds of theology&quot; claim, not the rest of the material.
&lt;font face=&quot;Antiqua, serif&quot;&gt;''[[User:Hrafn|Hrafn]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Hrafn|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Hrafn|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;''('''[[M:Precisionism|P]]''')&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 11:13, 14 November 2010 (UTC)

* The ''proponent'' issue was not previously specified.  It will be best dealt with by retitling that section as ''History''.  Varro's part was to provide an analytical scheme which is helpful to understanding this history of the matter.  This is described in the Shanks source.

* I shall add a quote to the citation of ''Die Theologie der frühen griechischen Denker'' to clarify this.

:*That will not affect the fact that the material is ''irrelevant'', in that it doesn't establish Varro as one of the &quot;Key proponents&quot; of Natural Theology. 

* I shall also remove the leading banner tags as these seem stale or redundant.

[[User:Colonel Warden|Colonel Warden]] ([[User talk:Colonel Warden|talk]]) 11:31, 14 November 2010 (UTC)

:*Neither banner is &quot;stale or redundant&quot;. &lt;font face=&quot;Antiqua, serif&quot;&gt;''[[User:Hrafn|Hrafn]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Hrafn|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Hrafn|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;''('''[[M:Precisionism|P]]''')&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 11:42, 14 November 2010 (UTC)

* The request for citations at the article level is redundant to the request for citations at particular points.  The latter are preferable because they are clear and actionable.  The request for an expert is stale and the talk page discussions indicate that we have adequate expertise here. [[User:Colonel Warden|Colonel Warden]] ([[User talk:Colonel Warden|talk]]) 11:49, 14 November 2010 (UTC) 

Oh, and I would point out that Colonel Warden deleted 5 {{tl|fact}} tags, without providing citations for the material they were tagging. This is generally considered to be [[WP:VANDALISM]] (e.g. see {{tl|uw-tdel3}}). &lt;font face=&quot;Antiqua, serif&quot;&gt;''[[User:Hrafn|Hrafn]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Hrafn|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Hrafn|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;''('''[[M:Precisionism|P]]''')&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 11:26, 14 November 2010 (UTC)

:* Not sure what you're talking about there.  Which five?  See also [[WP:AGF]].  [[User:Colonel Warden|Colonel Warden]] ([[User talk:Colonel Warden|talk]]) 11:31, 14 November 2010 (UTC)

::*Sorry, it was six: (i) &quot;Besides Zarathushtra's Gathas...&quot;, (ii) Thomas Barlow, Bishop of Lincoln, (iii) William Derham &amp; (iv) his influence on Paley, (v) William Paley &amp; (vi) Horace Mann.[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Natural_theology&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=396681981&amp;oldid=396656254] Your pretending not to know what I'm talking about, and your long history of pulling such stunts (e.g. [[User talk:Colonel Warden/Archive 3#Removal of tags|here]], only a few days ago), means that you've long since used up any assumption of good faith. &lt;font face=&quot;Antiqua, serif&quot;&gt;''[[User:Hrafn|Hrafn]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Hrafn|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Hrafn|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;''('''[[M:Precisionism|P]]''')&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 11:38, 14 November 2010 (UTC)
:::* That's clearer.  This was inadvertent, as when I read your edit summary and looked at the diff, I only noticed the removal of material and missed the word ''tags''.  When making bold and controversial edits, it seems best not to bundle them with other minor edits as the latter will tend to be overlooked and get lost in the wash. [[User:Colonel Warden|Colonel Warden]] ([[User talk:Colonel Warden|talk]]) 11:46, 14 November 2010 (UTC)

::::*'''No''', these were '''not''' &quot;bold and controversial edits&quot; (merely removal of long-tagged, and irrelevant, material), and '''you''' are ''solely'' responsible for failing '''both''' to read the edit summary '''and''' to read the dif carefully. &lt;font face=&quot;Antiqua, serif&quot;&gt;''[[User:Hrafn|Hrafn]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Hrafn|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Hrafn|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;''('''[[M:Precisionism|P]]''')&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 11:57, 14 November 2010 (UTC)

:::::* The material is not irrelevant, being discussed in this context by multiple reliable sources, and so shall be restored in the course of further improvement.  [[User:Colonel Warden|Colonel Warden]] ([[User talk:Colonel Warden|talk]]) 12:12, 14 November 2010 (UTC)

::::::*What sources discuss Varro as one of the &quot;Key proponents&quot; of Natural Theology? (&quot;Key proponents&quot; being the section title.) &lt;font face=&quot;Antiqua, serif&quot;&gt;''[[User:Hrafn|Hrafn]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Hrafn|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Hrafn|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;''('''[[M:Precisionism|P]]''')&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 12:16, 14 November 2010 (UTC)

:::::::* This point is covered above.  It is the section title and ordering of the material which is the problem, not the references to Varro.  I plan a general cleanup which will address this and numerous other issues.  All will become clear when the article is written better. [[User:Colonel Warden|Colonel Warden]] ([[User talk:Colonel Warden|talk]]) 12:30, 14 November 2010 (UTC)

::::::::*Varro didn't &quot;provide an analytical scheme&quot;, that scheme was provided by the Stoics (via [[Publius Mucius Scaevola]]), Varro simply inherited/reiterated it (e.g. see [http://books.google.com/books?id=IXJjDD61NmIC&amp;pg=PA80&amp;dq=%22Marcus+Terentius+Varro%22+natural+theology+-inpublisher:icon&amp;as_brr=0&amp;cd=2#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Marcus%20Terentius%20Varro%22%20natural%20theology%20-inpublisher%3Aicon&amp;f=false here]). &lt;font face=&quot;Antiqua, serif&quot;&gt;''[[User:Hrafn|Hrafn]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Hrafn|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Hrafn|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;''('''[[M:Precisionism|P]]''')&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 12:43, 14 November 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::* This is one of the sources which I had in mind too.  It is good that we are reaching consensus. [[User:Colonel Warden|Colonel Warden]] ([[User talk:Colonel Warden|talk]]) 12:53, 14 November 2010 (UTC)

{{outdent}}
*Except that this source merely mentions Varro in passing, as a bit player in getting from the Stoics to Augustine. You'll need to work harder to demonstrate that Varro had a prominent part to play in the development of NT. &lt;font face=&quot;Antiqua, serif&quot;&gt;''[[User:Hrafn|Hrafn]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Hrafn|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Hrafn|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;''('''[[M:Precisionism|P]]''')&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 13:20, 14 November 2010 (UTC)

*If you're wanting to write about Varro's influence on NT, I'd suggest you might want to start with ''[http://books.google.co.nz/books?id=-x509fsKPZ8C&amp;dq=history+%22natural+theology%22 Studies in the History of Natural Theology]''. &lt;font face=&quot;Antiqua, serif&quot;&gt;''[[User:Hrafn|Hrafn]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Hrafn|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Hrafn|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;''('''[[M:Precisionism|P]]''')&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 13:40, 14 November 2010 (UTC)
:* Again, this is another source which I had identified as promising.  As you are now being more productive and thinking along the same lines, it seems most efficient that you work further upon this topic while I attend to [[aircraft design|another topic]] which is even greater need of attention.  More anon. [[User:Colonel Warden|Colonel Warden]] ([[User talk:Colonel Warden|talk]]) 14:45, 14 November 2010 (UTC)

::*I believe that what I said was that &quot;if ''you're'' wanting to write about Varro...&quot; and pointing you away from a source that barely mentions him. That was not an offer to write material myself. Although I have access to that one source, I lack the ''context'' to see how he fits into the wider-scale development of NT. This, as much as the lacking of sourcing, is the problem with the article -- the whole thing reads like a series of snapshots, rather than a coherent narrative about the philosophical development of the concept. It makes for bad articles. I already have another such article on my plate -- and one that I've both got a better handle on, and easier access to better sources. So re-writing the history and development of Natural Theology will have to wait for now. &lt;font face=&quot;Antiqua, serif&quot;&gt;''[[User:Hrafn|Hrafn]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Hrafn|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Hrafn|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;''('''[[M:Precisionism|P]]''')&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 15:29, 14 November 2010 (UTC)

== Radical morphology ==

[Moved from [[User talk:Hrafn]] ]

Hello, Hrafn;

Would you be able to insert some kind of definition (parenthetical gloss, etc.) for radical morphology in [[Natural theology]]? I'm unfamiliar with the term (which is why I redlinked it); otherwise, I'd have done it myself. Thank you! [[User:J. Spencer|J. Spencer]] ([[User talk:J. Spencer|talk]]) 23:27, 11 January 2011 (UTC)

#Discussion of articles belongs on article talk.
#The phrase &quot;radical morphology&quot; was taken directly from the cited source, Alexander &amp; Numbers(2010)p. 107 -- which in turn cites [http://www.jstor.org/pss/3024816 The Life of Dr. Knox] (to which I have no access). I assumed that A&amp;N considered it relevant to Knox's Bridgewater comments, so I followed suit. Nothing in the passage suggested that they were using &quot;morphology&quot; in a sense different from [[morphology]], so I included a link to that article. Likewise nothing indicated to me that they were using &quot;radical morphology&quot; as a distinct [[term of art]], so I objected to the redlink. Your options appear to be threefold: (i) read 'The Life of Dr. Knox' to discover what they meant, (ii) leave the phrase as is or (iii) remove it as being confusing to the reader.
&lt;font face=&quot;Antiqua, serif&quot;&gt;''[[User:Hrafn|Hrafn]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Hrafn|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Hrafn|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;''('''[[M:Precisionism|P]]''')&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 05:01, 12 January 2011 (UTC)

::This obviously refers to [[Radicalism (historical)]] and [[Morphology (biology)]]. More specifically, it's about the new anti-establishment medical campaigners associated with the [[British Medical Association]] and ''[[The Lancet]]'', in particular [[Thomas Wakley]] whose support of radical anatomy and attacks on the Bridgewater Treatises were rather more significant than Knox's. {{Citation
 | last = Desmond
 | first =Adrian J.
 | year = 1989
 | title =The Politics of Evolution: Morphology, Medicine, and Reform in Radical London
 | publisher =University of Chicago Press
 | isbn =0-226-14374-0 }} covers this: p. 20 mentions the &quot;Bilgewater&quot; books being pilloried in the radical press, pp. 114 cites Knox attacking Cooper and Bell's attempts to find design functions for deformities as &quot;sometimes very pompous and imposing, as in the Bridgewater Treatises, but still downright nonsense&quot; and calling natural theology &quot;a vile patchwork, almost peculiar to British physiology, a jumble of expedients and contrivances to meet difficulties.&quot; It continues on to p. 117 with discussion of Wakely's views on the topic, and gives more on the views of Knox on pp. 388–389. It doesn't specifically say that Knox coined the term &quot;Bilgewater&quot;, but associates him with it. Will aim to return to this when time permits, [[User:Dave souza|dave souza]], [[User talk:Dave souza|talk]] 11:02, 12 January 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>2nnlkftes8a6521jcka8yce32pltbwd</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
