<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Rama</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>19376724</id>
    <revision>
      <id>501182374</id>
      <parentid>491149849</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-07-08T01:44:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Terrymacro</username>
        <id>3522143</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* ARCHEO-ASTRONOMY */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="44331">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=PR
|action1date=17:30, 28 February 2006
|action1link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Rama/archive1
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=41604480

|action2=GAN
|action2date=20:14, 10 April 2006
|action2result=listed
|action2oldid=47845237

|action3=GAR
|action3link=Talk:Rama/GA1
|action3date=19:37, 2 July 2009 (UTC)
|action3result=delisted
|action3oldid=299550885

|currentstatus=DGA
|topic=Philrelig
}}
{{WikiProject India|class= c|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Hinduism|class= c|importance=Top|myth=yes|vaishnavism=yes}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=C|importance=Top}}
{{WPBiography|living=no|class=c 
|listas = Rama
}}
{{archive box|auto=yes}}

== Historicity section ? ==

Do we need this section at all, which currently contains claims by non-notable auto-didacts, which have been covered by popular media (in the weird news of the day style) but engendered ''no'' scholarly response ? I can't imagine that any other encyclopedic article will care to include this [[WP:UNDUE|undue]] [[WP:RECENTISM|recentism]]. &lt;br&gt;
Note: There ''may'' be respectable sources on the historicity of Rama (comparable to the ones in [[Historicity of Jesus#References]]), which would justify retaining this section. I am only claiming that the ''current contents'' are non-notable and not the topic ''per se''. [[User:Abecedare|Abecedare]] 21:42, 29 September 2007 (UTC)
:unnotable as it stands. I left it tagged for a while out of courtesy, but since it remains unaddressed, I suggest we remove it. There is some half-notable literature claiming that the Ramayana depicts the society of the Indus Valley Civilization (which flourished 2,000 years before the epic), your best bet for this is [http://satyameva-jayate.org/2007/09/22/search-for-a-historical-shrirama/ S.R.Rao] (the &quot;[[Dwaraka]] is Atlantis&quot; chap), but not even Rao goes as far as claiming a &quot;historical Rama&quot;. --[[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|(𒁳)]]&lt;/small&gt; 10:45, 3 October 2007 (UTC)
::there is {{cite journal | author = Akso Parpola | title = Pandaih and Sita: On the Historical Background of the Sanskrit Epics | journal =  Journal of the American Oriental Society | volume = 122 | number = 2 | date = April-June, 2002 | pages = 361-373 | doi = 10.2307/3087631 | url = http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0003-0279%28200204%2F06%29122%3A2%3C361%3APASOTH%3E2.0.CO%3B2-U&amp;size=LARGE&amp;origin=JSTOR-enlargePage}} [[User:Doldrums|Doldrums]] 13:24, 3 October 2007 (UTC)
:::Most of these articles (such as the one by [[Asko Parpola]]) talk about the possible historical background of Ramayana, so this stuff should go to the article [[Ramayana]]. [[User:Utcursch|utcursch]] | [[User talk:Utcursch|talk]] 13:58, 3 October 2007 (UTC)

What has happened to the article [[Historicity of Rama]]. It was deleted under the claim of being moved to the article: [[Rama]] but now the section has been removed!! Please replace this info. [[User:Kkrystian|Kkrystian]] 17:46, 7 October 2007 (UTC)
:Kindly explain the deletion of [[Historicity of Rama]] and the history section under [[Rama]]. I think the explanation/reasons given here are unsatisfactory.'''[[User:BalanceRestored|&lt;span style=&quot;color:navy;font-size:12;&quot;&gt;BalanceΩrestored&lt;/span&gt;]] '''&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:BalanceRestored|&lt;font color=&quot;tan&quot; face=&quot;Times new roman&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 08:51, 17 October 2007 (UTC)

::Here's a site dedicated to the Historical [[Rama]] -http://www.historicalrama.org/ . Other sources:
* [http://lakdiva.org/aryan/rama.html  Lord Ram was born in 5114 BC] 
*[[&quot;Ramlila in Delhi (Lav Kush Ramlila Committee, Redfort),&quot; http://www.lavkush.com]]*  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/59.176.15.235|59.176.15.235]] ([[User talk:59.176.15.235|talk]]) 15:24, 10 October 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
* [http://books.google.com/books?id=95wbAAAAIAAJ&amp;q=%22Historical+Rama%22&amp;dq=%22Historical+Rama%22&amp;pgis=1 History Versus Casuistry: Evidence of the Ramajanmabhoomi Mandir Presented by the Vishva Hindu Parishad to the Government of India in December-January 1990-91, By Viśva Hindū Parishad, Vishva Hindu Parishad, Published by Voice of India, 1991]
([[User:Ekabhishek|Ekabhishek]] ([[User talk:Ekabhishek|talk]]) 16:56, 1 October 2008 (UTC))

==Rama v Rama Raghava==
The two articles are about the same person. Thus they should be merged with a redirect. Any reasons not to do it? &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Tahoma;&quot;&gt;[[User:Wikidas|Wikidās ॐ]]&lt;/span&gt; 19:14, 12 April 2008 (UTC)

== Bot-generated content ==

A computerised algorithm has generated a [[User:Anybot/Rama|version of this page]] using data obtained from [[AlgaeBase]].  You may be able to incorporate elements into the current article. Alternatively, it may be appropriate to create a new page at [[Rama (alga)]]. [[User:Anybot|Anybot]] (&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Smith609|contact operator]])&lt;/small&gt; 16:07, 21 February 2009 (UTC)

== Rama Appeared 20 Million Years Ago ==

It is know from Vedic Sources that Rama appeared almost 20 million years ago in the 24th Treta-Yuga on the current Manvantara.  Shouldn’t his birth almost 20 million years ago be listed in the article.  Here are some of the many sources I have found that confirm Rama incarnated 20 million years ago in the 24th Treta Yuga of the Current Manvantara.  Please let me know what you think.  Thanks.

http://www.girirajji.com/other-avtars.html
 
http://sreeramakshetram.net/

http://www.indianresurgence.com/hindutva11.htm

http://nitaaiveda.com/Essays_and_Articles/When_did_Lord_Rama_appear.htm

http://www.iskconbrampton.ca/IB_Newsletter/NewsletterApr&amp;May08.pdf 

http://www.heb.gov.sg/hindumagazine/shm-sriramachandra.html

http://www.indiadivine.org/audarya/spiritual-discussions/30963-dating-ramayana.html

http://www.hvk.org/articles/0208/63.html

http://sanjit-sdps.blogspot.com/2007/09/how-old-is-ram-setu-dr.html

http://www.indiadivine.org/audarya/spiritual-discussions/35117-how-long-ago-lord-sri-ramachandra-present-earth.html

http://acharya.iitm.ac.in/mirrors/vv/literature/brahma.html

http://bharata-hindunation.blogspot.com/2008/09/ram-setu-save-our-heritage.html 

http://www.indiadivine.org/audarya/vedic-culture/185285-authentic-india-hindu-history-timeline-corrected-british-distortions.html

http://indiaculture.net/talk/messages/128/9712.html?1002297138

http://hitxp.wordpress.com/2007/09/16/birth-date-of-rama/

http://bhargavasarma.blogspot.com/

http://books.google.com/books?id=a2KPChj7lTwC&amp;pg=PA511&amp;lpg=PA511&amp;dq=What+yuga+did+Rishabha+appear+in%
3F&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=NaZ_39f4aS&amp;sig=Lojrt-0tCNFKeBAYQgbTZRNapI8&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=BwH9SYO4Jp7EtAOXnoDXAQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2
[[User:Eronel189|Eronel189]] ([[User talk:Eronel189|talk]]) 02:53, 5 May 2009 (UTC)

:Thanks for bringing this issue to the talk page, instead of adding the content repeatedly to this article and [[Ramayana]]. Note that:
:# Rama is not a [[Vedas|Vedic]] deity. The primary sources for him are the Ramayana and the Puranas.
:# None of the sources you list above are acceptable for wikipedia; see [[WP:RS]] for waht kind of sources are considered reliable. For subjects like [[Rama]], [[Ramayana]], we essentially need to look for articles or books by reputable authors published by mainline publishers.
:That said, if you can find a source that talks about the traditional dating for Rama's life, we can add that to the article and attribute it to the relevant scriptural text. [[User:Abecedare|Abecedare]] ([[User talk:Abecedare|talk]]) 03:21, 5 May 2009 (UTC)

== THE VEDAS, VEDIC CULTURE, SANSKRIT, THE VEDIC PERIOD, and HINDUISM  ARE OVER 311 TRILLION, 40 BILLION YEARS OLD ==

Hi I, I am writing this because I believe there needs to be serious change on Wikipedia articles involving the age of the Vedas, Vedic Culture, Sanskrit, The Vedic Period, and Hinduism.  I already acknowledge that science does not agree with the fact that the Vedas are hundreds of trillions of years old, but even so there could still be some acknowledgement that Hindus do believe there  Religion, Culture, and Vedas are Hundreds of trillions of years old as it was revealed to Bramha by Krishna (Vishnu) at the time of his birth about 158.7 trillion years ago.  The Vedas were spoken in Sanskrit and then Bramha spoke it to mankind and  the Vedas were written down in Sanskrit hundreds of trillions of years ago by Mankind.  Bramha lives for 311 trillion, 40 billion years and about 51 years of his life is over.  This means the Vedas have been spoken for at least 158.7 trillion years.  There are many cycles of Brama.  After Bramha dies there is a period of unmanifestation in the Universe which lasts for 311 trillion, 40 billion years (the lifetime of Bramha).  Then a new Bramha is born and Krishna (Vishnu) speaks the Vedas to him again and thus it is passed on to Mankind.  This is a central belief in Hinduism about the Orgin of the Vedas.  Also the Avatars of Vishnu appear millions, and billions of years ago.  For example Krishna appeared in the 28th Treta-Yuga of the current Manvantara 5236 years ago and He spoke the Bhagavad-Gita in around 3141 BC. This gives the age of the Bhagavad-Gita 5,150 Years.  In the Bhagavad-Gita it is mentioned that Krishna first spoke the Bhagavad-Gita to the Sun God Vivisvan over 2 million years ago.  This should be mentioned.  In Hinduism Rama incarnated nearly 20 million years ago in the 24th Treta Yuga in the current Manvantra and Parshurama incarnated over 41 million years ago in the 19th Treta Yuga.  Vamana is said to have incarnated 93 million years ago in the 7th Treta Yuga of the current Manvantara and Matsya, Kurma, Nrismha, and Varah incarnated at the beginning of the current Manvantara during the Satya Yuga which means they incarnated over 120 Million year ago.  It is also mentioned that these Lila or Kalpa Avatars descend every 8.64 Billion Years (A Day of Bramha).  I think that these are important beliefs that should be mentioned.  I have spent many hours  finding many reliable sources about these beliefs.  I am not saying that you have to believe this and state this as truth.  All I am saying is that in the Wikipedia articles you acknowledge this as Hindu beliefs.  It is important that this is at least acknowledged as important Hindu beliefs of the date of their religion and gods.  You can still keep Your Scientific European dates of the Vedas  of 1,000, 2,000 years but it would be nice if you acknowledged the fact that Hindus believe their religion, culture, and Vedas are hundreds of trillions of years old and their incarnations have appeared millions and billions of years ago.  I have included sources on the declining life expectancy of the Yugas.  The length of Bramh’s day and Life, Creation of the Vedas, many sources confirming Hindu’s believe in 330 Million Gods and sources that state the 25 lila avatars of Vishnu and that they descend once in day Bramha.  I have given many sources that state Hindus believe the Bhagavad-Gita is older than 5,000 years old.  Since Krishna incarnated  during the last Dvapara Yuga 5,236 years ago and Kali-Yuga began on 3102 BC. When Krishna departed.  This means our current Kali-Yuga began 5,111 years ago.  Also I given information on Manvantars and shown that a Manvantara is about 307 million years long and a new Manu lives in Each Manvantara.  When the Flood wipes out the population every 307 million years Manu restores the Vedas and Vedic Civilization.  Also during every Dvapara Yuga God descends and writes down the Vedas for a new Kali-Yuga.  I have given names for all of these writers in each Dvapara Yuga.  All of this information is sourced.  Also every 8.64 billion years after Bramha wakes up from his night he restores the Vedic Civilization in the Universe and the Vedas are thus written down again every time Bramha wakes up.  Bramha lives for 311 trillion, 40 Billion Years and his day is 4.32 billion years long and his night is also 4.32 billion years long.  Bramha has 360 days in his 1 year and he lives for 100 of his years which means he lives for 36,000 days.  This means that Bramha restarts the Vedic Civilization 36,000 times during his life and the Vedas are rewritten over 36,000 times in Sanskrit and given to Humanity.  In addition the Vedas are written at the end of every Dvapara-Yuga to prepare for the Ignorace of the Kali-Yuga.  Since people will be generally less intelligence the Vedas are re-written at the end of every Dvapara-Yuga.  Vysa was the last one of these writers who re-wrote the Vedas 5,200 Years ago.  I have given the age of all of these Yugas as Satya Yuga is 1.728 Million Years long, Treta Yuga is 1.296 Million Years long, Dvapra Yuga is 864,000 years long, and Kali-Yuga is 432,000 Years long.  Since there are innumberable Bramhas the Vedas are rewritten also every 622 trillion, 80 billion years.  Krishna (Vishnu) first gives Bramha the Vedas and then in 311 trillion, 40 billion years Bramha dies and there is an equal period of unmanifestation  of 311 trillion, 40 billion years in which the Universe is void.  This equals 622 trillion, 80 billion years.  Then another Bramha is born the Vedas are rewritten again.  The Vedas are written in Sanskrit and since like the Vedas Sanskrit is present in innumerable cycles of 311 trillion, 40 billion years Sanskrit as a language is also considered eternal.  Can’t this be acknowleged in  the Hindu articles as important beliefs of Hindu’s.  I am not asking for you to accept this as true, I am only asking you to acknowledge the fact that this is what Hindu’s believe about the Vedas, Sanskrit, and their religion.  They believe that the Vedas are hundreds of trillions of years old, and Sanskrit too.  Thus they believe Hinduism was founded by God and is many hundreds of trillions of years old.  Can this just be acknowleged that Hindu’s believe the Bhagavad-Gita is about 5,150 years old, than Krishna appeared 5,236 years  ago that Rama appeared about 20 million years ago and Parshurama appeared about 41.5 million years ago and Vamana apperared about 93 million years ago and that Matsya, Kurma, Varah, and Nrisma appeared over 120 million years ago and that they all appear every 8.64 billion years (A day of Bramha).  Here are my many sources about these topics.  Thank You for taking the time and effort to read this.



I have many sources that show that in Satya Yuga the average lifespan was 100,000 years.
In Treta Yuga the average lifespan was 10,000 years.
In Dvapara Yuga the average lifespan was 1,000 years.
Here are some sources.

YUGA LIFESPANS

http://veda.krishna.com/encyclopedia/time.htm

http://www.salagram.net/cycleOages.html

http://www.salagram.net/kalki.html

http://www.reference.com/browse/wiki/Yugas

 http://books.google.com/books?id=a2KPChj7lTwC&amp;pg=PA486&amp;lpg=PA486&amp;dq=People+live+for+100,000+years+in+Satya+Yuga&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Na_Z7ba4fL&amp;sig=WUK0Ea_OmIAfl7267iQrEH7RAtw&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=iqqMSoj7NoTysQOTrIDkCQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false

http://www.starworldnews.com/kalpas-and-yugas.html

http://www.7thunders.com/mf/vision7/currentageofdarkness.pdf
 
http://www.srivaishnava.org/sgati/sddsv2/v02019.htm

http://www.healthandyoga.com/html/news/psychological/spm_yae.asp

 http://www.harekrishnatemple.com/bhakta/chapter19.html

http://www.vaikunt.org/AyyaVaikuntar/kalanemi.htm

http://courseware.acadiau.ca/courses/engl/3663/wiki/index.php/Kalyug

http://www.thelemapedia.org/index.php/Yuga

http://salvia.us/archive/10815.shtml

http://sawaal.ibibo.com/puja-and-rituals/which-r-4-yugas-according-hinduism-454649.html

http://answers.google.com/answers/threadview/id/538112.html

http://www.scribd.com/doc/7708796/Yuga


Here are some sources proving that there are 330 Million gods in Hinduism

330 MILLION HINDU GODS

http://www.angelfire.com/id/croon/india/hindugods.html

http://www.slamnet.org.uk/re/hinduism.htm

http://www.angelfire.com/id/croon/india/krishna.html

http://www.gotquestions.org/hinduism.html
http://vpverma.spaces.live.com/Blog/cns!67605D0E98041091!115.entry

http://hindu.newsbeet.com/story/330-Million-Gods-in-Hindu-Religion/

http://hindu.newsbeet.com/

http://www.madison.com/communities/americanhindu/pages/Hinduism_is_the_.php?php_page_set=0

http://www.festivalsinindia.net/gods/index.html

http://www.religiousportal.com/HinduDeities.html

http://www.religiousportal.com/HinduDeities.html

http://www.newsreleaser.com/0000004577.html

http://www.cbn.com/health/fitness/bagby_yoga-alternative.aspx

http://jmm.aaa.net.au/articles/16402.htm

http://www.philosophy-religion.org/thought/religious-biblical-religion.htm

http://www.charismamag.com/display.php?id=13291

http://www.worldlanguage.com/Japanese/Products/Lonely-Planet-Travel-Guide-India-10th-Edition-English-45071.htm

http://www.sujanks.com/hindu/


Here are my sources for Brahma’s 311 trillion, 40 billion year lifespan.  I have many sources but if you would like more I could get thousands more just ask.  Thank You.

BRAMHA’S LIFESPAN IS 311 TRILLION, 40 BILLION YEARS AND HIS DAY IS 8.64 BILLION YEARS

http://vedabase.net/bg/8/17/en1


http://hinduism.iskcon.com/concepts/111.htm

http://www.kanglaonline.com/index.php?template=printkshow&amp;kid=910

http://www.hindunet.org/srh_home/1997_12/0006.html

http://www.bookrags.com/wiki/Hindu_units_of_measurement

http://www.experiencefestival.com/kalki-avatara

http://www.utahkrishnas.com/main/page.asp?id=999

http://www.holloworbs.com/daitya.htm

http://www.experiencefestival.com/years

http://www.deepmusic.org/essence.htm

http://namahatta.org/en/node/6996

http://bhagavadgitaasitis.com/8/17/en1

http://www.krishna.org/sudarsana/archive/mail/msg00008.html

http://www.krishna.org/sudarsana/archive/mail/msg00005.html

http://experiencefestival.com/treta_yuga/page/2

http://experiencefestival.com/yuga/page/2

http://www.newtalavana.org/bhaktivrksha/week-35.htm

http://members.fortunecity.com/bala595/hindu.htm

http://www.yoga-philosophy.com/eng/kala.htm

http://www.theosociety.org/pasadena/soph/sopsml05.htm

http://www.theosophy.com/theos-talk/200607/tt00447.html

http://www.theosophy.com/theos-talk/200212/tt00702.html


RAMA APPEARED 20 MILLION YEARS AGO IN THE 24TH TRETA YUGA OF THE CURRENT MANVATARA
The first source is a reliable source from ISKCON (INTERNATIONAL SOCIETY FOR KRISHNA CONSCIOUSNESS)
http://www.iskconbrampton.ca/IB_Newsletter/NewsletterApr&amp;May08.pdf  (Official Source from the International Society for Krishna Consciousness (ISKCON)
http://www.girirajji.com/other-avtars.html 
http://sreeramakshetram.net/
http://www.indianresurgence.com/hindutva11.htm
http://nitaaiveda.com/Essays_and_Articles/When_did_Lord_Rama_appear.htm
http://www.iskconbrampton.ca/IB_Newsletter/NewsletterApr&amp;May08.pdf http://www.heb.gov.sg/hindumagazine/shm-sriramachandra.html
http://www.indiadivine.org/audarya/spiritual-discussions/30963-dating-ramayana.html
http://www.hvk.org/articles/0208/63.html
http://sanjit-sdps.blogspot.com/2007/09/how-old-is-ram-setu-dr.html
http://www.indiadivine.org/audarya/spiritual-discussions/35117-how-long-ago-lord-sri-ramachandra-present-earth.html
http://acharya.iitm.ac.in/mirrors/vv/literature/brahma.html
http://bharata-hindunation.blogspot.com/2008/09/ram-setu-save-our-heritage.html http://www.indiadivine.org/audarya/vedic-culture/185285-authentic-india-hindu-history-timeline-corrected-british-distortions.html
http://indiaculture.net/talk/messages/128/9712.html?1002297138
http://hitxp.wordpress.com/2007/09/16/birth-date-of-rama/
http://bhargavasarma.blogspot.com/
http://books.google.com/books?id=a2KPChj7lTwC&amp;pg=PA511&amp;lpg=PA511&amp;dq=What+yuga+did+Rishabha+appear+in%3F&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=NaZ_39f4aS&amp;sig=Lojrt-0tCNFKeBAYQgbTZRNapI8&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=BwH9SYO4Jp7EtAOXnoDXAQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2



MATSYA APPEARED 122 MILLION YEARS AGO AT THE BEGINNING OF THE MANVATARA AND ALSO 2 BILLION YEARS AGO AT THE BEGINNIG OF BRAMHA’S DAY

Here is an account of Matsya’s incarnation

http://bvml.org/SBBTM/sma.html




THE 25 LILA OR KALPA AVATARS OF VISHNU APPEAR EVERY 8.64 BILLION YEARS

Here is a list of the 25 Avatars of Vishnu known as Lila Avatars. They are also referred to as Kalpa Avatars because they appear every Kalpa or day of Bramha which is 8.64 billion years.

http://www.veda.harekrsna.cz/encyclopedia/avatars.htm#2

KRISHNA APPEARS EVERY 8.64 BILLION YEARS

http://www.vnn.org/editorials/ET0008/ET23-6179.html


THE VEDAS ARE OVER 311 TRILLION, 40 BILLION YEARS OLD

Krishna spoke the Vedas to Bramha during his birth 311 trillion, 40 Billion years ago.  Thus the Vedas are 311 trillion, 40 Billion years old.  Bramha then passed the Vedas on to mankind.  Since the Vedas were originally spoken in Sanskrit by Krishna to Bramha to mankind this means that the Sanskrit language is also over 311 trillion, 40  billion years old.

http://www.veda.harekrsna.cz/encyclopedia/vedas-purpose-origin.htm

http://www.hinduwisdom.info/Hindu_Cosmology.htm

http://www.sepiamutiny.com/sepia/archives/003342.html


THE BHAGAVAD-GITA IS OVER 5,000 YEARS OLD

The fact that the Bhagavad-Gita was written during the Mahabharta means that the Mahabharta is also over 5,000 years old.

http://news.iskcon.com/node/1593

http://www.yoganetwork.co.uk/about-yoga/classic-yoga-texts/bhagavad-gita.html (Dated to 3141 BC)
http://www.highestwisdom.com/

http://www.creedopedia.com/topics/Bhagavad-Gita

http://satyuga.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=63&amp;Itemid=30

http://www.indiadivine.org/audarya/spiritual-discussions/449905-when-bhagavad-gita-written.html

http://www.lifepositive.com/chinmayamission/gita.html

http://veda.wikidot.com/bhagavad-gita

http://www.sacredriversyoga.com/bhagavad.html

http://www.bhagavad-gita.org/Articles/vyasa.html

http://search.techrepublic.com.com/search/bhagavad+gita.html

http://ccsenet.org/journal/index.php/ass/article/view/947

http://www.iskconhk.org/html/en/activities/events/index.php?CLm=11&amp;CLd=9&amp;CLy=2007&amp;c_num=Demo_horizontal

http://www.teosofia.com/gita/gita-intro.html

http://nytsanga.blogspot.com/

http://www.kuzhalmannamagraharam.info/articles/bhagavadgita-and-management.html

http://scsmath-canada.com/

http://www.rickross.com/reference/krishna/krishna35.html

http://www.asitis.com/8/17.html

http://www.advaita.org.uk/discourses/enlightenment/enlightenment.htm

http://press.krishna.com/book/export/html/5

http://www.iskconbellingham.com/?page_id=12

http://www.anusha.com/krishna.htm


There are Millions of more sources If you want Just Search IT.


Thank You once again for your time and effort.

[[User:Eronel189|Eronel189]] ([[User talk:Eronel189|talk]]) 22:28, 6 May 2009 (UTC)

:Eronel189, As I mentioned above, if you have a [[WP:RS|reliable source]] for the traditional dating of Rama's life, we can include that information in the article. Huge text dumps and listing numerous unreliable website is worth nothing, and edit-warring is not the way to go. [[User:Abecedare|Abecedare]] ([[User talk:Abecedare|talk]]) 20:15, 8 May 2009 (UTC)
::Agreed. Text dumps about yugas do not constitute a conversation. The birthplace is still there at Ayodhya? Its there, so it ain't 40 billion years old. No tract of land survives for 311 Trillion, 40 billion years--[[User:Whiteguru|Whiteguru]] ([[User talk:Whiteguru|talk]]) 03:31, 16 February 2011 (UTC).

== Lead image edit-warring ==
{{Gallery
|width=150
|lines=2
|File:Hanuman_before_Rama.jpg|Current image
|File:Srisita_ram_laxman_hanuman_manor.JPG|Alternate #1
|File:Rama Sita Lakshmama.jpg|Alternate #2
|File:Rama-Sita coronation.jpg|Alternate #3
}}

Truth only truth, the article has had a stable lead/infobox image for at least a year and a half. Rather than edit-warring, you should discuss your proposed change, and try to find consensus for a new image (or to keep the current image). See [[WP:CON]] to learn how to work in cooperation with other editors, and then follow those guidelines by trying to find consensus on this talk page. Thanks, [[User:Priyanath|Priyanath]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Priyanath|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/i&gt; 20:24, 8 June 2009 (UTC)

:The main image has been updated for the better of the reader, so that he or she gets the best. The previous image is a painting that is more of a personal opinion as it shows Rama, Laxman, and Sita in modern outfits (Mughal in my opinion). It is merely a painting. The image that I have updated has been taken from a [[Hindu temple]] and this is what is the general trend of depiction of Ram and Sita in Hindu temples in India and abroad. Anyone who has been to a few Hindu temples can confirm the validity of my update. Run a Google search on Ram and you will find that my image edit is deserved.[[User:Truth only truth|Truth only truth]] ([[User talk:Truth only truth|talk]]) 21:30, 8 June 2009 (UTC)

::The proposed lead image is a [[Wikimedia Commons]] file: [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Srisita_ram_laxman_hanuman_manor.JPG]. It has been taken from [[Bhaktivedanta Manor]], a temple in Watford [[England]].[[User:Truth only truth|Truth only truth]] ([[User talk:Truth only truth|talk]]) 21:36, 8 June 2009 (UTC)

:::I've put the latest image you are proposing in the box above, along with the current image. Editors are invited to give feedback, or propose other images. I personally ''much'' prefer the current one, as the other is not very artistic or notable/historic. If you click on the large version of each one, that is especially true. The current image is a 17th century painting from the [[Smithsonian Museum]]. Truth only truth, thanks for discussing, and please give several days for other editors to give their opinion so there can be consensus. [[User:Priyanath|Priyanath]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Priyanath|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/i&gt; 21:48, 8 June 2009 (UTC)

The [[:File:Srisita_ram_laxman_hanuman_manor.JPG |proposed image]] is already included in the article- just scroll down and look !  Instead of edit-warring on the lede image why not try searching for better examples that (1) have some historical value/significance, and (2) perhaps depict Rama more clearly (larger fraction of the image), (3) have a free license ? [[User:Abecedare|Abecedare]] ([[User talk:Abecedare|talk]]) 22:12, 8 June 2009 (UTC)

:I am aware of this but putting an image from down to up is not against any Wiki policy. My cause is clear -- the depiction should be as close to acceptance as possible .[[User:Truth only truth|Truth only truth]] ([[User talk:Truth only truth|talk]]) 04:57, 9 June 2009 (UTC)

I have added [[:File:Rama Sita Lakshmama.jpg| another possible alternative (#2)]]. It's no better than the current choice, but at least shows a blue-skinned Rama in yellow dhoti, as is traditional for Vishnu avatars in Indian art. [[User:Abecedare|Abecedare]] ([[User talk:Abecedare|talk]]) 22:27, 8 June 2009 (UTC)

If one takes out the Hanuman from the present image [http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/0/0b/Hanuman_before_Rama.jpg] then it does not even look like an image of Ram, Sita, and Laxman. The ideal image would be [http://bhaktiyoga.files.wordpress.com/2009/04/lord_rama_pg16_l1.jpg], we are looking for such a copyright free image. Most [[Hindus]] have images like [http://bhaktiyoga.files.wordpress.com/2009/04/lord_rama_pg16_l1.jpg] in their home temples. The main image is need not illustrate art but reality.[[User:Truth only truth|Truth only truth]] ([[User talk:Truth only truth|talk]]) 04:57, 9 June 2009 (UTC)
:I am not sure what you mean by, &quot;not illustrate art but reality&quot;. Any lead image of Rama will necessarily be an artistic depiction of Rama. All three images above + the bhaktiyoga image are simply examples of such representations during different time periods. 
:See the infobox image in [[Ganesha]] and read its footnote to see what would make an ideal candidate. Museums or books are likely to be the best places to look for  such images and iconographic analysis. [[User:Abecedare|Abecedare]] ([[User talk:Abecedare|talk]]) 06:05, 9 June 2009 (UTC)
::'Reality' means a depiction which common people understand in the present day. If a painting was produced in the 17th century and has an artistic impression, it does not mean that it is the generally accepted impression. We can use both the images you have suggested in this article in the art section on Rama, but I think for the main image we need a better one like [http://bhaktiyoga.files.wordpress.com/2009/04/lord_rama_pg16_l1.jpg].  [[User:Abecedare|Abecedare]], your uploaded image of Parvati-Ganesh [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Parvati_Ganesha.jpg], which was being used as a lead image in the article on [[Parvati]] is highly offensive. Roaming in a T-shirt painted with your uploaded image [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Parvati_Ganesha.jpg] in India would lead a person into serious troubles. More can be discussed on image sense.[[User:Truth only truth|Truth only truth]] ([[User talk:Truth only truth|talk]]) 08:49, 9 June 2009 (UTC)
::: About [[:File:Lord Ram.jpg]], if I remember right, this image was the infobox image of this article before it was deleted on Commnons as copyright violation. Now, it is uploaded again. About [[:File:Srisita_ram_laxman_hanuman_manor.JPG]], the marble statues that ISKCON temples often have, do not reflect the blue colour of Rama's traditional iconography.--[[User:Redtigerxyz|&lt;font color = &quot;red&quot; &gt;Redtigerxyz&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt; [[User talk:Redtigerxyz|Talk]] &lt;/sup&gt; 04:37, 12 June 2009 (UTC)
:::: Alternate #3 is a common representation of Rama's coronation. --[[User:Redtigerxyz|&lt;font color = &quot;red&quot; &gt;Redtigerxyz&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt; [[User talk:Redtigerxyz|Talk]] &lt;/sup&gt; 13:44, 12 June 2009 (UTC)
::::: In my opinion, Alternate #3 is fit to be the lead image. I vote for Alternate #3. -- [[User:Truth only truth|Truth only truth]] ([[User talk:Truth only truth|talk]]) 21:11, 12 June 2009 (UTC)

Alternative #3 is worth including in the article. The only problem in making it the lede image is that it would be difficult to list all the persons shown in the poster, since that may make the caption unwieldy for the infobox. Also, Red, is there a way to photoshop out the blowup in the bottom-center of the image ? [[User:Abecedare|Abecedare]] ([[User talk:Abecedare|talk]]) 21:20, 12 June 2009 (UTC)
:: I tried that but lots of hands in between. The caption could be &quot;coronation of Rama with Sita (center on the throne), surrounding by his brothers and other deities including Hanuman (bottom left)&quot; No need to enlist everyone. --[[User:Redtigerxyz|&lt;font color = &quot;red&quot; &gt;Redtigerxyz&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt; [[User talk:Redtigerxyz|Talk]] &lt;/sup&gt; 04:27, 13 June 2009 (UTC)
::: Fine for now and an improvement over the current image. Can update if and when we find better example. [[User:Abecedare|Abecedare]] ([[User talk:Abecedare|talk]]) 04:58, 13 June 2009 (UTC)
:::: Now the lead image makes sense. -- [[User:Truth only truth|Truth only truth]] ([[User talk:Truth only truth|talk]]) 22:05, 13 June 2009 (UTC)

: The lead image doesn't contain the source [[User:Ashmrcool|Ashish Sharma]] ([[User talk:Ashmrcool|talk]]) 13:04, 7 December 2010 (UTC)

:: The lead image has the source in the description as British Museum. --[[User:Redtigerxyz|&lt;font color = &quot;red&quot; &gt;Redtigerxyz&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt; [[User talk:Redtigerxyz|Talk]] &lt;/sup&gt; 16:05, 7 December 2010 (UTC)
:::The lead image as at 16 February 2011 is not an appropriate image for this page. It is more an idol than is it an image that captures the essence of Rama, Sita, his court, and the Ramayana. --[[User:Whiteguru|Whiteguru]] ([[User talk:Whiteguru|talk]]) 03:26, 16 February 2011 (UTC)
{{Talk:Rama/GA1}}

== Other Views of Rama ==

Hi everybody, I have seen in many articles such as Jesus, and Krishna many views of each are provided in different religions for example, a Christian View of Jesus is given along with a Muslim view, a Bahai view ect, and with Krishna a Amhadhiya Islam view is given, a Jain view, ect.  For the same reason of expanding this article could we give a Krishna Conscious view of Rama as the 22nd avatara of Krishna?  I think this would be nice since other deities have multiple views.  I was also wondering if the other 25 avatars of Krishna could also get a Krishna Conscious view so that the articles can be well balanced with many different viewpoints. Please let me know if this is okay.  Thank You very much for your time and cooperation.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/75.15.186.94|75.15.186.94]] ([[User talk:75.15.186.94|talk]]) 04:34, 10 December 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:ISKCON's focus on Krishna is important, and mentioned in the [[Krishna]] article. However their views on other avatars are not noteworthy features of the subjects, and are best discussed in [[ISKCON]] and [[:Category:International Society for Krishna Consciousness]] articles. [[User:Abecedare|Abecedare]] ([[User talk:Abecedare|talk]]) 05:50, 10 December 2009 (UTC)

:: The ISKCON view is a sectarian, minority  view, not of mainstream Hinduism and Vaishnavism. --[[User:Redtigerxyz|&lt;font color = &quot;red&quot; &gt;Redtigerxyz&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt; [[User talk:Redtigerxyz|Talk]] &lt;/sup&gt; 06:21, 10 December 2009 (UTC)


That's good but since in many articles such as the Jesus article so many views are given from different religious beliefs.  Isn't it only fair that a Krishna Conscious view is also included.  In articles like the Jesus article there are Muslim views, Christian, Sikh Views, Amhadyia views, Hindu Views, Krishna Conscious views, Buddhist views etc.  This is a good article because it is well rounded and includes more than one view.  For this reason I don't think it is unreasonable to add one small sentence in the beginning explaining a differing view. What do you think?  Thank You very much for your time and cooperation.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/75.15.186.94|75.15.186.94]] ([[User talk:75.15.186.94|talk]]) 05:04, 11 December 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:As explained above ISKON's view is undue in this article because (1) ISKOCN forms a small sliver of Hinduism (few thousand among around a  billion Hindus), and (2) its views on Rama are neither central to its beliefs, nor are they a noteworthy feature of the subject of this article. You'll note that ISKCON is mentioned on the [[Krishna]] page, because while they still represent a tiny minority view, ISKCON is partially responsible for the spread of Krishna awareness in the West. Since the latter reason does not apply here, or any other Vishnu avatar pages, ISKCON's views on those are best discussed at [[ISKCON]] and [[:Category:International Society for Krishna Consciousness]] articles. [[User:Abecedare|Abecedare]] ([[User talk:Abecedare|talk]]) 05:23, 11 December 2009 (UTC)

== mythology? ==

why does it say mythology? is this also said for other religions on wikipedia? [[Special:Contributions/71.105.87.54|71.105.87.54]] ([[User talk:71.105.87.54|talk]]) 09:53, 2 May 2010 (UTC). Rama might have been a mythological figure, but as he is considered to be a real God re-incarnate by Hindus, one must not start a wiki page on him stating him to be a myth - just like is done in case of the wiki pages on Jesus Christ and Allah. Only later on - on the page - the issue of him being real or mythological should be highlighted.

== Rama's Birth Time ==

The Previous date 1450 BC for Rama's Birth makes no sense.  Krishna is known to be born at the end of Dvapara Yuga in 3228 BC.  Rama was born in the 24th Treta Yuga which would place his birth around 20 Million BC.  The Laghu-bhagavatamrta confirms Rama was born in the 24th Treta Yuga.  Even if Rama was born in the current Treta Yuga he would still have been born atleast 2 Million years ago.  Since 5,112 Years of Kali Yuga has passed, and before that 864,000 years of Dvapara Yuga, and 1.296 Million Years of Treta Yuga.  By Hindu calculations it would be impossible to come up with a date of 1450 BC unless Rama was born thousands of years after Krishna.  Rama came much before Krishna.  I changed the date according to Shrila Rupa Goswami's Laghu-bhagavatamrta.  I also posted sources for Shrila Rupa Goswarmi's Laghu-bhagavatamrta below.  The exact mention of Rama's birth can be found on page 69 of the first source which is a PDF.  I included this for easy and quick access to the information.  Even if this information isn't enough to establish a dating, it is still universally known among Hindus that Rama was born in Treta Yuga which would place his birth a tleast one million years if he was born in the current Treta-Yuga.  The article says Hindus believe Rama was born in 1450 BC but Hindus believe Rama was born in Treta Yuga not Kali Yuga.  Hindus Believe Rama was born before Krishna not 2,000 years after Krishna.  This means that even if Rama was born in the most recent Treta Yuga Hindus believe he must have been born at least 1 million years ago.   1450 BC is impossible because that would he was born in Kali-Yuga about 2,000 years after Krishna.


http://www.prabhupada.de/kusakratha/Kusakratha_Laghu-Bhagavatamrita.pdf
http://nitaaiveda.com/All_Scriptures_By_Acharyas/Rupa_Goswami/Laghu-Bhagavatamrta.htm
http://www.prabhupada.de/kusakratha.htm

:We do not source things from scripture. We source from reliable secondary sources, such as the analysis by historians of historical texts and data. The detail you are changing is sourced. It may not be changed. If you find a [[WP:RS|reliable secondary source]] which has a different opinion, you may ''add'' that opinion with a citation as to the source of the opinion to the article. If there are multiple notable opinions, we report them all. [[User:Yworo|Yworo]] ([[User talk:Yworo|talk]]) 15:05, 28 December 2010 (UTC)

:: The assertions that &quot;We do not source things from scripture. We source from reliable secondary sources, such as the analysis by historians of historical texts and data.&quot; is apparently not too correct, especially religious matter. For example, on page [[Jesus]], there are many references directly quoted from the Bible and other scriptures: http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Mt%2016:16;&amp;version=ESV; http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Lk%201:35;&amp;version=ESV; http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Mk%201:1;&amp;version=ESV; http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Jn.%203:18;&amp;version=ESV; etc. 

::Please see reference material on just one page: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesus#See_also, http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesus#Notes, http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesus#References, http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesus#External_links, etc. Please desist from applying different parameters for different religious pages.[[User:thisthat2011|&lt;font color=&quot;#FF9933&quot;&gt;.असक्तः सततं कार्य कर्म समाचर &amp;#124; असक्तः हि आचरन् कर्म..&lt;/font&gt;]] 06:56, 3 May 2011 (UTC)

::: in the '''21st century BC''' topic, it states &quot;According to Hindu tradition, lifetime of Rama, the 7th Avatar of Vishnu&quot;.  Does anyone know the source of this statement?  Does anyone know a scholarly estimate for Rama's timeframe?  Timing based on yugas obviously does not work. BTW, i have read an interesting observation form a researcher from the early 19th century who stated that all numbers of years from ancient texts had to be divided by at least 1,000 to get the real number, as it was a technique to hide the correct information.  [[User:Terrymacro|Terry Macro]] ([[User talk:Terrymacro|talk]]) 07:03, 28 April 2012 (UTC)

==File:Lord-Rama-Wallpaper-6.jpg Nominated for speedy Deletion==
{|
|-
| [[Image:Icon Now Commons orange.svg|50px]] 
| An image used in this article, [[commons:File:Lord-Rama-Wallpaper-6.jpg|File:Lord-Rama-Wallpaper-6.jpg]], has been nominated for speedy deletion at [[Wikimedia Commons]] for the following reason: ''Copyright violations'' 
;What should I do?
|-
|
| Speedy deletions at commons tend to take longer than they do on Wikipedia, so there is no rush to respond. If you feel the deletion can be contested then please do so ([[commons:COM:SPEEDY]] has further information). Otherwise consider finding a replacement image before deletion occurs.

''This notification is provided by a Bot, currently under trial'' --[[User:CommonsNotificationBot|CommonsNotificationBot]] ([[User talk:CommonsNotificationBot|talk]]) 16:23, 2 June 2011 (UTC)
|}

== Suggested changes to header ==

Rama is the Supreme God in the sects [[Ramanandi sect|Ramananda Sampradaya]] (the largest monastic order in south Asia, in which he is the [[Saguna Brahman]]) and [[Sant Mat]] (in which he is [[Nirguna Brahman]]), and is described as such in the scriptures [[Adhyatma Ramayana]] and [[Ramcharitmanas]] – the latter being one of the most popular scriptures in Hinduism, often called the Bible of northern India in the West. Given this, I believe the header of the article should at least mention these points of view in a sentence in addition to the seventh incarnation of Vishnu. Given these are widely held views (by the largest Sampradaya of Hindus and as per the equivalent of Bible in north India), per [[WP:DUE]] they should be included in the header in my opinion. Somebody talked about an ISKCON view which is held by a much smaller number of people and including it would be giving undue weight to a minority view. 

I have made a draft of the proposed new introduction under [[User:Nmisra/1]]. Please let me know if it looks okay, and suggest changes if it does not. I will make the changes in a week's time if there are no objections. [[User:Nmisra|Nmisra]] ([[User talk:Nmisra|talk]]) 03:15, 11 September 2011 (UTC)

Nmisra's version without references:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Rama, Devanāgarī: राम ; Rāma, Vemu ; Burmese: ရာမ Jàma̰ ; Javanese: Ramavijaya ; Khmer: ព្រះរាម Phreah Ream ; Lao: ພຣະຣາມ Phra Ram ; Malay: Megat Seri Rama ; Tamil: ராமர் Ramar; Thai: พระราม Phra Ram )[1] is one of the central figures and symbols in Hinduism.[2] He is the seventh avatar of Vishnu in several Vaishnava and Hindu traditions, and in the Ramayana of Valmiki.[3][4] He is the absolute and supreme God in the Ramananda Sampradaya (the largest monastic order in Hinduism),[5][6][7][8][9][10][11] and in the Adhyatma Ramayana and Ramcharitmanas. He was born in Suryavansha (Ikshvaku Vansh) ...
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

My version replacing the current Para 1 of the lead:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
'''Rama''' (Sanskrit: राम, IAST: Rāma)[1] or Ramachandra (रामचंद्र, IAST: Rāmacaṇdra) is one of the central figures in [[Hinduism]], specifically [[Vaishnavism]] and the protagonist of the [[Hindu epic]] [[Ramayana]]. He is worshipped as the seventh avatar of [[Vishnu]] in several Vaishnava and Hindu traditions, however regarded as the Supreme Being in some Rama-centric traditions. Rama is described as a [[Suryavansha|Suryavanshi]] king of [[Ayodhya]] and regarded as a historical individual by Hindus, who lived on in the last quarter of [[Treta Yuga]]. [End of para 1 of lead]
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Main points:
# Move all non-Sanskrit versions to Etymology sections. 
# Create section &quot;Worship as Supreme God&quot; or &quot;Ramaism&quot; to include details and the references collected. Not in lead --[[User:Redtigerxyz|&lt;font color = &quot;red&quot; &gt;Redtigerxyz&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt; [[User talk:Redtigerxyz|Talk]] &lt;/sup&gt; 05:18, 11 September 2011 (UTC)

::My view: Suggesting material additions to content first. The header as explaining the content can be considered as well. It is an interesting addition. Also Etymology suggestion looks good.&lt;font color=&quot;#FF9933&quot;&gt;इति इतिUAनेति नेति[[User_talk:thisthat2011 | &lt;font color=&quot;#FF9933&quot;&gt; Humour Thisthat2011&lt;/font&gt; ]]&lt;/font&gt; 09:35, 7 May 2012 (UTC)
==ARCHEO-ASTRONOMY==
The information provided in this section is a fringe theory and with no references provided, it should be removed in its entirety.  Unless some supporting evidence is provided, I will be deleting this section. [[User:Terrymacro|Terry Macro]] ([[User talk:Terrymacro|talk]]) 01:43, 8 July 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>itp9sxp1zxkl79wn5jyiqalcbdutrne</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
