<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Gautama Buddha</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>3396</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519787411</id>
      <parentid>518805432</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-25T16:43:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2.101.142.2</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Inspiration of Gautama Buddha */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="32959">{{Talk header |search=yes }}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 7
|minthreadsleft = 5
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Gautama Buddha/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Auto archiving notice |bot=MiszaBot I |age=3 |units=months }}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn 
|target=/Archive index |mask=/Archive &lt;#&gt; |leading_zeros=0 |indexhere=yes |template= 
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=no|class=C|core=yes|listas=Buddha, Gautama}}
{{WikiProject Buddhism|class=C|importance=top}}
{{WikiProject Hinduism|class=C|importance=mid|myth=yes}}
{{WikiProject India|class=C|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Nepal|class=C|importance=High|history=yes}}
{{WikiProject Philosophy|class=C|importance=High|philosopher=yes}}
{{WikiProject Japan|myth=yes |class=C |b1=no |b2=yes|b3=yes|b4=yes|b5=yes|b6=yes |importance=low |religion=yes }}
{{WikiProject Bahá'í Faith|class=C|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=C|importance=top}}
{{WP1.0|v0.5=pass|class=C|importance=Top|category=Philrelig|VA=yes}} 
}}

== Birthplace(Kapileswara, Orissa) ==

Some of the references for birthplace in Orissa (#7 - 15) in fact state Lumbini as birth place, some only speculate Orisa could be the birthplace, and some are opinion essays. The contention that Orrisa is the birthplace should remain, but needs to be reworded to reflect correct information from credible and [[Wikipedia:Verifiability#What_counts_as_a_reliable_source|reliable]] sources only.
-[[User:BikashDai|BikashDai]] ([[User talk:BikashDai|talk]]) 16:14, 7 September 2012 (UTC)

== Buddha general description ==

Buddha was born in Nepal and he started his preaching from Nepal and not India. There is a big global political misunderstanding about his birth and teachhing that started from India and the word India in case of lord buddha in India is totally wrong. Buddha is a term used to describe the completely developed potential of each life. Once that life is competely aware of the causes of suffering and able to live only in truth from wisdom and compassion without any limitation then they made be called a Buddha.
Siddhartha Buddha is the only such life to have lived on the earth. However according to his teachings every life has the potential to reach this stage and countless numbers of Buddhas exist in different dimensions at any time. He was born in Nepal, Lumbini and started preaching from Nepal itself although there is a misunderstanding about his birth and preaching in India first.
Because every life has the potential to become Buddha there is no limit to the number of Buddhas. This is the main teaching which Siddartha Buddha explained as being the difference between Buddhism and the religions of the world.

== can not edit [even with a registration] ==

The word Buddha is a title for the first awakened being in an era.

the concept buddha means awakened one, there are COUNTLESS buddhas but no one can be lord gautam buddha who was born n brought up in nepal and he started his preaching from Nepal.

[[User:PadmaPhala|PadmaPhala]] ([[User talk:PadmaPhala|talk]]) 07:12, 29 June 2012 (UTC)

I {{agree}} with PadmaPhala about the meaning of Buddha. There is another page [[Buddhahood]] that explains the meaning of Buddha. A disambiguation page will be necessary after we have wikipedia articles about other major buddhas. Currently, Gautam Buddha is the only buddha known to the vast majority of the world. [[User:BikashDai|BikashDai]] ([[User talk:BikashDai|talk]]) 16:32, 7 September 2012 (UTC)

== About birth year and death year of Gautama Buddha at en.wikpedia.org ==

Almost all historical records accept that.........

* '''Buddha was born on a full moon day in BC 623'''.
* '''Buddhism was founded by Lord Buddha in BC 588'''.
* '''The Lord Buddha died (Nirvana) in BC 543 at the age of 80. These are correct years about Buddha'''.

But I saw years of Gautama Buddha at your en.wikipedia.org cited about Buddha's INCORRECT birth year and Buddha's INCORRECT death (Nirvana) year. You can do verify that history of Shwedagon Pagoda's ages in Burma (Myanmar). According to historical records, the Shwedagon Pagoda is over 2600 years old since B.C 588. Shwedagon is the oldest pagoda and the most ancient historical pagoda in Burma and in the world. The Shwedagon Pagoda, enshrining four Buddha hair relics, was built by King Okkalapa and two brother merchants in BC 588, the year when Lord Buddha gained enlightenment. Everyone can visit and testify to any document. You can visit following websites.

* [[http://www.myanmathadin.com/news/culture/2302-myanmar-to-hold-grand-religious-function-to-mark-2600th-anniversary-shwedagon-pagoda.html]]
* [[http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/666/]]
* [[http://dbsusa.org/?page_id=2]]
* [[http://www.sitagu.org/resources/files/Suzan_Hart_&amp;_Sayadaw.pdf (please see page 10 and 11)]]
* [[http://thetruelordbuddha.blogspot.com/]]
* [[http://www.knowledgerush.com/kr/jsp/db/viewuser.jsp?userId=21915&amp;penname=Doctrine+of+Lord+Buddha]]
* [[http://www.unz.org/Pub/SingletonEsther-1908v01-00124]]
* [[http://festivals.iloveindia.com/buddha-purnima/]]

Thank you for your reading!

&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[Special:Contributions/180.183.120.76|180.183.120.76]] ([[User talk:180.183.120.76|talk]]) 10:19, 4 July 2012 (UTC)

:According to the review article cited in the intro to this entry (&quot;The Dating of the Historical Buddha: A Review Article&quot; by L.S. Cousins):

{{blockquote|Within the Eastern Buddhist tradition of China, Vietnam, Korea and Japan (especially the latter two countries) the traditional date for the Mahaparinibbana (death) of the Buddha was 949 B.C., although a variant giving 878 B.C. is also possible. Earlier and down to the fifth century A.D. a date of 686 B.C. seems to have been fairly common. ... In the Northern Buddhism of the Tibeto-Mongolian cultural area the Mahaparinibbana was officially dated to 881 B.C., the origin of which is not clear. Both Chinese and Tibetan scholars were, however, well aware that many other dates had been advanced. This is in sharp contrast to the Southern Buddhist tradition, which has retained no memory of any disagreement over the basic chronology of events since the Buddha's lifetime.  ... The era they preserve places the Buddha's Mahaparinibbana in 543 B.C.}}

:So, it is not the case that all traditional Buddhists agree on the Buddha's dates. More recent scholarship casts doubts on all of those traditional dates. Cousins concludes, &quot;we should no doubt speak of a date for the Buddha's Mahaparinibbana of c.400 B.C - I choose the round number deliberately to indicate that the margins are rather loose.&quot;&amp;mdash;[[User:Greg Pandatshang|Greg Pandatshang]] ([[User talk:Greg Pandatshang|talk]]) 15:24, 4 July 2012 (UTC)


One of the problems with these &quot;protected&quot; topics is that once again we depend on the ever so careful and always repeating editor which has given us a homogenized version of history.  When the article states, regarding the birth year of Buddha, that &quot;most scholars agree&quot;, they fail to also mention that a good percentage of these scholars cite each other or copy the copies of a previous copier.  But since Buddhism is so unique, we must fail not to take certain things into consideration, such as how could the largest biography of one man (by 300 BC)have been somewhat codified in several centuries.  By Asoka's time Buddhism shows all the developmental signs of being at least several centuries old. It is well known that the Buddhists and Jains both claimed the king Ajatasatru as a convert to thier faith, and although most scholars agree that not one Indian religion has correctly recorded the order of kings from Upper India, it can be reasonably certain that Ajatasatru's date is firm.  That the Buddhists went about trying to convert both the lower class and demented kings is well known in Indian history, so much so that, before his conversion to Buddhism, it would be right to say that Hitler was an Asoka. This is just one point of many that you  probably wont get from the &quot;experts&quot;  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.111.161.30|76.111.161.30]] ([[User talk:76.111.161.30|talk]]) 19:13, 4 October 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== A few prevailing errors ==

Hello folks. I would like to draw your collective attention to a longstanding misconception in this article regarding the earliest sources for the life of the Buddha. The earliest source for the Buddha's life is the [[Pali Canon]] which precedes the sources currently mentioned by around three hundred years. An entire biography has been composed on the Buddha's life using first person statements drawn from the [[sutta pitaka]]. I refer to 'The Life of The Buddha' by [[Bhikkhu Nanamoli]]. This is a widely used and quoted source. Please will someone with an account correct this state of affairs.

* Buddha was born to Kshatriya tribe 
* Real name was Siddharth
* He was honest,intelligent and generous person
* He left his family,palace and all his belongings to his son
* He meditated under a palm tree and found &quot;Buddhism&quot;.
* He found people had problems because of their greed.They do wrong things to get more things like others.
* His teachings were spread far away places.
* Died at an age of 80 at Parnivana stage in Nepal.
* His last meal will be the source of the greatest merit as it was his last meal.

== Gautama and Siddartha the same? ==

I have watched many documentaries on this so-called one world new age religion of the west called new-age buddhism.  Its called buddhism because of its lies though.  Gautama and Siddartha are two different people.  Not only that but I will step it up a notch and claim Shakyhumni is a different person as well.  If there is one jesus christ there is one Gautama.  He was a giant from a royal family of north east india.  He was of Japanese ancestry.  The other demonic figure idolized or portrayed in eastern statues is siddartha.  He was an indian prince from South-western India whom crown was over thrown.  Gautama was born in late may and a well known traveler affiliated with Orpheus whom died in an urban environment.  He had a wife like the other version of the story.  Sid was born in April or late march he was human but humans had thick yellow skin 1200bce via traits from the past races (see rama's small human dragon race of nara).  He died under a tree by eating a seed and entered nirvana because the seed is poison to a being whom's mind is that far into 'enlightment' or actual creation of forms in the east. One version of the story has a wife much later after 6 yrs of meditation whilst the other version was born with a wife within the palace city walls.  Buddha never had two wives, so Gautama was born 400bce around war-time in india and spread of economic war governments whilst siddartha was 1200bce in tribal lands where competitions took place.  Gautama was tricked by not turning a guest down when offered bread.  His bowls could not take the wheat and he slowly started to die, he went into the city to die.  Both died by simply eating.  The reason why there is a tibet and etc was 100 bce creation of Tibet by a monk named shakyhumni.  His name is taken from scripture, as well he helped create china and the long line of lamas or disciples or aspirants via egypto-tibetan sources.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Asfd666|Asfd666]] ([[User talk:Asfd666|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Asfd666|contribs]]) 19:04, 2 August 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Pretty interesting stuff huh? And whats funny is I researched the names and Shakyhumni was a white aryan japanese.  Silver skin.  His name is Shakuhan which is a word Shakyhumni in chinese before it was chinese.  Nope couldn't be the same people.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Asfd666|Asfd666]] ([[User talk:Asfd666|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Asfd666|contribs]]) 20:03, 6 August 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Well, the above is all unsourced and fringey in extremis. However, it's interesting to reflect on the Buddha's names. Jayarava has some interesting points on his blog. Basically, the name Siddhartha appears in scripture very rarely and is quite late. Most of the time in scripture, he is named simply Gautama &amp;mdash; in fact, it's not totally clear that that is a family name rather than a given name. Part of the mystery of the name is that the Buddha's family is often identified as a Kṣatriya clan, whereas Gautama is a well-known Brahmin name. Jayarava observes that the Buddha's father is never identified as a Gautama, but his mother and step-mother (who were sisters) are both called Gotami. He concludes that the Buddha's people took their clan names through matrilineage and his mother's family (who were [[Koliyans]]) were a Brahmin clan.&amp;mdash;[[User:Greg Pandatshang|Greg Pandatshang]] ([[User talk:Greg Pandatshang|talk]]) 14:25, 7 August 2012 (UTC)

True, Gautama's race or family betrayed him and created the japanese, just like shakyhumni did so the tibet race (which as we know became chinese as well as the japanese race) and siddartha the indian race, but that would be too extreme wouldn't it?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Asfd666|Asfd666]] ([[User talk:Asfd666|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Asfd666|contribs]]) 00:33, 16 August 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Edit request on 17 August 2012 ==

Gautam Buddha Was not Avatar Of Vishnu. Please remove this.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/122.169.248.108|122.169.248.108]] ([[User talk:122.169.248.108|talk]]) 10:30, 17 August 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Edit request on 28 August 2012 ==

{{edit semi-protected|answered=yes}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;
gautam buddha was not born in india... and kapilvastu is not in india.. he was born in kapilvastu which is in lumbini district of NEpal.. please correct it
&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[Special:Contributions/14.102.109.172|14.102.109.172]] ([[User talk:14.102.109.172|talk]]) 10:22, 28 August 2012 (UTC)

:{{ESp|rs}} [[User:Floating Boat|&lt;font color=&quot;teal&quot;&gt;A boat&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Floating Boat|&lt;font color=&quot;navy&quot;&gt;that can float!&lt;/font&gt;]] [[Special:Contributions/Floating Boat|&lt;font color=&quot;purple&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;(watch me float!)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 13:09, 28 August 2012 (UTC)

edit request on 31 August 2012 
Here I want to protest and to confirm again that Gautam Bhudda was born in Nepal's kapilvastu of Lumbini District. He was from the Sakya Community of the area, hence he is also called as Sakya Muni. The picture in of the birth place that is taken in the wikipidia is of that same place. you can confirm that via searching google earth as well. This is a great mistake that you should correct as soon as possible, since it hurt the feeling of all us Nepalese.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Nirugrg2012|Nirugrg2012]] ([[User talk:Nirugrg2012|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Nirugrg2012|contribs]]) 04:25, 31 August 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
* What exactly is the content that you want to change? - [[User:SudoGhost|Sudo]][[User_talk:SudoGhost#top|Ghost]] 04:54, 31 August 2012 (UTC)
* The birthplace of Lord Buddha should be changed to it's respectable and original place. i.e Kapilbastu, Lu,bini, Nepal. And the information of the birthplace as Indian subcontinent should be removed. For real information on Lord Buddha's birthplace feel free to visit Nepal and visit the birthplace yourself and read the ancient books in the various old monasteries related to Lord Buddha.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Nepami|Nepami]] ([[User talk:Nepami|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Nepami|contribs]]) 15:37, 14 September 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
**You said the same thing below, please keep the discussion in one place, I've responded there. - [[User:SudoGhost|Sudo]][[User_talk:SudoGhost#top|Ghost]] 16:32, 14 September 2012 (UTC)

== Correct the birthplace of Gautama Buddha, and the information related to Suddhodana ==

The birthplace of '''Lord Gautama Buddha''' (Founder of buddhism) as mentioned in the wiki is given as '''from the Indian subcontinent'''. Lord Gautama Buddha was born in ''''''Kapilbastu'''''', '''''Lumbini''''', '''''Nepal''''' and '''Nepal''' is not an '''Indian Subcontinent'''. Lord Buddha was originally a prince of Kapilvastu who was born and raised there. He latter left the palace seeking  enlightenment and went to the south(Indian region). The sources of this information are the books about Lord Gautama Buddha. And also the ''''''Shakya''''''s are the original resident of '''Nepal'''. ''''''Suddhodan'''''' the father of Lord Gautama Buddha was the king of Kapilvastu and not the 'elected chief of a tribal confederacy' as mentioned in the wiki. These can also be found on the books about Lord Gautama Buddha and his life. The originally written books describe these clearly while the other books printed by copying the information (By mostly Indians) from these books describes the birth place and the king as completely different places and position. You can find the books at the old monasteries dedicated to Lord Buddha in Nepal. And also the other things to prove the birthplace of Lord Gautama Buddha is that the king Ashoka build the ''''''Ashoka pillar'''''' at Lord Gautama Buddha's birth place as his gratitude lies also in Kapilvastu, Lumbini, Nepal. Nepal is the original birth place of Lord Gautama Buddha and it is not any Indian subcontinent. And if anybody seeks more source or proofs i gladly welcome them to Nepal and visit the place.

So i request the writer of this article to review the content and do the correction that is needed in the wiki about Lord Gautama Buddha.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Nepami|Nepami]] ([[User talk:Nepami|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Nepami|contribs]]) 15:29, 14 September 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Nepal is in the Indian subcontinent.  The exact place of birth is not universally agreed upon, although it is usually given as in present-day Nepal, the only thing all of the differing sources on the birthplace have in common is that it is somewhere in the Indian subcontinent, and all of this is reflected in the article. - [[User:SudoGhost|Sudo]][[User_talk:SudoGhost#top|Ghost]] 15:35, 14 September 2012 (UTC)

It is not about the agreeing. The birth place is located in the Kapilvastu, Lumbini, Nepal. It is discussed by other people as it is in other places but is truely in Nepal. So the place name should be mentioned in the aricle's first sentence.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Nepami|Nepami]] ([[User talk:Nepami|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Nepami|contribs]]) 16:57, 14 September 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Again, that's not reflected by reliable sources.  We cannot say &quot;the birthplace is X&quot; as if it is a universally accepted fact, because it isn't.  The first sentence of the article does not say anything about a birthplace whatsoever, so there isn't any incorrect information to fix. - [[User:SudoGhost|Sudo]][[User_talk:SudoGhost#top|Ghost]] 20:07, 14 September 2012 (UTC)

== Sources on Gautama Buddha's birthplace ==

This is becoming a habit...

===Kapilavastu===
A quick scroll through my library gave four sources. In chronology of first publishing c.q revised publication:

====A.K. Warder 2000 (first edition 1970, third revised edition 2000)====
* {{citation | last =Warder | first =A.K. | year =2000 | title=Indian Buddhism | place=Delhi | publisher =Motilal Banarsidass Publishers}}

Warder writes (p.45):
{{quote|The Buddha [...] was born in the Sakya Republic, which was the city state of Kapilavastu, a very small state just inside the modern state boundary of Nepal against the Indian frontier.}}

====Hans Wolfgang Schumann, 1998 (first print 1982)====
* {{Citation | last =Schumann | first =Hans Wolfgang | year =1998 | title =De historische Boeddha | place =Rottersam, Netherlands | publisher =Asoka}}

Schumann writes (p18):
{{quote|Kapilavatthu, de vaderstad van de Boeddha, waarin hij de eerste 29 jaar van zijn leven doorbracht, ligt niet ver van de grens die tegenwoordig het koninkrijk Nepal van het staatsgebied van de republiek India scheidt. De vader van de Boeddha heette Suddhodana 'Die zuivere rijst verbouwt' en behoorde tot de stam de Sakiya's. De Sakiya's waren ''khattiya's'' en behoorden dus tot de (toen nog) hoogste kaste, de krijgs- of beter: ambtsadel, die het bestuur en de rechtshandhaving van de Sakiya-republiek tot taak had. Uit hun midden werd, indien nodig, de nieuwe raja gekozen, de president der republiek en voorzitter van de raadsvergadering. In het midden van de zesde eeuw v. Chr. was het Suddhodana die het raja-ambt vervulde.&quot;}}

In translation (Google translate, in brackets my adaptations):
{{quote|Kapilavatthu, the home town of the Buddha, [where] he [lived the] first 29 years of his life, is not far from the border that now [separates] the kingdom of Nepal [from] the area of ​​the Republic of India. The father of the Buddha [was called] Suddhodana &quot;[Who grows]] pure rice&quot; and belonged to the tribe [of the] Sakiya. The Sakiya's were Khattiya's'' and thus belonged to the (then) highest caste, the martial-or better: nobility of office, which [had the task of] the administration and enforcement of the Sakiya republic. From their midst was, if necessary, [elected] the newraja, the president of the republic and president of the council. In the middle of the sixth century BC. [it] was Suddhodana [who fulfilled] the raja-office.}}

====Maurice Walsh, 1995====
* {{Citation | last =Walsh | first =Maurice | year =1995 | title =The Long Discourses of the Buddha. A Translation of the Digha Nikaya | place =Boston | publisher =Wisdom Publications}}

Walsh writes (p.20):
{{quote|He belonged to the Sakya clan dwelling on the edge of the Himalayas, his actual birthplace being a few miles north of the present-day Indian border, in Nepal. His father was in fact an elected chief of the clan rather than the king he was later made out to be, though his title was ''raja''  - a term which only partly corresponds to our word 'king'. Some of the states of North India at that time were kingdoms and others republics, and the Sakyan republic was subject to the powerful king of neighbouring Kosala, which lay to the south.}}

====Peter Harvey, 1990 (first publication, reprint 1995)====
* {{Citation | last =Harvey | first =Peter | year =1995 | title =An introduction to Buddhism. Teachings, history and practices | publisher =Cambridge University Press}}

Harvey writes (p.14):
{{quote|We know that Gotama was born in the small republic of the Sakka (Skt Sākya) people, which straddles the present border with Nepal and had Kapilavatthu as its captial.}}

Harvey also writes (p.15):
{{quote|In the early Buddhist texts, there is no ''continuous'' life of the Buddha, as these concentrated on his teachings. Only later, between 200 BC and 200 AD, did a growing interest in the Buddha's person lead to various schools producing continuous 'biographies', which drew on scattered accounts in the existing ''Sutta'' and ''Vinaya'' collections, and floating oral tarditions. These 'biographies' include the sarvastivadins' ''Lalitavistara'', the Theravadins' ''Nidanakatha'', and Asvaghosa's poem, the ''Buddhacarita''. The details of these are in general agreement, but while they must clearly be based around historical facts, they also contain legendary and mythological embellisgments, and it is often not possible to sort out one from the other. While the bare historical basis of the traditional biography will never be known, as it stands it gives a great insight into Buddhism by enabling as to see what the ''meaning'' of the Buddha's life is to the Buddhists: what lessons it is held to contain.}}

====Conclusion====
These four sources agree that Gautama Buddha was born &quot;was born in the Sakya Republic, which was the city state of Kapilavastu, a very small state just inside the modern state boundary of Nepal against the Indian frontier&quot; (Warder):
* The Buddha was born at the Indian sub-continent.
* The Buddha was born in the Sakya republic.
* The Buddha was ''not'' born in present-day Nepal; 2500 years ago there was no present-day Nepal, but the Sakya-state.
* The Sakya-state was situated in what today is Nepal
* The Buddha was not the son of a king, but the son of an &quot;elected chief&quot;.
* The Buddha's biography was written later from scattered pieces of information.

Friendly regards, [[User:Joshua Jonathan|Joshua Jonathan]] ([[User talk:Joshua Jonathan|talk]]) 08:32, 21 September 2012 (UTC)

===Orisa c.q. Kapileswar===
* [http://www.hindu.com/fline/fl2204/stories/20050225001008800.htm] No sources or references.
* [http://www.rediff.com/news/2002/sep/16spec.htm] Very interesting. Unfortunately no written sources (books, journals, etc.) ...
* [http://www.srilankaguardian.org/2008/03/buddha-born-in-orissa-scholars.html]  Copies other sites; no references &amp; sources.
* [http://orissa.gov.in/e-magazine/Journal/jounalvol1/pdf/orhj-3.pdf The Orissa historical research journal, Volume 47] Really interesting. But I've no idea what the credibilities of this journal are.
* [http://books.google.nl/books?id=1sAKAAAAYAAJ&amp;q=The+Real+Birthplace+of+Buddha+orissa&amp;dq=The+Real+Birthplace+of+Buddha+orissa&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=L5uWT9uxBcTorAev-_3SDQ&amp;redir_esc=y] A book publication. That's good - though it does not prove yet that Orisa was the Buddha's birthplace.

At least it's interesting, though I do get the impression that these webpages are mainly published by Orisa-connected people, wether citisens or archeaologists working there. Nevertheless, at least it's interesting. Compliment for the effort to find sources! Friendly regards to everyone, [[User:Joshua Jonathan|Joshua Jonathan]] ([[User talk:Joshua Jonathan|talk]]) 09:19, 21 September 2012 (UTC).

::Valid references should remain but the [[Wikipedia:Verifiability#Questionable_sources|questionable ]] sources should be removed to to comply with the Wikipedia policy on [[Wikipedia:Verifiability#Reliable_sources|relaible sources]] and also for [[NPOV|neutral point of view]]. Thank you Joshua for checking them all. I was not able to verify all in-text references because some of those links were blocked by my institution's firewall for web security reasons.--[[User:BikashDai|BikashDai]] ([[User talk:BikashDai|talk]]) 19:17, 28 September 2012 (UTC)

== Edit request on 20 September 2012 ==

{{edit semi-protected|answered=yes}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;
Following section is very wrong and need to be corrected please.
''''Gautama is said to have developed supramundane abilities including: a painless birth conceived without intercourse; no need for sleep, food, medicine, or bathing, although engaging in such &quot;in conformity with the world''''
please contact Kalyana dharma peramuna through info@srikalyanadharma.org(web site wwww.srikalyanadharma.org)
This is a very trustworthy organization with participation of highly educated buddhist monks in Sri Lanka.
Buddhism is not a religion.It's a philosophy which guide you how to get rid of sufferings in our lives by understanding the cause of suffering.
Buddhism shows the path to understand the link between mind and suffering.
&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[Special:Contributions/64.231.65.186|64.231.65.186]] ([[User talk:64.231.65.186|talk]]) 02:05, 20 September 2012 (UTC)
:If I understand correctly, the objected to passage is speaking of one of many traditions, which is in conflict with a/the Sri Lankan traditions beliefs. Either way, need some sort of source that isn't an e-mail address.--[[User:Tznkai|Tznkai]] ([[User talk:Tznkai|talk]]) 03:00, 20 September 2012 (UTC)
::Setting this as answered (and it is denied)--[[User:Tznkai|Tznkai]] ([[User talk:Tznkai|talk]]) 04:28, 24 September 2012 (UTC)

== Edit request on 25 September 2012 ==

{{edit semi-protected|answered=yes}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;

In the first paragraph, it is written that buddha was born in indian subcontinent. It is absolutely true but it gives a vague meaning and most people understands this expression as buddha was born in India.

I would like to request to avoid such ambiguity and clearly mention that buddha was born in Lumbini,Nepal.

I think this would give more clear view.

Regards
&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[Special:Contributions/165.229.108.130|165.229.108.130]] ([[User talk:165.229.108.130|talk]]) 08:10, 25 September 2012 (UTC)
:See the discussions above for this issue. [[User:Torreslfchero|Torreslfchero]] ([[User talk:Torreslfchero|talk]]) 08:33, 25 September 2012 (UTC)
:I am closing this request as it appears this issue is currently being discussed elsewhere on this talk page. &amp;mdash;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#808080&quot;&gt;[[User:Kuyabribri|'''KuyaBriBri''']]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#008080&quot;&gt;[[User_Talk:Kuyabribri|''Talk'']]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 13:42, 25 September 2012 (UTC)

== Inspiration of Gautama Buddha ==

Two primary means of inspiration of the initiating figures in all beliefs exist, either by dreams or by visions. Both are the means by which the Creator (any other defining name) speaks to humanity (see Numbers 12:6 in the Bible) to inspire them for: 
1. work,
2. life goals, 
3. relationships, 
4. timely information or knowledge, 
5. principles or morals to live by, 
6. health and diet, 
7. foreseen cautions and dangers. 

All dreamed or visioned content falls under these 7 categories (or their sub-categories). 

[[Gautama Buddha]] was a visioner (so were [[Mohammed]], [[Guru Nanak]], [[Nostradamus]] and some of the biblical prophets. The most apocalyptic and prophetic content of the Bible is dreamed). Very little is said about his visioning or prophetic content he received. Not much is said about how he taught his followers to vision or how to use what they got as visions. Is this oversight by the site's maintainers, or the effects of religion's bureaucracy and the related ignorance and inability of later followers? (Every religion suffers a loss of knowledge about the inspiration and nature of its use of its founding figure(s) due to bureaucratized disbelief and ignorance of the very people who took on the job of maintaining ALL the knowledge, methods and techniques. The knowledge and use is always replaced or superimposed by rites, rituals, calendrical events and other social or superficial content making emulation of the functions of inspiration extremely difficult and frequently devalued.) [[Special:Contributions/67.225.52.80|67.225.52.80]] ([[User talk:67.225.52.80|talk]]) 16:12, 26 September 2012 (UTC) Alan Harmony  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/67.225.52.80|67.225.52.80]] ([[User talk:67.225.52.80|talk]]) 15:33, 26 September 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Wikipedia needs [[WP:RS|reliable sources]] to [[WP:V|verify]] information in articles.  Do you have any reliable sources for this? - [[User:SudoGhost|Sudo]][[User_talk:SudoGhost#top|Ghost]] 16:07, 26 September 2012 (UTC)
Reliable? hardly... few take anything not researched by English or American professors to be reliable or verified. [[Special:Contributions/67.225.52.80|67.225.52.80]] ([[User talk:67.225.52.80|talk]]) 16:12, 26 September 2012 (UTC) Alan Harmony

==Was he real?==
Hi guys.  Forgive me for asking but this article appears to be written in such a way as to assume that this guy really existed. Are there any contemporary sources which prove that?  How about something written at the time of his life by a &quot;hostile witness&quot;...  Someone who acknowledged he did exist, but did not support him.  Looking at the tone of say [[Jesus]] and looking at this article it appears that the author is far more certain that Buddha was real than Jesus. [[Special:Contributions/2.101.142.2|2.101.142.2]] ([[User talk:2.101.142.2|talk]]) 16:43, 25 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>f2s2agxkvw7ysed7a38jtx9qrjw2ffu</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
