<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Romanian Orthodox Church</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1281016</id>
    <revision>
      <id>476028416</id>
      <parentid>441863143</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-02-09T22:49:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>CommonsNotificationBot</username>
        <id>14413849</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Notification of possible deletion of [[:commons:File:420 Conducatorii de partid si de stat.jpg|File:420 Conducatorii de partid si de stat.jpg]] ([[User_talk:ErrantX|feedback]], Version [[User:CommonsNotificationBot/changelog|r97]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="63019">{{ChristianityWikiProject|class=B|importance=|eastern-orthodoxy=yes|eastern-orthodoxy-importance=}}
{{WPRA|class=B}}

This article is very large, but it is terribly biased, with so many items coming from what appear to be a very nationalistic view. I will try my best to made it NPOV, but I ask for everyone's help. [[User:Crculver|Crculver]] 12:34, 15 Dec 2004 (UTC)

: It appears to me to be a hodgepodge :) [[User:Bogdangiusca|Bogdan]] | [[User talk:Bogdangiusca|Talk]] 13:35, 15 Dec 2004 (UTC)

Hodgepodge toi_même :) Terribly biased is only the ignorance of some of would-be editors, like crculber. And biased ignorance is not a point of view. It is only this - a terrible lack of points of view. Whoever wants to have a God's like point of view, above bird's eye views and even above common sense is obscene. Nobody invented a more poorly disgusting substitute of objectivity than would-be self-righteous vigilantes. Invoking npovism while you promote a prepostorous povista, yourself, is the so called &quot;no point of view fallacy&quot;. It also strikes my senses like a madman's attempt to be rational. Alas, rationalizing madness in the form of &quot;encyclopedias&quot; without the concept of truth is only a point of view - the worst ever, and the only possible dust-raising non-resting maelstrom. Learn from logical developments based on knowledge:

All of these, in conclusion, might explain the huge success of Christianity in the Romanian regions, which may demonstrate the very first attested organization of Christianity for a complete nation in Europe.

==Religious intolerance==  	 
According to [[United_States_Department_of_State|US department of state]] International Religious Freedom Report [http://parl.gc.adventist.org/documents/world_reports/wr2000.htm], there were many cases in which Orthodox church acted against other minority religions.

''Several minority religious groups complained that local authorities and Orthodox priests prevented religious activities from taking place, even when the groups had been issued permits. The Seventh-day Adventist Church reported difficulties in obtaining approvals to use public halls for religious activities following pressure by Orthodox priests.'' 	 

''According to minority religious groups, the local inspectors for religion classes are typically Orthodox priests who deny accreditation to teachers of other religions. According to Baptist reports, in some cases, school directors denied access in their schools to teachers of neo-Protestant religions. Religious teachers are permitted to instruct only students of the same religious faith. However, minority religious groups, including the Baptist Church, credibly asserted that there were cases of children pressured to attend classes of Orthodox religion. The Seventh-day Adventist Church also complained that the School Inspectorate of Cluj County included in the school curriculum only one of the requested three classes on Adventist religion, although there were sufficient students for three full classes. In addition, the Baptist Church reported that, at some festivities in public schools, all students, irrespective of their religious affiliation, must attend Orthodox religious services. The same reportedly happened in the Army.''

==Christianized Dacians==

: According to an old theory... However, the weight of evidence, from archaeological to linguistical to ecclesiastical history...

I can't believe this. The article is claiming that that the Dacians were already Christianized when they were conquered by the Romans. That's original. :-) [[User:Bogdangiusca|Bogdan]] | [[User talk:Bogdangiusca|Talk]] 19:03, 15 Dec 2004 (UTC)

It's not original. You just have to copy and paste from Tertullianus. Do you know where? Do you care? Indeed, who cares? Your opinion is much more important than his, isn't it ? And the super-POV aka &quot;non-pov&quot; is the golden standard. I am right because I am nonpov? Where did I hear this &quot;argument&quot; before ? Ah, Stalin !

: Indeed, Tertullianus enumerates about 25 nations and lands Christians could be found, among them, there are the Dacians. However, let me remind you that it was written around the year 200 AD, therefore about a century after the Roman conquest of the Dacians. This is not a proof that the Dacians were Christians before that. [[User:Bogdangiusca|Bogdan]] | [[User talk:Bogdangiusca|Talk]] 19:31, 5 Jan 2005 (UTC)

Bogdane, Duhul Bisericii nu este polemic, ci irenic. 

: O fi el irenic, dar duhul wikipediei e NPOV.

Ce e duhul wikipediei? Ce emanatie ? Sau doar pronatie ? ;-)

Dacii erau, de la Philippi la Axiopolis, primii m&amp;#257;rturisitori. 

: În afar&amp;#259; de Sci&amp;#355;ia Mic&amp;#259;, nu exist&amp;#259; nici o dovad&amp;#259; c&amp;#259; dacii au fost cre&amp;#351;tiniza&amp;#355;i.

Nu pricepi bre! Ce înseamna pentru tine dacii? Abecedarul ? Dacii au un timp si un spatiu. Tu crezi ca romanii au cucerit mai mult de 20% din tinuturile orizontului dacic, si ca au facut asta cu mai mult de doua legiuni mai bine de cinci generatii? Nici macar. Daca nu exista dovezi nu înseamna ca sunt dovezi ca nu exista. Foloseste capul si judeca si singur. Sunt convins ca o poti face fara wikinfectia meningelor cu laturile ei npoviste, stahanoviste sau doar dinamoviste.

Consensul cercet&amp;#257;rilor, f&amp;#257;r&amp;#257; pete, este acesta.

: Nu e nici un consens. To&amp;#355;i marii istorici români spun c&amp;#259; în Dacia, cre&amp;#351;tinismul a venit odat&amp;#259; cu Imperiul Roman.

Nu e consens ca nu vrei tu! Tu ce consens ai ?

De ce te apuci tu s&amp;#257; rescrii Scripturile, Sfânta Traditie si istoria neamului românesc? Ce fac ei, nu desface! Nu uita ca au fost martiri iar neamul românesc este crestin de la radacinile sale pâna la Judecata De Apoi. Neamul nu este o constructie umana, ci o realitate Hristologica. Daca nu pricepi, nu pune punctele tale de vedere sau ale altora în marele cazan în care se încearca topirea si distilarea adevarului. Tu esti de-al nostru, nu de-al lor.

: &quot;Amicus Plato - amicus Aristoteles - magis amica veritas&quot; :-) [[User:Bogdangiusca|Bogdan]] | [[User talk:Bogdangiusca|Talk]] 21:13, 9 Jan 2005 (UTC)

Ai uitat pe &quot;sed&quot;. Dar ai facut lectiile ceva mai bine azi. Oricum, daca ti-e prieten adevarul, nu se vede din ce scrii. Astept multe ameliorari si sunt mereu pe-aproape sa te corectez in ce minuni mai faci...

Cu drag, întru Hristos, 
Al t&amp;#257;u, Dan


----

: However, the weight of evidence, from archaeological to linguistical to ecclesiastical history, points to a different story, especially since [[Paul of Tarsus|Saint Paul]] and [[Silas|Silvanus]] first preached into the ''Miniature Macedonian Rome'' of [[Philippi|Caesarea Philippi]] and only later in [[Rome]] proper.

: An impressive number of [[toponym]]s, ethnographical material and the most ancient church tradition - also attested in writing by [[Eusebios]] since the [[4th century]] follow Saint Andrew, the '''Apostle of Dacia and Scythia Minor'''. All of these could not possibly have been maintained ''in situ'' in a non-Christian organized Dacia: If the Christian faith were only brought there by Romans or Roman prisoners rather than growing locally as a grass root phenomenon, then only a few early Christian remains would be on record. In fact, the Roman army deserted north-of-Danube, Left Bank Dacian provinces ''in corpore'' starting as soon as the Goths (who were christianized only later) invaded it, around [[240]] AD. There are more recent historians who maintain that Christianity became widespread much later, with the Byzantine troops of the [[Eastern Roman Empire]] then with the extension of ''Byzantine'' '''[[Romania]]'''. Others still point to the Caucasian [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]] or [[Iberia]], and the Lesser [[Armenia]] as the first Christian countries. All of them fail to explain the unique liturgical [[vocabulary]] of Romanian which could only have been acquired at the very sources of Early Christianity. Cunningly, even [[Edward Gibbon]], as early as the [[1780]]s, vindicates an early Christianization beyond the Left Bank of the Lower Danube.

: After [[297]], on the territory of the Roman province of [[Scythia Minor]] (now [[Dobrudja]], between the Right Bank of the [[Lower Danube]] and [[Tomis]] on the western shores of the [[Black Sea]]), [[martyrs]] of the [[Christianity|Christian faith]] are legion.

: Had Dacians received Christianity as ''religio illicita'' only via the crypto-Christians among the Roman troops (therefore after the Dacian Wars ended in [[106]], and before the [[276]] Roman military retreat) the deep, lasting and ''grass root organization'' of the Early Romanian Orthodox Church would remain unexplained. Truth of the matter, as always, must be searched within a larger body of knowledge:

I don't know what do with these. :-) [[User:Bogdangiusca|Bogdan]] | [[User talk:Bogdangiusca|Talk]] 19:19, 15 Dec 2004 (UTC)

That's honest. Than don't, Bogdane, who cares what your name means for Isacceans, and etymologists :-)

: There is nothing that could indicate a pre-Roman Christianization of the Dacians: none of the Dacian words that were kept into Romanian are in any way linked to religion; all early church sites were in the Roman Empire. I am still waiting for references that indicate otherwise. [[User:Bogdangiusca|Bogdan]] | [[User talk:Bogdangiusca|Talk]] 22:17, 5 Jan 2005 (UTC)

Dragul meu, ideea ta despre daci, stramosii tai, este o imagine de Epinal. Vrei sa citesti o carte introductiva ? Este la http://perso.wanadoo.fr/pleiadele.dacilor/ Are password dar poti sa-i scrii autorului ca mine si ti-l da gratis.

==Dumitru Staniloae==

Was Father Dumitru Staniloae really regarded widely as the undisputed greatest Christian theologian of the 20th Century? Should there be quotes from all the denominational figures? Or perhaps &quot;one of the greatest&quot; could be better? (I'm not editing the article as I have no knowledge of who Staniloae is) --[[User:Whitti|Whitti]] 01:36, Dec 26, 2004 (UTC)

==Not NPOV and/or factual wrong==
Moved from the article:
: Factors involved in Christianization of Dacians
: Neighboring the [[Roman Empire]] well before the birth of [[Jesus Christ]], Dacians were organized religiously in a system that impressed the authors of antiquity, from [[Plato]] to [[Saint Justin Martyr]] and [[Tertullianus|Quintus Florus Septimius Tertullianus]] - the famous [[Carthagina|Carthaginian]] [[church father]] from the late [[2nd century]]. In ''[[Adversus Iudaeos]]'', Tertullianus literally and explicitly mentioned Dacians as followers of [[Jesus Christ]].
:Much unlike others who were converted later and sometimes only ''&quot;upside-down&quot;'' - by force, starting with their military leaders (peoples extant or only arriving in Europe after the birth of [[Jesus Christ]]), Dacians were not migratory hordes. Although they had that proven military might usually associated by the Roman authors with the epithet of ''barbarians'', Dacians also followed a well established centralized authority, maintained a continuous record of spiritual tradition, exerted harmonious systems of trade and thrived on self-sustained economics.
:All of these must have prepared conversion to Christianity in a solid, lasting, and now very well proven manner.

:Rich [[Romanian language|Romanian]] [[folklore|folkloric]] [[ethnographic]]al and [[tradition]]al material and some extremely rich or unique archaeological records demonstrate a solid, organized, and widespread Christian life at the Lower Danube well in advance of the first [[ecumenical synod]]s. From the times of ethnogenesis, the Eastern Roman people of Romania grew in parallel (and indeed symbiosis) with Orthodox Christianity. Notably, the [[Old Church Slavonic]] and [[Gothic Rune]]s [[alphabet]]s have been developed north of the Lower Danube by missionaries of the [[New Rome]], to help Christianize the Goths and the Slavic invaders of that Roman Empire [[limes]]. Complete Christianization of the Slavic peoples, with help from the Daco-Romanian population, gradually succeeded towards the officially recorded year, later in the [[10th century]], three hundred years after their invasion of the [[Byzantine Empire]].

==Oldest Known ? By Whom? By Wikipedissimi eruditissimi viri ?==

In fact there are hundreds perhaps even thousands of churches older than the one you illustrate, by an indiscriminate, uncritical cut and paste &quot;process&quot; of thinking. A few dozen are still being researched today by the competent archeologists. 

: Oldest know ''ORTHODOX'' church. Those you are mentioning are indeed Christian, but of the old Roman rite. Remember that Orthodoxy came from South of Danube, which explains why it is in [[Turnu Severin]]. [[User:Bogdangiusca|Bogdan]] | [[User talk:Bogdangiusca|Talk]] 15:28, 13 Jan 2005 (UTC)

Look under the fundations of extant Churches and you will always find older ones. The Orthodox are always at the foundation! Even I could quote you a few dozen here below, with the approximate date of foundation :

 333 Beroes - oldest in SE Europe Piatra Frec&amp;#259;&amp;#355;ei (jude&amp;#355;ul Tulcea)&lt;br&gt;
 353 Callatis - Mangalia, (jude&amp;#355;ul Constan&amp;#355;a)&lt;br&gt;
 357 Dinogetia - Gârvan (jude&amp;#355;ul Tulcea)&lt;br&gt;
 358 Troesmis - Igli&amp;#355;a-Turcoaia, (jude&amp;#355;ul Tulcea)&lt;br&gt;
 358 Axiopolis - Hinog lâng&amp;#259; Cernavoda (jude&amp;#355;ul Constan&amp;#355;a)&lt;br&gt;
 358 Constantiana - Capul Dolojman&lt;br&gt;
 359 Noviodunum - Isaccea&lt;br&gt;
 361 Ulmetum - Pantelimon&lt;br&gt;
 364 Ibida - Slava Rus&amp;#259; singura din Scythia Minor cu trei altare spre r&amp;#259;s&amp;#259;rit&lt;br&gt;
 365 Isvoarele&lt;br&gt;
 367 Niculi&amp;#355;el (on this very page, next illustrations)&lt;br&gt;
 369 Densu&amp;#351; - oldest north of lower Danube still in use today&lt;br&gt;
 398 Slaveni ? (jude&amp;#355;ul Olt)&lt;br&gt;
 412 Sarmizegetusa (jude&amp;#355;ul Hunedoara)&lt;br&gt;
 457 Porolissum - Moigrad (jude&amp;#355;ul Salaj)&lt;br&gt;
 435 Morisena - Cenad (monastery)&lt;br&gt;
 449 Sucidava - Celei (jude&amp;#355;ul Timi&amp;#351;)&lt;br&gt;
 860 D&amp;#259;bâca&lt;br&gt;
 900 Corbii de piatr&amp;#259;&lt;br&gt;
1177 Bodrogu Vechi (Hodo&amp;#351;) Ciala&lt;br&gt;
1057 Dinogetia - Gârvan (jude&amp;#355;ul Tulcea) - reconstructed&lt;br&gt;
1066 Alba Iulia (actual catholic cathedral was built upon it)&lt;br&gt;
1168 Drobeta - Turnu Severin&lt;br&gt;
1304 &quot;Biserica din deal&quot; din Ieud&lt;br&gt;

Before the independence, &quot;'''prea luminatul, blagocestivul &amp;#351;i de Hristos iubitorul, r&amp;#259;posatul Io Radu Negru Voivod la leat 6800 (1292)'''&quot; had a document mentioning Câmpulung as capital. How would you figure a capital without (at least a Metropolitan) Church?

1370 Biserica metropolitan&amp;#259; din Severin, sub Vladislav Vlaicu 

To your satisfaction, Avars, Bulgars and their Slavic slaves destroyed, between 525 and 900, a great number. That doesn't mean there are not older churches than the one in the misleading German picture.

Bibliography? Where should you start, really ? For instance, read the Apostles, read Tertullianus, read the published local folklore, visit the places, read some Church History, read some Romanian history, and then (and only then) please come back here for a really useful, factual contribution. These are indispensable passages. Without them and with more of your scissors, Wikipedia becomes a Fictionary :O)

You are however right in at least one aspect - not far from Turnu Severin, at Schela Cladovei, you have the oldest shrine, with a clear inscription beneath it, and the first stable city in Europe, some 11,967 years old !

==Bogdane, de ce desfigurezi articolul despre Biserica str&amp;#259;mo&amp;#351;easc&amp;#259;?==

Tu e&amp;#351;ti de-al nostru, sau în solda Wikidio&amp;#355;ilor?
Tu denigrezi istoria patriei sau o distilezi doar, ca s&amp;#259; &quot;cadreze&quot; cu masturba&amp;#355;ia intelectual&amp;#259; a &quot;mae&amp;#351;trilor gânditori&quot; de la Bomipedia?
Nu uita c&amp;#259; tu e&amp;#351;ti cine e&amp;#351;ti, iar nu o pocitanie f&amp;#259;r&amp;#259; identitate, ca ei, pentru c&amp;#259; anonimii pe care tu îi &amp;#351;tergi din articol &amp;#351;i-au dat via&amp;#355;a lor f&amp;#259;r&amp;#259; ca s&amp;#259; crâcneasc&amp;#259;. Sau tu vrei s&amp;#259;-i mai omori odat&amp;#259; prin uitare?
Altfel nu uita c&amp;#259; Mihnea Turcitul, de&amp;#351;i arâta acelora ca un pom înflorit, era pe dinl&amp;#259;untru doar un lac împu&amp;#355;it.

Vezi c&amp;#259; mâine este Boboteaz&amp;#259;!
Mai spal&amp;#259; din p&amp;#259;cate, apoi începe anul altfel, mai bine.

Cu dragoste întru Hristos,

Dr Dan Jâp&amp;#259;, MD, PhD
danjipa la taie-mi nasul.freemail.iris-ward.com

:: Eu aş zice că o dai în şovinism ... tipul vrea să ofere o viziune '''REALISTĂ''' a BOR ... tocmai din cauza asta acest articol nu ar trebui editat de cei ca tine, adică simpatizanţi ai lui hristos (am scris intenţionat cu h mic :P), cărora le este mult prea greu să păstreze o imagine obiectiva a subiectului tratat.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/92.82.87.111|92.82.87.111]] ([[User talk:92.82.87.111|talk]]) 11:48, 19 July 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Why an anonymous?==
Aren't there thousands of monks with a Christian name ? Also, for whom is &quot;oldest known&quot; legend kept? Aren't there knowledgeable editors around ?





==The Wrong images abund, the good ones are deleted==
Again, aren't there knowledgeable editors around ?

=== Fallacious statement ===
&quot;Romanians hold that their church is the first national, first attested and first apostolic (church built by the Apostles themselves) in [[Europe]]&quot; - This statement is preposterous, especially considering that the autocephalous Romanian church dates back to the 19th century. [[User:VMORO|VMORO]]

My poor friend, you are prepostorously ignorant in the matter and you'd better maintain your pathetic points of view in the general direction of the Wikipodologic background noise (nu pun intended). What do you know about what you write? Since when autocephalic features equal the list of firsts? You are in deep confusion, so go back to the Fox channel news where you build your preposterous sentences, especially considering that your own culture does not date back more than the 19th century...

::If you want to say something meaningful, sign it. If not - hold your mouth shut. My country's culture goes back to the 7th century and beyond that. Considering that as late as the 17th century the official language of the church and state in Wallachia was Bulgarian, your beating in the chest looks a bit absurd. [[User:VMORO|VMORO]]

Dear VMORO,&lt;br&gt;
I'm Danilo Prepeleac Jâp&amp;#257;, and i respect both you and your nation as much as I respect truth. When i child, like many in Bucharest, I learned your language in order to look at sume decent TV - the only one accessible there under that name, BTV. However, I will not argue abut facts, but Bulgarian was never an official or liturgical language north of the lower Danube. Old Slavic perhaps, but only in the context of &quot;boscorodeala&quot;. Besides, the Germans had their Gothic alphabet and their first Bible translated north of the Lower Danube, by Ulfila, from local (Latin-written) copies. The first ecumenical council, Saint Sava, and all those bishops and martyrs used a Romance language in Church for six or seven centuries before the Slavs even enetered Scythia Minor, to say nothing about settling there. Old Bulgarian is a language now so tragically lost with its Asian origins (Balkh? Volga? Urals?). The Dacians, neo-Dacians, Daco-Romans, Daco-Romanians, proto-Romanians, Balkan Latin, Aromanians - you name it - but we both know I refer to the people of the place, the autochtonous people north and south of the Lower Danube, were not distracted by the Arian heresy either. Bulgarians first emerged as a Czarate only with a Vlach Czar, and do we need to recall the most famous &quot;Bulgarian&quot; Johannitius... They say I have a Bulgarian name too... Yet both you and I know I am only a Vlach. Please pardon me if once again I looked anonymous and stupid, to say nothing about chest pains. &quot;Do not confuse your brother. If you lose his esteem, you lose Christ. And if you love your brother's heart, you've earned a place in Christ!&quot;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
With love in Christ,&lt;br&gt;
Yours, Dan

==Stakhanov had a field day in his tomb==
==By seeing you, buddies, at work, defiguring this article, the game of numbers has won==
===Problem is, what?===

You have diluted the meaning of the article. You have &quot;edited&quot; out the text, by betraying the spirit of the original until it became nonsense. This article no longer represents what it says it describes. When I read it today, I couldn't stop from washing my eyes in &quot;shock and awe&quot;. Common sense, historical data and that special living &quot;thing&quot; which animated the original are now killed. Although I attempted to mend fences, I only found the text to be beyond repair. This is now only an administrative document, produced by a committee. This no longer is conveying sense.

It's useless to argue with you. You don't understand facts, and  interpretations, let alone value and synthesis. You don't use logic. You pretend under some fictitious &quot;reason&quot; - since I cannot, in good faith call a movement of bile which yields generous helpings of canned stuff under such name a &quot;reason&quot; - to offer &quot;arguments&quot;. Yet they are not arguments at all. Since they don't follow the spirit of the writing, they are useless. Zilch, nada, zero. I wonder, why do you still &quot;edit&quot;? What do you still manage to find attractive in this business of attrition which only turns the so called encyclopedia into a permanent sandbox?

The texts I used when I learned the alphabet at age five were really more consistent than the castrated, back-of-the envelope global touristic brochure keeping busy in gathering dust. The article was about a living, truthful institution. People, wake up! This Wikipedia is only a pathetic attempt to rewrite everything with dust machines and without the concept of truth. And without truth - be it only living &quot;glue&quot; - you are only raising dust forever. I see no real point in continuing to raise or even attempt to settle this dust myself, given such &quot;learned&quot; environment. Go back to your buckets and spades and do it yourself if you have nothing better to do.

Is ''this'' what you, people, keep calling an &quot;encyclopedia&quot;? If so, by all means, without me, Keep digging :-)

==Additions==
: The bishops consecrated by Saint Andrew and their successors continuously existed inside all territories inhabited by Dacians
I would like a reference.
Do your homework. I won't read you the ABC. We're here to edit at some presumably academic level :O) But OK, you are my brother. Do you have 397 K free on your page for me to dump a list of BASIC references :-) Yours, Dan
: In order to avoid the persecution organized by the Imperial Roman authorities they had to dwell for ever deeper into the Dacian land
I would like a reference.
Same as above. But don't worry, i have time to upload. do you have time to download :-) Yours, dan
: When the Romanians formed as a people, it is quite clear that they already had the Christian faith, as proved by Tradition
Tradition is not a proof. 
Well, if it is not a proof, what proof do you have you are Romanian and not some Guarani wikipedissimus :-) My first caveat for you evidence-based medicine or only thirst, is &quot;absence of evidence and evidence of absence&quot;. Seven steps further, we'll present you the dreaded &quot;proof&quot;, but prepare for it if you can really stand it. It's for mature people only :-) Dar tu ai uitat ca suntem amândoi acas'acas ?
: The Elder of the Village in Church. This masterpiece of the 1930s in the collection of the Village Museum is so representative of the two millennia of the Romanian Orthodox Church that its name - ''Sfetnicii lui Decebal'' - neither needs mention, nor needs translation
What? If you mean that this was kept from the time of Decebal, you surely jest.
Bogdane, you have for ever more homework to do...
[[User:Bogdangiusca|Bogdan]] | [[User talk:Bogdangiusca|Talk]] 21:37, 10 Jan 2005 (UTC)

==Stoi, pa&amp;#351;ol na turbinca dakumentî i faktî==
Auzi, Bogdane, cu cererile tale de ? ''e v i d e n c e'' ? îmi aminte&amp;#351;ti nu de stalini&amp;#351;tii care cereau mereu ? dakumentî ? ci de ungurii care ziceau c&amp;#259; nu-s dovezi c&amp;#259; românii i-au precedat, deci Ardealul e al lor iar românii sunt din lun&amp;#259;, Marte din post sau din stele. La fel bulgarii, ca s&amp;#259;-&amp;#351;i fac&amp;#259; loc în istorie undeva prin [[Dacia Mediterranea]], ziceau c&amp;#259; nu?s dovezi c&amp;#259; românii s-ar fi format la sud de Dun&amp;#259;re, etc., deci românii trebuie neap&amp;#259;rat s&amp;#259; se fi format în Ardeal, undeva. Capisci, tukanaglava ? Oriunde numai nu acolo unde sunt de fapt. Nici ungurii nici bulgarii nu b&amp;#259;gas&amp;#259;r&amp;#259;, chipurile, de seam&amp;#259;, c&amp;#259; românii, cei dintotdeauna aici, au fost, sunt &amp;#351;i vor fi ai locului, cel mai numero&amp;#351;i &amp;#351;i cei mai zdraveni la capul lor, &amp;#351;i în inima lor, mai tare ca orice petec de hârtie al acelora. Tu, de altfel, cum dovede&amp;#351;ti c&amp;#259; e&amp;#351;ti din Isaccea ''de fel'' ? Mormonii au dakumentî c&amp;#259;-s cutare din catastife pe sute de ani în spate. Exist&amp;#259; ceva similar la Isaccea ? Deduci oare din lipsa acelor dakumentî c&amp;#259; tu nu exi&amp;#351;ti de fel, necum la Isaccea ? ''Capisci'' ? Orice document este atât de bun cât e valoarea ciobului sau petecului pe care exist&amp;#259;, dac&amp;#259; nu-i interpretat, în duhul, litera &amp;#351;i contextul s&amp;#259;u. Pentru asta se cer cuno&amp;#351;tiin&amp;#355;e. De aceea exist&amp;#259; istorici chiar în timpul cut'n'pasteitului. Dar asta este cu totul alt&amp;#259; poveste, doar avem azi cocleala guglitului &amp;#351;i lustrul dakumentîlui, nu-i a&amp;#351;a ? :-)

Uite, dragul meu, bibliografie '' e l e m e n t a r &amp;#259; ''  pentru urm&amp;#259;toarele &amp;#351;apte zile:&lt;br&gt;

==Bibliografia s&amp;#259;pt&amp;#259;mânii a treia - 9-15 Ianuarie 2005==
* Biserica Ortodox&amp;#259; Român&amp;#259;, ''Monografie-Album'', Editura Institutului Biblic &amp;#351;i de Misiune al B.O.R., Bucure&amp;#351;ti, 1987, pp. 253-282.
* Arhivele mân&amp;#259;stire&amp;#351;ti din Bucium
* Lucr&amp;#259;rile p&amp;#259;rintelui Arsenie Papacioc
* Lucr&amp;#259;rile p&amp;#259;rintelui Arsenie Boca
Uite-te un pic printre titluri, sau m&amp;#259;car la poze, apoi mai vorbim.&lt;br&gt;
Cu dragoste întru Hristos,&lt;br&gt;
Al t&amp;#259;u, Dan

== Let's use English here ==

This is the English-language Wikipedia. Discussions on Talk 

pages need to be in English so that the entire user community 

can participate. I'm not saying this out of some sense of 

superiority as a native English speaker--I also speak Romanian 

and am writing this from Cluj--but from a desire to let everyone 

here understand what's going on. [[User:Crculver|Crculver]] 16:06, 

11 Jan 2005 (UTC)

OK, dear [[User:Crculver|Crculver]], as you wish. So here it is: An 

abstract of this page: Not so important for you, I'm afraid, only 

some didactic and bibliographic stuff, at least so far. Training 

Bogdan for some proficiency in the editing business... I also must 

excuse myself for the next week or so, for some pressing, really 

for ever more pressing medical issues (my main business being 

medical, as a MD during daytime I'm only writing here during 

nightshifts... Also, I'm glad to hear you are from Cluj - I have a lot 

of Aromanian friends there.

''Incidentally'', Tu cu ce po&amp;#355;i contribui la articol, sau 

m&amp;#259;car la discu&amp;#355;ii? Cuno&amp;#351;ti ceva despre 

subiectul pe care vrei s&amp;#259;-l editezi, sau doar te afli pe-aici în 

treab&amp;#259;, ca Bogdan, cu câteva puncte de vedere personale ? 

i'm afraid Google machine translation will have a field day for the 

really difficult technical words here... Tu chiar vorbe&amp;#351;ti &amp;#351;i scrii 

române&amp;#351;te? Then, may I suggest, as a proof of your technical 

proficiency and skills, or only as a service for the ''entire user 

community'' could you please translate a few technical issues 

from this discussion, so that at least you can, may and even will 

participate? I am, of course, not saying this out of some sense of 

superiority as a native Romanian speaker writing for your understanding about the Romanian National Church, Biserica Neamului Românesc  :-)&lt;br&gt;

== Let's ''use'' English here but let's ''understand'' Romanian if we write about Romanian Issues==
We need some credentials or at least some proof of proficiency in the subject matter if we want to contribute to it. As a Romanian myself, I take this article quite seriously, and would not like to see it being fragmented, diluted and outrageously defigured by some self-centered self-righteous &quot;naive&quot; editing. This is, I'm afraid, mandatory for at least some credibility. Such proof may include, but is not limited to knowledge of the Romanian language, history and culture, a proven interest or only information about the basic bibliography. I'm waiting for your proofs. If you don't know what you are writing about, please don't take my time and don't make me read you loud the operating manual. For instance Bogdan here above says about an alleged consensus, that it belongs to quote all Romanian historians unquote. I'd like to see on what data does he maintain the above personal point of view. Thank  you.

With love in Christ,&lt;br&gt;
Dan

== About recent change ==

I have attempted to show that the nationalistic beliefs held by one editor are not shared by the scholarly community, or even most Romanian Orthodox. I have spoken to several devout Orthodox today to seek their opinion on these distortions, and all are embarassed to know that someone is obsessed with proving their Church the first in Europe. After all, that's not what reputable works of history hold. Since the idea that the Romanian Orthodox was the first is a folk belief rooted in some circles, it deserves mention. However, the scholarly community has overwhelmingly held that the Church in Romania dates from a later time, and this is the view that should prevail.

If someone tries to fight this, I will take this to Request for Mediation. And I daresay this ethnocentric view would lose. Wikipedia generally does not look kindly on people trying to say that their countries or institutions hold a more special or holy place among others. [[User:Crculver|Crculver]] 17:11, 11 Jan 2005 (UTC)&lt;br&gt;

==Against active ignorance and ideology-based stickers, unsubstantiated and really mean==

''I have attempted to show''&lt;br&gt;
Have you attempted to edit the article, or to find anything pertinent, about the subject matter?


''if someone tries to fight this, I will take this to Request for Mediation.''&lt;br&gt;
Mediate what? Mediation works with good will partners. You only attempt, by your own admission, to offer a party line. We need serious contributors here not supervisers. If you want to supervise, simply find something you are competent in, or only comfortable with. I will not take the tag you want to stick to me. If you want to write a neutered, castrated, touristical brochure please remember this is an encyclopedia. This is written by experts, for anybody to judge, not by ''commissars of the (Wiki)people'' who want to promote the new Stalinism.

''I have spoken to several''&lt;br&gt;
Who are they? Can't they speak for themselves? Can't you be serious? What's that? A menace, an argument, or a scholarly debate ? Or a fact? Neither. So we don't take this into consideration.

''However, the scholarly community has overwhelmingly held that the Church in Romania dates from a later time''&lt;br&gt;
I  never heard a more blatantly stated half-truth. Is this good will? On exactly what do you base your opinion? Put data and knowledge where your mouth is!

''and this is the view that should prevail.''&lt;br&gt;
Ah, I see. So you don't care to know anything about the article and you only want some POV to prevail. Well, in this case it's all clear and settled. Go [NPOV here].


''And I daresay this ethnocentric view would lose.''&lt;br&gt;
Who are you to say that? Are you a prophet, a collaborator or just a troll? Why don't you sign your contributions with some credentials. As a whole, for things you either don't care to understand, or you don't want to be understood outside your self-centered, egotist, indeed manic point of view, we don't have arbitration, we have disinterest. We really are not interested in your guesswork and your asking around. If you can edit something pertinently, in good will, with at least some proof of interest, or even if only you can argue, using facts and reason, please go ahead. If not, do not, please also do not make me lose time with your &quot;stickers&quot; and name calling game. I will only answer arguments based on data from you, since I really have no time to lose with ideological komissars promoting the POV of the party line against &quot;the opium of the people&quot;. This makes Wikipedia a Fictionary where someone wants to rewrite everything without the notion of truth.

With love in Christ,&lt;br&gt;
Dan

== Cleanup ==

Being not an expert, I nevertheless find the article rather unclear. The very old history claimed is in stark contrast to the 1885 autocephaly. At least the status before autocephaly should be better explained.

Done. In the article and on this page!

: In brief, the Romanians were Christianized during the Roman Empire and were then isolated from the rest of the Christians until around the 11th century, when Byzantine Orthodoxism was adopted. In 1885, after the Romanian independence was gained, the Church separates itself from Byzantine Orthodox Church and becomes &quot;autocephalous&quot;. [[User:Bogdangiusca|Bogdan]] | [[User talk:Bogdangiusca|Talk]] 17:20, 12 Jan 2005 (UTC)

This is downright wrong, and corresponds to a hmm, let's say, what, a &quot;sixth grade&quot; reasoning? Frankly, my fellow citizen, could you care to explain in writing using a language of reason, how could Christians in a whole country be ''isolated'' for eleven centuries? This scandalous argument was used by Roessler, a reactionary &quot;historian&quot; to deny Romanians the right to exist. Nothing is isolated in this world, and Christians neither. Bogdane, you may wish to study some bibliography before making irresponsible communications in public. What about the Epistle to Diognet? I don't know what you mean by Byzantine Orthodoxism, perhaps you care to explain this in terms of Orthodoxy. Also, I presume you know about the Schism. Before, everybody was Orthodox except for heretics. Lastly, I don't understand the quotation marks in autocephalous. The sequence of tenses in English, used properly couldn't hurt either if you care to express rationally. All in all, Bogdan, it's time for you to grow up to the task and be a responsible editor. Start by answering questions, this is a minimal courtesy in this culture (and the Western one) and then perhaps continue by using the flow, not the flaws of logick :-)

The external links section should be trimmed down to the most useful links for the  english speaking reader. Two links were dead at the time of my testing. Some links have no content at all about the Romanian Orthodox Church.

[[User:Pjacobi|Pjacobi]] 15:54, 2005 Jan 12 (UTC)


Agreed on all planes, [[User:Pjacobi|Pjacobi]]. I dunno why the previous &quot;trimmers&quot; used such &quot;logic&quot; as scissors. I leave to them, since I think it's up to them to mend the fences, and not only the logical thread which they cut. On the other hand, I should have been more careful with logic myself. The logical thread is now broken. In fact, the only thing which still seems clear at this point in time (and I take the opportunity to answer your kind suggestions) is autocephaly. Theologically, the Church is something different than an institution. Canonically, it is an institution and therefore there are laws, dependencies, and relationships of an institutional kind, to which the ROC abide. The article should have made the point, and explain the canonical and the theological standpoints clearly.

See you soon again here, in the limits of time in this crazy world!


Theologically, the Church is something different than an institution. It is the Body of Christ in this world. Canonically, the Church is an institution and therefore there are laws, dependencies, and relationships to which autocephaly corresponds. This explains why the Romanian Orthodox Church, a national church since the Romanian nation exists, needed autocephaly after the independence of the Romanian state, and also why this Church is as old as Christianity itself. Unique to Romanians are a number of theological and canonical features: Although this is not always recognised by the outside world, Romanians regard their church to be the first national, first attested, and first apostolic (church built by the Apostles themselves) in Europe.

This not a matter of pride, but an opportunity to pursue a spiritual mission in the world which is uninterrupted since the times of Jesus Christ Himself, as carried on by Saint Paul, and saint Andrew. This tradition is maintained and continued in dignity and with deep peace in the depths of the heart. The Prayer of the Heart comes in mind whenever the current decay in time so aptly called &quot;''sminteala''&quot; tries to take over &quot;the hearts and minds&quot; like all dying fashion. The Saint Tradition is maintained with that special flavor of the Orthodox Faith named with a word that cannot be translated - ''smerenie''.


Disagree. A national church is not presented ethnocentrically. It is as it is - a national church. You can't delete this fact without sinning. But you may not like truth, as I explained in talk pages


/* Cleanup */ Crculver, this is the second time you make defigurements in the article without knowing what you do, and without explaining them. This is a last warning!

==Crculver, this is the second time you make defigurements==
Crculver, this is the second time you make defigurements in the article without knowing what you do, and without explaining them with something more mature than sticking pre-canned stuff, &quot;ethnocentricity&quot; tags and this sort of fabricated mud. Moreover, you don't answer to critics, and you put yourself above criticism. I offered you the second warning, now you are being watched and we will pursue you for vandalim the very moment you touch this sensitive issue again! For the record, you have admitted you care to impose your POV above all, above logic, discussion and even above common sense. Consider yourself warned for the last time! I will not lose time with you any longer, unless you care to change your &quot;supervising&quot; attitude and your mindless scissors with something more human. There is a serious concern here about your acts since you seem to menace the freedom of religion for a whole people with malicious censorship, which is not only sensitive, but an extremely serious issue about universal human rights!

With love in Christ,
Dan

==Crculver, this is the second time you make defigurements==
Crculver, this is the second time you make defigurements in the article without knowing what you do, and without explaining them with something more mature than sticking pre-canned stuff, &quot;ethnocentricity&quot; tags and this sort of fabricated mud. Moreover, you don't answer to critics, and you put yourself above criticism. I offered you the second warning, now you are being watched and we will pursue you for vandalim the very moment you touch this sensitive issue again! For the record, you have admitted you care to impose your POV above all, above logic, discussion and even above common sense. Consider yourself warned for the last time! I will not lose time with you any longer, unless you care to change your &quot;supervising&quot; attitude and your mindless scissors with something more human. There is a serious concern here about your acts since you seem to menace the freedom of religion for a whole people with malicious censorship, which is not only sensitive, but an extremely serious issue about rights!

With love in Christ,
Dan

== Image (elders) ==

[[Image:Batranii-Oas.jpg|thumb|center|900px|The Elder of the Village in Church. This masterpiece of the 1930s in the collection of the Village Museum is so representative of the two millennia of the Romanian Orthodox Church that its name - ''Sfetnicii lui Decebal'' - neither needs mention, nor needs translation]]

I removed this image, because it assumes that this &quot;[[Decebalus]]' council&quot; kept it's form in the last 2,000 years. That is really wrong. No name of a Roman or Dacian ruler whatsover was kept in the folklore of the Romanian people during the Middle Ages. Also, it has nothing to do whatsoever with the Orthodox Church. [[User:Bogdangiusca|Bogdan]] | [[User talk:Bogdangiusca|Talk]] 21:24, 12 Jan 2005 (UTC)

It assumes nothing, as the legend says, it only illustrates what you don't care to read. I thought it might help you, as a member of the younger generation who learn history easier from the colored glossy albums :-)

With love in Christ,
Dan

==Hi, VMORO==
Please stop censoring the ROC article, and if you want to discuss arguments, please use them. We have a common cause of truth in Christianity, against enemies of Christ, and we are mature enough not to let ourselves being dismembered by hidden agendas. Didn't you see they used laser-guided 2500 lb &quot;arguments&quot; against the Serbs? Not that Serbs aren't stubborn, they are, and even against our Romanian Church inside Serbia, but they are human beings and thou shalt not kill!
I'm sure Romanians and Vlachs in Bulgaria aren't pampered either, but you are a Christian and we are brothers above all. So please forgive my stubborn insistence, for which Bulgarians are also known in our anecdotes :-)

With love in Christ,
Dan

== Dan, you misunderstand Wikipedia ==

Dan, you seem to misunderstand Wikipedia. We are not here to be Christian evangelists and claim that Christianity is true, because that is not NPOV. We are here to develop a neutral encyclopedia that respects the general findings held by the scholarly community. If you want to prostelytize, do it elsewhere. I belong to the same faith as you, but I am embarassed when you cause disruption and make false statements in the name of our religion.

My friend, having edited a few tens of thousand of pages I can barely keep my big belly in the deep laughter. Orthodoxy, being the ''right'' tradition, does not employ evangelizers. We are witnesses not advocates :-) As for ''prostelytize&quot;, please ask Bogdan what it means in Romanian for I can't help laughing to tears ;-) As for ''belonging to the same faith as you'' let me doubt it dear brother, as a precautionary scholarly principle :-)

Can you show any reputable scholarship that supports the view that the Dacian nation was Christianised before the arrival of the Romans? You are representing a minority viewpoint here, you need to present citations. Don't you think the fact that many users are reverting your changes suggests that you are not presenting a good argument?

Sure, look into the biblio, and ask Bogdan for some translations. He'll be happy to oblige such a paragon of internationalism, globalist and anti-Christian :-)

Furthermore, this is an egregious error which I will remove:

: Fully Autocephalous since 1885 the Romanian Orthodox Church is part of 
: the spiritual, political and national identity of Romanians.

I'm afraid not, it is part of the identity of ''some'' Romanians. The Magyar and German minorities (who in English usage are just as Romanian as anyone else, because they have Romanian citizenship) are very rarely Orthodox. Even among ethnic Romanians there are thousands of Uniate Catholics and, especially among the youth, atheists. You cannot make such a blanket statement about a colourful, multi-ethnic state like Romania.

Remove youself from the egregious error you try to perpetrate :-)
With love in Christ,
Dan

&quot;Some&quot; are more then twenty million, ''id est'' more than 93.11 percent of the nation, which need not be terrorized by a bunch of pharisees claiming the rights which themselves have no intention to respect. To reduce the truth to the mantra of postmodernism does not an edit make, but shows a disgusing attempt to destroy a nation. The nation, however, is a reality. And this is an article about the Romanian Orthodox Church, not about your mantra. I see you will stop from no subterfuge in order to prevent me exert my religious freedom and my basic human rights, which are universal, by the way, no matter what garbage you throw on them!

Please register an account. Making dozens of changes just from an IP address is somewhat anti-social. [[User:Crculver|Crculver]] 16:59, 13 Jan 2005 (UTC)

I can't log in my account being banned for one year :O)

: Our anonymous friend, Dan, had an account ([[User:Irismeister]]) but he was banned from editing. ([[Wikipedia:Requests_for_arbitration/Irismeister|one], [[Wikipedia:Requests_for_arbitration/Irismeister 2|two]] and [[[Wikipedia:Requests_for_arbitration/Irismeister 3|three]]) [[User:Bogdangiusca|Bogdan]] | [[User talk:Bogdangiusca|Talk]] 19:09, 13 Jan 2005 (UTC)

:: Well, that explains a lot. I've reported him again at Requests for Arbitration and hopefully we'll see this IP at least disappear. [[User:Crculver|Crculver]] 15:45, 14 Jan 2005 (UTC)

My friends, your disregard for truth has attained epic proportions, the measure of which are only matched by your self-centered, chauvinistic, and self-sufficient mind and heart. You simply are not interested in learning. You are reciting the mantra period. You cannot bear to talk for you are afraid of the ridicule and of the immensity of the desert in your understanding. This is called hubris. I see nothing in the talk, except for a backlog of unanswered questions and your unexplained cuts, plus your refusal to either refer to or read and quote the basic bibliography. Bogdane, you know what your Christain name signifies, please try to live up to the expectations, when you have such a name and a citizenship. Otherwise you'll be Bogdan Turcitul, like the abovementioned Mihnea

Mihnea încalec'&lt;br&gt;
Calu'su tropot'&lt;br&gt;

== [[Romanian Catholic Church]] ==

Dan said when reverting:
: ''Uniate is not Catholic, Bogdane, but Orthodox. Why do you confuse things so much ?)''

I am quite sure &quot;The Romanian Greek-'''Catholic''' Uniate Church&quot; is a '''Catholic''' Church. :-) [[User:Bogdangiusca|Bogdan]] | [[User talk:Bogdangiusca|Talk]] 19:47, 13 Jan 2005 (UTC)

Oups, you picked the wrong Google:&lt;br&gt;
Uniate Church
Any of the Orthodox Churches that accept the Catholic faith and the supremacy of the pope and are in full communion with the Roman Catholic Church, but retain their own liturgy and separate organization.

In Ukraine, despite being proscribed 1946?89, the Uniate Church claimed some 4.5 million adherents when it was once again officially recognized. Its rehabilitation was marked by the return of its spiritual leader, Cardinal Miroslav Lubachivsky, to take up residence in Lvi?v in western Ukraine after 52 years? exile in Rome.&lt;br&gt;
Bogdane, Bogdane, ai s&amp;#257; devii Gâg&amp;#257; dac&amp;#257; r&amp;#462;mâi doar la prima pagin&amp;#257; din Gâg&amp;#257;l :-)

== &quot;first national, first attested, and first apostolic&quot; ==

To the anon, who is re-inserting:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
''Romanians know their church to be the first national, first attested, and first apostolic (church built by the Apostles themselves) in Europe.''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
This is a bold claim, and maybe one of those that can never be objectively be decided pro or against. Perhaps you should expand the rationale behind this claim?

Other churches having similiar claims most often back up their claim be given lists of [[apostilic succession]] from the apostles. Of course this is not a true objective proof of the fact of apostolic succession but at least of the claim of apostolic succession. See for examples:
* [[List_of_Patriarchs_of_Antioch]]
* [[List of Patriarchs of Babylon]]
* [[:de:Liste der Patriarchen der Armenischen Apostolischen Kirche]]
* [[List of Patriarchs of Alexandria]]
[[User:Pjacobi|Pjacobi]] 10:55, 2005 Jan 14 (UTC)

== Ongoing vandalism ==
A wise man once said that the only thing he does know is that he does not know anything. Well obviously we can not be as wise, but at least we should try. I noticed that there is one person here who intentionally promotes a POV style in this article. Although I do not disagree with most of his claims (except the with the fact that the Dacians were christianized and a few other minor facts), I do not think it is ETHICAL to impose my point of view to others. Moreover, this article is written with a lot of passion, which is not necessarily a bad thing, but it is inapropriate, considering the fact that Wikipedia is supposed to be a source of objective knowledge.
Another thing that is obvious is that whenever someone tries to express their point of view, they are violently silenced by claiming that they are just novices in learning history or even by offending them. I hope you will not offend me when you reply to this message, Dr. Jâp&amp;#259;.
It is also obvious that the aforementioned person strongly disagrees with largely accepted Wikipedia policies. Why do you still write here if you do not agree with the Wikipedia NPOV policies?&lt;br&gt;
A, si pe final asa, mai am o intrebare: sunteti cumva un simpatizant al Partidului Romania Mare?&lt;br&gt;
Ioan

==Irismeister/Dan Jipa is banned from Wikipedia==

Dan Jipa, formerly [[User:Irismeister]], is currently under a one-year Arbitration Committee ban (see [[Wikipedia:Requests for arbitration/Irismeister 3]] and [[Wikipedia:Requests_for_arbitration/Admin_enforcement_requested#Irismeister]]). Users are encouraged to revert all contributions and admins are encouraged to block all attempts at access. Furthermore, the ban timer is reset with every contribution - [[User:David Gerard|David Gerard]] 20:20, 14 Jan 2005 (UTC) (for the ArbCom)

Well, I should say it was about time. [[User:VMORO|VMORO]]

:The English Wikipedia is huge, so it's hard for people to know of everywhere a banned user might show up again ;-) - [[User:David Gerard|David Gerard]] 00:24, 15 Jan 2005 (UTC)

== Old references ==

Irismeister's references, moved from the article:

* Mircea P&amp;#259;curariu, ''Istoria Bisericii Ortodoxe Române'', Sophia, Bucure&amp;#351;ti, 2000 (the standard text in Romanian, well updated, complete, superbly printed - an excellent reference.)
* ''The Sayings of the Desert Fathers'': ''The Alphabetical Collection'' (Translated with a foreword by Benedicta Ward, SLG), Cistercian Publications, Kalamazoo, Revised edition 1984.
* ''Cel&amp;#259;lalt Noica'': M&amp;#259;rturii ale monahului Rafail, înso&amp;#355;ite de câteva cuvinte de folos ale p&amp;#259;rintelui Symeon, edi&amp;#355;ie îngrijit&amp;#259; de Pr. Eugen Dr&amp;#259;goi &amp;#351;i Pr. Ninel &amp;#354;ugui, Editura Anastasia, Bucure&amp;#351;ti, 1994 (father Rafail Noica, one of the most accomplished figures in the Orthodox spiritualiy is the &quot;other&quot; Noica because his father [[Constantin Noica]] is the most famous Romanian philosopher.)
* Arsenie Papacioc ''Scrisori câtre fiii mei duhovnice&amp;#351;ti'' (Editura Mân&amp;#259;stirii Dervent, Constan&amp;#355;a, 2000). 
* Arsenie Papacioc ''Duhovnici români în dialog cu tinerii'' (Editura Bizantin&amp;#259;, Bucure&amp;#351;ti, 1997). 
* Arsenie Papacioc ''La Mãnãstire te desfiin&amp;#355;ezi ca personalitate omeneasc&amp;#259; în personalitate îngereascã'' - interviu, în ''Epifania'', noiembrie-decembrie 1997.

== Dreapta credin&amp;#355;&amp;#259; ==

I've made the article more neutral by removing the fact that the church is most often known as Dreapta credin&amp;#355;&amp;#259;. This is simply untrue. As a Romanian, the most common way that people, both Orthodox and not Orthodox, refer to it, is &quot;Biserica Ortodox&amp;#259;&quot; and the followers are simply &quot;ortodoc&amp;#351;i&quot;. Dreapta credin&amp;#355;&amp;#259; is in my view a terribly biased term. [[User:Ronline|Ronline]] 06:30, 11 Apr 2005 (UTC)


== Boscorodirea (in Romanian) ==
i don't know how NPOV could this link be, being on the site of a baptist organisation with openly criticizes  orthodoxism (try reading the section about orthodoxy on that site) &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:82.77.81.53|82.77.81.53]] ([[User talk:82.77.81.53|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/82.77.81.53|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

== Orthodoxy is the right word ==
Let the -isms rest in peace :O) &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:81.249.53.175|81.249.53.175]] ([[User talk:81.249.53.175|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/81.249.53.175|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

== &quot;Uniate&quot; ==

The English term &quot;Uniate&quot; is increasingly seen as offensive. We should reword several portions of the article to reflect current usage. [[User:Crculver|CRCulver]] 03:22, 11 December 2005 (UTC)

== Articolul nu ne reprezint&amp;#257! ==
Este castrat, asta este &quot;neutralizat&quot;. Asta face &quot;enciclopedia&quot; unui pornocrat! &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:194.158.124.24|194.158.124.24]] ([[User talk:194.158.124.24|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/194.158.124.24|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;
: Thank you for the very helpful comment! [[User:Bogdangiusca|bogdan]] 20:55, 19 January 2006 (UTC)

You are welcome! Castration and neutralization, bad taste and censorship aren't. &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Rishimeister|Rishimeister]] ([[User talk:Rishimeister|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Rishimeister|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

: Of course, I assume adding only information from trustable sources is considered castration of the imagination, right ? :-) [[User:Bogdangiusca|bogdan]] 22:08, 23 January 2006 (UTC)

::What in particular do you object to? Remember, this is a neutral encyclopedia that shouldn't have a pro-Orthodox point of view. [[Image:Flag of Europe.svg|20px]][[Image:Flag of Romania.svg|20px]] '''[[User:Ronline|Ronline]]''' [[User talk:Ronline|✉]] 06:35, 24 January 2006 (UTC)


== Image ==
The image is beautiful -- I do not know how to nominate it for use as a featured image, but I suggest it's worthy. [[User:Adamdavis|Adamdavis]] 00:16, 19 June 2006 (UTC)

==Coronation of Ilie Stănescu as ''International King of the Rroma'' at Curtea de Argeş==
You can find the discussed chapter [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Romanian_Orthodox_Church&amp;oldid=96970627#Coronation_of_Ilie_St.C4.83nescu_as_International_King_of_the_Rroma_at_Curtea_de_Arge.C5.9F here].

I added back this chapter, as it was a big scandal at the time.[[User:Dl.goe|Dl.goe]] 18:25, 28 December 2006 (UTC)
:[[User:Crculver|Crculver]] removed it:''Rv non-notable''
I added back the content template. The discussion is not yet finished. More opinions are needed.[[User:Dl.goe|Dl.goe]] 19:54, 29 December 2006 (UTC)

== Mitropolitul Banatului ==

A fost uitat Mitropolitul Banatului, IPS Nicolae (Corneanu) &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[Special:Contributions/89.15.156.186|89.15.156.186]] ([[User talk:89.15.156.186|talk]]) 17:14, 30 March 2007 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;


==List of Patriarchs==

Following the comments on the talk page of the above, should the list be included here - or have more information on it (why the change in titles etc?)

How does the inter-patriarch-period operate - is it similar to the (Catholic) inter-papacy? [[User:Jackiespeel|Jackiespeel]] 16:00, 6 August 2007 (UTC)

== Schools in 1947-48 ==

:''As a result of measures passed in 1947-48, the 2300 elementary schools operated by the church were closed''

I would have thought they were taken over by the state, not closed. [[User:Bogdangiusca|bogdan]] ([[User talk:Bogdangiusca|talk]]) 09:33, 7 June 2008 (UTC)

::Good point. Ramet does say &quot;closed&quot;, though, and she's quite an expert on religion in Romania. On the other hand, one would imagine at least some of those buildings, equipped as they were to be schools, would remain as schools. (I know of a (Catholic) school in Brăila that became a tuberculosis hospital, but that's just one example.) Anyway, that's what the source writes, but adding &quot;or taken over by the state&quot; would probably not be inaccurate, since the number of schools was rather large. [[User:Biruitorul|Biruitorul]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Biruitorul|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 04:12, 8 June 2008 (UTC)

== 'Unique' features ==

I agree that Latinate language is unique in the Liturgy in Rumania; however as I demonstrated the synod of the Church of Cyprus currently has 8 of the chorepiskopous, so it's not unique to Rumania is it? Also I have seen this mentioned for the Patriarchate of Antioch, in the Turkish bit. [[User:Eugene-elgato|Eugene-elgato]] ([[User talk:Eugene-elgato|talk]]) 21:32, 4 February 2009 (UTC)

== Blank spaces ==
In my opinion the article explores fairly well the relationship of the church with the Communist regime however mentions in no way its ties with the far-right particularly during the late thirties and the war-years. [[User:Plinul cel tanar|Plinul cel tanar]] ([[User talk:Plinul cel tanar|talk]]) 07:00, 21 May 2009 (UTC)
:Indeed, and actually at some point I'll be adding in more from Cioroianu on the Communist period. Regarding relations with Antonescu and the Guard: that's a very rich topic much deserving of our attention. I can't promise anything myself soon, but it's planned. - [[User:Biruitorul|Biruitorul]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Biruitorul|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 07:24, 21 May 2009 (UTC)
:: I was wondering if we should keep the historically chronological organization or go for a criticism section. [[User:Plinul cel tanar|Plinul cel tanar]] ([[User talk:Plinul cel tanar|talk]]) 08:50, 21 May 2009 (UTC)
::: IMO, the criticism should go in the history section, not in its own section. [[User:Bogdangiusca|bogdan]] ([[User talk:Bogdangiusca|talk]]) 09:17, 21 May 2009 (UTC)
:::: I was thinking of an article more like the one about [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]]. That would allow for a vaster range of criticism to be expressed: antisemitism during the last years of [[Miron Cristea]]'s patriarchate, collaboration with communist totalitarian regime and the [[Securitate]] but also more recent xenophobic rhetoric, interference in politics, reluctance to return greek-catholic property, charges of corruption against notable bishops. [[User:Plinul cel tanar|Plinul cel tanar]] ([[User talk:Plinul cel tanar|talk]]) 12:22, 21 May 2009 (UTC)
:::Personally, I'm with Bogdan here. &quot;Criticism&quot; articles/sections tend to be POV magnets (I refer you to [[Criticism of Traian Băsescu]]), and besides, what was the target of criticism is also an integral part of the Church's history. It seems odd to talk about, say, the cathedrals built in the 1930s in the &quot;history&quot; section and the links to the Guard in the &quot;criticism&quot; section - especially when [[Biserica Casin|some churches]] were ''built'' by the Guard. - [[User:Biruitorul|Biruitorul]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Biruitorul|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 14:24, 21 May 2009 (UTC)
::::OK, you have a point. Historical facts such as the Holy Sinod explicitly taking position in favor of depriving non-orthodox Romanians and ethnic minorities of their citizenship definitely belongs to the History section (and there is no reason to fork it into a criticism section). [[User:Plinul cel tanar|Plinul cel tanar]] ([[User talk:Plinul cel tanar|talk]]) 14:49, 21 May 2009 (UTC)

==Eastern European calendar:  Naming proposal==

On this glorious Easter Tuesday, united around the world, here is an update on the progress of the ballot.

:Option 1 - Meletian calendar - 1 vote (recommended option)
:Option 2 - New calendar (Eastern churches) - no votes (this option is not recommended)
:Option 3 - No change - 2 votes (this option is not recommended)
:Option 4 - &quot;Revised&quot; Julian calendar - no votes (this option is not recommended)

To vote by proxy, write QUICKVOTE and sign with four tildes.   If you want your proxy to vote in a particular way, add the option number in brackets.   Thus QUICKVOTE (1) means your vote will be cast in favour of option 1.

The tilde is the wavy line ~ sometimes placed above n (in Spanish) or a or o in Portuguese where, following the shorthand of medieval Latin copyists, it marks the omission of a following letter n.

'''This is not the place to vote'''.   Click on this link [[Talk:Revised Julian calendar#Proposal to change article name]], read the manifestos and then add your vote underneath the others. [[Special:Contributions/212.85.12.219|212.85.12.219]] ([[User talk:212.85.12.219|talk]]) 15:28, 6 April 2010 (UTC)

Uma Paschoa muito feliz a todos.   '''O povo unido jamais sera vencido'''. [[Special:Contributions/212.85.12.219|212.85.12.219]] ([[User talk:212.85.12.219|talk]]) 15:28, 6 April 2010 (UTC)

==Founder==

Please ad the Moldavian metropolis as a co-founder metropolis or delete the Wallachian metropolis on the &quot;founder&quot; tab! That'd wrongly imply that the Romanian Patriarchy has been evolved only from Wallachian metropolis.[[User:FabricioRB|Fabricio]] ([[User talk:FabricioRB|talk]]) 19:58, 3 May 2011 (UTC)
==File:Mitropolia Iasi.jpg Nominated for Deletion==
{|
|-
| [[Image:Icon Now Commons orange.svg|50px]] 
| An image used in this article, [[commons:File:Mitropolia Iasi.jpg|File:Mitropolia Iasi.jpg]], has been nominated for deletion at [[Wikimedia Commons]] in the following category: ''Deletion requests July 2011'' 
;What should I do?
|-
|
| A discussion will now take place over on Commons about whether to remove the file. If you feel the deletion can be contested then please do so ([[commons:COM:SPEEDY]] has further information). Otherwise consider finding a replacement image before deletion occurs.

''This notification is provided by a Bot'' --[[User:CommonsNotificationBot|CommonsNotificationBot]] ([[User talk:CommonsNotificationBot|talk]]) 12:36, 28 July 2011 (UTC)
|}
==File:420 Conducatorii de partid si de stat.jpg Nominated for Deletion==
{|
|-
| [[File:Image-x-generic.svg|100px]] 
| An image used in this article, [[commons:File:420 Conducatorii de partid si de stat.jpg|File:420 Conducatorii de partid si de stat.jpg]], has been nominated for deletion at [[Wikimedia Commons]] in the following category: ''Deletion requests February 2012'' 
;What should I do?
''Don't panic''; a discussion will now take place over on Commons about whether to remove the file. This gives you an opportunity to contest the deletion, although please review Commons guidelines before doing so.
* If the image is [[WP:NFCC|non-free]] then you may need to upload it to Wikipedia (Commons does not allow fair use)
* If the image isn't freely licensed and there is no [[WP:FUR|fair use rationale]] then it cannot be uploaded or used.

''This notification is provided by a Bot'' --[[User:CommonsNotificationBot|CommonsNotificationBot]] ([[User talk:CommonsNotificationBot|talk]]) 22:49, 9 February 2012 (UTC)
|}</text>
      <sha1>grn3aq03g748b4euth38z0d59un2cv2</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
