<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Pythagoras</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>39309</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521517970</id>
      <parentid>516645441</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-05T15:03:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JRalphS</username>
        <id>17829708</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Pythagorean Hammers */ the ratios apply also to wind, brass, percussion and other musical instruments</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="36310">{{Talk header}}
{{WP1.0|class=B|importance=top|category=Math|v0.5=pass|WPCD=yes}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{physics|class=B|importance=low|bio=yes}}
{{maths rating|frequentlyviewed=yes|vital=Y|class=B|importance=Top|field=mathematician}}
{{WikiProject Biography|living=no|class=B|s&amp;a-priority=Top|core=yes|s&amp;a-work-group=yes|listas = Pythagoras}}
{{WikiProject Philosophy|class=B|importance=high|philosopher=yes|ancient=yes|logic=yes|metaphysics=yes}}
{{WikiProject Classical Greece and Rome|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Greece|class=B|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=B|importance=Top}}
}}
{{Archive box|[[/Archive 1]]}}

==According to legend, the way Pythagoras discovered that musical notes could be translated into mathematical equations==

I heard on a radio 4 program, or something on the BBC I think, that he noticed it in grass / reeds, as they were waving in the wind like slowed down strings on instruments - and believed the patterns (of intervals, nodes, harmonics and so on) to be universal, music essentially. 

I would be interested to chat with someone who understands superstring theory to a higher level than myself to know if the theory also allows for that in the model. If it does, he may have been laughably close to what's on the way, over two millenia ago (oldest scientific prediction that was correct?). :)  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/86.166.134.7|86.166.134.7]] ([[User talk:86.166.134.7|talk]]) 08:27, 23 June 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Deleted content==
&lt;blockquote&gt;
He was the first man to call himself a philosopher, or lover of wisdom. Many of the accomplishments of [[Plato]], [[Aristotle]] and [[Copernicus]] were based on the ideas of Pythagoras. Unfortunately, very little is known about Pythagoras because none of his writings have survived. Many of the accomplishments credited to Pythagoras may actually have been accomplishments of his colleagues and successors.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

I have deleted this. 

The very first claim is specious at best, useless and confusing at worst: without being backed up by a clear primary source, there is no need to make a mention of it. It is also confusing, as we don't know whether a historical or a modern context is being put upon the term philosopher: 'philosophy' in the 6th Century BC referred to an investigator of natural principles (e.g. Thales, Anaximander, Democritus). Ipso facto, the person who wrote this may not be translating with a view to clarity: it would be far more clear for a reader today to be told that &quot;he was the first man to call himself a ''scientist''&quot; or some other term approaching the idea of an investigator into nature. 
But even beside the contextual problems, why is this even noteworthy in an introductory paragraph? And is it true? Several other pre-Socratics approach calling themselves philosophers, as Heraclitus hints in writing that &quot;men who are lovers of wisdom must be inquirers into many things.&quot;
The second statement is a spill-over into the first statements mistake. Pythagoras had a strong influence upon Plato's metaphysics as well as later mathematicians and astronomers. That is not to say he made their achievements possible. 
The last two statements then contravene what the former two sentences have wagered. It is rather a mess.

I will keep this removed from the article until it is brought up to snuff or there is a robust reason for why it should be kept. [[User:Across.The.Synapse|across the synapse]] 19:04, 18 September 2007 (UTC)

:See my comment immediately above yours.  Primary sources for Pythagoras as introducer of ''philosophos'' include: Cicero, Tusculan Disputations, 5.3.8-9, Diog. Laert. 1.12, 8.8, Iamblichus ''VP'' 58.  I've added the citations to the article &amp; done a modest bit of additional pruning to reflect your concerns about some of what is admittedly crap in what you removed.  But be more careful &amp; less confident with &quot;specious at best&quot; etc.&amp;mdash;the primary source for ''philosophos'' was in fact already included in the article's first footnote!  [[User:Wareh|Wareh]] 19:15, 18 September 2007 (UTC)


&lt;blockquote&gt;He was the first man to call himself a philosopher, or lover of wisdom&lt;/blockquote&gt; 
I saw this scentence and was wondering if we could authoritatively state that, before Pythagoras, nobody in the world called themselves a ''philosopher'' or a ''lover of wisdom''. Instead of such a blanket statement, I felt a scentence that mentions this within the context of the reference material or of the region would be right.  [[User:Sudarshanhs|Sudarshanhs]] ([[User talk:Sudarshanhs|talk]]) 17:35, 7 January 2008 (UTC)


&lt;blockquote&gt;He was the first man to call himself a philosopher, or lover of wisdom&lt;/blockquote&gt; 
Actually, Pythagoras was the first to use the term 'philosophy.' Perhpas this could be used instead? [[User:Winderful1|Winderful1]] ([[User talk:Winderful1|talk]]) 15:13, 24 July 2008 (UTC)

==Pythagoras in Miletos?==
According to The Histories by the Herodotus, book V, chapter 126: 

&quot;126. This was the counsel of Hecataios; but Aristagoras was most
inclined to go forth to Myrkinos. He therefore entrusted the
government of Miletos to Pythagoras, a man of repute among the
citizens, and he himself sailed away to Thrace, taking with him every
one who desired to go; and he took possession of the region for which
he had set out.&quot;

Herodotus mentions Pythagoras in his Book IV, chapter 92 as &quot;Pythagoras the son of Mnesarchos&quot;. Therefore it looks like Pythagoras lived in Miletos, too. Do you know some other sources confirming/rejecting this?  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/91.127.65.104|91.127.65.104]] ([[User talk:91.127.65.104|talk]]) 18:40, 10 November 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==&quot;Roles&quot; of numbers in decad==
I've removed this material, since it was unsourced, and the &quot;roles&quot; assigned to the numbers do not, by and large, agree with the epithets that appear in the Iamblichan ''Theology of Artithmetic'' (listed by David R. Fideler in Appendix II of Kenneth Sylvan Guthrie, ''The Pythagorean Sourcebook and Library'', ed. David R. Fideler [Grand Rapids: Phanes, 1987]). If a good source for the removed material exists, it can be readded. [[User:Deor|Deor]] ([[User talk:Deor|talk]]) 21:17, 6 January 2008 (UTC)

==Young man line?==

According to the articule Pythagoras was a young man when Polycrates took over Samos yet according to the dates Pythagoras would have been about 30. Not really young. 

572 B.C minus 538 B.C 

~~Anonymous  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/98.202.20.158|98.202.20.158]] ([[User talk:98.202.20.158|talk]]) 21:46, 24 January 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==First reference to Pythagoras in 2nd cent. CE?==

&lt;blockquote&gt;This would explain the lack of reference to a man Pythagoras until 150 AD, given that he would have been of interest to contemporary philosophers (Aristotle referred to the so-called Pythagoreans).&lt;/blockquote&gt;

What about Livy's (died 12/17 CE) mention of him? Roberts translation from Wikisource:

&lt;blockquote&gt;His master [Numa's] is given as Pythagoras of Samos, as tradition speaks of no other. But this is erroneous, for it is generally agreed that it was more than a century later, in the reign of Servius Tullius, that Pythagoras gathered round him crowds of eager students, in the most distant part of Italy, in the neighbourhood of Metapontum, Heraclea, and Crotona. (1.18)&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/128.186.86.199|128.186.86.199]] ([[User talk:128.186.86.199|talk]]) 20:52, 25 February 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;

:And what about Heraclitus and Xenophanes--both contemporaries of Pythagoras who mentioned him (and apparently as a man--known to them by reputation if not in person):

:[[http://books.google.com/books?id=2gLPbFKwY5EC&amp;pg=PA48&amp;lpg=PA48&amp;dq=Pythagoras+Xenophanes&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=W_y3FSWatP&amp;sig=-Qaclr8KF4ilkvS2D4pPnaUO63E&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=OquXScTJOZj8Mr3kqIQM&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=10&amp;ct=result#PPA48,M1 This book]] (see p. 48 and following) goes into some depth about the references to Pythagoras in Xenophanes and some other contemporaries and near-contemporaries.

:This paper talks about the Heraclitus/Pythagoras material:

:“Heraclitus' Critique of Pythagoras' Enquiry in Fragment 129,” Oxford Studies in Ancient Philosophy 35 (2008), 19‑47.

:The paragraph on sources is undoubtedly correct that later sources invent the &quot;classical Pythagoras&quot; and attribute to him all sorts of improbable things.  But it's goes a little overboard when it suggests there are no references at all to Pythagoras as a person early on--even contemporary.

:[[User:Bhugh|Bhugh]] ([[User talk:Bhugh|talk]]) 06:03, 15 February 2009 (UTC)

::Quite right. [[Herodotus]] mentions Pythagoras (''Histories'', iv. 95), as does [[Plato]] (''Republic'', 600 AB). I've removed the offending passage. [[User:Singinglemon|Singinglemon]] ([[User talk:Singinglemon|talk]]) 21:56, 16 February 2009 (UTC)

== Pythagoras was phoenician, not greek! ==

he was not a greek. hes father is from tyre , a phoenician mercant.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/93.80.10.252|93.80.10.252]] ([[User talk:93.80.10.252|talk]]) 14:31, 26 September 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Your source? [[User:BlackPearl14|&lt;font color=&quot;#6666FF&quot; &gt;BlackPearl14&lt;/font&gt;]][[User talk:BlackPearl14|&lt;sup&gt;[&lt;font color=&quot;#667722&quot;&gt;talkies!&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;•&lt;/sup&gt;[[Special:Contributions/BlackPearl14|&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#CCOO66&quot; &gt;contribs!&lt;/font&gt;]&lt;/sup&gt;]] 01:17, 27 September 2008 (UTC)
HIS FATHER MNESARHUS IS A CLASSICAL GREEK NAME  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/79.103.222.135|79.103.222.135]] ([[User talk:79.103.222.135|talk]]) 20:15, 15 April 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

no historic record writes his father was a phoenician.he was a agreek merchant in phoenicia.his name shows that  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/79.103.222.135|79.103.222.135]] ([[User talk:79.103.222.135|talk]]) 20:23, 15 April 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Tetrachtys -&gt; Tetractys ==

Perhaps Tetrachtys should be Tetractys? [[User:Bayle Shanks|Bayle Shanks]] ([[User talk:Bayle Shanks|talk]]) 09:05, 18 October 2008 (UTC)

Nice catch.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/77.49.8.244|77.49.8.244]] ([[User talk:77.49.8.244|talk]]) 18:24, 11 February 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

I noticed that there is no image of the Tetractys on this page, and I think it would help if there were an illustration, since it's described but it's difficult to visualize.  I can't add one myself because I don't have a registered account and the page is semi-protected, but here is the link to the one in the commons, so someone else could add it:  http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/6/66/Tetractys.svg/200px-Tetractys.svg.png  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/81.81.159.202|81.81.159.202]] ([[User talk:81.81.159.202|talk]]) 21:30, 25 January 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Pythaogras -&gt; Pythagoras ==

And perhaps Pythaogras should be Pythagoras?
(I'd have edited this myself, it the page weren't protected from vandalism...)
[[User:sunadirE|sunadirE]] ([[User talk:sunadirE|talk]]) 01:57, 1 January 2010 (UTC)

Thanks - done. --[[User:Annielogue|Annielogue]] ([[User talk:Annielogue|talk]]) 16:55, 1 January 2010 (UTC)

== King Arthur ==

Read the article on [[King Arthur]]. Nowhere is the Arthurian legend presented as fact. The legend was created in romances over half a millenium after he was said to have lived. Those writing it knew it so, even if they prefaced it with &quot;the following is based on real events from real history&quot;, Dan Brown stylee.  Of course, there may have been a dude called Arthur, and he may have been a King, but if so, the Arthurian legend is no more likely to contain correct biographical facts about historical Arthur than a treatise on the tomato. If there are any, it is coincidence, not good history.

And yet the biographical facts in this article on Pythagoras are presented with authority. 'Pythagoras lived at 34 Greek Street' , 'Pythagoras liked to cut his sandwiches into triangles', 'Pythagoras invented playing cards'.  Nobody knows! The legend of the dude Pythagoras was created by romantics 500 years later. These guys knew they were doing so. The story of the bean eating hippy Pythagoras is certainly a popular one to repeat, but not a real history. If there was a dude Pythagoras in the Pythagoreans , you are about as likely to find correct biographical facts about him in the article [[King Arthur]] than in this one.

Most of this article should be moved to the Pythagoreans, which also needs some scepticism. The bean-eating hippy legend can be repeated, but not presented as truth. Wikipedia, writing something down does not make it true. &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment addedby [[User:Matt me|Matt me]] ([[User talk:Matt me|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Matt me|contribs]]) 10:08, 25 October 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Wrong. First, Pythagoras, his students, and the Pythagorans were very secretive because '''they believed their knowledge was not meant for the uninitiated and profane'''. Unlocking his and their history is very different than the development of the Arthurian legend. Second, &quot;Philolaus, a not-so-secretive Pythagorean, wrote a book 50-75 years after Pythagoras death&quot; - p.4, ''The Music of Pythagoras'' by Kitty Ferguson (Walker 2008). Third, '''There Are No Coincidences'''. Fourth, if you or anyone is going to criticize certain facts presented in this or any Wikipedia article, then refer to the exact statements, not your silly made-up ones, i.e. &quot;Pythagoras lived at 34 Greek Street&quot;. And to refer to Pythagoras as a &quot;hippy&quot; is like referring to Jesus as a hippy; it's ignorant and very disrespectful of one of history's greatest and most influencial minds. - [[User:Brad Watson, Miami|Brad Watson, Miami]] ([[User talk:Brad Watson, Miami|talk]]) 13:52, 8 October 2012 (UTC)

==Sarmoung Brotherhood==
n Studies in Comparative Religion (Winter 1974), it is said that according to the Armenian book Merkhavat, the Sarmoung Brotherhood, also referred to as the 'Inner Circle of Humanity', originated in ancient Babylon circa 2500 BC,[2] at around the time the Egyptians built the Great Pyramid of Giza. The Ouspensky Foundation state that the brotherhood was active in the golden Babylonian time of Hammurabi (1728-1686 BC) and is connected with Zoroaster, the teacher of Pythagoras (born c. 580 BC–572 BC, died c. 500 BC–490 BC). According to the Foundation, Pythagoras stayed for twelve years in Babylon.[3]; http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sarmoung_Brotherhood [[User:Wblakesx|Wblakesx]] ([[User talk:Wblakesx|talk]]) 23:29, 1 January 2009 (UTC)

==Weasel Language / Edit Request==
&quot;...however some have questioned the scope of his contributions to mathematics and natural philosophy.&quot;
This is vague, baseless, and obviously weasel language.[[Special:Contributions/72.200.108.251|72.200.108.251]] ([[User talk:72.200.108.251|talk]]) 01:57, 26 May 2009 (UTC)

:True.  [[WP:SOFIXIT]]. [[User:Dicklyon|Dicklyon]] ([[User talk:Dicklyon|talk]]) 04:25, 26 May 2009 (UTC)

(I agree...) 

(1) Please improve the 2nd paragraph to the parent article (i.e. the second lead paragraph) For starters, Please make the following changes:(a) Move the key sentence &quot;It was said that he was the first man to call himself a philosopher, or lover of wisdom,[refferance 4] and Pythagorean ideas exercised a marked influence on Plato, and through him, all of Western philosophy.&quot; to the beginning (head) of the paragraph - i.e place it 2nd to the indroductory sentence: &quot;Pythagoras made influential contributions...&quot;  (b) Improve the lengthy sentence: (&quot;However,...&quot;; currently the 3rd sentence in the paragraph) change to &quot;However, because legend and obfuscation so cloud his work (even more than other pre-Socratic philosophers) many question the authenticity of his ascribed contributions.&quot; [the words 'to mathematics and natural philosophy' are redundant and slow the pace of the article]...  

(2) Please remove the word 'Allegedly' (under the 'Influence On Plato' section; 1st paragraph) and place the introductory remark &quot;Tradition has it,...&quot; at the beginning of the first sentence.  

(Thanks; that's all; Keep up the good work.)  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Seipjere|Seipjere]] ([[User talk:Seipjere|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Seipjere|contribs]]) 17:22, 22 September 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Clean-up attempt ==

I made a partial attempt to clean-up this article. I added a section on the (un)reliability of the sources to the top of the article. It's been taken from the beginning of the 1870 ''[[Dictionary of Greek and Roman Biography and Mythology]]'' article on Pythagoras. I rewrote the ''Life'' section; again, just pulling bits and bobs from the DGRBM article as I saw fit. I haven't done much to the rest of the article, although I deleted a couple of outlandish paragraphs and sentences, and I rearranged the article extensively. The section on ''Pythagoreans'' has no citations, and is a bit too uncritical for my tastes, but for now, I've moved it further down the article. This had the advantage of bringing the only really-well-written bit of the article upwards - the section on the ''Pythagorean theorem''. [[User:Singinglemon|Singinglemon]] ([[User talk:Singinglemon|talk]]) 21:53, 8 September 2009 (UTC)
:Well, since it had no references, I decided to rewrite the section on ''Pythagoreans'' as well, using some of the material which was there before. It's not great, but I hope the page as a whole, looks more reliable now. [[User:Singinglemon|Singinglemon]] ([[User talk:Singinglemon|talk]]) 21:13, 11 September 2009 (UTC)

== Edit request from 94.173.119.63, 30 March 2010 ==

{{tlp|editsemiprotected}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;

The yellow animation demonstrating pythagoras theorem ends with a mistake in the final equation. It should be a plus sign, not a minus sign, between the squares of the shorter sides.


&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[Special:Contributions/94.173.119.63|94.173.119.63]] ([[User talk:94.173.119.63|talk]]) 21:48, 30 March 2010 (UTC)
:Looks like a plus sign to me. Perhaps you need to adjust your monitor display. [[User:Deor|Deor]] ([[User talk:Deor|talk]]) 22:26, 30 March 2010 (UTC)

::Looks right to me. It is a plus sign, though the Vertical line '''|''' is much more bold than the Horizontal line &lt;sup&gt;_&lt;/sup&gt; . Unless I am mistaken.
::{{notdone}} since it seems there is no need to. &lt;sup&gt;[[User:Avicennasis|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot; size=&quot;1px&quot;&gt;Avic&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;[[User talk:Avicennasis|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot; size=&quot;1px&quot;&gt;enna&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Avicennasis|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot; size=&quot;1px&quot;&gt;sis&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sub&gt; &lt;small&gt;@&lt;/small&gt; 22:36, 30 March 2010 (UTC)

== signs of confusion... ==

Hi folks,

Furthur to my post about the yellow Pythagoras Theorem animation plus sign, which I now realise must have seemed somewhat ridiculous;

OK, sorry to doubt that you hadn't checked the article for simple errors... I do beg your pardon.

After first checking my own sanity, I have checked using another browser on my computer and indeed the sign is now shown as a strong black plus. It is also showing as a somewhat lighter plus sign when the gif is enlarged using the browser ( Safari 1.3.2 ) I originally viewed the article with. However, for some reason when the animation plays through in the small size at the side of the main article page using this browser version it shows as a minus sign - I kid you not. Changing screen resolution does not help. Perhaps it is something to do with the browser version not displaying the particular font characters correctly at small sizes.

Anyway, thanks for a great animation and your time. I'm just tucking into a large plate of humble pie.

Cheers.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/94.173.119.63|94.173.119.63]] ([[User talk:94.173.119.63|talk]]) 23:24, 1 April 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==[[Shape of the earth]]==

I though Pythagoras was one of the most prominent early proponents of the [[Spherical Earth]] concept. If so, maybe we should mention that in the article about him. --[[User:Ed Poor|Uncle Ed]] ([[User talk:Ed Poor|talk]]) 19:05, 17 April 2010 (UTC)
:There are almost no reliable facts known about what Pythagoras thought, and that's especially the case for the mathematical and scientific doctrines which were later fostered upon him. I see the Wikipedia page on the [[Spherical Earth]] does credit him with this. The idea apparently comes from [[Diogenes Laertius]], viii. 48:
:&lt;blockquote&gt;He [Pythagoras] was the first to call the heaven the universe and the earth spherical, though Theophrastus says it was Parmenides, and Zeno that it was Hesiod.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
:James Evans (''The History and Practice of Ancient Astronomy'', page 47) says about this passage: &quot;the statements by later Greek writers merely reflect the propensity for attributing every discovery to one or another of their ancient wise men.&quot; Charles H. Kahn, (''Pythagoras and the Pythagoreans: a brief history'', page 53) just says that &quot;the spherical earth is a distinctive innnovation of the Western [i.e. [[Magna Graecia]] ] cosmological tradition in [[Parmenides]] and [[Empedocles]], whereas the [[Ionian School (philosophy)|Ionian]] tradition preserves the flat earth.&quot; Both Evans and Kahn agree that the idea may have originated in the Pythagorean school, but nothing more. We can add this to the page if you like, but with the health-warnings too. [[User:Singinglemon|Singinglemon]] ([[User talk:Singinglemon|talk]]) 15:48, 19 April 2010 (UTC)
::Well I've not updated this page, but I've updated the page on the [[Spherical Earth]] to indicate the doubts about ascribing the idea to Pythagoras. [[User:Singinglemon|Singinglemon]] ([[User talk:Singinglemon|talk]]) 19:45, 19 April 2010 (UTC)

:::Well, if Pythagoras is taking undue credit, let's go back to what the sources say. It sounds like his 'school' adopted someone else's good idea. --[[User:Ed Poor|Uncle Ed]] ([[User talk:Ed Poor|talk]]) 02:24, 22 April 2010 (UTC)

I edited the following... '''Many attribute Pythagoras with discovering the [[Spherical Earth]] theory &lt;ref]http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/44846249/&lt;/ref]. Others believe that the accomplishments credited to Pythagoras may actually have been accomplishments of his colleagues and successors.''' - [[User:Brad Watson, Miami|Brad Watson, Miami]] ([[User talk:Brad Watson, Miami|talk]]) 14:01, 8 October 2012 (UTC)

== Edit request from 69.196.66.216, 28 April 2010 ==

{{tn|editsemiprotected}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;


&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[Special:Contributions/69.196.66.216|69.196.66.216]] ([[User talk:69.196.66.216|talk]]) 18:55, 28 April 2010 (UTC)
he is a very handsome man who is a eqyptian and was a mathematician. Nothing is known about him

:Thanks for your thoughts; however, we only add information from [[WP:RS|reliable sources]].&lt;small&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border: 1px solid; background-color:darkblue;&quot;&gt;[[User:Chzz|'''&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:darkblue; color:#FFFFFF&quot;&gt; &amp;nbsp;Chzz&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;''']][[User talk:Chzz|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00008B; background-color:yellow; border: 0px solid; &quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;►&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 19:12, 28 April 2010 (UTC)

{{notdone}}

== 'Pythagorean motto': &quot;God is ever a geometer&quot; ==

In researching the history of '''Greek gematria''' - the ''alphanumeric'' quality of a language - we are pointed to Pythagoras and the Pythagoreans. There is an ancient Greek motto: &quot;God is ever a geometer&quot; (ἀεὶ ὁ Θεὸς ὁ μέγας γεωμετρεῖ), whereas, counting the letters of the words (3,1,4,1,5,9) reveals the first six digits of pi (3.14159). This confirms that 'Step 1' of Greek gematria is simply counting the number of letters in a word/name and that 'Step 2' is the gematric sum of a word/name. There's a question of whether &quot;God is ever a geometer&quot; is rightfully accredited to Pythagoras, the Pythagoreans, or to Plato? - Brad Watson, Miami, FL [[Special:Contributions/65.34.180.54|65.34.180.54]] ([[User talk:65.34.180.54|talk]]) 12:20, 15 May 2010 (UTC)

Anyone? - [[User:Brad Watson, Miami|Brad Watson, Miami]] ([[User talk:Brad Watson, Miami|talk]]) 13:57, 8 October 2012 (UTC)

== Edit request from 81.30.240.226, 17 May 2010 ==

{{tld|editsemiprotected}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;
there are a few spelling mistakes in the article on Pythagoras, so I feel the need to correct them.

&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[Special:Contributions/81.30.240.226|81.30.240.226]] ([[User talk:81.30.240.226|talk]]) 12:43, 17 May 2010 (UTC)

{{ESp|n}} Welcome and thanks for wanting to improve this article. This template is used to allow a non-autoconfirmed editor to make changes to a semiprotected article using another editor as a proxy. Please specify what you want changed in a 'please change X to Y' degree of detail and someone will make the changes for you, unless there is a problem. Thanks again, [[User:Celestra|Celestra]] ([[User talk:Celestra|talk]]) 13:30, 17 May 2010 (UTC)


==Pending changes==
This article is one of a  number (about 100) selected for the early stage of the trial of the [[Wikipedia:Pending Changes]] system on the English language Wikipedia. All the articles listed at [[Wikipedia:Pending changes/Queue ]]  are being considered for level 1 pending changes protection.

The following request appears on that page:

{{Mbox|text=Many of the articles were selected semi-automatically from a list of indefinitely semi-protected articles.&lt;br /&gt;Please confirm that the protection level appears to be still warranted, and consider unprotecting instead, before applying pending changes protection to the article.}}

Comments on the suitability of theis page for &quot;Penfding changes&quot;  would be appreciated.

Please update the [[Wikipedia:Pending changes/Queue|Queue]] page as appropriate.

Note that I am not involved in this project any much more than any other editor, just posting these notes since it is quite a big change, potentially

Regards, ''[[User:Rich Farmbrough|Rich]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Rich Farmbrough|Farmbrough]]'', 23:37, 16 June 2010 (UTC).

== &quot;strange&quot; results of a Y! search took user to a Wiki archived page, &quot;talk: pythagor......&quot;, ad nauseam.... ==

'''Bold text'''

...a search for &quot;bogus string theory&quot; offered few results, and too, Wiki ppl might (convivially?) ponder this and related results, etc.

--dave

[[Special:Contributions/75.250.7.74|75.250.7.74]] ([[User talk:75.250.7.74|talk]]) 06:52, 24 June 2010 (UTC)

==In Our Time==
{{In Our Time|Pythagoras|b00p693b|Pythagoras}}
''[[User:Rich Farmbrough|Rich]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Rich Farmbrough|Farmbrough]]'', 03:19, 16 September 2010 (UTC).

== Edit request from 24.5.240.215, 8 October 2010 ==

{{tlx|edit semi-protected}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;
Please change the Date of Birth and Date of Death from &quot;B.C.&quot; (Before Christ) to &quot;B.C.E.&quot; (Before Current Era)

That is all. 

&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[Special:Contributions/24.5.240.215|24.5.240.215]] ([[User talk:24.5.240.215|talk]]) 01:53, 8 October 2010 (UTC)
:Declining request per [[WP:ERA]]—either abbreviation is acceptable if used consistently throughout an article. [[User:Deor|Deor]] ([[User talk:Deor|talk]]) 02:23, 8 October 2010 (UTC)
:{{ESp|n}} See above. Thanks, &lt;b&gt;[[User:Stickee|Stickee]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Stickee|(talk)]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/b&gt; 02:35, 8 October 2010 (UTC)

== Edit request from Junks, 20 November 2010 ==

{{tl|edit semi-protected}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;
in the section, Influence on Plato, the link to http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_Western_Philosophy should point here instead: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_History_of_Western_Philosophy

&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[User:Junks|Junks]] ([[User talk:Junks|talk]]) 15:43, 20 November 2010 (UTC)
:{{ESp|d}} &amp;nbsp; — '''&lt;font class=&quot;texhtml&quot;&gt;[[User:Jeff G.|Jeff]] [[User:Jeff G./talk|G.&amp;nbsp; ツ]]&lt;/font&gt;''' 16:17, 20 November 2010 (UTC)

== Edit request from 82.22.255.145, 4 December 2010 ==

{{Tld|edit semi-protected}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;
Hi, I'm female,and if I wanted to read up about a Mathematician, Pythagoras, I don't see why I have to be told women (50% of the population) are common property. You state many women were part of the Pythagoras group, but you imply they were there for non-academic reasons, which you have no right to do. The quotes are unrelated (you state different sources) put together to make (until you come up with evidence) an inaccurate statement. 

Please change 'The claim that they put all their property into a common stock is perhaps only a later inference from certain Pythagorean maxims and practices.[55] On the other hand, it seems certain that there were many women among the adherents of Pythagoras.[56]' to 
'The claim that they put all their property into a common stock is perhaps only a later inference from certain Pythagorean maxims and practices.[55] It seems certain that there were many women among the adherents of Pythagoras.[56]

&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[Special:Contributions/82.22.255.145|82.22.255.145]] ([[User talk:82.22.255.145|talk]]) 18:58, 4 December 2010 (UTC)

Hi, thanks for that. I've made an edit which I hope removes any possible confusion. --[[User:Annielogue|Annielogue]] ([[User talk:Annielogue|talk]]) 22:14, 4 December 2010 (UTC)

== Sumerian's Discovery of a^2+b^2=c^2? ==

http://www.nytimes.com/2010/11/23/science/23babylon.html?_r=1&amp;src=me&amp;ref=homepage  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/97.21.108.30|97.21.108.30]] ([[User talk:97.21.108.30|talk]]) 00:54, 17 December 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:The Babylonians' familiarity with the concept of Pythagorean triples (and speculation about whether they had a proof of the theorem) is already mentioned and sourced in the [[Pythagoras#Pythagorean theorem|Pythagorean theorem]] section of this article and in the &quot;History&quot; section of the [[Pythagorean theorem]] article, where an image of the same cuneiform tablet pictured in the NYT article appears. What is your question or suggestion? [[User:Deor|Deor]] ([[User talk:Deor|talk]]) 01:22, 17 December 2010 (UTC)

==Pythagorean Hammers==

I was having a difficult time finding '''anywhere on the internet''' the truth about the Pythagorean hammers; the story is clearly mythical, but everyone treats it as scientific truth (probably because the truth of the perfect proportions can be so easily demonstrated with strings that most people do not question whether the same would be true for hammers, or not). Anyway, fixed now, and I gave two sources. [[User:Terez27|Terez27]] ([[User talk:Terez27|talk]]) 16:53, 2 January 2011 (UTC)

&quot;This legend has since proven to be false by virtue of the fact that these ratios are only relevant to string length (such as the string of a monochord), and not to hammer weight.[48][49] However, it may be that Pythagoras was indeed responsible for discovering these properties of string length.&quot; 

The ratios are not &quot;only relevant to string length&quot;, but to vibrating air columns, such as in wind and brass instruments, and vibrating lengths of wood or metal, such as in xylophones, marimbas, vibraphones, accordions and harmonicas. Wind instruments have holes with or without keys to shorten and lengthen the air column to produce different pitches. Brass instruments often use valves to control the length of tube used to create an air column, and hence the basic pitch produced. Trombones vary the air column length with a telescopic slide - the more the slide is pulled out, the longer the column and thus the lower-pitched the basic note. By blowing into different holes in a harmonica, different lengths of metal (reeds) are vibrated to create different pitches. Accordions use bellows to vibrate the reeds, which are selected by keys or buttons. The longer the key on a xylophone, the lower-pitched the note it will produce when struck.

A common way to demonstrate the principle is to strike identical bottles containing different amounts of water; those with more water - and hence shorter air columns - will produce higher-pitched notes. The principle can also be readily seen in acoustic church organs, where the shorter the pipe, the higher the pitch it produces.
[[User:JRalphS|JRalphS]] ([[User talk:JRalphS|talk]]) 15:03, 5 November 2012 (UTC)

== Edit request on 12 January 2012 ==

{{edit semi-protected|answered=yes}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;
i want to write the origination of phytagoras theorem that how dd it come into existence
and how did he found that
This is the origination:-
One day phythagoras was drawing the same with some stick,he found that if a square is drawn on each side of 3-4-5 triangle,the area of the 2 small squares added together equals to the area of larger square
He examined it with other right angle triangle and it true with them too.6&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;+8&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;=10&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; the set of 3 numbers viz (3,4,5)
(6,8,10)(9,12,15)came to be know as phytagoras triplets

&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[User:Vaibhavmav|Vaibhavmav]] ([[User talk:Vaibhavmav|talk]]) 17:50, 12 January 2012 (UTC)

== Pronunciation of Pythagoras ? ==

Whats the English pronunciation of Pythagoras? (for those that haven't grown up in English) Any kind of IPA key seems to be missing. --[[User:Zom-B|Zom-B]] ([[User talk:Zom-B|talk]]) 05:09, 23 May 2012 (UTC)

== .... ==

The Right Angle Triangle Theorem is not his fuckin fathers property.

It is a classic geometrical relationship known to many cultures.
:Which is why that fact is mentioned right there in the article. Please sign your contributions to talk pages, and try not to use them as a forum. [[User:Nczempin|Nczempin]] ([[User talk:Nczempin|talk]]) 15:14, 21 June 2012 (UTC)

== error in external link  ==

about fragments, from the university of hanover. Corrected link must be: http://history.hanover.edu/texts/presoc/pythagor.html  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/82.134.244.241|82.134.244.241]] ([[User talk:82.134.244.241|talk]]) 20:26, 5 September 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:{{done}}. [[User:Deor|Deor]] ([[User talk:Deor|talk]]) 22:41, 5 September 2012 (UTC)

== &quot;Everything is number&quot; - Pythagoras ==

'''&quot;Everything is number&quot; is attributed to Phythagoras''' &lt;ref]citation needed&lt;/ref]. Anybody got a good source for that? I'm working on it. - [[User:Brad Watson, Miami|Brad Watson, Miami]] ([[User talk:Brad Watson, Miami|talk]]) 14:04, 8 October 2012 (UTC)
:{{tl|Citation needed}} is what you need, not a reference saying citation needed.  Make sure the source meets [[WP:RS]].  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 14:29, 8 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>np4uyd0r9fz6uynux6bw0doy0b7t1gl</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
