<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Perpetual virginity of Mary</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>718794</id>
    <revision>
      <id>500678038</id>
      <parentid>500667129</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-07-04T17:25:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>History2007</username>
        <id>3684925</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Referencing of quotations */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="31716">{{Christianity WikiProject|class=b|catholicism=yes|catholicism-importance=mid|saints=yes|saints importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Women's History|class=C|importance=high}}
{{archive box|[[/Archive 1|2004-2007]]}}
{{dyktalk|14 June|2004|entry=...that devout [[Roman Catholic|Catholics]] believe in the '''[[Perpetual Virginity of Mary]]'''?}}
== MacCulloch Book ==

Hi All,  The ref to the phrase &quot;This argumentation was repeated, not only by later Catholic theologians, but by the magisterial Protestant Reformers as well&quot; is given as &quot;D. MacCulloch, The Reformation: a History (Penguin Books, 2003) pp. 614.&quot;.  From a couple of sites I have the title as &quot;Reformation : Europe's House Divided&quot;.  There is a book &quot;The Reformation: a History&quot; but it is a different book, and under 300 pages, so I guess that the error in the ref is with the title, and I will amend accordingly.  [[User:Springnuts|Springnuts]] ([[User talk:Springnuts|talk]]) 21:39, 16 January 2008 (UTC)
==Biblical Passages==
In the section currently called Biblical Passages and their Historical Interpretation the ''Protoevangelium of James'' is mentioned or quoted twice.  Clearly, it doesn't belong.  While it is called apocryphal, its very presence in this section is (and has been for a long time) wrong and misleading.  It has far less (=&quot;no&quot;) value for helping to determine the Biblical background or basis of the doctrine, and ought to come out or move to a different section.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:LindsayH|LindsayH]] ([[User talk:LindsayH|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/LindsayH|contribs]]) 06:43, 21 January 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
Whoops, forgot to sign, now i see some bot did it.  Oh well.  Cheers, [[User:LindsayH|Lindsay]] ([[User talk:LindsayH|talk]]) 06:49, 21 January 2008 (UTC)
:Good point - it overlapped with the section on 'Antiquity', so I have moved it there and merged the two paragraphs.  It is now better, I think, but perhaps unwieldy.  [[User:Springnuts|Springnuts]] ([[User talk:Springnuts|talk]]) 22:38, 21 January 2008 (UTC)
::Unwieldy?  Maybe, but it flows well.  Good work.  The other mention, since it illustrates an eary interpretation of adelphoi can surely stay.  I slightly twiddled with the language, so i hope it's good and clear.  Cheer, [[User:LindsayH|Lindsay]] ([[User talk:LindsayH|talk]]) 13:19, 23 January 2008 (UTC)
== Evangelical position == 
I think it might be worth a mention that this position is rejected by mainstream evangelical Christianity today.
[[Special:Contributions/78.145.39.64|78.145.39.64]] ([[User talk:78.145.39.64|talk]]) 17:09, 21 December 2010 (UTC)
== Cites for denominational teachings ==

Previously the claim that this was a doctrine of the Roman Catholic, Eastern Orthodox, and Oriental Orthodox churches was cited all by a reference to the Cathechism of the &quot;Catholic Church&quot;. Obviously this cite is only sufficient for the RCC at best, and therefore the cite was moved to merely the Roman Catholic part of that claim, and a citation needed was added next to both Eastern Orthodox and Oriental Orthodox.

A cite recently was added next to the Eastern Orthodox part, but the link did not work so it has been removed and the citation needed put back up.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.231.188.215|76.231.188.215]] ([[User talk:76.231.188.215|talk]]) 04:49, 29 February 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

No cite was provided as proof of the universal teachings of the Eastern Orthodox and Oriental Orthodox, so the claim was changed and qualified. [[User:Deusveritasest|Deusveritasest]] ([[User talk:Deusveritasest|talk]]) 23:57, 2 March 2008 (UTC)

The first sentence in the current version of this page states that this is a dogma of the Roman Catholic, Eastern Orthodox, and Oriental Orthodox Churches. I believe this is incorrect. I think it is a dogma of the Roman Catholic Church, but I believe it is only a doctrine, not a dogma, of the Eastern Orthodox Church. I have no idea where it stands among the Oriental Orthodox, so I hesitate to edit this sentence.[[User:Orthodox hillbilly|Orthodox hillbilly]] ([[User talk:Orthodox hillbilly|talk]]) 04:44, 15 July 2009 (UTC)

== criticism ==

I'm not very experienced at this but I've noticed that this page is very imbalanced.  There is no representation for modern interpretations other than those in support of this doctrine.  Can we get a criticism section at the very least?  Many historical interpretations are stated which are easily countered by a modern interpretation but there is no section for this?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.229.192.217|76.229.192.217]] ([[User talk:76.229.192.217|talk]]) 08:01, 24 September 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Where would it be appropriate to add this case against the doctrine of perpetual virginity?  The case starts with psalm chapter 69.  Verse 9 is this - &quot;I have become an outcast to my kin, a stranger to my mother's children.&quot;  It is clearly a psalm from Christ's perspective and a prophecy as it is the source for the famous line &quot;instead they put gall in my food; for my thirst they gave me vinegar.&quot; which is mentioned as a fulfilled prophesy in the New Testament.  Next, we can know the brothers and sisters mentioned were not children of Joseph from a prior marriage because Jewish people didn't have more than one &quot;firstborn&quot;. This is evidenced in Genesis 49:3 when Jacob calls his sons from different mothers and tells Reuben that he is the firstborn - obviously because he was chronologically born first.  If Joseph had children from a previous marriage, someone else would have been the first born. Luke 2:22 &quot;When the time of their purification according to the Law of Moses had been completed, Joseph and Mary took him to Jerusalem to present him to the Lord 23(as it is written in the Law of the Lord, &quot;Every firstborn male is to be consecrated to the Lord&quot;  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.229.192.217|76.229.192.217]] ([[User talk:76.229.192.217|talk]]) 08:48, 24 September 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

The modern opposition is quite simple, and encompasses what most Protestants believe about the subject: the idea of Mary's perpetual virginity not only has no basis in scripture, it is flatly contradicted by the most obvious literal interpretation of the Gospels. Catholic and Orthodox doctrine bends over backwards to reinterpret the text is a less plausible way to get around the contradiction. It's understandable that they don't have a problem with the lack of scriptural basis; Catholic and Orthodox Christianity are not sola scriptura. But the idea that non-scriptural doctrines can ''contradict'' scripture and still be Christian makes no sense to me. [[Special:Contributions/75.76.213.106|75.76.213.106]] ([[User talk:75.76.213.106|talk]]) 22:42, 25 December 2010 (UTC)

== Original investigation refuting the virginitas post partum aspect of the perpetual virginity of mary ==

hello, i just want to comment that i have done a paper on this subject, and i tackle it from a fresh perspective, which to be honest, its weird that nobody has done it before me (that i know of)and i wish to add this view to this article, just want some feedback, to see what others think, here ill outline the basics of my results

so the deal is this, insted of tackling this subject from the gospels, i try to sustain that mary had at least one more brother, the one the apostle paul met according to (Gal 1:19 But other of the apostles saw I none, save James the Lord's brother.)

i know this text in itself may not amount to much, since the word being used is adelphos, the same used in the gospels, and thus it could easly mean cousins, which is one of the official postures of the catholic church.

but this text united with the following, give new life to the traditional interpretation of adelphos, the text is COL 4:10
which reads: (Aristarchus my fellow prisoner greets you, with Mark the cousin of Barnabas (about whom you received instructions: if he comes to you, welcome him) 

as of the time of the apostle paul the word anepsios (g431 strong) was exclusive for cousin 

(according to vines expository dictionary on the new testament, it reads the followin: in Col 4:10 denotes a &quot;cousin&quot; rather than a nephew (AV, &quot;sister's son&quot;). &quot;Cousin&quot; is its meaning in various periods of Greek writers. In this sense it is used in the Sept., in Num 36:11. In later writings it denotes a nephew; hence the AV rendering. As Lightfoot says, there is no reason to suppose that the Apostle would have used it in any other than its proper sense. We are to understand, therefore, that Mark was the cousin of Barnabas)

now this is true specialy if you are a sola scrptura beliver,the word is only used in the LXX in Num 36:11 (For Mahlah, Tirzah, and Hoglah, and Milcah, and Noah, the daughters of Zelophehad, were married unto their father's brothers' sons) 
LXX (11 και εγενοντο Θερσα και Εγλα και Μελχα και Νουα και 
Μααλα θυγατερες σαλπααδ τοις '''ανεψιοις''' αυτων )

what does this mean then? this means that the apostle paul knew and used the word for cousin in greek in one of his epistles, so he was not respecting hebrew tradtion (as some debate the evangelist did) by using adelphos to mean cousin.

conluding, had the apostle ment to say that James was kin or cousin to the lord, we now have ample evidence that he wouldve used the correct word, yet he said brother. therefore, mary did in fact had other sons, wich would rebuke the belif of the perpetual virginity. 

just want to add that this is only refering to the virginitas post partum aspect of the perpetual virginity, and not to the virgin conception or birth, which of course all branches of christianity adhere to.
[[User:Gabrielsol|Gabrielsol]] ([[User talk:Gabrielsol|talk]]) 02:08, 8 November 2008 (UTC)

:Per Wikipedia policies original research is not permitted.  Please read the article [[WP:NOR]] [[User:Marauder40|Marauder40]] ([[User talk:Marauder40|talk]]) 14:37, 10 November 2008 (UTC)

Obviously i would not use this article to &quot;publish&quot; my original investigation, let me  quote of the article you linked 
&quot;This policy does not prohibit editors with specialist knowledge from adding their knowledge to Wikipedia, but it does prohibit them from drawing on their personal knowledge without citing their sources.&quot;

just want my published investigation to form part of this subject, specialy since it is done on the subject, of course, it would be writen in a neutral way, just adding some information, which i belive is relevant.[[User:Gabrielsol|Gabrielsol]] ([[User talk:Gabrielsol|talk]]) 06:27, 11 November 2008 (UTC)

:especificly, let me show you where and why my investigation is a logical and relevant add, there is a part of the article named &quot;biblical passages and their interpretation&quot; which for some reason omits the passage where this is investigation is based upon, galatians 1:19, and its one of the many passages used with the others mentioned there, to refute the post partum aspect of the perpetual virginity. so if the results of this investigation are to be added, they would be added only as a small, cited, neutral, explanation of the very relevant and very important passage of gal 1:19. thanks  [[User:Gabrielsol|Gabrielsol]] ([[User talk:Gabrielsol|talk]]) 06:38, 11 November 2008 (UTC)

==Immaculate conception==
In many cases, the Perpetual Virginity is confused or confounded with the Immaculate Conception, and this may just as well be noted. [[User:ADM|ADM]] ([[User talk:ADM|talk]]) 00:02, 12 January 2009 (UTC)

:Yes. Done. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 00:57, 12 January 2009 (UTC)

==Claims that Count Saint Germain is Saint Joseph==
I have found this interesting claim that Saint-Germain/[[Enoch]]/Metatron was also Saint Joseph, the husband of Mary. This would  mean theologically that Joseph is an incarnation of the [[Holy Spirit]] and that he is divine in his non-incarnated form. Now, [[Metatron]] cannot sin, therefore any special relationship between Joseph and Mary would not be counted as sin. This would explain why many Catholics give a special cultus to Joseph and the Holy Family. [http://www.missionsaintgermain.com/id58.html] [[User:ADM|ADM]] ([[User talk:ADM|talk]]) 03:55, 20 March 2009 (UTC)

:Hi, although interesting, it is clearly ''original research'' and [[WP:OR]] disallows its use, even if it is 100% true. The missionsaintgermain site is not a reliable 3rd party type site either. But in any case, this is clearly a WP:OR siuation. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 03:09, 21 March 2009 (UTC)

This seems to be factually in error.  I am not Catholic, but I hardly believe that this thesis explains why such emphasis is given to the &quot;holy family.&quot;  Whatever the reason is it can hardly be explained in terms of Joseph being divine, otherwise he would play a larger role in Catholic theology than Mary, but as it is he not only does not play such a role, but is often neglected in comparison to the other Saints.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/129.62.119.81|129.62.119.81]] ([[User talk:129.62.119.81|talk]]) 06:53, 1 September 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Section on Protestantism==

This section is utterly useless and contains statements that are either incomprehensible or completely wrong. For example, the opening sentence states: &quot;From the fifth century on no opposition whatever to the doctrine was expressed in either East or West.&quot; What does the statement even *mean*? That no Protestants have opposed the doctrine? This is patently absurd as most Protestants do not believe in the perpetual virginity of Mary. The entire section cherry picks various Protestant figures and tries to establish their belief in this doctrine, but makes no mention of the majority of Protestant leaders that do not support the belief. The entire section needs a rewrite because as it stands now it is nothing more than a POV love letter to the doctrine of Mary's perpetual virginity. [[User:Supertheman|&lt;font color=&quot;darkblue&quot;&gt;Supertheman&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;darkblue&quot;&gt;(&lt;/font&gt;[[User_talk:Supertheman|&lt;font color=&quot;darkblue&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;font color=&quot;darkblue&quot;&gt;)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 12:39, 7 June 2009 (UTC)
:You are perfectly right about the opening sentence.  It is obviously incomplete.  I have endeavoured to complete it, so that it makes sense.  The heading of the section is indeed misleading: the section is not about Protestantism, but only about the Protestant Reformation.  I have fixed that too.  It would be good to include views of modern Protestants, who in this matter do not agree with Luther and his contemporaries.  Can you help by adding a section on their views?  [[User:Lima|Lima]] ([[User talk:Lima|talk]]) 18:16, 7 June 2009 (UTC)

::Not being familiar with Protestant views I can not say that I agree or disagree. But whenever I read &quot;majority of X believes Y&quot; I wonder who did a formal survey on that. Given that there are multiple Protestant views, could whoever adds anything please be sure to have exact references for each assertion on majority of X believes Y. Thanks. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 18:48, 7 June 2009 (UTC)

: I too think that this section is oddly constructed, and that the &quot;Biblical passages and their interpretations&quot; section is too weighted in the &quot;pro&quot; perpetual virginity position. [[User:Tuckerresearch|TuckerResearch]] ([[User talk:Tuckerresearch|talk]]) 05:20, 24 August 2009 (UTC)

The line that is given to Calvin's views on the matter should either be eliminated, expanded, qualified or made to link to the article on his views.  As it stands, it is misleading: it gives the impression that he (like Wesley and Luther, the theologians he is sandwiched between) affirmed the doctrine.  In reality he rejected it more emphatically than most Protestants, since he thought virginity within marriage would violate the nature of the marriage covenant.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/129.62.119.81|129.62.119.81]] ([[User talk:129.62.119.81|talk]]) 06:47, 1 September 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:This article fails to be a balanced and NPOV presentation bu overstating Protestant belief that Jesus could emerge from Mary's uterus without rupturing her hymen, or that her hymen was miraculously restored after expanding so his head could pass through. Protestants I have heard discuss it only go so far as to grant her getting pregnant without having intercourse, but assume a natural delivery. [[User:Edison|Edison]] ([[User talk:Edison|talk]]) 20:24, 28 December 2009 (UTC)

== Virginity ''during'' birth ==
What is the significance of this statement, which comes up multiple times in the article? Why would a virgin before giving birth lose her status in virtue of having done so? Was there a tradition that babies being delivered were, in the process of birth, metaphorically engaged in intercourse with their mothers? --[[User:Gargletheape|Gargletheape]] ([[User talk:Gargletheape|talk]]) 14:50, 15 December 2009 (UTC)
:The meaning is: with hymen intact.  [[User:Lima|Lima]] ([[User talk:Lima|talk]]) 19:05, 15 December 2009 (UTC)

: this Belief is not supported by any face - it is from a RELIGION - that speak volumes!  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:GADFLY46|GADFLY46]] ([[User talk:GADFLY46|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/GADFLY46|contribs]]) 02:23, 2 April 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:: Obviously a woman's body changes after giving birth. Her hymen was intact, nothing was changed. Her body was as if she never gave birth. --[[User:Willthacheerleader18|Willthacheerleader18]] ([[User talk:Willthacheerleader18|talk]]) 12:23, 14 November 2010 (UTC)

:::Virginity is not defined by an intact hymen.  Many virgins do not have intact hymens. [[User:Slrubenstein|Slrubenstein]]   |  [[User talk:Slrubenstein|Talk]] 17:52, 8 December 2010 (UTC)
::::It is important in church teaching. Her body was not changed by the birth at all. --[[User:Willthacheerleader18|Willthacheerleader18]] ([[User talk:Willthacheerleader18|talk]]) 21:53, 8 December 2010 (UTC)

:::Non sequitor.  You are not responding to what I orte.  I said that many virgins do not have intact hymens.  Did you think I was referring to some ''other'' virgins who also gave birth to sons?  I wrote that many virgins do not have intact hymens, I am talking about virgins, not about girls who have had children.  Wasn't it obvious that I was not referring to any change occuring during conception, pregnancy, or birth.  The Church cannot possibly teach that Mary's body underwent no changes from birth - she got bigger, and surely began to menstruate, these are changes.  Many girls break their hymens during childhood. [[User:Slrubenstein|Slrubenstein]]   |  [[User talk:Slrubenstein|Talk]] 23:22, 8 December 2010 (UTC)
::::I do not think you are understanding what I am saying. her body was not changed BY the birth. Yes, she was pregnant and got &quot;bigger&quot;, but after she gave birth, her body was as it was she had never had child. --[[User:Willthacheerleader18|Willthacheerleader18]] ([[User talk:Willthacheerleader18|talk]]) 21:26, 9 December 2010 (UTC)
:::I understand exactly what you are saying.  Can you tell me '''where'' I ever even hinted that her body was changed BY the birth?  Since I never suggested that, your comment does not follow mine. [[User:Slrubenstein|Slrubenstein]]   |  [[User talk:Slrubenstein|Talk]] 22:57, 9 December 2010 (UTC)
::::&quot;The Church cannot possibly teach that Mary's body underwent no changes from birth - she got bigger, and surely began to menstruate, these are changes&quot;. Those changes went away, to a point as if they never had happened. That is all. I don't see how that is so confusing to you. --[[User:Willthacheerleader18|Willthacheerleader18]] ([[User talk:Willthacheerleader18|talk]]) 23:43, 9 December 2010 (UTC)

:::I am not confused, you are.  All I said was that there is no reason to think she had an intact hymen, that simply has nothing to do with virginity. [[User:Slrubenstein|Slrubenstein]]   |  [[User talk:Slrubenstein|Talk]] 01:29, 10 December 2010 (UTC)
::::Then your comments on this section have no meaning. I never said an intact hymen was necessary for virginity. Be civil. All I said was that the church teaches her body was not changed. I never even originally commented on something you said, you wrote to me. The church teaches her body was uncorupted and her hymen was intact. Got a problem? Address the Pope. --[[User:Willthacheerleader18|Willthacheerleader18]] ([[User talk:Willthacheerleader18|talk]]) 16:43, 10 December 2010 (UTC)
:::You wrote &quot;Her hymen was intact,&quot; with no evidence, and and Lima wrote that virginity = intact hymen.  I was responding to these two comments, by you and by Lima - you are not the only one participating in this discussion and I have a right to reply to Lima, not just you, so please be civil.  Where does the Church teach that her hymen was intact?  A torn humen is no more a corruption of the body than mensturation, or the growth of pubic hair.  So your point about corruption of the body is irrelevant.  And I must ask you, where have I ever suggested that her giving birth to Jesus changed her body?  Please be civil and respond to what I wrote, and not to what I did not write, when you respond to me. [[User:Slrubenstein|Slrubenstein]]   |  [[User talk:Slrubenstein|Talk]] 17:35, 10 December 2010 (UTC)

== Question about the introduction ==
The last sentence of the second paragraph says: &quot;However, since the Desert Fathers these individuals have been interpreted by some as possibly cousins or relatives of Jesus.&quot;  It is confusing.  Is it saying that the Desert fathers had this interpretation, or is it saying that this interpretation dates to the time of the Desert Fathers.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/96.27.111.8|96.27.111.8]] ([[User talk:96.27.111.8|talk]]) 20:45, 13 November 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Josephus==

Esoglou, it would appear that Josephus believed that James was the brother of Jesus, as did the early Jewish sources. I will leave it to you to work it into the article from a NPOV. Cheers - [[User:Ret.Prof|Ret.Prof]] ([[User talk:Ret.Prof|talk]]) 11:37, 15 November 2010 (UTC)
:Done.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 12:01, 15 November 2010 (UTC)

== Believed de fide? ==

In order to prevent an edit war, I wanted to explain why I would like to change the following statement:

&quot;The doctrine of the perpetual virginity of Mary, which is believed de fide, i.e. held as having the highest degree of certainty among doctrines, states that...&quot;

The statement implies that all religions follow this doctrine, particularly if you don't know what &quot;de fide&quot; means. The definition of de fide listed there implies that it is a certain, verified truth. I'll reword it to make it clearer. ~[[User:Araignee|Araignee]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Araignee|talk]] &amp;bull; [[Special:Contributions/Araignee|contribs]])&lt;/small&gt;  19:17, 7 May 2011 (UTC)

:No it does ''not'' mean that at all. But this is a less than smart discussion and I will let it go. Makes no big difference to the article and an IP will probably change it in 6 months anyway. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 19:42, 7 May 2011 (UTC)

::Did you look at the current edit? Are you happy with that? ~[[User:Araignee|Araignee]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Araignee|talk]] &amp;bull; [[Special:Contributions/Araignee|contribs]])&lt;/small&gt;  20:22, 7 May 2011 (UTC)

:::I will be very happy not to talk about this any more. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 21:01, 7 May 2011 (UTC)

== Islam ==
Both sources mentioned are Catholic sources and neither reference a reason why the Muslims might believe it, instead simply stating that the Qur'an affirms the perpetual virginity. However, while the Qur'an does clearly support the virgin birth of Jesus, it does not state or imply celibacy or virginity after the fact, nor does this notion mesh with Muslim culture. ~[[User:Araignee|Araignee]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Araignee|talk]] &amp;bull; [[Special:Contributions/Araignee|contribs]])&lt;/small&gt;  22:52, 31 August 2011 (UTC)

:So do you have [[WP:RS]] sources that supports your statement, or is it just your ''personal opinion'' that &quot;nor does this notion mesh with Muslim culture&quot;. The way Wikipedia works is that personal opinions do not matter, so you need a [[WP:RS]] source to refute those statements. As is, those seem like WP:RS sources, and that is what we have to go by, not use [[WP:primary]] sources such as the Qur'an itself. So, you will either come up with RS sources, or I will re-instate those items. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 23:04, 31 August 2011 (UTC)

::I have added two reliable references that are focused on Islam rather than mentioning an unsourced opinion in passing. ~[[User:Araignee|Araignee]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Araignee|talk]] &amp;bull; [[Special:Contributions/Araignee|contribs]])&lt;/small&gt;  01:11, 1 September 2011 (UTC)
:::Looks better now. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 01:13, 1 September 2011 (UTC)

== Protestant views ==

The lead section correctly states that early reformers supported the concept of perpetual virginity.  Current doctrine of diverse protestant churches, including Lutheran and Anglican however, does not.  The citations do not support the statement.   This needs correcting. [[User:Rlsheehan|Rlsheehan]] ([[User talk:Rlsheehan|talk]]) 17:18, 25 September 2011 (UTC)

:How did you determine they do not? I am pretty sure I checked those last month, but not 100% sure. Did you look them up, all 5 of them? [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 18:25, 25 September 2011 (UTC)

::The citations concentrate on the views of the early reformers.  There are two problems:  1) Just because Luther said something does not make it current policy or belief of the many different Lutheran churches. Several of his published  thoughts are not current Lutheran belief.   2) Protestant churches often do not have strong formal published doctrines: there may be published creeds and statements of concord but individual regions, synods, churches, and parishoners are not bound by them.  The most important Protestant document is the Bible, [[sola scriptura]], and that does not discuss perpetual virginity.
::I have seen nothing that suggests current broad Protestant belief in the perpetual virginity of Mary.   [[User:Rlsheehan|Rlsheehan]] ([[User talk:Rlsheehan|talk]]) 19:02, 25 September 2011 (UTC)

:::Please answer the question: Did you read the citation texts? Read [http://books.google.com/books?id=ZP_f9icf2roC&amp;pg=PA1134&amp;dq=merriam+webster+perpetual+virginity&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=mYF_TvmvD8jOswbqspUn&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CC8Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false this one] &quot;maintained by some Anglican and Lutherans&quot; then check the others yourslef, before jumping to conclusions. Now, 4 more to check. Check first, type later. Easy? [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 19:33, 25 September 2011 (UTC)

:Let's read them carefully.   The  sentence in question is: &quot;Currently Lutheran and some Anglican churches endorse the doctrine of perpetual virginity, but it is not held in all of these churches&quot; and has THREE citations.
:Reference 5 is the Webster dictionary that says &quot;...also maintained by some Anglican and Lutheran theologians&quot;.  This is a far cry from an endorsement of the churches!  I would support this statement in the article because it is supported by a good reference.  This reference does not support the current wording.
:I have not read reference 10 but it suggests &quot;a lifelong belief of Luther&quot;.  Again, this is not endorsement by all Lutheran churches.
:Reference 11 was written by an Anglican grad student and is not an endorsement by the Anglican communion.
:The citations do not support the current wording.  Let's change the wording to that of the dictionary.  [[User:Rlsheehan|Rlsheehan]] ([[User talk:Rlsheehan|talk]]) 21:57, 25 September 2011 (UTC)

::No big deal. Done. Also [http://books.google.com/books?id=aSImuYu9ztsC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Jackson,+Gregory+Lee,+Catholic,+Lutheran,+Protestant:+a+doctrinal+comparison.&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=Ncl_Tq3hNISk4AS2l4X0Dg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCwQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=virginity&amp;f=false read this]. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 00:25, 26 September 2011 (UTC)

== Clarification? ==

Perhaps I have misunderstood, but I feel that the following line (from the section about the Early Church) would be more accurate with the insertion of the word in italics:
&quot;The document discusses Mary’s virginity before birth, the absence of labor pains, and how a midwife’s examination demonstrated Mary’s virginity during birth, thus asserting the virginity of Mary before, during, and ''immediately'' after the birth of Jesus.&quot;
[[User:WookMuff|WookMuff]] ([[User talk:WookMuff|talk]]) 01:50, 2 December 2011 (UTC)

:I have not actually read the original document, but one needs see if it also asserts it elsewhere as weeks afterwards, etc. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 02:32, 2 December 2011 (UTC)
::We don't have access to the Gambero book, and the other cited source, which is on patrology, may well give the exact text of the Protoevangelium, so are we permitted to give the text of the Protoevangelium itself as source?  I have tentatively done so, making the statement in the article reflect what the Protoevangelium actually says.  If you think it illegitimate to do so, just revert.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 07:47, 2 December 2011 (UTC)

:::I see no problem with your edit. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 08:33, 2 December 2011 (UTC)

== Referencing of quotations ==

While references in ledes are not normally required it is required that ALL QUOTATIONS are referenced even when in the lede. [[User:Afterwriting|Afterwriting]] ([[User talk:Afterwriting|talk]]) 11:20, 4 July 2012 (UTC)

:Don't get upset now. The refs were in the body, you could have just copied them. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 11:50, 4 July 2012 (UTC)

::Not upset, just pointing out what should have been obvious. [[User:Afterwriting|Afterwriting]] ([[User talk:Afterwriting|talk]]) 15:58, 4 July 2012 (UTC)

:::Ok... no big deal anyway. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 17:25, 4 July 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>bx8f0f3vznhee0re4va1ocyibnv37er</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
