<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Vatican City</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>811045</id>
    <revision>
      <id>514453639</id>
      <parentid>513846997</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-25T07:41:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Esoglou</username>
        <id>11289927</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Name */ cmt</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26257">{{Outline of knowledge coverage|Vatican City}}
{{talkheader}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=FAC
|action1date=04:17, 3 Feb 2005
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Archived nominations/December 2004
|action1result=not promoted
|action1oldid=10126106

|action2=PR
|action2date=16:12, 7 January 2007
|action2link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Vatican City/archive1
|action2result=reviewed
|action2oldid=99110706

|currentstatus=FFAC
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Vatican City|class=c|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject European Microstates|class=c|importance=Top|Vatican City=yes|Vatican City-importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Christianity|class=c|importance=High|catholicism=yes|catholicism-importance=Top}}
{{WP City of Rome|class=c|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Italy|class=c|importance=Top}}
{{WPCountries|importance=Top|class=c
| b1 &lt;!--Referencing &amp; citations--&gt; = no
| b2 &lt;!--Coverage &amp; accuracy    --&gt; = yes
| b3 &lt;!--Structure              --&gt; = yes
| b4 &lt;!--Grammar &amp; style        --&gt; = yes
| b5 &lt;!--Supporting materials   --&gt; = yes
| b6 &lt;!--Accessibility          --&gt; = yes}}
{{WPCities|class=c|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Architecture|class=c|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject World Heritage Sites|class=c|importance=Top
|b1 &lt;!--Referencing &amp; citations--&gt; = no
|b2 &lt;!--Coverage &amp; accuracy    --&gt; = yes
|b3 &lt;!--Structure              --&gt; = yes
|b4 &lt;!--Grammar &amp; Style        --&gt; = yes
|b5 &lt;!--Supporting materials   --&gt; = yes
|b6                                = yes}}
{{WP1.0|v0.5=pass|class=C|category=Geography|WPCD=yes}}}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2005-02-11|oldid1=10180195|date2=2006-02-11|oldid2=38342723|date3=2007-02-11|oldid3=107109352|date4=2008-02-11|oldid4=190541123|date5=2009-02-11|oldid5=269490913}}

== Duplicate images ==

The image of St. Peter's Square in the Head of State section appears again under Citizenship. Its the same photo. Can we delete one? I recommend deleting the second one. It appears under the 360 degree image.[[User:Racerx11|Racerx11]] ([[User talk:Racerx11|talk]]) 13:14, 23 January 2011 (UTC)
:Done.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 15:35, 23 January 2011 (UTC)

== Sports Section doesn't seem appropriate ==

I removed the sports section from the article as there doesn't appear to be any reliable secondary sources that support it's inclusion.   In fact Google search for the Vatican Football team only reveals Wikipedia or mirror sites. 

Here is the section as it was in case someone can find proper sources for it:
Vatican City has no sport league or stadium. It has sometimes fielded a [[Vatican City national football team|national football team]] drawn from the Swiss Guards (dual Vatican and Swiss citizens), members of the Papal council,{{Clarify|date=March 2010}} and museum guards (Italian citizens). Since the Swiss Guards, who have Vatican City citizenship, are not free in sufficient numbers except for short periods, the national team can play international matches only rarely, on which occasions they may draw an interested press. The [[Vatican City national football team]] plays at [[Stadio Pio XII]] in Italy.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}}  Many of the Pontifical seminaries in Rome compete in the [[Clericus Cup]] football tournament each winter and spring.  The Cup is organised by the Italian [[:it:Centro Sportivo Italiano|Centro Sportivo Italiano (CSI)]].  [[Vatican Radio]] reports on the outcomes of the Cup's matches which are held at the [[Knights of Columbus]] football fields at the Oratory of St. Peter on the Gelsomino Hill in Rome.
In 2008 the Dutch Fellowship of Fairly Odd Places C.C. challenged the Vatican into raising its own National Team. Subsequently a first cricket match ever between their National side and the Dutch team was played at the Stadio dei Marmi. The Vatican XI won by 9 wickets. All Vatican XI players were of Indian descent.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}}

[[User:Elmmapleoakpine|Elmmapleoakpine]] ([[User talk:Elmmapleoakpine|talk]]) 02:00, 26 January 2011 (UTC)
==File:1 euro coin Va serie 3.png Nominated for speedy Deletion==
{|
|-
| [[Image:Icon Now Commons orange.svg|50px]] 
| An image used in this article, [[commons:File:1 euro coin Va serie 3.png|File:1 euro coin Va serie 3.png]], has been nominated for speedy deletion at [[Wikimedia Commons]] for the following reason: ''Copyright violations'' 
;What should I do?
|-
|
| Speedy deletions at commons tend to take longer than they do on Wikipedia, so there is no rush to respond. If you feel the deletion can be contested then please do so ([[commons:COM:SPEEDY]] has further information). Otherwise consider finding a replacement image before deletion occurs.

A further notification will be placed when/if the image is deleted. ''This notification is provided by a Bot, currently under trial'' --[[User:CommonsNotificationBot|CommonsNotificationBot]] ([[User talk:CommonsNotificationBot|talk]]) 11:20, 16 May 2011 (UTC)
|}

== Government Type ==

In the box the government type is described as &quot;Ecclesiastical sacerdotal monarchical&quot;, it's pretty obvious that you can't put three adjectives without a noun there so I'll change it to &quot;Ecclesiastical sacerdotal absolute monarchy&quot; as the website of the Vatican state says it is an absolute monarchy. What I wonder is: shouldn't theocracy be in there too?--[[User:Tomvasseur|Tomvasseur]] ([[User talk:Tomvasseur|talk]]) 22:21, 8 July 2011 (UTC)
:The punctuation indicates that the now three descriptions (ecclesiastical, sacerdotal-monarchical, absolute monarchy) are all derived from reliable sources. They should report the sources faithfully.  The first two are adjectives qualifying the noun &quot;type&quot;.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 06:23, 9 July 2011 (UTC)
:: OK, but monarchical monarchy is a bit superfluous, &quot;ecclesiastical, sacerdotal, absolute monarchy&quot; should be enough. I don't think the source of sacerdotal-monarchical is misused by leaving out monarchical.--[[User:Tomvasseur|Tomvasseur]] ([[User talk:Tomvasseur|talk]]) 20:47, 10 July 2011 (UTC)

== Dependent territory? ==

Would it be useful to call the Vatican City a dependent territory of the Holy See? Or would that count as original research?
[[User:Andrewgdotcom|Andrewgdotcom]] ([[User talk:Andrewgdotcom|talk]]) 20:08, 27 July 2011 (UTC)

== Vatican the largest spiritual state ==

Croatian writer Giancarlo Kravar: Vatican is by its territory the smallest state in the world, but has the largest spiritual territory.[[Special:Contributions/78.2.80.116|78.2.80.116]] ([[User talk:78.2.80.116|talk]]) 00:12, 7 September 2011 (UTC)
:A somewhat striking turn of phrase, but not an objective statement for insertion in the article.  &quot;Spiritual territory&quot; can be seen as a contradiction in terms, and the spiritual allegiance referred to is not to the state but to the Holy See.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 06:37, 7 September 2011 (UTC)

== What is the capital city of the Vatican? ==

If &quot;capital city&quot; means &quot;the city where the seat of government is located&quot;, the Vatican's capital would be the city of Rome, isn't it? &quot;Vatican City&quot; is not an actual city, it's just the official name of the state. Yes, I am aware that this would be a unique case of a state being smaller than its capital city, but so what? Please consider changing the relevant information in the article. [[Special:Contributions/88.203.176.7|88.203.176.7]] ([[User talk:88.203.176.7|talk]]) 21:47, 14 October 2011 (UTC)
:Isn't anybody going to comment on my proposal? The Vatican may be considered a &quot;city-state&quot;, but there is no such city as &quot;Vatican&quot;, there have never been any (separate) cities within Rome, before or after the Lateran Treaty. Doesn't it mean that the Vatican's capital city is Rome? If someone objects that Rome is an Italian (and therefore foreign) city, this is not true -- Rome is not entirely Italian, since a part of it belongs to another state. Please share your thoughts on the subject. [[Special:Contributions/88.203.176.7|88.203.176.7]] ([[User talk:88.203.176.7|talk]]) 20:50, 20 October 2011 (UTC)
::That's a very interesting idea. A lot of it depends on how you define what a city is, which is surprisingly more complicated than it sounds. The administrative definition of Rome no doubt doesn't include the Vatican City, as it would be restricted to Italy. Anyway, if you can find any sources backing you on this, please present them. I think in the end we have to accept that the Vatican is a very sui generis state, and issues like this which would be clear for other countries aren't so in this case. [[User:Chipmunkdavis|Chipmunkdavis]] ([[User talk:Chipmunkdavis|talk]]) 22:17, 20 October 2011 (UTC)
:::Well, you are talking about the ''Italian'' part of Rome, which definitely doesn't include the Vatican. But, in my opinion, Rome is (at least ''de-facto'') a divided city, not unlike pre-1990 Berlin and pre-1967 Jerusalem -- politically it belongs to two different states, but geographically it is still a single city, of which the Vatican is clearly a part. And when explaining ''what'' city is the capital of some state, we usually mean the geographical concept, don't we? Of course, when talking about the city itself, we switch to the administrative definition, and in a case of a divided city these are two different things. As a compromise we could say that the Vatican's capital is &quot;Vatican's part of Rome&quot;, but isn't it redundant? I'm sorry I don't have any sources backing this idea, but it just seems logical. And let's not forget, the Vatican is the center of the ROMAN Catholicism :) [[Special:Contributions/88.203.176.7|88.203.176.7]] ([[User talk:88.203.176.7|talk]]) 23:05, 22 October 2011 (UTC)
:Vatican City is the seat of government of the Holy See. It should be noted that the Holy See posseses several extra-territorial polities outside of Vatican City and also claims soveriegnty over some minor portions of the former British Mandate of Palestine. Thus i would assume that Vatican City is the capital of the Holy See but that the state of Vatican City itself has no capital.[[User:XavierGreen|XavierGreen]] ([[User talk:XavierGreen|talk]]) 21:16, 21 October 2011 (UTC)
::As I understand it, the Vatican and the Holy See are two different things -- the first one is a political entity (a state), and the second one is a religious institution, so the seat of government of the Vatican cannot be the Holy See. But, as a state, the Vatican does have its seat of government, and it is located in a part of the (geographical) city of Rome. So, if we must say in which city the Vatican's government is located (in other words, what city is its capital), the answer should be Rome in my opinion. [[Special:Contributions/88.203.176.7|88.203.176.7]] ([[User talk:88.203.176.7|talk]]) 23:05, 22 October 2011 (UTC)
::: The usual assumption is that a country is far more extensive than any of its individual cities, towns, lakes, parks or what have you.  That assumption holds true in 99.99% of cases.  But not in this case.  This country has no cities that are in any sense different things from the country itself.  It is its own city, and its own capital city.  There are arrangements and agreements about how the relationship between the city of Rome (and the nation of Italy more generally) and the Vatican City is to be conducted.  None of which makes the city of Rome a part of the Vatican City or vice-versa.  The Vatican City is as separate from Rome as the Sahara Desert is, for the purposes we're talking about.  Imo.  --  [[User:JackofOz|&lt;font face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;Jack of Oz&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:JackofOz#top|&lt;font face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[your turn]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 23:17, 22 October 2011 (UTC)
::::Does making a part of a city foreign territory remove this part from the city ''geographically''? Of course not -- the city remains a single geographical object (although it's ''administratively'' divided). For example, a foreign embassy in London is, technically, a foreign territory -- does this mean the embassy in question is not in London? The same applies to the Vatican -- it is definitely within the (''geographical!!!'') city of Rome, without being part of Italy. This is possible, because Rome itself is a divided city! I never said Rome (as a whole) is part of the Vatican, but the other way round is actually true -- the Vatican is definitely a part of (not the Italian, but the geographical) Rome. Please, read my previous thoughts on the matter as well. [[Special:Contributions/88.203.176.7|88.203.176.7]] ([[User talk:88.203.176.7|talk]]) 21:14, 1 November 2011 (UTC)
:::::Embassies aren't foreign territory, they remain under the ultimate sovereignty of the state they're in. What is a geographical city? [[User:Chipmunkdavis|Chipmunkdavis]] ([[User talk:Chipmunkdavis|talk]]) 00:55, 2 November 2011 (UTC)
::::::A city is a geographical object that will still exist even if the state controlling it disappeared or were replaced by another state. And Rome is a perfect example for this -- it has been a part of many different countries through the centuries. From a purely geographical point of view, Rome is, and has always been, a single city, regardless of the current political/administrative situation. The same was true for other divided cities in the past, like pre-1990 Berlin and pre-1967 Jerusalem -- you don't think West Berlin was a separate city, do you? The correct way of addressing the issue, in my opinion, would be saying that the capital of Italy is the ''Italian part'' of Rome, and the capital (seat of government) of the Vatican is the ''Vatican part'' of Rome. [[Special:Contributions/88.203.176.7|88.203.176.7]] ([[User talk:88.203.176.7|talk]]) 18:53, 21 December 2011 (UTC)
::::::This seems to be a lot of fuss about just nothing.  As if the Vatican City State must necessarily have a &quot;capital city&quot;!  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 14:15, 2 November 2011 (UTC)
:::::::Well, the article says that the Vatican's capital is &quot;Vatican City&quot;, which is definitely not correct -- there is no such city, it's just the ''official name'' of the state. And every sovereign state must have a capital city (the seat of its government), otherwise it's not really sovereign. [[Special:Contributions/88.203.176.7|88.203.176.7]] ([[User talk:88.203.176.7|talk]]) 18:53, 21 December 2011 (UTC)
::::::::Nauru doesn't have an official capital. [[User:Chipmunkdavis|Chipmunkdavis]] ([[User talk:Chipmunkdavis|talk]]) 21:12, 21 December 2011 (UTC)
:::::::: 88.203.176.7, sovereign countries can do whatever they like about their seats of government and all the rest, without it having any implications for their sovereignty.  Your ''&quot;every sovereign state must have a capital city (the seat of its government), otherwise it's not really sovereign&quot;'' is the wildest OR on your part.  
:::::::: The main question here is really a semantic issue.  Is [[Lesotho]] &quot;a part of&quot; [[South Africa]], or is it &quot;within&quot; South Africa?  Is the [[Australian Capital Territory]] &quot;a part of&quot; [[New South Wales]], or is it &quot;within&quot; NSW?  I prefer the latter wording in both cases.  You could say Vatican City is &quot;a part of&quot; Rome but you'd have to qualify that statement by saying it's true only geographically speaking, not administratively speaking.  Because if you don't add that qualification, you're misleading people.  Far better not to go there at all; it's within Rome - simple, concise, accurate, not misleading.  --  [[User:JackofOz|&lt;font face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;Jack of Oz&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:JackofOz#top|&lt;font face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[your turn]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 20:04, 7 January 2012 (UTC)

== Archive Request ==

I think that this talk page needs to start being archived as the length of the page is getting long. So can someone please start archiving this talk page. --[[User:Clarkcj12|Clarkcj12]] ([[User talk:Clarkcj12|talk]]) 21:01, 25 January 2012 (UTC)

:Done. [[User:Scolaire|Scolaire]] ([[User talk:Scolaire|talk]]) 18:26, 3 February 2012 (UTC)

== Protest! ==

Think of &quot;[[Habemus papam]]&quot;! Latin is spoken in Vatican City. --[[Special:Contributions/80.108.185.49|80.108.185.49]] ([[User talk:80.108.185.49|talk]]) 18:57, 3 February 2012 (UTC)
:So is English, and German, and French, and Spanish, and ...  The official documents of the ''state'' are all in Italian.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 20:43, 3 February 2012 (UTC)

== Mafia &quot;boss&quot; was buried along with the Popes ==

Croatian writer Giancarlo Kravar: Italian criminal Enrico De Pedis, killed 1990th the calculation of the mafia, was buried along with some of the Popes in St.  Apollinare`s Basilic. The body of the &quot;boss&quot;, suspected of having links with the masonic lodge P2 and the Vatican Banking was exhumated and he, in consultation with the family, buried in a Roman cemetery. The affair was discovered and resolved at the initiative of the Vatican.[[Special:Contributions/78.2.93.78|78.2.93.78]] ([[User talk:78.2.93.78|talk]]) 18:10, 20 May 2012 (UTC)
:This article is about ''Vatican City State'', not about the Basilica of Saint Apollinare, wherever it is.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 18:39, 20 May 2012 (UTC)

== Wine consumption (under Culture) ==

Previously this article contained a calculation of crime rate in Vatican City in relation to its minute population, which presented a distorted picture of that population.  Now someone has added a calculation of wine consumption in Vatican City in relation to its population.  I think this also gives a false picture.  For one thing, much of the wine is consumed by people having their meals at the [[Domus Sanctae Marthae]].  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 06:50, 14 June 2012 (UTC)
:I don't think so. 59 liter per year makes less than 0,2 liters per day, that is a glass. Considering that the tiny population is made of adults, this is quite low, at least in Italy, where drinking some wine during meals is part of our culture since thousands of years. Moreover, if I can add something personal, each time that I had meals in a monastery, (red) wine was on the table. Anyway, I doubt that this info can be considered as notable and, if yes, I would rephrase it. The agenda behind it is quite obvious. [[User:Alessandro57|Alex2006]] ([[User talk:Alessandro57|talk]]) 07:03, 14 June 2012 (UTC)
==Revert of my edit==
Hi [[User:Chipmunkdavis|Chipmunkdavis]] ([[User talk:Chipmunkdavis|talk]]), my edit was sourced, via Wikipedia (only citing area figure). As for being arbitrary, is there some rule against that? Can't an editor use a self-chosen comparison and point out an interesting fact? [[Disneyland]] is an internationally known tourist destination, and pointing out that fact that the Vatican is smaller than even an amusement park, isn't that useful and interesting? I will revert your revert for now, until I understand your reasoning, and unless discussion among the community agrees with your POV. Thanks. [[User:Mistakefinder|Mistakefinder]] ([[User talk:Mistakefinder|talk]]) 03:53, 18 June 2012 (UTC)
: I removed the comparison between Vatican City and Disneyland, as of [[Wikipedia:Neutral point of view/Examples]] (Geographical bias). As Italian (and Roman), this comparison is meaningless to me, and to all the people who never visited Disneyland. Anyway, I think that an (unbiased, that is not southern Californian centric :-)) hint about the real size of the state could be useful. N.B. for Mistakefinder: a basic rule of Wikipedia is that one cannot use a Wikipedia article  as source/reference for another article. Bye [[User:Alessandro57|Alex2006]] ([[User talk:Alessandro57|talk]]) 05:38, 18 June 2012 (UTC)
::Never source from wikipedia, it's not at all a reliable source ([[WP:CIRCULAR]]). As Alessandro57 says, that comparison will be meaningless to anyone who hasn't gone to disneyland. There's no rule against arbitrary information per se, but there is a sense of when information is Due or Undue. A comparison to an amusement park is undue, as there is no discernable reason why the Vatican should be compared to amusement parks, and no reason at all to pick an individual one. There are tons of things it could be compared to, but individuals can just do that themselves by simply comparing at area figures. [[User:Chipmunkdavis|CMD]] ([[User talk:Chipmunkdavis|talk]]) 14:25, 18 June 2012 (UTC)
:::Correct. Although, reading the news coming from ''oltretevere'' on these days, such a comparison is not totally out of place :-) [[User:Alessandro57|Alex2006]] ([[User talk:Alessandro57|talk]]) 14:29, 18 June 2012 (UTC)
::::How about I just point out, instead of specifically Disneyland, that it's smaller than many theme parks? The point is that it's so small that it's smaller than such entities (theme parks, parks, etc) that are smaller than cities? It is smaller than [[Central Park]] in New York and [[Griffith Park]] in Los Angeles too. I think the the average person does't have a good sense of area size unless we compare it to a place people can relate to, and I know this is true talking to various friends, for example, when I mentioned 20 acres and he had no idea how big that is.  [[User:Alessandro57|Alex2006]], what's ''oltretevere''? Is it the Youtube show about &quot;settimanale di informazione&quot;? [[User:Mistakefinder|Mistakefinder]] ([[User talk:Mistakefinder|talk]]) 18:28, 23 June 2012 (UTC)
:::::We should find an entity which is known to all the mankind, then one could use it in the article. ''Oltretevere'' (&quot;behind the Tiber&quot;) is an Italian synonymous for the Vatican. The reason for it is that most of the center of Rome (with the Italian parliament, the seat of the President, and so on) lies on the left bank of the river, while only the Vatican (and Trastevere, which belongs to Italy and whose name is incidentally a corruption of Transtiberim, which means ''oltretevere'' in Latin) lie of the right bank. [[User:Alessandro57|Alex2006]] ([[User talk:Alessandro57|talk]]) 19:03, 24 June 2012 (UTC)
::::::I don't think it's possible to find an entity known to all of &quot;mankind&quot;. That requires you to survey everyone on earth whether he/she has knowledge of it. Originally I only used Disneyland since I thought it's a world-renowned amusement park (which I doubt many would disagree). Anyway, is the rule of thumb that basically we shouldn't draw a comparison to something else in an article?  I've revised my language to compare with only the city of Rome, and express that it's smaller than many towns, amusement parks, and parks. I'll post that now. Is it then at least appropriate to put the comparison to Disneyland or any specific place in the reference note? [[User:Mistakefinder|Mistakefinder]] ([[User talk:Mistakefinder|talk]]) 01:01, 25 June 2012 (UTC)
As &quot;universally known&quot; I meant an object, as for example a football field (with the appropriate multiplication factor), so that people can have a rough idea of Vatican's area. And please forget this story of Disneyland and amusement parks that, beside being senseless, could also hurt the sensibility of some (over sensible) Catholic. About Disneyland, again, it can be world famous, but here in Europe almost none has an idea about its area. Finally, please read the [[WP:NOR]] guideline. [[User:Alessandro57|Alex2006]] ([[User talk:Alessandro57|talk]]) 12:03, 25 June 2012 (UTC)

:If we can forget about Disneyland comparisons for a minute, I think that Alex2006 observation about Trastevere, right bank, etc. go under &quot;Geography&quot; somewhere with an appropriate reliable citation. But not the other bank! Thanks. [[User:Student7|Student7]] ([[User talk:Student7|talk]]) 23:31, 29 June 2012 (UTC)
::Why? I don't think that Trastevere and Vatican have much in common, besides being placed on the same bank of the river... [[User:Alessandro57|Alex2006]] ([[User talk:Alessandro57|talk]]) 08:14, 2 July 2012 (UTC)
:::One quote was &quot;Oltretevere ('behind the Tiber') is an Italian synonymous for the Vatican.&quot; The other was &quot;only the Vatican .... a corruption of Transtiberim, which means ''oltretevere'' in Latin) lie [on] the right bank.&quot; This seems like geography. Not sure which is which, though. If it is factual it should be under &quot;geography&quot; subsection, with proper citation. [[User:Student7|Student7]] ([[User talk:Student7|talk]]) 22:41, 4 July 2012 (UTC)
::::The remarks about &quot;oltretevere&quot; (beyond, rather than behind, the Tiber) and Trastevere are best forgotten.  &quot;Oltretevere&quot; is a still recent Italian term, almost slang in character, to mean &quot;the Vatican&quot; in all senses, especially in the sense of &quot;Holy See&quot;.  [[Trastevere]] is an official district (&quot;rione&quot;) of Rome situated south and southeast of the [[Borgo (rione of Rome)]], of which Vatican City would be part, if it weren't a separate state.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 06:54, 5 July 2012 (UTC)

I agree 100% about the not notability of the two terms. Just a little remark: &quot;Oltretevere&quot; is not that recent, since it was born with the Italian conquest of Rome in 1870, and became since then a common term in the Italian political literature to denote the Holy See. [[User:Alessandro57|Alex2006]] ([[User talk:Alessandro57|talk]]) 08:40, 5 July 2012 (UTC)
:Exactly.  From a certain perspective, 1870 is &quot;still recent&quot;, even if not simply &quot;recent&quot;.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 19:25, 5 July 2012 (UTC)

== Name ==

The name of The Vatican City State should also be given in Latin. Other language Wikipedia pages do.

[[User:Ybgursey|Ybgursey]] ([[User talk:Ybgursey|talk]]) 09:28, 21 September 2012 (UTC)

The Italian of &quot;Holy See&quot; should also be given.

[[User:Ybgursey|Ybgursey]] ([[User talk:Ybgursey|talk]]) 09:29, 21 September 2012 (UTC)
:Not one law or regulation of Vatican City State has been issued in Latin, so why give in Latin the name of Vatican City State, any more than the name of the Italian state?  Latin can be considered the official language of the Holy See, which publishes official documents in many languages, including Italian, but why choose to give the name in Italian rather than, say, Chinese, or rather than French, which is the official ''diplomatic'' language of the Holy See?  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 07:41, 25 September 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>pugty2rsc91iub5a6mqjpnezo0dl67w</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
