<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Thealogy</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>31445</id>
    <revision>
      <id>495296441</id>
      <parentid>495296041</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-05-31T13:49:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Phoenixred</username>
        <id>14015597</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Wikipedia:WikiProject|WikiProject]] tagging</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13292">{{talkheader}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Feminism|class=start|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Theology|class=start|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=Start|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Neopaganism|class=Start}}
}}
{{Archive banner|state=uncollapsed}}
{{GOCEreviewed}}

__TOC__

== Templates, recent edits ==

I don't see how the issues raised in the templates removed have been settled, so I've restored them. I also don't understand why For the common term, see [[Theology]] was removed. Jackiestud, you were asked not to remove the templates, yet you removed them again with no discussion. Why do you keep acting this way? The para above needs to be dealt with. Eg ''Monotheasm'? some reliable sources for the term? [[User:Dougweller|Dougweller]] ([[User talk:Dougweller|talk]]) 19:10, 23 June 2009 (UTC)

in obvious cases of long unreferenced essays, I suggest you should just remove the offending material rather than tag the article with half a dozen warnings :o) &quot;thealogy&quot; is already a tongue-in-cheek coinage of Bonewits', but &quot;monotheasm&quot; is just all-out dadaism, or should I say dadaasm. --[[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|(𒁳)]]&lt;/small&gt; 08:58, 25 June 2009 (UTC)

I have to delete the comparison with Sophia in the Eastern Orthodox tradition. For one thing, Sophiology does not carry the same weight, and for another it is not a mainstram Orthodox view - Bulgakov, its main proponent in the early 20th century, was asked to let it go.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/194.66.200.1|194.66.200.1]] ([[User talk:194.66.200.1|talk]]) 15:41, 3 November 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==split?==
this article discusses 
*the history ofhte term itself
*[[feminist theology]]
*feminist theology within the [[goddess movement]] in particular.
I find it doubtful whether it should remain a standalone article. 
It could be merged into [[goddess movement]] or else split between [[feminist theology]] and [[goddess movement]]. I do not see any potential for development under this title. It will just remain a problem article indefinitely. --[[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|(𒁳)]]&lt;/small&gt; 09:11, 25 June 2009 (UTC)

:I recommend renaming to &quot;Feminist spirituality&quot; (see my previous comment above), and moving some material over to &quot;Goddess movement&quot;... [[User:AnonMoos|AnonMoos]] ([[User talk:AnonMoos|talk]]) 13:06, 12 December 2009 (UTC)

::By the way, the French article &quot;Théalogie&quot; was removed on Feb. 24th because &quot;Ce néologisme ne rassemble pas suffisamment de sources pour étayer un article encyclopédique&quot;... [[User:AnonMoos|AnonMoos]] ([[User talk:AnonMoos|talk]]) 11:34, 11 April 2010 (UTC)

== merge-proposal response ==

Merging is proposed by a May, 2008, Merge template on the article and discussed on this talk page under [[Talk:Thealogy#split?|split?]]. I oppose.
* It should not be merged into an article on any deity because theology can be polytheistic and thus so can thealogy.
* It should not be merged into an article on feminist spirituality since spirituality includes how one lives life in practical terms (e.g., how one might compromise with one's pure thealogy/theology) and not simply the theory intended behind how one lives.

[[User:Nick Levinson|Nick Levinson]] ([[User talk:Nick Levinson|talk]]) 17:32, 12 July 2010 (UTC)

::I agree with point #1, but disagree with point #2 -- that just means that a feminist spirituality article could cover points other than &quot;thealogy&quot;.  Two terms don't have to have exactly the same denotation for the Wikipedia articles on them to be merged...  In any case the word &quot;thealogy&quot; still pretty much violates ancient Greek word compounding rules, and seems to lack scholarly respectability as compared to some of the alternatives (such as &quot;feminist spirituality&quot;). [[User:AnonMoos|AnonMoos]] ([[User talk:AnonMoos|talk]]) 19:25, 12 July 2010 (UTC)

:::Okay; I've changed my mind on merging into an article titled ''feminist spirituality''. Go ahead, when it's been written.

:::I had assumed a merger proposal implied the existence of the destination article. It turns out, however, that [[feminist spirituality]] is only redirecting, and so is [[feminist spirituality movement]]. So, if you want to write a more wide-ranging article and subsume thealogy within it, making it a nonredirect and [[thealogy]] a redirect, that makes sense.

:::On ancient grammar regulating modern usage: No, definitely no. The grammar police are wrong. Language must be, and is, a tool for communication and thus must fit prospectively-communicating users' needs, and not one ancient Greek is alive today. Were we bound to ancient language rules simply because they exist, then we should be bound to ancient cultural practices generally, absent any distinction as to why one set should bind and the other not. In that case, we should embrace slavery, since it was an ancient practice very much approved by the leaders, elites, and other users of proper language.

:::As to whether scholars respect the word, what matters is whether the word is in use, even as an alternative, and it is. Scholars and you and I are free to choose what words we'll use, and in doing so we're not limited to whether it has been endorsed by scholars. Their choices are sometimes a lagging indicator of acceptance.

:::Best wishes on writing the article. Thanks. [[User:Nick Levinson|Nick Levinson]] ([[User talk:Nick Levinson|talk]]) 01:27, 13 July 2010 (UTC)

== I have updated the posting on thealogy ==

Hello everyone,

Shan, I have added to what you have written here and updated the entry with more recent contributions to the field. I hope you don't mind, but I have clarified or reworded a few sentences as I felt they were confusing and unclear as they were currently written. I have adjusted some of the language to fit the 'neutral' bent of Wikipedia, though I agree with Shan's point, that all knowledge is subjective.

I am hoping that this update post meets the standards set forth by Wikipedia and that these tags can be removed now. I am happpy to revise or update any of what I added and am open to critique on the topic. I tried my best to be as &quot;neutral&quot; as possible and will gladly add more or take out anything that seems questionable. 

I feel I can write in this area because thealogy is my field of expertise. I teach thealogy at the university level, and in one of the few universities where such a course is even offered. Most universities do not offer courses in thealogy, but some courses will touch on it but under the broader discourse of feminist theology.  Ocean Seminary college is I believe the first university to actually offer courses solely in the field of Goddess Thealogy and this is where I teach. I am also the founder and director of the Institute for Thealogy &amp; Deasophy which just formed several months ago in an attempt to expand and legitimate the discourse of thealogy. So I have added some of the material directly from that site and I assure you that this material was all authored by me. 

I look forward to your comments and feedback. 

Angela Hope [[User:Theklabast|Theklabast]] ([[User talk:Theklabast|talk]]) 19:34, 22 August 2010 (UTC)

== Oppose the Merger ==

Hello again,

I forgot to add that I oppose the merger. Feminist spirituality refers to a broad phenomenon which encompasses beliefs, values, practices, modes of praxis and so on. Thealogy on the other hand is a distinctive discourse that focuses simply on the beliefs related to Goddess spirituality. It more accurately falls under the field of Religious Studies. It is not a subfield within feminist spirituality necessarily as not all spiritual feminists do thealogy....some do theology. The distinction is important to make. Some do feminist theology while others partake in feminist thealogy. I think too that thealogy is beginning to develop more and more into its own robust discourse, distinctive from theology rather than as as subfield within theology. More and more thealogians are publishing their work like myself, Patricia Iolana, Paul Reid Bowen, D'vorah Grenn, and Jill Hammer. Carol Christ will be publishing some more thealogical articles in a forthcoming book that I am editing called Thealogies of the Goddess: Dialogues within the Spiritual Feminist Community&quot;. So Goddess feminism is not waning but certainly waxing, and more and more scholars and practitioners are writing in the field of thealogy. Just my two cents. Hope this helps. 

Angela Hope [[User:Theklabast|Theklabast]] ([[User talk:Theklabast|talk]]) 19:44, 22 August 2010 (UTC)



-----
i think we r all part of God because of our souls, and that is insane to include God only within feminine or masculine sphere; GOD has no gender though lets not waste our precious time!!!
So that means whoever physically, emotionally, and intellectually satisfied has GOD in her or him!!!  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/198.53.74.158|198.53.74.158]] ([[User talk:198.53.74.158|talk]]) 11:23, 11 April 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Copy-edit ==

I am currently going through on a copy-edit as part of the March [[WP:GOCE|Guild of Copy Editors Backlog Elimination Drive]] drive. It really does seem though that part of this could be considered original research, or essay-like. Any thoughts? -[[User:Pax85|Pax85]] ([[User talk:Pax85|talk]]) 18:34, 7 March 2011 (UTC)
:I tried what I could, and then placed a tag at the top of this page as a reminder to place the &lt;nowiki&gt;{{copyedit}}&lt;/nowiki&gt; tag once the current issues have been looked over. Any questions, and please contact me! -[[User:Pax85|Pax85]] ([[User talk:Pax85|talk]]) 19:22, 7 March 2011 (UTC)
:: What does [[Gravity Field and Steady-State Ocean Circulation Explorer]] have to do with Goddesses?  Are they hoping to find some? [[User:Biscuittin|Biscuittin]] ([[User talk:Biscuittin|talk]]) 17:49, 18 March 2011 (UTC)
::: Oops. That should be a link to the Guild of Copy Editors. It is corrected now. Thank you. :) -[[User:Pax85|Pax85]] ([[User talk:Pax85|talk]]) 18:33, 18 March 2011 (UTC)

:See my previous comments above and at [[Talk:Thealogy/Archive_1#Inappropriate_past_merger_.28Feminist_spirituality.29]]... [[User:AnonMoos|AnonMoos]] ([[User talk:AnonMoos|talk]]) 18:58, 18 March 2011 (UTC)

== Etymology ==

Could somebody who knows please add something explaining the etymology of the word: why does &quot;theology&quot; imply the study of a masculine God, but &quot;thealogy&quot; imply a female God or a feminist take on theology. Is it Greek? [[User:GrindtXX|GrindtXX]] ([[User talk:GrindtXX|talk]]) 18:54, 9 February 2012 (UTC)

:It's kind of pseudo-Greek, since Classical-language compounding didn't really work that way.  On the other hand, it doesn't violate the rules of Greek any more than &quot;homophobia&quot; also does... [[Image:SFriendly.gif|20px]] -- [[User:AnonMoos|AnonMoos]] ([[User talk:AnonMoos|talk]]) 19:07, 11 February 2012 (UTC)

::Thanks, but I'm still confused. Is it that &quot;theo&quot; means god, but &quot;thea&quot; means goddess? And if so, can you add something to that effect to the article? I'm sure I'm not the only one who'd like to know! [[User:GrindtXX|GrindtXX]] ([[User talk:GrindtXX|talk]]) 21:00, 16 February 2012 (UTC)

:::θεος was &quot;god&quot; and θεα was &quot;goddess&quot;, but the -o- vowel in a word like θεολογια didn't have specifically-masculine reference, and the rules of classical Greek compounding don't really allow an -a- vowel to replace the -o- vowel in that position... [[User:AnonMoos|AnonMoos]] ([[User talk:AnonMoos|talk]]) 02:01, 17 February 2012 (UTC)

These are all great questions, and because this is a new emerging field, and it is very much it's own branch of thealogy, apart from feminist theology, I will try and help answer the questions inlcuded in this talk page.  I will also try and add some of the missing citations.  This may take a few days, so please be patient.  All the best, [[User:LadyAthene|LadyAthene]] ([[User talk:LadyAthene|talk]]) 15:45, 15 April 2012 (UTC)LadyAthene

== Revisions and Corrections Beginning ==

Dear All,
I am currently working on revising this entry per the difficulties mentioned here in the talk page.  I have started with the opening paragraph, and I will revise them and mark them {{copy-edit}} as each section is complete.  As I'm new to this process I hope you'll bear with me as I stumble through it.  Any advice is greatly appreciated.  My knowledge base comes from my doctoral research in literature, theology and the arts, co-founder of the Institute for Thealogy and Deasophy, and my place as one of the emerging contemporary thealogians.  

Peace,
[[User:LadyAthene|LadyAthene]] ([[User talk:LadyAthene|talk]]) 15:59, 16 April 2012 (UTC)LadyAthene


-- the full article has been revised.  There is at least one citation that I could not document.  All other citations have been sorted and an extensive Further Reading list provided.  
Peace [[User:LadyAthene|LadyAthene]] ([[User talk:LadyAthene|talk]]) 20:53, 16 April 2012 (UTC)LadyAthene</text>
      <sha1>ctdey0w9klegs754605iqk4a5pvsxo7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
