<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Religious denomination</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>6873488</id>
    <revision>
      <id>505850261</id>
      <parentid>505850136</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-08-05T04:29:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>66.75.110.26</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* The mention of Hindu denominations is wrong */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9272">{{talk header}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell |1=
 {{WikiProject Christianity|class=stub|importance=high}}
 {{WikiProject Religion}}
}}

==Rewrite==
This article could really use a rewrite in some parts, such as the first sentence: Redundancy like &quot;long-established subgroup&quot; with &quot;existed for many years&quot; just looks bad.  There are several other places with grammar problems or style issues.  --[[User:Cromwellt|Cromwellt]]|[[User talk:Cromwellt|talk]]|[[Special:Contributions/Cromwellt|contribs]] 21:02, 6 September 2006 (UTC)

==&quot;almost no physical hostility&quot;==
Is there ever really any active &quot;hostility&quot; between Lutheran groups, particularly of a physical nature? [[User:Mutt Lunker|Mutt Lunker]] ([[User talk:Mutt Lunker|talk]]) 23:25, 23 December 2007 (UTC)

Physical verses spirital hostility
There may not be physical hostility, how ever there are spiritual hostility called unforgiveness concerning God, self and others with in the Lutheran denominations as well as all denominations. The message of Grace is a message of forgiveness. Forgiveness is the true application of love. The atributes of forgiveness are the fruits of the spirit. All denominations in the Christian faith believe in grace, but few truly understand and apply grace. God wishes grace not justice. Not judging  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/204.11.86.25|204.11.86.25]] ([[User talk:204.11.86.25|talk]]) 05:12, 2 April 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Population statistics ==

Can we have some numbers, perhaps a piechart showing the precentages of the denominations? [[User:Faro0485|Faro0485]] ([[User talk:Faro0485|talk]]) 06:20, 17 April 2009 (UTC)

==  Multi-denominational ==

While editing another article that described a significant Multi-denominational religious service, I attempted to wikilink it but it was redirected to a for-profit organization. I changed the redirect to Religious denomination. I then added a section describing multi-denominational to satisfy my need to define it to support the article I was originally working with so it meets my needs at the moment.

However, due to my lifetime of work with the US Military, I know that my poor attempt at defining it and describing the concept will never do the concept justice. Perhaps someone much more expert then I can improve that section beyond what I could hope to do.  I asked for assistance on the [[Chaplain]]'s article talk page as well.  Sincerely, [[User:Veriss1|Veriss]] ([[User talk:Veriss1|talk]]) 22:05, 18 October 2010 (UTC)


==Definition requires to be more specific==

Current:
A religious denomination is a subgroup within a religion that operates under a common name, tradition, and identity.


Proposed:
A religious denomination is a ''counterfeit version'' of an original religion that has broken away from it's root and continues on to operate under cover of the common name of the founding religion, usually having a ''form'' of it's tradition and identity but not the original. [see schism] LET TRUTH PREVAIL!!! TROLLING IS FUN!!!09:37, 17 January 2011 (UTC)

:'''Oppose''': The phrases ''&quot;counterfeit version&quot;'' and ''&quot;operate under cover&quot;'' appear to be very POV (Point of View) as they carry with them an impression that the flavor of the religion in question is somehow illegal or illegitimate.  That claim may be recognized in some discussions boards and forums but here it would require a very well sourced and neutrally written section explaining the why's and wherefores.  I believe that the current definition is both accurate and non-point of view.  Wikipedia is not a place for crusades but is a place for people to work together to share knowledge.  Please keep that in mind and please share your knowledge with us.  Cheers!  [[User:Veriss1|Veriss]] ([[User talk:Veriss1|talk]]) 09:46, 21 January 2011 (UTC)

To: Veriss1: A denomination is a piece that has broken away from the original, not POV but fact. If it waddles and quacks and has a bill, It's safe to say it's a duck. If it's offended that someone calls it a duck does and exclaims POV! does that change the fact? LOL! :) LET ACCURACY PREVAIL!!! TROLLING IS FUN!!!10:36, 21 January 2011 (UTC)

:'''Still Oppose:''' I still feel that the phrases &quot;counterfeit version&quot; and &quot;operate under cover&quot; appear to be very POV (Point of View) as they carry with them an impression that the flavor of the religion in question is somehow illegal or illegitimate in the eyes of some presumably authoritative group. Your response did not address that nor the issue that labeling these breakaway groups in such a manner would be POV in the eyes of many readers.  Which group is authorized to make these pronouncements and determinations that they are &quot;counterfeit&quot; and operating under cover?  I am a lapsed Catholic so don't have a dog in the protestant denomination issue but I do want everyone to have a level playing field.  What issue are you trying to rectify?  Cheers!  [[User:Veriss1|Veriss]] ([[User talk:Veriss1|talk]]) 04:34, 4 March 2011 (UTC)

==At least clean the definition==

PART 1) &quot;A religious denomination is a subgroup within a religion.&quot;  &lt;--fact

(I would like to use the word &quot;division&quot; because that's what a subgroup is and the word is a more clear and accurate term to use. IMO.)

PART 2) &quot;that operates under a common name, tradition, and identity.&quot; &lt;---speculation/not fact.

That's why they are denominations, because they do not operate the same tradition and have different identifiers which usually call for a difference in name or title it's also why billions of people have died fighting because of difference. Just invite a baptist to mass or a Pentecostal to a mosque and see. Because Islam stems from the same book Christianity does but it is considered a different religion and they even believe in Jesus. So. Part 2 is erroneous. FACT. Not POV.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Wkdemers|Wkdemers]] ([[User talk:Wkdemers|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Wkdemers|contribs]]) 10:36, 21 January 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Bring some references to the discussion please.  [[User:Veriss1|Veriss]] ([[User talk:Veriss1|talk]]) 04:36, 4 March 2011 (UTC)

== misleading map ==

The map used on this page is misleading.  The United Kingdom, where Catholics represented ~9 percent of the population, is striped for mixed Catholic/Protestant, while the United States, where ~22 percent of the population is Catholic is shaded only as Protestant.  I don't have the tools to edit a map like this, but at least one of these countries ought to be changed, and I think 22 percent of the population ought to be enough for the U.S. to be classified as mixed.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/128.135.189.179|128.135.189.179]] ([[User talk:128.135.189.179|talk]]) 17:03, 3 January 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:In addition, some African countries are described as being predominantly of &quot;nature religions&quot; when in fact the largest faith is Christianity.  Catholicism is the largest faith of Benin and Togo, and Protestantism the largest of Liberia.  Christians, collectively, form majorities in Madagascar and Central African Republic, although it's possible that individual denominations do not outnumber animists. [[Special:Contributions/12.239.145.114|12.239.145.114]] ([[User talk:12.239.145.114|talk]])  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|undated]] comment added 19:15, 26 May 2012 (UTC).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!--Template:Undated--&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== The mention of Hindu denominations is wrong ==

The article states:

&quot;In Hinduism, the major deity or philosophical belief identifies a denomination, which also typically has distinct cultural and religious practices. The major denominations include [[Shaivism]], [[Shaktism]], [[Vaishnavism]] and [[Smartism]]&quot;

That's not the same as Christian or Jewish or Muslim denominations. Hinduism is an [[umbrella term]] which many religions fall under, it is not a religion itself. The so-called denominations mentioned above, are in fact different religions. Similar to how Islam, Judaism and Christianity are all based off of the same religious tradition of Abraham----Vaishnavism, Shaivism, etc, also share common roots in the Vedas, but they're not different denominations of a single religion like Methodist or Baptist, Shia or Sunni, etc. '''they worship different Gods.''' In Hinduism a denomination of a religion is called a [[sampradaya]], e.g. some well known Vaishnava denominations include the [[Sri Sampradaya]], the [[Brahma sampradaya]], and the [[Vallabha Sampradaya]].

Others have complained about this at the talk for [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Hindu_denominations#Title_of_the_article the wikipedia article on Hindu denomination].


[[Special:Contributions/66.75.110.26|66.75.110.26]] ([[User talk:66.75.110.26|talk]]) 04:18, 5 August 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>ax7ul7pjp0sdefjr00drjq2eni6ezvi</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
