<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Isaac</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2244435</id>
    <revision>
      <id>515929349</id>
      <parentid>515867427</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-04T09:13:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dougweller</username>
        <id>1304678</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Enhance the Article */ format and reply, thanks</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="36386">{{ArticleHistory|action1=PR
|action1date=07:44, 13 March 2007
|action1link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Isaac/archive1
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=114748890

|action2=GAN
|action2date=08:18, 13 March 2007
|action2result=listed
|action2oldid=114753110

|action3=GAR
|action3link =Talk:Isaac/GA1
|action3date=26 May 2009
|action3result=kept
|action3oldid=292079683

|currentstatus=GA
|topic=Philrelig
}}

{{WikiProjectBannerShell|collapsed=yes|1=
{{WikiProject Bible|class=GA|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=GA|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Christianity|class=GA|importance=High|saints=yes|saints-importance=High|needs-infobox=yes}}
{{WikiProject Judaism| class= GA | importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Islam|Prophets-of-Islam=yes|class=GA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Biography
|living=no
|class=GA
|listas=Isaac
}}
}}

==Merge==
The page should not be merged Jews and Muslims dispute the importance of Isaac / Ishaq. Due to inaccuracy in the writing of the later works Ishmael is seen to have been sacrificed to instead of Ishaq. This dispute may offend people of either faith if combined together.

Should the base article just be about Isaac the biblical personage and the rest of the material moved to a disambiguation page? A lot of it is not relevant to the main article. [[User:FeanorStar7]]

I would beg to differ.  Everything mentioned about Isaac is relevant.  It is the biblical personage that makes him who he is.  Without that, why would we look for him in the encyclopedia anyway?  AMEN BROTHER

The section &quot;Isaac in Qu'ran&quot; is the same as the section on [[Isaac]]. Maybe merging + adding the prophet template on Isaac? The same is done by [[Ishmael]]) &lt;br/&gt;
[[User:Blubberbrein2|Blubberbrein2]] 09:32, 16 March 2006 (UTC)
: I second this, since it is the same person (just a different perspective). BTW, I think you mean [[Ishaq]] (not [[Isaac]]) should be merged with this article. --Benjamin, 200606011340
&lt;br/&gt;
If you have a page for [[Ishaq]], you ought to have one Yitzak, the Hebrew patriach. Better to have one page to explain the scriptural entity as interpreted by the three faiths of The Book.
:I agree with the merge. What made my mind up on this is when I noticed that [[Isaac]] has a link to the Arabic Wikipedia but Ishaq doesn't. (On the other hand, Arabic is all Greek to me, so I can't comment on whether or not the Arabic Wikipedia makes any distinctions between the two variants of the name). [[User:Robert Happelberg|Robert Happelberg]] 21:59, 27 June 2006 (UTC)

== Yeah... ==

They should merge the sections, especially because Isaac is often considered the least important of the Patriarchs and needs more info from the Ishaq article.
-This statement is not accurate, these Patriachs are equal in importance.


Yes I think they should be merged and also ishaq should be written as &quot;is'haq&quot; to avoid mispronounciation of &quot;sh&quot;


I do not believe they should be merged. Though physically it talks of the same character the content about what each religion is based off is totally different which changes the role of Isaac.

It's the same person: bottom line.  Creating a different page for the Arabic name for the same person is just a way of oh-so-subtly saying that Muslims don't really know what they're talking about.  One page, with differing accounts given in historical order... just like the real world!  Imagine! &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/70.175.21.20|70.175.21.20]] ([[User talk:70.175.21.20|talk]]) 17:22, September 13, 2006 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;

:Yes, except that the Ishaq page was created by Muslims. Are they saying that the rest of us don't know what we're talking about? I'm not willing to say that... --[[user:Eliyak|Eliyak]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Eliyak|T]]&lt;/small&gt;·&lt;small&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Eliyak|C]]&lt;/small&gt; 17:58, 13 September 2006 (UTC)

There is nothing to worry about.This will not change anything.

Yes they should merge the documents but they should make two separate catagories for biblical and Quranic interpretation of Isaac's life. What do you think?

Yep, that's the most reasonable option. It should be formatted like [[Ishmael]]. Keeps it consistent and NPOV etcetera etcetera

== What? ==

&quot;Three explanations for Isaac's name are given: the first is that his mother Sarai(Sarah) laughed when told by God that she would have a son in her old age (Genesis 17:16-17); in the second, it is Sarah who laughs (Genesis 18:10-12)&quot;  She's the one who laughs both times?

== 2 contradicting definitions, only 1 truth ==

Sorry to say but 1/2 of the article is inaccurate. &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[Special:Contributions/67.81.105.212|67.81.105.212]] ([[User talk:67.81.105.212|talk]]) 07:29, 16 January 2007 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;

== Secondary sources ==

Do we need to use secondary sources for the &quot;Isaac in the Hebrew Bible&quot; section? --[[User:Aminz|Aminz]] 10:08, 23 February 2007 (UTC)

== Meaning ==
In a secondary source, I found the following statement: &quot; Stories about Issac appear in Genesis 17-28. Although they are largely to be ascribed to J, P is represented at the beginning (17:15-27) and end (27:46-28:9), and E in 21:1-7 and 22:1-19 (-&gt; Pentateuch).&quot;

I was wondering what does J,P, and E mean? --[[User:Aminz|Aminz]] 07:53, 1 March 2007 (UTC)

:I do not know a lot about it, but we have an article about it at [[Documentary hypothesis]]. [[User:Tom harrison|Tom Harrison]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Tom harrison|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 14:48, 1 March 2007 (UTC)
:: Thanks very much. --[[User:Aminz|Aminz]] 21:33, 1 March 2007 (UTC)

== Passed &quot;Good article&quot; ==
:'''[[Wikipedia:Good article nominations|GA]] review''' (see [[Wikipedia:What is a good article?|here]] for criteria)
#It is '''reasonably well written'''.
#:a ''(prose)'': {{GAList/check|???}} b ''([[Wikipedia:Manual of Style|MoS]])'': {{GAList/check|aye}}
#It is '''factually accurate''' and '''[[Wikipedia:Verifiability|verifiable]]'''.
#:a ''(references)'': {{GAList/check|aye}} b ''(citations to reliable sources)'': {{GAList/check|aye}} c ''([[Wikipedia:No original research|OR]])'': {{GAList/check|aye}}
#It is '''broad in its coverage'''.
#:a ''(major aspects)'': {{GAList/check|aye}} b ''(focused)'': {{GAList/check|aye}}
#It follows the '''[[WP:NPOV|neutral point of view]] policy'''.
#:a ''(fair representation)'': {{GAList/check|aye}} b ''(all significant views)'': {{GAList/check|aye}}
#It is '''stable'''.
#:{{GAList/check|aye}}
#It '''contains [[Wikipedia:Images|images]]''', where possible, to illustrate the topic.
#:a ''(tagged and captioned)'': {{GAList/check|???}} b ''lack of images (does not in itself exclude GA)'': {{GAList/check|aye}} c ''(non-free images have [[Wikipedia:Image_description_page#Use_rationale|fair use rationales]])'': {{GAList/check|aye}}
#'''Overall''':
#:a ''Pass/Fail'': {{GAList/check|aye}}
An overall well-written article. I am impressed at how the citations give this article reliability (most religion-related articles tend to be filled with NPOV). For future development of this article, I have a few suggestions: 1) check the grammar and typos; 2) include more images, especially in the sections near the end. Other than that, I have nothing to say. [[User:King of Hearts|King of]] [[User:King of Hearts|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;&amp;hearts;&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:King of Hearts|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;&amp;diams;&lt;/font&gt;]] [[Special:Contributions/King of Hearts|&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;&amp;clubs;&lt;/font&gt;]] [[Special:Emailuser/King of Hearts|&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;&amp;spades;&lt;/font&gt;]] 01:16, 14 March 2007 (UTC)
:I have a little to say. The use of the copyrighted image Robert B. Sherman &quot;Sacrifice&quot; [Image:Sacrifice 600.JPG] seems to be a violation of the type cited at [[Wikipedia:Non-free content#Examples of unacceptable use]]. It is a non-notable, non-iconic, copyrighted image used illustrate an article. That image also seems to have an incorrect tag (it is not an &quot;'''poster for an event'''&quot; used &quot;'''to illustrate the event in question'''&quot;). I have removed the image from the article for these reasons. [[User:69.72.2.72|69.72.2.72]] 21:25, 23 April 2007 (UTC)

I believe this page is incorrectly named and should be moved to [[Isaac (biblical character)]] or something of the sort.  This page is more appropriately along the lines of [[Matthew]] or [[Andrew]].  Andrew McNaughton, 8:54, May 6 2007 (AEST).

==Isaac and the paternity of Abraham==

The paternity of Abraham for Isaac is not sure. (Cf.[http://www.geocities.com/isaac.paradox Isaac paradox]). [[User:Isaacsonornot|Isaacsonornot]] 13:58, 15 May 2007 (UTC).

==bible verses==
The bible verses should be applied with the {{tl|bibleverse}} template.--[[User:Sefringle|Sefringle]] 23:38, 20 May 2007 (UTC)

==Note 28==
Note 28 says, &quot;(see also Qur'an 38:45 and Qur'an '''29:27-26''')&quot;. Question is: How can a quote be from one verse to an earlier one? [[Special:Contributions/90.230.233.43|90.230.233.43]] ([[User talk:90.230.233.43|talk]]) 12:42, 18 March 2008 (UTC)

== common misspellings ==

My name is Isaac and it seems as though most people spell it Issac almost instinctively. Any idea if this alternative spelling is very common? &amp;mdash;''[[User:Memotype|Memotype]]''::&lt;small&gt;'''[[User talk:Memotype|T]]'''&lt;/small&gt; 22:09, 17 November 2008 (UTC)

==GA Reassessment==
I have submitted this article to a GA Reassessment as part of the GA Sweeps project.  I found the article to not meet GA criteria and I held it for further work.  Thanks to the diligence of several editors the article has been brought back to GA quality and I will be happy to keep it as GA.  Click [[Talk:Isaac/GA1|here]] for my review.  Thank you to the editors who took on the article's fixes.  [[User:H1nkles|H1nkles]] ([[User talk:H1nkles|talk]]) 16:31, 26 May 2009 (UTC)

{{Talk:Isaac/GA1}}


==Etymology==
The recent rewriting of the 'etymology' section is imo not an improvement to the article and I reverted it&lt;br&gt;
(@PiCo: Firstly, I apologize if my edit summary appeared to accuse you of non-good faith editing, that was not my intent.)

I think the previous version was better for the following reasons:
:* The new version uses &quot;purportedly&quot; (see [[Wikipedia:Words_to_avoid#So-called.2C_supposed.2C_purported.2C_alleged]]). The previous version ascribed this explanation to &quot;Genesis&quot; and &quot;the biblical narrative&quot;, which is more neutral and more informative.
:* The new version rejects this explanation and says that &lt;i&gt;in fact&lt;/i&gt;, it is a Canaanite name derived from the god El. This is unencyclopedic for three reasons.
::* First, that it claims to 'know for a fact' where the word came from, which is nearly always a dubious claim when dealing with etymological history, especially of ancient languages.
::* Second, because the word &quot;El&quot; is not always a name, according to the Wikipedia article on [[El_(God)]]:
:::&quot;In Northwest Semitic usage ʾl was both a generic word for any &quot;god&quot; and the special name or title of a particular god who was distinguished from other gods as being &quot;the god&quot;, or in the monotheistic sense, God.&quot;
::* And thirdly, because the name &quot;Yiṣḥāq&quot; does not even include the name &quot;El&quot;, so first saying that it is short for &quot;Yitzhakel&quot;, and then claiming that it was derived from the name &quot;El&quot; seems to me not a very solid argument, and it certainly does not warrant the claim that this is &quot;in fact&quot; so.
Therefore, I reverted the change, however, if the terms &quot;purportedly&quot; and &quot;in fact&quot; are replaced and the varying views are ascribed to adequate sources (as was the case in the original version), the  new version would also be acceptable to me. [[User:Lindert|Lindert]] ([[User talk:Lindert|talk]]) 16:31, 1 June 2009 (UTC)

:Thank you for your courteous explanation. The word &quot;purportedly&quot; was in the original source, which is Avner Falk, an Israeli psychologist/historian (meaning he writes biographies and histories from the point of view of the psychology of his subject - in this particular book he was ambitiously attempting to analyse the &quot;Jewish psychology&quot; - I'm not sure such a thing exists). But for the derivation of Yitzakhel, Falk's own source is William F. Albright, who is a leading scholar and cannot be lightly dismissed. It is Albraight who traces Yitzakh to Yitzhakel, on the basis that the name Yitzakh by itself is not the normal form of any name of the time, while a name in the form of a theophoric is quite normal, and the -el theophoric is attested. As for El being the name of a specific god, Albright more or less takes for granted that there's no point in a theophoric that doesn't relate to a specific god - this was what I meant by saying that El is always a name - it's always a name when used in a theophoric. (I'd be quite happy to drop the &quot;purportedly&quot; - although I doubt that the bible is in fact attempting an atymolygy, as paronomasia rarely included true etymology at that time). [[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 01:13, 2 June 2009 (UTC)

== &quot;Only son&quot; ==

I keep correcting the statement that Isaac was &quot;the only son&quot; of Abraham, only to have it reverted and even to be labeled as vandalism. However, the Bible lists other sons of Abraham - [[Ishmael]], [[Zimran]], [[Jokshan]], [[Medan (son of Abraham)|Medan]], [[Midian]], [[Ishbak]] and[[Shuah]]. I note that the bible repeatedly describes Isaac as &quot;the only son&quot;, but the meaning and reason for the description is subject to speculation which is not covered in the article. There is no reason why the description needs to repeated in this article on a factual point.[[User:Ewawer|Ewawer]] ([[User talk:Ewawer|talk]]) 22:54, 7 November 2009 (UTC)
:First of all, your edits certainly were not vandalism and should not have been labeled as such.
:That being said, you are right that Abraham had more sons in addition to Isaac, but the original wording of the article: &quot;the only child of [[Abraham]] and [[Sarah]]&quot; was intended (I think) to mean that Isaac was the only son of Abraham that was born to Sarah. In my opinion the original version was clear enough, but apparently it can cause confusion. I will change it to &quot;the only son [[Abraham]] had with his wife [[Sarah]]&quot;. This retains the information that Abraham had no other sons with Sarah. If you know of a better expression feel free to improve on this. [[User:Lindert|Lindert]] ([[User talk:Lindert|talk]]) 10:25, 9 November 2009 (UTC)

== Slightly unclear statement ==

&quot;According to the Book of Genesis, Abraham was 100 years old when Isaac was born, and Sarah was beyond childbearing years.&quot;

As written, this sounds as if the Book of Genesis specifically says she was beyond childbearing years, which seems kind of odd (a blatant contradiction in fact) if it also says she had a child at that age. Is the sentence actually trying to say that her alleged age, according to the Bible, was beyond the age at which women are nowadays known to be capable of bearing children? (In other words, her Biblical age was incorrect, exaggerated, not meant to be taken literally, etc.)

Could the sentence be clarified?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/81.129.130.64|81.129.130.64]] ([[User talk:81.129.130.64|talk]]) 14:55, 17 November 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:The sentence is based solely on the biblical story. The apparent 'contradiction' is intentional in Genesis. Genesis states that 'it ceased to be with Sarah after the manner of women.', which is commonly understood to mean that her menstrual cycle had ceased. That she nonetheless bore a child (at age 90) is therefore considered (by the author of Genesis) to be a miracle. [[User:Lindert|Lindert]] ([[User talk:Lindert|talk]]) 21:51, 17 November 2009 (UTC)

== Isaac's sacrifice in Islam ==
I have edited this article I dont think there is anything to say because the sources for that was the Quran and the verses of the Quran are mentioned in the edited article and Ive also kept a conclusion and literal proof for the editings I have made

One thing I deleted was the theory that some Muslim scholars say that Isaac and Jacob were both promised for Sarah so this means Ishmael was sacrificed. This Beleif and theory is false! because never does the Quran say in Arabic so? the verses that talk about Isaac and Jacob in arabic states that &quot;we gave her the good news of Isaac and after Isaac Jacob&quot; but what many english speakers don't know is that in Arabic grammer the letter BA was kept beside Isaac's name. the letter BA is a letter kept when someone wants to use the word 'with&quot; so the Quran said we gave her glad tidings with Isaac by using the letter BA but however after that the Quran clearly says and after him we gave good news of Jacob but it doesnt use the letter BA the letter BA was only used with Isaac meaning that the angels came to talk about Isaac but after Isaac grew and the sacrifice occured god told Abraham about the birth of Jacob because the style of the Quran tends to talk about something and then states the future act .. the Quran clearly says that the three angels only gave news of Isaac in many verses i mentioned in the article and there is no verse talking about Jacob and the three angels except this one and like i mentioned earlier this verse used the letter BA to say with &quot;we gave her glad tidings with Isaac'&quot; BUT IT DOESNT USE THE LETTER BA WITH JACOB so clearly this verse talks about Isaac and then states the future of when Jacob was born long after Isaac grew with his father TO WALK AND WORK .. nowhere in Islamic tradition or the Quran it states that Jacob had a relation with the tidings of Isaac.. so this is another proof as well as I MYSELF HAVE EDITED THE ARTICLE AND CLEARY MADE THE STORY CLEAR SO A READER WOULD DEFINATLY UNDERSTAND MY POINT WITHOUT HAVING A LOOK AT THIS TALK PAGE... there are many things i didnt mention AS PROVE OF THE BINDING OF ISAAC IN ISLAM  like the birth of Isaac give to Abraham when Abraham left his people or when abraham was ordered to sacrifice the un-named son who grew up with him and was given to him miraculously and clearly every knows that Ishmael was taken away from Abraham when he was just a baby nor did Ishmael have a miraculous birth nor did he live with his father to work and walk ....the quranic verse are kept in the article! ... Il put some here to make it easier to see



037.083
YUSUFALI: Verily among those who followed his Way was Abraham.

037.084
YUSUFALI: Behold! he approached his Lord with a sound heart.

037.085
YUSUFALI: Behold! he said to his father and to his people, &quot;What is that which ye worship?

037.086
YUSUFALI: &quot;Is it a falsehood- gods other than Allah- that ye desire?


037.087
YUSUFALI: &quot;Then what is your idea about the Lord of the worlds?&quot;

037.088
YUSUFALI: Then did he cast a glance at the Stars.


037.089
YUSUFALI: And he said, &quot;I am indeed sick (at heart)!&quot;

037.090
YUSUFALI: So they turned away from him, and departed.

037.091
YUSUFALI: Then did he turn to their gods and said, &quot;will ye not eat (of the offerings before you)?...

037.092
YUSUFALI: &quot;What is the matter with you that ye speak not (intelligently)?&quot;

037.093
YUSUFALI: Then did he turn upon them, striking (them) with the right hand.

037.094
YUSUFALI: Then came (the worshippers) with hurried steps, and faced (him).

037.095
YUSUFALI: He said: &quot;Worship ye that which ye have (yourselves) carved?

037.096
YUSUFALI: &quot;But Allah has created you and your handwork!&quot;

037.097
YUSUFALI: They said, &quot;Build him a furnace, and throw him into the blazing fire!&quot;


037.098
YUSUFALI: (This failing), they then sought a stratagem against him, but We made them the ones most humiliated!


037.099
YUSUFALI: He said: &quot;I will go to my Lord! He will surely guide me!

037.100
YUSUFALI: &quot;O my Lord! Grant me a righteous (son)!&quot;


037.101
YUSUFALI: So We gave him the good news of a boy ready to suffer and forbear.

037.102
YUSUFALI: And when (his son) was old enough to walk with him, (Abraham) said: O my dear son, I have seen in a dream that I must sacrifice thee. So look, what thinkest thou? He said: O my father! Do that which thou art commanded. Allah willing, thou shalt find me of the steadfast

037.103
YUSUFALI: So when they had both submitted their wills (to Allah), and he had laid him prostrate on his forehead (for sacrifice),

037.104
YUSUFALI: We called out to him &quot;O Abraham!

037.105
YUSUFALI: &quot;Thou hast already fulfilled the vision!&quot; - thus indeed do We reward those who do right.

037.106
YUSUFALI: For this was obviously a trial-

037.107
YUSUFALI: And We ransomed him with a momentous sacrifice:

037.108
YUSUFALI: And We left (this blessing) for him among generations (to come) in later times:

037.109
YUSUFALI: &quot;Peace and salutation to Abraham!&quot;


037.110
YUSUFALI: Thus indeed do We reward those who do right.

037.111
YUSUFALI: For he was one of our believing Servants.


This verse says the WHOLE STORY ... a son was given to Abraham after Abraham left his pagan people and THIS SON WAS UN NAMED BUT WHAT THE READER CAN TAKE AS A CLUE IS THAT  THE UN-NAMED SON WAS A CHILD GIVEN TO ABRAHAM AFTER HE LEFT HIS PAGAN PEOPLE





019.041
YUSUFALI: (Also mention in the Book (the story of) Abraham: He was a man of Truth, a prophet.

019.042
YUSUFALI: Behold, he said to his father: &quot;O my father! why worship that which heareth not and seeth not, and can profit thee nothing?

019.043
YUSUFALI: &quot;O my father! to me hath come knowledge which hath not reached thee: so follow me: I will guide thee to a way that is even and straight.


019.044
YUSUFALI: &quot;O my father! serve not Satan: for Satan is a rebel against (Allah) Most Gracious.

019.045
YUSUFALI: &quot;O my father! I fear lest a Penalty afflict thee from (Allah) Most Gracious, so that thou become to Satan a friend.&quot;

019.046
YUSUFALI: (The father) replied: &quot;Dost thou hate my gods, O Abraham? If thou forbear not, I will indeed stone thee: Now get away from me for a good long while!&quot;

019.047
YUSUFALI: Abraham said: &quot;Peace be on thee: I will pray to my Lord for thy forgiveness: for He is to me Most Gracious.


LOOK AT THIS



019.048
YUSUFALI: &quot;And I will TURN away from YOU (ALL) and from those whom ye invoke besides Allah: I will call on my Lord: perhaps, by my prayer to my Lord, I shall be not unblest.&quot;

019.049
YUSUFALI: When he had TURNED away from THEM and from those whom they worshipped besides Allah, We bestowed on him Isaac and Jacob, and each one of them We made a prophet.

these verses talk about ISAAC GIVEN TO ABRAHAM WHEN ABRAHAM LEFT HIS PAGAN PEOPLE SO THIS PROVES THAT THE UN-NAMED SACRIFICED SON WAS ISAAC BECAUSE THE EARLIER VERSE THAT MENTIONS THE SACRIFICE SAYS ABRAHAM WAS GIVEN A UN-NAMED SON ....... WHO WAS GIVEN TO HIM RIGHT AFTER HE LEFT HIS PAGAN PEOPLE AND  LIKE I SAID .. THESE VERSES CLEARLY MENTIONS ISAAC BY NAME AS THE UN-NAMED SON WHO WAS GIVEN TO ABRAHAM WHEN HE LEFT HIS PAGAN PEOPLE.. so the conclsion is ... Isaac was binded  :)

ps. please do mind my grammer and rush in this talk page    thank you! [[Special:Contributions/84.255.149.155|84.255.149.155]] ([[User talk:84.255.149.155|talk]]) 13:30, 11 February 2010 (UTC)

== etymology ==

I removed the sentence &quot;''The term conforms to an established [[Northwest Semitic]] linguist type, but is not spoken elsewhere''&quot; from the etymology section, since I could not hazard a guess as to what it is intended to mean. I also wonder about the fact that the etymology section refers to &quot;{{Unicode|Yiṣḥāq}}'' which literally means &quot;may God smile''&quot;, but the lede says, &quot;''Hebrew: יִצְחָק,  Modern ''Yitzchaq''  Tiberian ''Yiṣḥāq'', 'he will laugh'&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;''&quot;. Is there a morpheme in ''Yiṣḥāq'' which means &quot;God&quot;?&amp;mdash;[[User:Greg Pandatshang|Greg Pandatshang]] ([[User talk:Greg Pandatshang|talk]]) 03:28, 12 February 2010 (UTC)

==source==
Iam not interpreting anything ,. Il make it simple and plain with my source the Quran

019.048
YUSUFALI: &quot;And I will TURN AWAY from you (all) and from those whom ye invoke besides Allah: I will call on my Lord: perhaps, by my prayer to my Lord, I shall be not unblest.&quot;

019.049
YUSUFALI: When he had TURNED AWAY from them and from those whom they worshipped besides Allah, WE bestowed on him Isaac and Jacob, and each one of them We made a prophet

... same story mentioned in detail here
037.099
YUSUFALI: He said: &quot;I will GO to my Lord! He will surely guide me!

037.101
YUSUFALI: So WE gave him the good news of a boy ready to suffer and forbear.

037.102
YUSUFALI: And when (his son) was old enough to walk with him, (Abraham) said: O my dear son, I have seen in a dream that I must sacrifice thee. So look, what thinkest thou? He said: O my father! Do that which thou art commanded. Allah willing, thou shalt find me of the steadfast
focus on the caps lock words to prove the Quran speaking for itself no interpretation no noting

 according to Islamic tradition and sahih hadith Ishmael was a baby when Abraham left him
with his mother and the next time he saw his son was when his son was old anf GREW WITH HIS MOTHER
  ....the story is mentioned in wiki iam not gonna add more[[Special:Contributions/82.194.62.25|82.194.62.25]] ([[User talk:82.194.62.25|talk]]) 18:07, 13 March 2010 (UTC)

:Highdeeboy, how many times do we have to explain to you that exegesis does not meet the standards for [[WP:RS|sources]]?  How many times do we have to explain to you that just mentioning that secondary sources exist is not enough, that you have to provide them?  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 19:36, 13 March 2010 (UTC)



My bad lol listen iam gonna make things sweet! I GOT THE PROVE OF PROOFS AND IT WILL MAKE U CHANGE ALL THE ARTICLES U HAD PROBLEMS WITH ME ;) UL SEE HEHEH

now look at that and read it this is the secondry source that Proves ISAAC IS THE SON! because the cousin of prophet Mohammed narrated the whole incident stating ISHMAEL WAS LEFT IN MECCA WHEN HE WAS SUCKLING HIS MOTHER'S!

see for yourself

HERE IS MY SECONDARY SOURCE ;)

http://www.sacred-texts.com/isl/bukhari/bh4/bh4_586.htm [[Special:Contributions/82.194.62.25|82.194.62.25]] ([[User talk:82.194.62.25|talk]]) 19:54, 13 March 2010 (UTC)

you know what!  IVE HAD IT WITH U

IAM TALKING TO ANOTHER USER ABOUT THIS BECAUSE U ARE SICK! leave me alone and dont u dare stalk me ..!  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/82.194.62.25|82.194.62.25]] ([[User talk:82.194.62.25|talk]]) 19:59, 13 March 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:That source says nothing about the attempted sacrifice, and it says nothing about Ishmael never seeing Abraham ever again. It actually says that Abraham and Ishmael did met again, and went to the Ka'ba. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 20:08, 13 March 2010 (UTC)

::Note that the IP is a sock puppet of the blocked editor {{user|Highdeeboy}}, IP now blocked (not by me) for 3 days. [[User:Dougweller|Dougweller]] ([[User talk:Dougweller|talk]]) 21:52, 13 March 2010 (UTC)

=my response=

No.1 :Id really appreciate it if the editors can remove all what Ive written before because it seems to confuse people
No.2 Yes what u say is true but when did he meet him .. The Quran states Ishmael met his father and built the kaaba .. is that something u say about a kid? .. no clearly its common sense we dont need to wonder .. Abraham returned to Mecca again when Ishmael was old and strong enough to build the Kaaba   but wait a sec

the Quran states the unknown son who was to be sacrificed GREW ALONGSIDE HIS FATHER?  was it Ishmael NO! because Ishmael only saw his father when he was an adult and after he had grown alongside his mother Hagar .. and u admitted it earlier .. so clearly it Isaac and there are tons or proofs and sources of it being Isaac but u continue to argue with me and use your status to block me so please make it simple because I used the same resources that you used ... you only used the Quran and I used that as a Primary source ... but i wanted to add a SECONDARY SOURCE that had nothing to do with Isaac but had general knowlege which proved me right from another point of view

one was Abraham given Isaac after he left his people and he was ordered to sacrifice this son
two was Ishmael never grew old to walk ALONGSIDE HIS FATHER because my secondary source states Ishmael was a baby when Abraham left him and when Abraham REMEET ISHMAEL AND THEY WENT TO THE KAABA .. he was already a grown man who grew alongside who?  His mother not his dad .. clear and simple but you took that as another excuse to use your status and block me for silly reasons

so Iam gonna once again show you my  much clearer source and expect you to be fair hopefully...


1......

focus on capslocks

019.048
YUSUFALI: &quot;And I will TURN AWAY from you (all) and from those whom ye invoke besides Allah: I will call on my Lord: perhaps, by my prayer to my Lord, I shall be not unblest.&quot;

019.049
YUSUFALI: When he had TURNED AWAY from them and from those whom they worshipped besides Allah, WE bestowed on him Isaac and Jacob, and each one of them We made a prophet


... same story mentioned in detail here

037.099
YUSUFALI: He said: &quot;I will GO to my Lord! He will surely guide me!

037.101
YUSUFALI: So WE gave him the good news of a boy ready to suffer and forbear.

037.102
YUSUFALI: And when (his son) was old enough to walk with him, (Abraham) said: O my dear son, I have seen in a dream that I must sacrifice thee. So look, what thinkest thou? He said: O my father! Do that which thou art commanded. Allah willing, thou shalt find me of the steadfast


no interpretation no opinion ...


2.......

Hadith 4:583

Narrated Ibn Abbas:
The first lady to use a girdle was the mother of Ishmael. She used a girdle so that she might hide her tracks from Sarah. Abraham brought her and her son Ishmael while she was SUCKLING him, to a place near the Ka'ba under a tree on the spot of Zam-zam, at the highest place in the mosque. During those days there was nobody in Mecca, nor was there any water So he made them sit over there and placed near them a leather bag containing some dates, and a small water-skin containing some water, and set out homeward. Ishmael's mother followed him saying, &quot;O Abraham! Where are you going, leaving us in this valley where there is no person whose company we may enjoy, nor is there anything (to enjoy)?&quot; She repeated that to him many times, but he did not look back at her Then she asked him, &quot;Has Allah ordered you to do so?&quot; He said, &quot;Yes.&quot; She said, &quot;Then He will not neglect us,&quot; and returned while Abraham proceeded onwards, and on reaching the Thaniya where they could not see him, he faced the Ka'ba, and raising both hands, invoked Allah saying the following prayers:

'O our Lord! I have made some of my offspring dwell in a valley without cultivation, by Your Sacred House (Kaba at Mecca) in order, O our Lord, that they may offer prayer perfectly. So fill some hearts among men with love towards them, and (O Allah) provide them with fruits, so that they may give thanks.' (14.37) Ishmael's mother went on SUCKLING Ishmael and drinking from the water (she had).

..................  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Highdeeboy|Highdeeboy]] ([[User talk:Highdeeboy|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Highdeeboy|contribs]]) 14:19, 17 March 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;


After Ishmael's mother had died, Abraham came after Ishmael's MARRIAGE in order to see his family that he had left before, but he did not find Ishmael there. When he asked Ishmael's wife about him, she replied, 'He has gone in search of our livelihood.

clearly when Abraham came again ISHMAEL WAS A MARRIED ADULT who grew ALONGSIDE HAGAR ...

037.102
YUSUFALI: And when (his son) was old enough to walk with him, (Abraham) said: O my dear son, I have seen in a dream that I must sacrifice thee. So look, what thinkest thou? He said: O my father! Do that which thou art commanded. Allah willing, thou shalt find me of the steadfast[[User:Highdeeboy|Highdeeboy]] ([[User talk:Highdeeboy|talk]]) 14:13, 17 March 2010 (UTC)

focuse on this verse ... the idendity of this son is that he grew with his father .. Ishmael was left a baby alognside his mom and ONLY GOT TO SEE HIS FATHER AGAIN WHEN HE GOT MARRIED AND WAS A MAN ENOUGH TO BUILD THE KAABA ...so the conclusion is that HE DIDNT GROW ALONGSIDE HIS FATHER .. he only REMET HIS FATHER WHEN HE WAS ALREADY OLD but the verse states this unknown son grew alongisde his father therefore this is another proof that its Isaac[[User:Highdeeboy|Highdeeboy]] ([[User talk:Highdeeboy|talk]]) 13:42, 27 March 2010 (UTC) ...

if you still refuse my claim then just forget everything and look at my new Idea please[[User:Highdeeboy|Highdeeboy]] ([[User talk:Highdeeboy|talk]]) 13:56, 27 March 2010 (UTC)

==Enhance the Article==
Listen I have an Idea
.. i think we should make this Neutral because you dont seem to ever be satisfied with me and aim really giving you more than what the other provide but its always NO! so i want you and I to edit that article and provide more support for my claim because there are many verses that support my claim so Id like to add them to the article but at the end of the day the article will still support Both fairly because i dont seem to see anything good conerning my side so id like to enhance it and make it fairly neutral and obviously you will have a look at it and see if its good or no ok?[[User:Highdeeboy|Highdeeboy]] ([[User talk:Highdeeboy|talk]]) 13:56, 27 March 2010 (UTC)

:The article neutrally represents what different [[WP:RS|reliable sources]] say.  Just because it does not include your personal opinion on which son the Quran refers to does not mean that the article is not neutral.  There has to be a source that by itself says &quot;some Muslims say it was Isaac.&quot;  Pieces of different sources that do not outright say &quot;it was Isaac&quot; do not work because that is [[WP:OR|original research]], which Wikipedia does not accept.  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 15:44, 27 March 2010 (UTC)

I dont get you ... one guy says this and the other says that .. [[User:Highdeeboy|Highdeeboy]] ([[User talk:Highdeeboy|talk]]) 15:41, 4 April 2010 (UTC)

== Resting place? ==

I know it's in our infobox person, but that's for people where we know they are historical persons and we have a definite 'resting place'. --[[User:Dougweller|Dougweller]] ([[User talk:Dougweller|talk]]) 10:14, 2 January 2011 (UTC)

[[Immanuel Kant]] had a fascinating interpretation of the binding of Isaac.  Given his important in philosophy (and really Western culture in general) over the last couple of hundred years I think there might be a sentence or two on the Kantian view here. --[[User:Christofurio|Christofurio]] ([[User talk:Christofurio|talk]]) 23:31, 3 May 2011 (UTC)

== Christian views - original research, no reliable sources ==

As the edit summary says, &quot;Christian View expanded based solely on Scripture and knowledge of &quot;types and shadows&quot; of Christianity.&quot; - in other words, original research using editor's own knowledge and primary sources. 
--[[User:Dougweller|Dougweller]] ([[User talk:Dougweller|talk]]) 06:10, 3 October 2012 (UTC)
:I have deleted the material as it fails several Wikipedia Criteria for inclusion. [[User:Jpacobb|Jpacobb]] ([[User talk:Jpacobb|talk]]) 22:19, 3 October 2012 (UTC)

::Thanks. [[User:Dougweller|Dougweller]] ([[User talk:Dougweller|talk]]) 09:13, 4 October 2012 (UTC)

== Listing as a &quot;Good article&quot; ==

Just a note that unless this is fixed, I think the article's Good article status will need to be reviewed as it no longer meets criteria 2 at [[Wikipedia:Good article criteria]]. I'll fix a couple of 'neverthelesses' that fail NPOV. [[User:Dougweller|Dougweller]] ([[User talk:Dougweller|talk]]) 06:15, 3 October 2012 (UTC)

:Seems to be fixed so no need for the tag anymore. [[User:Dougweller|Dougweller]] ([[User talk:Dougweller|talk]]) 09:13, 4 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>sc0yd4zogb2g7wwybfstzlr1iux3afg</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
