<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Superstition</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>18437990</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516493478</id>
      <parentid>516492724</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-07T15:57:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bermicourt</username>
        <id>7254364</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Change of definition has been undone */ cmt amdt</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="42892">{{notaforum}}
{{Rational Skepticism|class=Start|importance=High}}
{{WPOccult|class=Start|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Sociology|class=Start|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=Start|importance=Top}}


== Stray Thread ==

This is currently a very hard definition.  Most of us are influenced by superstition : lucky numbers, favourite items.  Superstition is deeply embedded in most cultures : just think of launching ships with bottles of wine, 'touch wood' etc.
: Many of those are customs based on superstitions. The people performing the custom might not actually believe in the superstition.

Don't you think superstition is just passing the responsibility on to someone else. Let it be fate, go

While many mentaly retarded activities might have roots in superstition, some of the people who engage in these activities may not necessarily believe in the original superstition.  Personally I despise various things for being superstitions, or at least I feel I do -- perhaps this feeling is superstitious. 

I don't think the definition at the head of the article adequately --[[Special:Contributions/84.13.252.81|84.13.252.81]] ([[User talk:84.13.252.81|talk]]) 16:45, 9 December 2009 (UTC)&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;s&gt;Block quote&lt;/s&gt;#REDIRECT [[--[[Special:Contributions/84.13.252.81|84.13.252.81]] ([[User talk:84.13.252.81|talk]]) 16:45, 9 December 2009 (UTC)Target page name
----
&lt;s&gt;&lt;s&gt;Strike-through text&lt;/s&gt;&lt;s&gt;&lt;s&gt;Strike-through text&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/s&gt;]]
&lt;/blockquote&gt;of pizza started the universe.&quot; How do you know if the universe was &quot;started&quot; or not--you weren't there, or maybe we all were and we've just forgotten, so it frankly IS unknowable at this point in existence if there even was a beginning...or that time really exists. It could all be in our heads as a current perception of 'time'--many cultures have no word for 'time' as they used to operate solely in the present moment, so no thoughts about the past or future. Our thoughts about the past and future are really what create 'time' in our own perception, no? If you don't think about the past and future, time doesn't exist now does it? If everything operates in cycles, then 'time' as a linear concept is just that, a concept that we in the modern age made up to label something.

Plus, using today's scientific physics jargon, if time is 'relative' it could operate into infinity or into nothingness  as it is not a constant (people just assume it is as that is what it appears to us standing on Earth travelling in a circle within the universe, within ??) And, who really knows whether 'god' didn't just have a hankering for a slice of pizza and thus created the universe? Maybe you're onto something! ;-) 

Scientists today assume they are correct in their theories, just like all scientists in past also did in their day and age. The best assumption we can logically make is to assume that most of what scientists can prove repeatedly is correct in action (eg., law of gravity), but if there are dissenting voices and still people speculating and arguing about HOW it works (eg., law of gravity), then you better not set your mind in stone about 'origins' just yet.[[User:Gnatbuzz|Gnatbuzz]] ([[User talk:Gnatbuzz|talk]]) 16:59, 18 June 2008 (UTC)






SUPERSTITIONS ARE STUPID UNBELEIVABLE STUFF AND WHOEVER BELEIVES THEM ALL IS GOING TO HAVE A REALY HARD LAIFE RUNNING AWAY FROM BIRDS AND CATS AND ALSO TRYING TO SKIP AN ENTIRE FLOOR ON A BUILDING IS JUST STUPID IDIOTIC AND YOU WILL GET URSELF HURT ( AND I BET THERE IS PROBABLY A SUPERSTITION THAT ALOWS YOU NOT TO GET SOME SORT OF SURGERY SO THAT MEANS YOU WILL BE INGURED FOR THE RES OF YOUR LIFE AND DIE ) THIS IS ALL BECAUSE OF SOMETHING THAT SOMEONE MADE UP MOST LIKELY JUST TO WATCH PEOPLE RUN AROUND ACTING STUPID!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/74.15.247.94|74.15.247.94]] ([[User talk:74.15.247.94|talk]]) 22:38, 27 February 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== religion == 
By defining superstition as ''misplaced'' religious feeling, the article suggests that there is a rightly placed religious feeling, even going so far as to give a Christian view of superstition. However, a lot of people would regard all religion as superstition. This would seem to be confirmed by the dictionary definition, which says nothing about ''misplaced'' attitudes:

''1. Unreasoning awe or fear of something unknown, mysterious, or imaginary, esp. in connexion with religion; religious betc. It was edited out, because not well formulated. The external links point to stuff like that, not really explaining the superstition in russia, asia and middle age europe. Superstition could explain christinaity from their viewpoint (at christianity article), it would get removed quickly as NPOV criticism/discussion. I do not know if it links to [[The Life of Brian]], but that's how christian believers might see an interpretation attempt from the sight of superstition. In asia, for instance the concept of [[godfather]] is uncommon. It is just true for western people. The article needs explanation, what superstition really is, not criticism/rationalizing and denial of it.

:: I think the primary difference is that religious belief has a source (e.g. walking under a ladder will cause you misfortune because God hates ladders) while a superstition has no source and is merely traditional paranoid belief (e.g. walking under a ladder is inherently an inexplicably unlucky).


:Most religions include supersition, principally in the form of prayers for specified outcomes.  But it is possible to be fully committed to and active in a religion without being superstitious at all, especially if one's prayer consists only in praise of God or a type of meditation through repeating familiar words.

:The familiar atheist and agnostic view that religion is superstition is  essentially a ''disparagement'' of religion rather than a ''description''. So I don't agree with Roy Bruback that &quot;a religion, like any thought, is superstitious if and only if it is untrue&quot;.  ''Definitions'' of religion and superstition ought not judge whether the beliefs they include are true or not; rather they should be based on description.

:So I would try the following.  The primary difference between supersition and religion is that superstitious belief is disorganised and religious belief is systematic.  Further, any set of religious beliefs exists within ''a religion'', which is more than mere belief and is ''a social institution'' combining belonging, history, architecture and sacred geography, scripture and revered literature, language, prayer, liturgy and shared observance, music, art, organisation and welfare, belief, authority, hierarchy and tradition.  There may be fokloric equivalents for supersition but they will not have the same degree of complexity.

:: Superstition : Religion :: Crime : Mafia ?  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/190.225.12.210|190.225.12.210]] ([[User talk:190.225.12.210|talk]]) 01:47, 7 April 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:::Well done. Next lesson, we'll try combining some '''words''' into '''sentences'''. [[User:Fuzzypeg|Fuzzypeg]][[User talk:Fuzzypeg|★]] 05:12, 23 April 2008 (UTC)

== Superstition and folklore - strange example ==

In the &quot;Superstition and folklore&quot; section their is an odd sentence - can any one explain the meaning or correct the grammar?

&quot;a pregnant female should avoid coming out of door, (i.e., avoid  exposing her to the sun) during the time of an eclipse&quot;


If you look at most superstitious actions they have a root in disseminating information in days where education was not widespread. Mainly told too the uneducated and children to prevent them from doing things that may cause physical and finacial damage.--[[Special:Contributions/121.54.2.3|121.54.2.3]] ([[User talk:121.54.2.3|talk]]) 07:20, 14 June 2008 (UTC)

Mirrors used to be very expensive and owned by the wealthy. It would have been easier to create a sense of fear in the slaves cleaning the mirror then to explain the value and fragility of the mirror.

Ladders tend to have people working on them, usually carrying some object. The danger to both the person on the ladder and the person below requires caution. What better way to create caution in uneducated workers then superstition.

Umberellas (both for rain and sun) caused fires in the days of gas lighting. To get the message across, that opening an umberella indoors gives a high chance of starting a fire in days of no/poor fire service, requires superstition.

Bad luck to step on cracks. focuses a child into looking where it puts its feet, good idea in days before good pavements. A broken ankle could take valuble work time thus money from a family.

The Magpie rhyme. Good for the farmers children. As magpies are pests to the farmer what better way to find out how many of the pests are in his field. I wonder how many children rushed back in to tell pops about the magpies in the field.

I could go on, but you see that in days gone by where reading and writing were premium, that the best way to educate against common mistakes was to highlight them with a superstition.


&quot;Asian&quot; needs to be capitalized.

== Superstitions by country/region ==
Scientists too are superstitious.The very term ‘scientist’ conjures up the image of an individual who would not compromise with his/her rational thinking nor repose faith in systems and beliefs that do not stand scientific scrutiny.

majority of Indian scientists are as pliable as the laymen in matters of religion, beliefs and sentiments.Giving their views on the survey report at a media conference organised by Centre for Inquiry, scientist P. M. Bhargava felt such a dichotomy in the attitude of scientists would not augur well for the country. “Perhaps this is the reason why after C.V. Raman, no single Nobel prize was won by Indian scientists. The scientific outlook should not be confined to the specific field of research but should extend to all spheres of life,” he said. Chandana Chakravarthy, member of the Centre criticised that scientists were bringing their personal belief systems into institutions where they work.

Citing instances of ISRO scientists going to Tirupati to seek divine blessings before launch of satellite missions or those calling on Sri Satya Sai Baba, the CFI chairman N. Innaiah said this was against the spirit of Indian Constitution that emphasised on promotion of scientific temper among people for rooting out superstitions.50 per cent of scientists covered, believed in Homoeopathy, 49 per cent believe in power of prayer.While 16 per cent believe in faith healing, 14 per cent have trust in Vasthu, astrology and 10 per cent in palmistry.For an overwhelming 93 per cent of scientists ‘secularism’ meant tolerance for various religions and philosophies while 83 per cent said it meant separation of religion from State/Government.

== Compilation of superstitions ==

I do not see this compilation pointless. The article looks very abstract, and contains a few superstitions at best. The explanation is scientific, but IMO wrong. The linked research pages are abstract, and not getting the point. I tried to write about it, but it was edited out. It was not very well written, though.&lt;br&gt;
It is possible to copy my tables (it is PD information).
I do not know any good site, which include a compilation of superstition in modern language. Some are good, but very long, and they contain weird superstitions.&lt;br&gt;
The pages now get hits by search engines, i am collecting the terms (which were searched) into a file. There are people searching &quot;european superstition&quot;, and around 30 other terms.&lt;br&gt;
The link removal has caused a decline in visitors, around 50 people came from here. 
Some vandalized my guestbook, but i can not verify where they came from. The same questions arise for [[Aztec_Calendar]]. I know the policy on external links.&lt;br&gt;
 &quot;The reason for superstition in asian countries: People abide a few abstract rules,&lt;br&gt;and in the cause of it, they also refrain from other undesireable action&lt;br&gt;(because this causes bad luck)&quot;


&quot;Among African Americans it is considered unlucky to sweep someone with a broom while cleaning house.&quot; Can someone please tell me what this means? 

:It means that if you are sitting in a chair or standing on the floor, and someone near you is sweeping the floor with a broomcorn broom and they sweep across your feet, it is considered very bad luck. To undo this, the person who has inadvertently swept you might touch, hug, or even kiss you. It's quite a common belief and custom. It is mentioned in the song &quot;The Blues What Am&quot; by Jazz GIllum.




Is it really correct to say that a gambler's luck is due to the law of averages? Every textbook on Statistics I've read says that the law of averages itself grows out of a misunderstanding of the law of large numbers -- that is, thinking that since the proportion of outcomes converges to a stable state in infinite time, the proportions must &quot;balance each other out&quot; in finite time. It seems more appropriate to make some sort of argument for the gambler's &quot;hot streak&quot; from binomial probability, saying that his success rate in a given session has a certain chance of happening during any given session, and increasing the number of sessions played increases the chances of *some session* displaying such a high rate of success. [[User:69.140.109.143|69.140.109.143]] 13:55, 21 May 2007 (UTC)

Has nobody read Carl Jung's &quot;Synchronicity&quot; essay outlining his experiments on 'lucky guesses'? He showed that when the player was in an excited state at the beginning of the test and wanting to really guess the cards right, they did. When the test got 'boring' over time, their correct guesses went down dramatically. One man though guessed the cards correctly over 90% of the time...he was deemed 'psychic'. But what the point of the test showed is that the observer has an effect on the observed when they put their full attention on the object being observed. This has also been proven in quantum physics looking at wave/point dynamics of photons...when 'observed' (with attention on them) the photons act as points, when not observed they act as waves. To discount current quantum physics understanding in the discussion of 'superstition' is negligent as it does denigrate something that may be fully explainable in many instances from a quantum physics understanding, but may be called 'superstition' when this is not understood so therefore biased by those doing the labelling.[[User:Gnatbuzz|Gnatbuzz]] ([[User talk:Gnatbuzz|talk]]) 17:26, 18 June 2008 (UTC)

== recent edit ==

I have not added new POV. I have not removed existing POV. The passage was a little repetetive, long and difficult to read. I have read it again a few times. I have not introduced spellings using unusual grammar. I hope there are not any typography mistakes this time. The phrase &quot;Better safe than sorry&quot; was taken from the internet, i have seen it somewhere else. One reference to urban legend was moved to &quot;See also&quot;. It reads interesting, and related to superstition.&lt;br&gt;
Erroneous Individual - this is a justification, and does not belong here. However it is possible to refer to a person, a research or a media giving such statements. This is already included (church statements). 

:Could you please explain what you mean by &quot;Urban legends, which are not scientifically prooved (justification) are put into correlation(s) which do no exist in physical, visible reality.&quot; as I can't figure out what you mean by it. Regards, [[User:MartinRe|MartinRe]] 12:40, 14 May 2006 (UTC)

== Fairly extensive revision for NPOV purposes ==
After months of kicking this article around and watching the debates, i took it upon myself to rewrite it for coherence of flow. I worked hard to not remove things that had been written, but i did delete redundancies that seem to have arisen from &quot;many cooks&quot; syndrome. Also, i broke the article apart into sections and made the rather radical choice &lt;insert smiley here&gt; to  describe superstition and give examples of it is at the top of the article, and to move all of the debunkining and skeptical viewpoints which formerly had been at the head of the article down to the bottom. The debunking posture was so thoroughly embedded in the article that on a second pass-through, i realized that every one of the six external links was to a skeptical or debunking web site. There were NO links to sites where people could actually go to study about superstitions, only links to places where people could go read about how stupid, dumb, bad, or unscientific they are. This biased writing shocked me a lot. I used google to find six sites on superstitions that have a folkloric and educational viewpoint; i could have found three dozen more. And i maY DO SO.


That cat sure looks gray to me.  Couldn't you have at least moved the ugly junk in the background before taking it?


This entry is in English. Therefore it should be written from an English speaker's point of view--anything else violates the NPOV principle. 

What if you were Chinese, living in China and you wanted to practice your English and learn about English-speaking culture? This article would be a disaster.

What if you were an American child doing a school project or paper on superstition and began your research here? Again, disaster. You'd fail because you would fail to address superstition withing the context of your assignment--your own culture.

Superstition is HUGE part of daily life in the English-speaking world. Many many many things we do, from which side of the raod we drive on, which hand we hold a fork in to the rules of ettiquette and polite interaction with everyone you come into contact with. What do YOU say when someone sneezes? Why? Superstition. And on and on.

This article and its current presentation violates the NPOV principle: It is an attack on English and American culture. It is not even subtle. 

This article should be changed as soon as possible to eliminate this bias.

== Psychological discussion? ==
Superstition is actually a rather interesting area of study in psychology and sociology with some important names who have investigated it (e.g. Skinner). This article avoids discussing any of the serious aspects of it instead providing a very brief definition and then citing lots of random examples and comparisons. Might I suggest refocusing the article toward the formal studies of the subject and have the existing content support that discussion?.

== An impossible article ==

I have no intention of getting involved in this article; I simply wanted to state my opinion (after stumbling across it) that it is one of the worst Wikipedia articles I have read. It opens with random listings of &quot;superstitions,&quot; and only after several pages gets to a semi-substantive yet entirely unsourced discussion of the topic. Whatever happened to the old definition: superstition is the other guy's religion? Out of curiosity I looked up the Encyclopedia Britannica article on the topic, which in this case is infinitely better than what Wikipedia has so far produced. It opens with the very sensible observation about &quot;superstition&quot;: &quot;An ambiguous word, it probably cannot be used except subjectively.&quot; In other words, the entire effort to write a NPOV article about &quot;superstition&quot; is doomed to failure, unless you begin from the principle that using the word &quot;superstition&quot; is in and of itself an attack (a slur) on someone else's closely held beliefs. What else needs to be said? Just my own POV... my sincere apologies if I have offended anyone who has spent time on the article...  But I suspect that few of you are regular 'wikipedians,' given that almost none have bothered to sign your comments.... --[[User:Potosino|Potosino]] 03:58, 1 July 2007 (UTC)
::I agree about the lack of organization, and have moved the listings on the bottom. As for the information and the style of writing, I haven't read the bulk of this stuff, so feel free to copyedit and re-write if need be. As they tell you on this site - be bold.--[[User:Gilabrand|Gilabrand]] 06:37, 1 July 2007 (UTC)

::I tend to agree with Potosino. The article starts with a faulty definition (are people who expect their prayers to be fulfilled superstitious?). Lists of superstitions do not really help. Only the Skinner paragraph is fine. But what about anthropology, what about the fact that there's a system? (Fishermen, hunters, sportspeople are superstitious, while farmers are not.) Anyway: I marked the article with a cleanup tag. [[User:GregorB|GregorB]] 21:26, 22 July 2007 (UTC)

I agree with Potosino, this is such a big undertaking. This article for starters at least should have the language cleaned up even if you don't add facts or change information. Right now the tone is so casual it really fails to be considered quality for an encyclopedic entry. Maybe if someone takes this small step it will help others be able to lend a further support. Right now though, I'm off to bed. [[User:71.187.190.88|71.187.190.88]] 03:18, 23 October 2007 (UTC)[[User:Forcefieldmaker87|Forcefieldmaker87]]

:I'm not convinced that it's impossible.  C. S. Lewis talks about magic and superstition as &quot;failed science&quot;; a belief that rubbing a toad on a wart will remove it is &quot;magic&quot; because it doesn't work.  &quot;Superstition&quot; is slightly more subtle since it involves &quot;luck&quot; which is much more subjective; if you believe that breaking a mirror causes bad luck, this may be a self-fulfulling prophecy.  Although [[folk religion]] has its share of superstitions, religious texts themselves mostly work at a different level and don't tend to contain these kind of &quot;if you do X, Y will happen&quot; statements that characterise superstitious beliefs.  Unfortunately &quot;superstition&quot; is often thrown around so loosely that these distinctions are lost.  That's not a reason for not trying though.  [[User:Pdch|Pdch]] ([[User talk:Pdch|talk]]) 20:39, 9 February 2008 (UTC)

:: Hooray for Potosino.  Not that it's impossible to do, but that as it stands, this article is impossible.  The semantic function of the word is left unexamined, when clearly it is pejorative, used by a speaker to discredit another more than describe.  There may be a superficial consistency among the things called a &quot;superstition&quot; by a society, and this phenomenon may be worth study.  The word, however, is clearly a word of derision, not description, and to define it here as an objective category is falsely conceived, and as Potosino says, unworthy.  

::But why has this not be dealt with in the half decade since his remarks?  This article screams out for radical revision.  A first good step would be simple deletion, until a smarter approach is adopted.  The Dutch article, noted below, may be a worthy stop-gap. [[User:ABShippee|ABS]] ([[User talk:ABShippee|talk]]) 21:48, 13 July 2012 (UTC)

:::We need to treat a topic in a [[WP:NPV|neutral way]]; this is one of the pillars of the project. Defining superstition only in terms of &quot;[t]he semantic function is clearly pejorative…a word of derision&quot; seems not to be an objective treatment. [[Anthropology#Cultural Anthropology|Cultural anthropology]] (as a quick example arrived at without engaging any deep consideration) would be a field  where &quot;derision&quot; would be inappropriate. As the semantic function remains &quot;unexamined&quot; in the article, a good first step would be to find some reliable sources and [[WP:SOFIXIT|fix the deficiency]]. Your &quot;simple deletion&quot; solution would probably be treated as simple vandalism. --[[User:Old Moonraker|Old Moonraker]] ([[User talk:Old Moonraker|talk]]) 07:38, 14 July 2012 (UTC)

== Bullcrap ==
Superstitions are as bad as believing in Horoscopes or eight-armed gods. Enough said. If you need further explanation to understand the reasoning behind my statement, then you better get your head checked to see if there is a brain in there.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/216.165.32.105|216.165.32.105]] ([[User talk:216.165.32.105|talk]]) 18:44, 1 March 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Now rephrase that so it's NPOV, and provide a secondary source. [[User:Leushenko|Leushenko]] ([[User talk:Leushenko|talk]]) 04:13, 19 March 2008 (UTC)
== Superstitions Reasonable ==
I think some superstitions can be based on reason. If you believe bad spirits cause disease, and also believe bad spirits are afraid of  garlic, then putting garlic on a sick person is reasonable. Today we know germs cause disease, and are killed by mold. Some superstitions start when someone incorrectly observes a cause and effect. For example, I win when wearing my &quot;lucky&quot; shoes. Maybe it is a superstition to believe, certain shoes will make you play better, not because of luck, but &quot;science.&quot; anyway, it seems to me, that most people use the word to describe a practice they don't believe in, although some call practices they believe in superstitions, so a definition could be beliefs about luck, though that is not the only definition. [[User:Rds865|Rds865]] ([[User talk:Rds865|talk]]) 03:18, 6 April 2008 (UTC)

:There are two potential debates here:
:#Are certain beliefs and practises &quot;superstition&quot;, or are they (to the contrary) reasonable/sensible?
:#Can superstitions be reasonable? (i.e. based on reason?)
:There's an important difference:  the first uses the traditional meaning and connotations of &quot;superstition&quot;; the second talks about redefining the word;. The term &quot;superstition&quot; has had strong pejorative connotations since its early usage, and if people are now trying to use the word to describe behaviour they regard as reasonable and rational, then they're effectively reclaiming the word, much as lesbians have reclaimed the previously pejorative term &quot;dyke&quot;. Taking a negative term and reinterpreting it in a positive light.
:I can see there is a certain element of this happening with the word &quot;superstition&quot;; perhaps you'd like to draft some explanation of this in the article? [[User:Fuzzypeg|Fuzzypeg]][[User talk:Fuzzypeg|★]] 22:46, 6 April 2008 (UTC)

::all forms of superstition have some kind of reason behind it, syaing that superstion is not based on reason is flawed. rather the reason used in making superstition is cause and effect, and the mechanics behind it are not fully understood... Something like that. [[Special:Contributions/204.10.222.30|204.10.222.30]] ([[User talk:204.10.222.30|talk]]) 15:12, 1 November 2010 (UTC)SPaceout

== Etymology ==

&lt;s&gt;An IP poster is deleting sourced material and replacing it with unsourced (which may or may not be correct) thus leaving the original footnote no longer supporting the material. Should I delete the source (bad), delete the unsourced material, or risk further edit skirmishing by recasting the text so that it reflects the source and adding a &lt;nowiki&gt;{{fact}}&lt;/nowiki&gt; request to the unsourced stuff? I prefer the last option, but I am trying to preclude any further skirmishing. --[[User:Old Moonraker|Old Moonraker]] ([[User talk:Old Moonraker|talk]]) 08:26, 27 June 2008 (UTC)&lt;/s&gt;

:The above was too hasty: I will separate the material so that the different sources (the new material ''does'' now  have a source) are reflected in separate pieces of text. --[[User:Old Moonraker|Old Moonraker]] ([[User talk:Old Moonraker|talk]]) 08:32, 27 June 2008 (UTC)
::Done. --[[User:Old Moonraker|Old Moonraker]] ([[User talk:Old Moonraker|talk]]) 08:40, 27 June 2008 (UTC)

:: Skirmishing? I was just surprised to see users revert to incorrect material. For further information on a Roman ''superstitio'' see ''Religions of Rome'' by Beard, North, and Price, pp. 216-217.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.107.220.143|76.107.220.143]] ([[User talk:76.107.220.143|talk]]) 18:53, 27 June 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:::Checked ''Beard, North, and Price'' on the suggested pages: it offers no etymology for superstitio, although a contemporary dictionary definition of &quot;religio&quot; is noted. Its burden is a comparison between &quot;superstitio&quot; and &quot;religio&quot;. There may be material there for [[Superstition#Superstition and religion]], lower down the page, if anybody feels like inserting it. --[[User:Old Moonraker|Old Moonraker]] ([[User talk:Old Moonraker|talk]]) 14:33, 30 June 2008 (UTC)

== More Stuff ==

In France (and, I believe, in Spain and Italy) actors believe the color green on stage brings bad luck. Similarly for ropes on stage (&quot;the hangman terror&quot;). They don't say &quot;bonne chance&quot; (=&quot;good luck&quot;) but &quot;merde&quot; (=&quot;shit&quot;). This last use has become common in all circumstances (e.g. exams, trips, etc...). It is in fact the only instance in which the word &quot;merde&quot; in French is likely not to offend anybody. 

Rabbits are banned on boats. They're believed to bring in bad luck. This folklore is most likely related to real events. Ancient sailors would bring on board easy-to-care-for live animals such as rabbits, which facilitated the proliferation of certain diseases. a superstiton is a fear or a belive so strong that you belive it is real and it exists but it is just in you'r mind  

Btw, the &quot;don't set your hat on your bed&quot; superstition claimed by the article to be commonly believed in South Carolina, is also widespread in France. As well as exiting one's house through the main bedroom window. It's said to also bring bad luck. Definitely, this is true when the bedroom is upstairs, and the bad luck ensuing is immediate. 

There are many, many more examples, of course, but the above two are specific enough to be added to the article. Especially since the color green seems to also have a bad reputation among anglophone actors.

== Superstition ==

http://www.superstitions.ca/




[[Special:Contributions/74.47.147.80|74.47.147.80]] ([[User talk:74.47.147.80|talk]]) 02:56, 6 November 2008 (UTC)Bob Frapple

&quot;Many extant superstitions are said to have originated during the plagues that swept through Europe. According to legend, during the time of a plague, Saint Gregory I the Great ordered that people say &quot;God bless you&quot; when somebody sneezed, to prevent the spread of the disease&quot; -&gt; Should this be in the intro? Feels a bit specific...  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/219.89.70.24|219.89.70.24]] ([[User talk:219.89.70.24|talk]]) 21:34, 11 January 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt; it is what is the people believe and how evety society are diffrent

== Superstition ==

--[[User:Cameramaster|Cameramaster]] ([[User talk:Cameramaster|talk]]) 15:26, 19 February 2009 (UTC)I think a very simple definition of superstition would be &quot; A belief in something that has no rational basis for belief and cannot be Substantiated by any means&quot;, this would also cover any religion as well.

The Ghost of Evangelene Skiddleton.


Evangelene Skiddleton lived in Moredock Hall in the West Midlands. Her and her family disappeared and Evangelene was only 9 at the time. We do not know much about the Skiddleton family, this information has been gathered from descendants of this family. Many people have seen sightings of Evangelene wearing a white dressing gown and she is completely alone. She had cherry lips and blonde hair. If you ever have a sighting of her, DO NOT MOVE under any circumstances, as she may approach. Evangelene has been sighted in Uttoxeter, Ashley, Aston and Hilderstone.

 &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/81.153.35.106|81.153.35.106]] ([[User talk:81.153.35.106|talk]]) 12:48, 17 April 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Maintenance ==

Speaking of unexplained phenomenon: odd that there are no archives or talk prior to 2008. Just a lot of random commentary so I've removed the article level tags, made a few neutral adjustments to lede, moved some stuff from it to the 1st &amp;sect; and put in global context. [[User:Lycurgus|Lycurgus]] ([[User talk:Lycurgus|talk]]) 09:32, 24 May 2009 (UTC)

== Inconsistent spelling ==

It seems to me that the spelling in this article is inconsistent: &quot;labeled&quot; and &quot;modeled&quot; are spelled according to American usage, whereas &quot;behaviour&quot; is spelt the way British writers would write it.
[[User:Frankly speaking|Frankly speaking]] ([[User talk:Frankly speaking|talk]]) 06:04, 2 September 2009 (UTC)

== Dutch version of this article ==

Is there anything like the [[:nl:Bijgeloof|Dutch version of this article]] on the English Wikipedia? 

Google translate gives the following translation of the contents (roughly corrected):
*1 Ambiguous concept
*2 Superstition and religion
*3 Popular superstition
*3.1 Unlucky number 13
*3.2 Horseshoes
*3.3 Umbrellas
*3.4 The clover
*3.5 Mirrors
*3.6 Knocking on wood
*3.7 Ladders
*3.8 Salt
*3.9 Birth and neonatal
*3.10 Solar eclipses
*4 Superstitions about animals
*4.1 Cat
*4.2 Leech 
*4.3 Magpie
*4.4 Mol
*4.5 Horse 
*4.6 Spider
*4.7 Bat
*4.8 Reptiles and amphibians
*5 Superstitions around plants
*5.1 The tree of life
*5.2 Linden
*5.3 The willow
*5.4 Kruidenwis
*5.5 The mistletoe
*5.6 Witch circle
*5.7 Elder
*6 Superstition on the calendar
*6.1 Superstitions associated with weekdays
*6.1.1 Sunday
*6.1.2 Monday
*6.1.3 Tuesday
*6.1.4 Wednesday
*6.1.5 Thursday
*6.1.6 Saturday
*6.2 Annual accident days
*7 Luck and accident
*7.1 Acts, objects and events that would bring misfortune
*7.2 Acts, objects and events that would bring happiness
*8 Other superstitious alphabetically

I have not been able to find this here. If it doesn't exist, is there a reason for it? [[User:Wiki-uk|Wiki-uk]] ([[User talk:Wiki-uk|talk]]) 17:50, 9 December 2009 (UTC)

== religion == 

The section on Superstition and Religion needs to have some additional examples of religious beliefs that could be regarded as superstitions. Some good examples can be found at: [http://www.other-voices.net/weird-beliefs.html this website].  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/98.70.115.17|98.70.115.17]] ([[User talk:98.70.115.17|talk]]) 19:06, 3 October 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Hi I AM Not A Fisic Edit BUt I Can Hel]p . Hold ON.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/66.131.190.6|66.131.190.6]] ([[User talk:66.131.190.6|talk]]) 20:13, 6 October 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Exampl ==

Examples O f SUper Stition.?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/66.131.190.6|66.131.190.6]] ([[User talk:66.131.190.6|talk]]) 20:16, 6 October 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Isnt The Clay HamsA A Chines Luck OBject.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/66.131.190.6|66.131.190.6]] ([[User talk:66.131.190.6|talk]]) 20:27, 6 October 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== [[Caste system in India]] ==

Considering a revert, as [[WP:TOPIC|off-topic]], of [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Superstition&amp;diff=411244600&amp;oldid=409958613 a recent edit] introducing the [[Caste system in India]] as a link. Views? --[[User:Old Moonraker|Old Moonraker]] ([[User talk:Old Moonraker|talk]]) 21:47, 31 January 2011 (UTC)
:This is about the following title:
::Russell, R. V., ''[http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/search.html/?default_prefix=author_id&amp;sort_order=downloads&amp;query=9405 The Tribes and Castes of the Central Provinces of India]'' (four vols.). London (1916).
:This is not only about the caste system in India, but about the culture of numerous tribes in central India. When searching for &quot;superstit&quot; in the contents of the different volumes, it appears that many superstitions in Indian culture are described and explained here. This is why I added it here. [[User:Wiki-uk|Wiki-uk]] ([[User talk:Wiki-uk|talk]]) 14:13, 1 February 2011 (UTC)
:: Thanks for the explanation. I was thinking about [[Wikipedia:Further reading#Topical]]: &quot;A large part, if not all, of the work should be directly about the subject of the article&quot;. --[[User:Old Moonraker|Old Moonraker]] ([[User talk:Old Moonraker|talk]]) 15:21, 1 February 2011 (UTC)

== Gender and superstitions ==

It seems to me that many agree that women are usually more superstitious than man. Any thoughts on that?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Ilya-42|Ilya-42]] ([[User talk:Ilya-42|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Ilya-42|contribs]]) 10:05, 23 June 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

: [[WP:OR|Original research]] is not allowed (consider that I could say &quot;It seems to me that many agree that men are usually more superstitious than women&quot;, just as easily). If you want to add something to the article, make sure you have a [[WP:RS|reliable source]] first. [[User:GManNickG|GManNickG]] ([[User talk:GManNickG|talk]]) 10:24, 23 June 2011 (UTC)

I believe this article needs to reference the gamblers falacy more. Both the gamblers falacy and superstition give people a false sense of control. For furthur reading, refer to The Science of Fear by Gardner.  [[User:Schmidsa|Schmidsa]] ([[User talk:Schmidsa|talk]]) 21:23, 8 February 2012 (UTC)
==File:Goddess Kaali.jpg Nominated for speedy Deletion==
&lt;!--TSTAMP:{{{4}}}--&gt;
{|
|-
| [[File:Image-x-generic.svg|100px]] 
| &lt;!--IMAGES--&gt;
An image used in this article, [[:File:Goddess Kaali.jpg|File:Goddess Kaali.jpg]], has been nominated for speedy deletion for the following reason: ''All Wikipedia files with unknown copyright status'' 
&lt;!--/IMAGES--&gt;
;What should I do?
''Don't panic''; you should have time to contest the deletion (although please review [[WP:CSD|deletion guidelines]] before doing so). The best way to contest this form of deletion is by posting on the image talk page.
* If the image is [[WP:NFCC|non-free]] then you may need to provide a [[WP:FUR|fair use rationale]]
* If the image isn't freely licensed and there is no fair use rationale, then it cannot be uploaded or used.
* If the image has already been deleted you may want to try [[WP:DRV|Deletion Review]]
To take part in any discussion, or to review a more detailed deletion rationale please visit the relevant [[:File:Goddess Kaali.jpg|image page (File:Goddess Kaali.jpg)]]

''This is Bot placed notification, another user has nominated/tagged the image'' --[[User:CommonsNotificationBot|CommonsNotificationBot]] ([[User talk:CommonsNotificationBot|talk]]) 08:04, 16 February 2012 (UTC)
|}

== Change of definition has been undone ==

The definition

&quot;Superstition is a belief or notion, not based on reason or knowledge, in or of the ominous significance of a particular thing, circumstance, occurrence, proceeding, or the like[1].&quot;

has been removed form the article, as it is unprecise and not fully encompassing, as is the definition it was meant to replace.

Imprecise meaning, that it does not allow an impartial judgement of whether a specific belief falls under the defintion, as does the definition is was meant to replace. Also it does not encompas all believes that must be regarded as superstition as it narrows it down to only beliefs in ominous consequenses. Superstition can just as well be (and often is) a belief in desired consequences.

The removed definition can as best be seen as an examplification of the general definition.

The removed definition seems to be have been put in solely because the person who did the edit found it in some online dictionary, and not because of any specific arguments for its superiority.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/87.63.36.114|87.63.36.114]] ([[User talk:87.63.36.114|talk]]) 22:12, 5 May 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:&quot;Found it in some online dictionary&quot;: the online dictionary entry in question is claimed to be ©&amp;nbsp;2012, whereas the material [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Superstition&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=163249324 first appeared here] in 1997. The external site may possibly be mirroring Wikipedia content. The deleted definition—&quot;a belief or notion, not based on reason or knowledge, in or of the ominous significance of a particular thing…&quot;—had the benefit of simplicity and clarity. I suggest keeping the new definition, but without supplanting the old one. --[[User:Old Moonraker|Old Moonraker]] ([[User talk:Old Moonraker|talk]]) 06:39, 6 May 2012 (UTC)

::The current definition is POV and needs replacing. There are clearly 2 viewpoints here. First there are atheists who would call all religious belief &quot;superstition&quot; and that is the thrust of the definition here. The second is the traditional and rather more specific definition that it refers to &quot;excessive&quot; or &quot;irrational&quot; belief in the supernatural, especially in bringing good or bad luck: lucky horseshoes being an example. That is a much more widely held understanding, even by those of religious persuasions. The second definition is reflected in the Oxford Dictionary of English which gives &quot;superstition&quot; as &quot;excessively credulous belief in and reverence for the supernatural: ''he dismissed the ghost stories as mere superstition'' and &quot;a superstition&quot; as &quot;widely held but irrational belief in supernatural influences, especially as leading to good or bad luck, or a practice based on such a belief:'' she touched her locket for luck...''&quot;. I propose we build the definition around something like that which is more neutral and backed by a responsible, international source.&lt;ref&gt;Soanes, Catherine and Stevenson, Angus (ed.) (2005). ''Oxford Dictionary of English'', 2nd Ed., revised, Oxford University Press, Oxford, New York, ISBN 978-0-19-861057-1. The ODE uses an international database and a team of experts from across the English-speaking world.&lt;/ref&gt;  --[[User:Bermicourt|Bermicourt]] ([[User talk:Bermicourt|talk]]) 15:51, 7 October 2012 (UTC)
&lt;references/&gt;</text>
      <sha1>i3zxuvjttsvy1e1n0mnstrvoy1elvl0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
