<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Kohen</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>72349</id>
    <revision>
      <id>493260304</id>
      <parentid>450391406</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-05-18T22:18:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>John Carter</username>
        <id>3358555</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>B class for Religion</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24234">{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 125K
|counter = 2
|minthreadsleft = 4
|algo = old(30d)
|archive = Talk:Kohen/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{talkheader|search=yes}}
{{auto archiving notice|bot=MiszaBot I|dounreplied=yes|age=30}}
{{WikiProject Judaism | class= B | importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=B|importance=Top}}

== Inaccuracies of this Page ==

To all who are interested: I unfortunately can no longer devote my time towards disputing what I believe to be a manipulation and fabrication of the basic truths regarding the Kohen Wiki Page. Even if I could devote my time; this would most likely prove futile as I lack authority and numbers on Wikipedia. There are two users in particular who revert everything I post. They claim that only English sources are accepted, though Rabbi Moshe Feinstein specifically forbade anyone from translating his Igerot Moshe. I have sources from the Magen Avram and Rema on the Shulchan Aruch, The Rivash on siman צד, the Igerot Moshe on Even Haezer 4 siman 39, The Yam Shel Shlomo Bava Kama perek ה siman לה and Chulin perek ח siman ד, the Chelkas Mechokek E''H 2:1 Divrei Yatziv by R' Y. Halberstam E.H. 6 and &quot;Yechaveh Da'at&quot; by R' O. Yosef, V 61, the Gra and Yaakov Emden. 

All I request is that there be some indication on a fitting part of this page that people today are treated as if they were Kohanim not because of a Torah commandment- but rather: in order not to cause arguments (darchei shalom). In addition I believe it is logical to assume that it is dishonest for one to quote the halachic opinion of the Rambam regarding Kohanim while at the same time entirely ignore his philosophical opinions about them. Lastly, the Gutnick Chumash in Devarim states that the role of the Kohen will be transfered to the Bechor when the third Beit Hamikdash is built; this too has been completely ignored simply because it comes from Chabad. 

There are statements that are left on the orthodox section of this page that come from Reformed, Conservative and Hebrew sources. There are statements that are left on the orthodox section of this page that are not even sourced at all. There are statements that are left on the orthodox section of this page who's sole authority come from as little as one shule or one Rabbi. Yet, my sources which consist of the most authoritative people in Jewish history are deemed as being outdated, in the wrong language or not popular enough. For instance, I was told that I cannot use the Yam Shel Shlomo (which the Magen Avram in the Shulchan Aruch quotes) or the Rivash because they were too old, the Igerot Moshe because it was in a different language, the Gutnick Chumash because this is &quot;only used by Chabad&quot; and is not popular enough and a YU Rabbi because he is only one Rabbi. Yet, an article about the practice of one modern Rabbi in the middle of no-where who allows women to receive alliyas by having a minyan composed of entirely Kohanim and women- was permitted to be left on and was not deemed to be independent research. 

To conclude; I can only assume that there are personal motivations by a large segment of the orthodox population to maintain whatever belief serves to benefit Kohanim while remove any information that serves as a detriment to them. There is a www.hebrewbooks.org link to all the sources mentioned above and more at the website www.kohen.webs.com   &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Ventura488|Ventura488]] ([[User talk:Ventura488|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Ventura488|contribs]]) 20:35, 2 September 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

&quot;this is not a yeshiva&quot; was what I was told; yet every Jewish section of Wikipedia is like this. For example, see the wiki Kashrut page where the Yoreh Dea is cited over ten times, together with the &quot;invalid hebrew Igerot Moshe&quot; and The Guide for the Perplexed on the philosophical reasons for Kashrut. This was sometimes added by the very same people who removed my sources from the SAME BOOK.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Ventura488|Ventura488]] ([[User talk:Ventura488|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Ventura488|contribs]]) 21:57, 2 September 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:You seem to be placing a lot of [[WP:DUE|undue emphasis]] on some ideas which you manage to support with scholary sources but without a reliable secondary source. For the purposes of this article, I suspect there is plenty of English-language material that could serve as the framework for most of the content. [[User:Jfdwolff|JFW]]&amp;nbsp;|&amp;nbsp;[[User_talk:Jfdwolff|&lt;small&gt;T@lk&lt;/small&gt;]] 22:50, 2 September 2010 (UTC)

::Ventura is correct that today, most &quot;benefits&quot; of Kehuna are because of &quot;darchei shalom&quot; and some imes where there is minimizable monetary loss (terumah and chazeh v'shok, as oposed ot bechor, where the loss is not minimizable) we do not allow modern kohanim to demand these monies. The tamim noraim are coming up and I wont have much time, but I'll try to look at the mar'eh m'komos (sources) that Ventura brought; they should be acceptable secondary sources--albeit printed in Hebrew as opposed to online in English, but [[Wikipedia:V#Non-English_sources]] specifically allows for this. -- [[User:Avraham|Avi]] ([[User talk:Avraham|talk]]) 22:56, 2 September 2010 (UTC)
:::Non-English is fine, but I think we should be at least sticking to mid-20th century or later sources. Given the extremely large number of commentaries written explaining sources like the [[Shulchan Aruch]], it's obvious that it's a complex [[WP:PRIMARY|primary source]] for Jewish law. I think even works like the [[Mishna Berurah]] qualify as complex [[WP:PRIMARY|primary source]]s. [[User:Jayjg|Jayjg ]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;DarkGreen&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Jayjg|(talk)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 03:22, 5 September 2010 (UTC)
::Well, being that the Shulchan Aruch is a condensation of the Bais Yosef which is a commentary on the Arba Turim which was a response to the Mishna Torah, I'm not sure it's a primary source. That's Halakhic history for you; every generation will write commentary on the works of the previous. The Mishnah Berurah is certainly not a primary source, as I have always been taught was that the Chofetz Chaim did not do much innovation but based his rulings on the majority of prior rishonim and acharonim. I'm not sure I'll have time for a while, but there is certainly useful sourcing in what Ventura brings; I'll track it down eventually. -- [[User:Avraham|Avi]] ([[User talk:Avraham|talk]]) 04:00, 5 September 2010 (UTC)
:::Avi, I hate to disagree with you, but they're all quite obviously primary sources of Jewish law. Even the Mishnah Berurah is a primary source; in fact, one of the main criticisms of it is the innovations in it, particularly in favoring written sources over ''minhag hamakom''. [[User:Jayjg|Jayjg ]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;DarkGreen&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Jayjg|(talk)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 04:43, 5 September 2010 (UTC)
::May I quote:
{{quotation|Primary sources  are very close to an event, often accounts written by people who are directly involved, offering an insider's view of an event, a period of history, a work of art, a political decision, and so on. An account of a traffic accident written by a witness is a primary source of information about the accident; similarly, a scientific paper is a primary source about the experiments performed by the authors. Historical documents such as diaries are primary sources.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Secondary sources are second-hand accounts, at least one step removed from an event. They rely for their material on primary sources, often making analytic or evaluative claims about them. For example, a review article that analyzes research papers in a field is a secondary source for the research.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Tertiary sources are publications such as encyclopedias or other compendia that mainly summarize secondary sources. Wikipedia is a tertiary source. Many introductory undergraduate-level textbooks are regarded as tertiary sources because they sum up multiple secondary sources.}}
::If anything, the Mishnah Berurah is at best a secondary source, since almost all rulings are based on previous poskim (even when ''minhag hamakom'' went against accepted poskim, yes 8-) ). Even if for the sake of argument, we deem the Shulchan Aruch or Mishnah Berurah as a primary source, and I will be happy to take this to WT:OR and discuss this, they may still be used to cite prevailing halachic opinion as per WP:OR which states: '''''&quot;A primary source may only be used on Wikipedia to make straightforward, descriptive statements that any educated person, with access to the source but without specialist knowledge, will be able to verify are supported by the source.&quot;'''''' Anyone with a rudimentary knowledge of Hebrew can open up one of these texts and read the words to verify the statements. -- [[User:Avraham|Avi]] ([[User talk:Avraham|talk]]) 05:59, 5 September 2010 (UTC)

www.kohein.com provides much more information on this issue. Many other poskim are also of the opinion that Kohanim today do not have yichus.  see: Magen Avraham 201:4. Y.D. 322 Taz 5 and Shach 9; Sh'elas Ya'avetz 155; Chazon Ish, Shvi'is 5:12. See also Rama O.C. 457:2 and Mishnah Berurah 22. &quot;Divrei Yatziv&quot; by R' Y. Halberstam, E.H. 6; &quot;Yechaveh Da'at&quot; by R' O. Yosef, V 61.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Ventura488|Ventura488]] ([[User talk:Ventura488|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Ventura488|contribs]]) 04:02, 15 September 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:::[[User:Ventura488|Ventura488]] may be [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3AKohen&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=375974763&amp;oldid=375974399 be biased] with his view of the modern Kohen--[[User:חודר לעומר|חודר לעומר]] ([[User talk:חודר לעומר|talk]]) 20:16, 2 September 2011 (UTC)

== Kohen or Kohein? ==

May i suggest the title be changed to Koh'''ei'''n or Koh'''ai'''n? reason being that in Hebrew the vocalization (nekudah) on the &quot;Hey&quot; (&quot;ה&quot;) is always a &quot;[[Zeire|Tzeireh]]&quot; (the &quot;ei&quot; and/or &quot;ay&quot; sound) and never a &quot;[[Segol]]&quot; (the eh sound)[[User:Marecheth Ho&amp;#39;eElohuth|Marecheth Ho&amp;#39;eElohuth]] ([[User talk:Marecheth Ho&amp;#39;eElohuth|talk]]) 18:06, 7 June 2010 (UTC)
:And?  It's dialectical.  Everyone else who knows the term, speaks English, and is not trained in Hebrew linguistics is going to say it's &quot;Kohen&quot;, which makes it common usage.  That's like me saying &quot;Yisrael&quot; should be &quot;Yisroel&quot; because that's how the Ashkenazi Jews pronounce things in Yiddish, and that since Modern Hebrew is a constructed language, what it says doesn't apply. 
:I happen to be a trained [[Orton-Gillingham]] instructor, and while I generally don't use expertise to leverage arguments, in this case it means that I know the mechanics of why a sound does what it does, but it's not specialized knowledge - any reading teacher can do this.  So let's talk about sounds and phonics: 

:In English we have four different constructions that generally make the /ay/ sound, and more if you want to get cute about loamwords.  ai, ay, a-consonant-e, and an open syllable a (usually with a soft c or s like &quot;erase&quot;) all make the sound you want (and I'll leave out &quot;et&quot; in &quot;valet&quot;). However, there are rules as to what comes before and after them as far as spelling is concerned.  &quot;-ain&quot; words (which fit your pattern) are like &quot;brain, train, sprain, paint&quot; etc., which need a consonant blend to come before it, or a &quot;t&quot; to come after it.  If there's an &quot;h&quot;, it still generally can't be by itself unless it's going to use &quot;ane&quot; (&quot;Hanes&quot; is the only thing that comes to mind), and &quot;Kohane&quot; is just not going to fly, because then it doesn't fit the Hebrew if you try to go backwards (doesn't read as a final nun).

:Also, &quot;ei&quot; generally does not say /ay/; it mainly says &quot;e&quot; as in &quot;receive&quot;, which requires a soft c, and only says &quot;ay&quot; when followed by a gh, like &quot;weigh, neigh, sleigh&quot;.  So if we want &quot;ay&quot; we get &quot;Koheighn&quot; as a spelling, which isn't proper English because gh is only followed by t, which then changes the whole piece to &quot;-ate&quot; (&quot;eight&quot;), &quot;ite&quot; (&quot;sleight&quot;), or silent (&quot;ought&quot;).  &quot;Koheight&quot; would therefore be &quot;Kohate&quot;, &quot;Kohite&quot;, or &quot;cot&quot;, none of which are even remotely correct, and also don't read the final nun like it's supposed to be read.  Your choices violate the rules of both languages. [[User:MSJapan|MSJapan]] ([[User talk:MSJapan|talk]]) 22:05, 2 August 2010 (UTC)

::to quote:  ''&quot;-ain&quot; words (which fit your pattern) are like &quot;brain, train, sprain, paint&quot; etc., which need a consonant blend to come before it, or a &quot;t&quot; to come after it. If there's an &quot;h&quot;, it still generally can't be by itself unless it's going to use &quot;ane&quot; (&quot;Hanes&quot; is the only thing that comes to mind)''.
what about Kohain (Kohen is -although used in modern hebrew, perhaps, not proper for encyclopedic knowledge), are there any other folks who would like to share their input?--[[User:Marecheth Ho&amp;#39;eElohuth|Marecheth Ho&amp;#39;eElohuth]] ([[User talk:Marecheth Ho&amp;#39;eElohuth|talk]]) 18:52, 19 November 2010 (UTC)

&quot;A Kohen (or Kohein, Hebrew כֹּהֵן, 'priest', pl. כוהנים, Kohanim) is a Jew who is in direct patrilineal descent from the Biblical Aaron.&quot;

This assumes that a Biblical Aaron actually existed.
It also assumes that no Jew ever took the name Cohen without being directly descended from anyone.
While some may believe this to be so - it cannot be stated as undisputed fact.

The Kohanim were priests.
That's the ONLY undisputable fact regarding Kohanim - and it is only implied in the opening paragraph.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/109.186.57.113|109.186.57.113]] ([[User talk:109.186.57.113|talk]]) 11:49, 12 December 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;


== Page name change ==

Propose change is to ''Kohain''.  

Reasoning: In [[Hebrew]], the vocalization (nekudah) on the &quot;Hey&quot; (&quot;ה&quot;) is a &quot;Tzaireh&quot; (the &quot;ai&quot; sound) and never a &quot;Segol&quot; (the eh sound).  Gentleman, cast please your votes--[[Special:Contributions/108.21.120.5|108.21.120.5]] ([[User talk:108.21.120.5|talk]]) 20:33, 20 February 2011 (UTC)
:Please review the discussion immediately above this one. [[User:Jayjg|Jayjg ]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;DarkGreen&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Jayjg|(talk)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 02:16, 21 February 2011 (UTC)
::That discussion put an effective end to koh'''e'''in, the proposed page name change is to Koh'''a'''in, i.e. the proposed change is from the current Kohen to Kohain--[[Special:Contributions/24.189.57.29|24.189.57.29]] ([[User talk:24.189.57.29|talk]]) 23:55, 21 February 2011 (UTC)
:::&quot;Kohen&quot; gets 2.6 million google hits. &quot;Kohain&quot; gets 38 thousand. Please review [[WP:COMMONNAME]]. [[User:Jayjg|Jayjg ]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;DarkGreen&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Jayjg|(talk)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 02:39, 22 February 2011 (UTC)
::::and? are we to build on common error? if we agree the mechanics of the name change are correct, the spelling of the masses should follow suit--[[User:Marecheth Ho&amp;#39;eElohuth|Marecheth Ho&amp;#39;eElohuth]] ([[User talk:Marecheth Ho&amp;#39;eElohuth|talk]]) 17:56, 22 February 2011 (UTC)
:::::Wikipedia doesn't attempt to &quot;correct&quot; the &quot;erroneous&quot; spellings used by &quot;the masses&quot;. [[WP:COMMONNAME]] is what guides Wikipedia's use of article titles. [[User:Jayjg|Jayjg ]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;DarkGreen&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Jayjg|(talk)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 02:04, 27 February 2011 (UTC)
::::::Encyclopedic articles should be accurate as much as us humans can strive for -I foresee change with the [[WP:COMMONNAME]] policy and with proper contemplation by Ernest contributors I hope sooner than later.--[[User:Marecheth Ho&amp;#39;eElohuth|Marecheth Ho&amp;#39;eElohuth]] ([[User talk:Marecheth Ho&amp;#39;eElohuth|talk]]) 14:26, 3 March 2011 (UTC)


== complete name change ==
By [[WP:COMMONNAME]] many of the names/spellings/refs in this article should be corrected.[[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 00:22, 1 September 2011 (UTC)
:such as?--[[User:חודר לעומר|חודר לעומר]] ([[User talk:חודר לעומר|talk]]) 22:02, 1 September 2011 (UTC)
::Hello, Hadar l'Omar? Can I ask what your username means? &quot;Piercing to Omar&quot;? Mine means &quot;in the blink of an eye.&quot; 
:::The title for a start. It's appropriate to use a foreign language term where scholarly sources use the term, and there is certainly case for using the Hebrew term Kohen in relation to articles on the Kohen family genealogy. However academic sources use the same as the JPS Tanakh, &quot;priest&quot; when discussing the priests of the tabernacle and temples. See e.g. Jacob Neusner ''A Theological Commentary to the Midrash: Sifre to Numbers'' 2001 p56 &quot;X:Vl &quot;...and the priest shall take some of the dust that is on the floor of the tabernacle and put it into the water:&quot; It should be sufficient dirt so that it can be discerned in the water (M. Sot 2:2G]. &quot; for a standard example. There are others. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 02:53, 2 September 2011 (UTC)
::::Hi &quot;in the blink of an eye.&quot;, feel free to ask about my surname once you've got it's pronunciation correct ;-).  
Are you suggesting that we change the page name to [[Priest]] or [[Jewish priest]]? if yes, that is not modern common usage.  (see stats above and [[artscroll]] [[Tanach]] for starters)--[[User:חודר לעומר|חודר לעומר]] ([[User talk:חודר לעומר|talk]]) 19:56, 2 September 2011 (UTC)
::::Besides the name of this article, which you discuss below, are you suggesting any other wording changes? [[User:Jayjg|Jayjg ]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;DarkGreen&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Jayjg|(talk)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 21:31, 5 September 2011 (UTC)

== [[Wikipedia:Naming conventions (use English)]] ==

{{quotation|The title of an article should generally use the version of the name of the subject which is most common in the English language, as you would find it in reliable sources}} [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 02:53, 2 September 2011 (UTC)

{{quotation|If (as will happen occasionally) something else is demonstrably more common in reliable sources for English as a whole, and this is not a question of national varieties of English, use that instead}}--[[User:חודר לעומר|חודר לעומר]] ([[User talk:חודר לעומר|talk]]) 20:08, 2 September 2011 (UTC)
::User חודר לעומר. But that evidently isn't the case here.
::This is not a case of a &quot;national variety of English&quot; since the Jewish Encyclopedia, Encyclopedia Judaica, Jewish Publication Society Tanakh, scholarly works by Jewish University-tenured academics all use the same English terminology for &quot;priest&quot; &quot;priesthood&quot; as other English speakers.
::When talking about the Kohen family/class in rabbinical Judaism, fine, yes clearly the title Kohen applies to a class in rabbinical Judaism who do not offer animal sacrifices in the Temple.
::However when talking about the ''kohenim'' of Baal, the ''kohen'' Melchizedek, the ''kohenim'' of tabernacle, Solomon's Temple, Second Temple, no reliable mainstream source uses the Hebrew word in English language texts. 
::Is there any [[WP:RS]] reason why [[priesthood (Judaism)]] and [[Kohen]] have to be in the same article?
::Further in Israeli publications and on he.wikipedia the Hebrew term כוהן is also used for Hindu etc. priests isn't it?  So why here on en.wikipedia can we not use the same English word as Jewish Encyclopedia, Encyclopedia Judaica, Jewish Publication Society Tanakh, etc.? [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 21:41, 2 September 2011 (UTC)
:::Some non-English words gain significant currency and use in English. &quot;Kohen&quot;, which gets 6.7 million Google hits and 137,000 Google Books hits, is one of those words. [[User:Jayjg|Jayjg ]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;DarkGreen&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Jayjg|(talk)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 21:34, 5 September 2011 (UTC)
:::::Jayjg, you're missing the point ...in regard to '''rabbinical''' kohen, yes. But not in regard to [Israelite priest] which gets 1,130,000. The Jewish Encyclopedia, Encyclopedia Judaica, Jewish Publication Society Tanakh, do not use the word &quot;kohen&quot; for Aaron any more than the &quot;kohenim&quot; of Baal or Dagon. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 22:07, 5 September 2011 (UTC)
::::::It seems where all missing the point here.  What, in other words, is your intention?--[[User:חודר לעומר|חודר לעומר]] ([[User talk:חודר לעומר|talk]]) 21:15, 6 September 2011 (UTC)
:::::::Hello חודר לעומר. The intention I hope of all editors is to follow [[Wikipedia:Naming conventions (use English)]] in regard to both [[priesthood (Ancient Israel)]], where the English word &quot;priest&quot; &quot;priesthood&quot; and English spellings &quot;Aaron&quot; &quot;Moses&quot; are used, and also regarding rabbinical [[Cohen]] families in [[WP:RS]] in English. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 04:36, 7 September 2011 (UTC)
::::::::&quot;Rabbinical kohens&quot; are descendants of Israelite priests - that's why they're called kohens. I don't understand your proposal. [[User:Jayjg|Jayjg ]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;DarkGreen&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Jayjg|(talk)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 23:22, 7 September 2011 (UTC)
:::::::::My proposal is that [[Wikipedia:Naming conventions (use English)]] is followed. This would mean the term &quot;priest&quot; is used for priests in the Tabernacle till Second Temple, &quot;kohen&quot; for rabbinical kohens. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 23:57, 7 September 2011 (UTC)
::::::::::I have just made [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Kohen&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=449042662&amp;oldid=447935038 some edits] following [[Wikipedia:Naming conventions (use English)]]. I have also moved section &quot;High Priest&quot; from rabbincial Judaism into Ancient Israel. And have taken out primary sources from footnotes into text where they occur, which I believe is normal practice where no secondary sources are cited. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 02:12, 8 September 2011 (UTC)
:::::::::::The term &quot;priest&quot; (with dictionaries sourcing the word to mean &quot;elder&quot;) is merely a loose translation of Kohen, and modern translations have by and large adopted that difference (this being in-line with [[Wikipedia:Naming conventions (use English)]] as &quot;Demonstrably more common in reliable sources for English as a whole&quot;).  Note too that a Kohen is qualified and may be young as well as old to be titled such -this being true from the times of [[Ahron]] up till today -whether they where in the Tabernacle till Second Temple era or the modern kohen. (I likewise do not agree with your making changes to the article prior to the completion of this discussion -I propose a revert.)--[[User:חודר לעומר|חודר לעומר]] ([[User talk:חודר לעומר|talk]]) 23:28, 12 September 2011 (UTC)
:::::::::::::Hello חודר לעומר - re &quot;Demonstrably more common in reliable sources for English as a whole&quot; please provide a mainstream English language printed source which uses terms such as &quot;the kohenim of Ancient Israel,&quot; &quot; or &quot;the kohenim in the Maccabean era&quot; etc. Thanks. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 23:46, 12 September 2011 (UTC)
::::::::::::::Hello [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]], please define what you mean by &quot;English language printed source&quot;--[[User:חודר לעומר|חודר לעומר]] ([[User talk:חודר לעומר|talk]]) 22:25, 13 September 2011 (UTC)
::::::::::::::::Hello חודר לעומר  Please see [[Wikipedia:Identifying reliable sources]] [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 00:56, 14 September 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>gzzxms53sjq7fdmliyc0ukyeoagdztt</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
