<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Orthodoxy</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1863950</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517840353</id>
      <parentid>498119451</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-15T01:29:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cab88</username>
        <id>71081</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Confusion about scope of this article */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11063">{{WikiProject Christianity|class=Start|importance=|theology-work-group=yes|theology-importance=}}
{{WikiProject Russia|class=Start|importance=mid|relig=yes}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=Start|importance=Top}}

I'm making some minor revisions on a factual basis, and providing a little more information. Also the extraneous last line of the article is both false and nonsensical. It's removed. --[[User:Kaelus|Kaelus]] 20:06, 9 May 2005 (UTC)

I might also expand the page and provide a detailed treatment of the development of the concept of orthodoxy throughout history, though this will have to be something of an overview; I'm sure there is a wealth of material already available on the respective religion pages (e.g. Islam, Christianity, etc). Are there any objections? --[[User:Kaelus|Kaelus]] 21:11, 9 May 2005 (UTC)

Most of the &quot;Claims to Orthodoxy&quot; section deals with the Christian Churches. Should this be spilt off into it's own section? (And the current section expanded with non-christian orthodoxy) [[User:128.104.114.136|128.104.114.136]] 21:11, 15 May 2005 (UTC)


There is an epistemological problem I can not get any clue on. How comes the word &quot;Orthodox&quot; was used among those to whom it should have resembled &quot;right, true&quot;, and to whom the(Eastern)Orthodox Church(which equals to Orthodox) should have seemed to be schismatic? Russian Orthodox Church believers would not use that term to define themselves nor in direct(since Greek has not that much influence there) neither in translated(in Russia it's not &quot;right thinking&quot; but &quot;right praising&quot;) form, so it doesn't seem that the usage comes from them.

This definition is very Christian-centric. I'm a buddhist and within buddhism we see various claims to orthodoxy, usually from very fixed schools who stick to just the buddhist texts, compared to sects who accept more pagan, indigenous practices and teachings. Shouldn't orthodoxy be a universal term to indicate adherence or not to a certain view of how a belief should be? So you can be an orthodox sioux but what would that mean for you? -skoria 1.30pm 17 October 2006


Hey bud, i dunno about you, but here is how i understand it, and this is how i will explain it.
People say Christianity, and they include many different &quot;terms&quot; when using this such as Catholics, Baptists, Protestants, etc. You get the idea. - Well - its all rubish. Christianity, in its one and true form belongs to Orthodoxy and only Orthodoxy. When Christianity began, it was all Orthodoxy, anfd from there it split. Let me try to explain this step by step.
ONE, and i emphasize that, one of our core themes is that Jesus died on the cross to save all humanity. In knowing he had to do so, he bestowed upon the 11 disciples, Judas was to go on and hang himself shortly after, the right to go teach and preach to people about this. He blessed each one of them, and gave them the knowledge and wisdom to pass down to the next generations. We in the Orthodox chuch call this apostolic doctrine. Our priests, to this day, continue this lineage. We have the blessing from our forefathers which has come from the Disciples, who got it from Christ. Now, some time ago, when these different sections were there, there was a bishop who was teaching some principle. Now, ultimately, all the bishops, except for this guy, got together and came to the conclusion that what he was teaching was incorrect, and told him to rectify his teachings. The Bishop objected, and there became a split in the church. - Where do we see this split? Roman Catholic church was formed from this split, headed by this bishop. So, now we have two branches. Now Orthodox people, they tend to stick to the Orthodox church, but under extreme conditions, we are able to go to a Catholic church and accept communion. Now why is this? Because, even though the split occured with Roman Catholics, they still have what we call the Apostolic Doctrine, hence the lineage. Now within Roman Catholic and Orthodox churches, the priests are priests because they go to seminary and such and learn specific things such as how to read and interpert the Bible, and how to minister to people. - No common person can do this. 
Now here is the kicker. Within the Roman Catholic church, when things started to go wrong, we have people defy the church. Not so much the priests, but the people. The preists knew better, due to their extensive education and handing of knowledge. However when the people revolted, we get splits such as Protestant, Baptists. They call themself Christians, but in actuality, all they believe in is one principle. Christ is their savior..... where in truth, Christianity contains more than this. Another thing is that their preists dont have this linage or 'Apostolic Doctrine' so to speak. And if they claim that they do, well then, here is another point where orthodoxy and catholocism differ, and thats the fact that our priests observe the sacraments, and i dont really see that with these Baptists, Protestants, Non-Denominational, or Penticostal. And even then we have the really messed up people like Jehovah Witnesses and Mormons. So in any case, do some soul searching, find your own groove. I know mine. Any christian, if you're reading this and thinking im bashing you, i honestly ask you to go look at all the complete facts and those roads will lead you inevitably to Orthodoxy. Im not condeming any sect or etc. i'm just spewing forth my opinion and the truths i was taught and have come to find while searching on my own.
Remember, the good book says &quot;You are no one to judge others. Judge and thou shall be judged.&quot; - But i am human and i have my flaws, so if this appears as a bashing, i sincerly apologize.
Your's truly in Christ.

== Emphasis on &quot;Greek&quot; ==

In the sections which discuss Orthodox Christianity, there is too much emphasis using the word &quot;Greek&quot;.  While it is true that in past centuries &quot;greek&quot; was used as a common adjective to describe the Orthodox Church as a whole, today it has too much of a connotation to mean actually Greek, like the church in or from Greece.  There are many parts of the united Orthodox Church that are not Greek (in country of origin or culture.)

Please consider the following revision:

''The word orthodoxy, is usually associated with the Orthodox (Christian) Church which is...'' 

There is no need to mention specific ethnicities in this page (which is more of a launch-point to topics concerning the word ''orthodoxy'' in general, and not meant to be specifically about Orthodox Christianity.)  It may be better to leave out the word &quot;Greek&quot; entirely.

Thanks.

--[[User:Johnmblack|Johnmblack]] 18:22, 31 January 2007 (UTC)

It has nothing to do with ethnicities. Saying &quot;'''Greek''' Orthodox&quot; is like saying &quot;'''Roman''' Catholic.&quot; You don't hear of things like French Catholic. They are just '''Roman''' Catholic. You can say you are Russian Orthodox, and thats fine (and literally correct), but you are still '''&quot;Greek&quot;''' Orthodox. Examples - The historical Church of Greek Constantinople... The New Testament (written originally in Greek). Ancient Greek and Latin are dead languages ...er... but these Church names are historically appropriate (if not a bit misleading when viewed from a modern mind set). It's not implying &quot;Greek&quot; in the ethnic sense at all (the entire concept of nationalism did not even exist until the 17th century). You don't need to be Greek to be Greek Orthodox anymore than an Irishman needs to be Italian to be Roman Catholic. We come here to Wikipedia -amateurs- and assume we are an authority on this or that subject, and we don't realize how ignorant we are about things we are so SURE we are correct about. Like perhaps I'm being right now. Just some food for thought.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Nikoz78|Nikoz78]] ([[User talk:Nikoz78|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Nikoz78|contribs]]) 11:10, 27 July 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Page redirect==
The page [[Orthodox]] is an immediate redirect to [[Orthodoxy#Orthodox Theology]]. I'd recommend simply redirecting [[Orthodoxy]]; suddently finding yourself in the middle of you-don't-know-which-page can be confusing. Thoughts? [[User:Samwaltz|samwaltz]] 17:59, 10 February 2007 (UTC)
:I agree. This just happened to me and for a second I was lost. --[[User:Kimonandreou|Kimon]] 15:03, 19 February 2007 (UTC)
:This is moi? [[User:Orthodoxy|Orthodoxy]]

!!The section on Eastern Orthodox Christians needs to be removed. It is slanted and full of errors.!!!!
==The term's sorigin==
Would anyone elucidate the issue of when the term in question actually first appeared (or to be found) within the Christian context.[[User:Muscovite99|Muscovite99]] ([[User talk:Muscovite99|talk]]) 17:54, 2 February 2008 (UTC)

== Seems POV ==

...&quot;adherence to well researched, well thought out accepted norms&quot;
This sounds POV in favor of orthodoxy. Really the term just means adherence to accepted norms, whether well thought out or not. I think &quot;well researched&quot; and &quot;well thought out&quot; should be remove to be less POV and more accurate.

[[Special:Contributions/209.134.115.80|209.134.115.80]] ([[User talk:209.134.115.80|talk]]) 18:13, 3 February 2011 (UTC)

== Origins of the 'apostasy' or 'heresy' concept ==

The previous version of the article had: , a concept largely unknown before the adoption of Christianity as the [[state religion]] of Rome on February 27, 380 by [[Theodosius I]], see also [[First seven Ecumenical Councils]] and [[State church of the Roman Empire]]

This is incorrect, since the earlier Council of Nicea (325) also had condemned certain groups as heretics, and there are writings by numerous church fathers at least about two hundred years prior to this (during the Roman persecution of Christians), that condemn various 'heretical' or apostatic groups. In any case, the idea of apostasy has no relation to the adoption of Christianity as a state religion.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/168.150.220.1|168.150.220.1]] ([[User talk:168.150.220.1|talk]]) 18:08, 21 May 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Confusion about scope of this article ==

This article is about the concept of &quot;orthodoxy&quot;, an English term that is [[Opposite (semantics)|an antonym]] of [[heterodoxy]], not [[Orthodox Christianity]]. It needs to be rewritten to move that information to the appropriate articles. See [[orthodoxy (disambiguation)]] for explanation. [[User:Editor2020|Editor2020]] ([[User talk:Editor2020|talk]]) 03:34, 18 June 2012 (UTC)
::This articles seem to be solely about religious orthodoxy. The term has been used in a much wider sense as in scientific orthodoxy and political orthodoxy. Either the article should be expanded to cover non-religious orthodoxy or moved to religious orthodoxy. --[[User:Cab88|Cab88]] ([[User talk:Cab88|talk]]) 01:29, 15 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>tuxxm528ijph7zavglb8zzz66ihakyn</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
