<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Magnificat</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>410546</id>
    <revision>
      <id>437245501</id>
      <parentid>436979359</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-07-01T15:38:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Graham87</username>
        <id>194203</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Help:Reverting|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/Cognate247|Cognate247]] ([[User talk:Cognate247|talk]]) to last version by Gerda Arendt</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20887">{{WikiProject Songs|class=Start|auto=inherit|importance=}}
{{ChristianityWikiProject|importance=Low|class=Start|catholicism=yes|catholicism-importance=mid|anglicanism=yes|anglicanism-importance=mid|lutheranism=yes|lutheranism-importance=mid|saints=yes|saints-importance=mid}}

==King James translation==
So, why is King James translation given here? I mean, isn't the King James translation mostly appropriate to articles specifically aimed at conservative Protestants, who have sufficient background in that language to not be put off by its archaic English.

:Leaving aside that the KJV is still the most widely distributed Bible translation, and definitely out of copyright, I still think it remains the best translation for poetic and hymn passages.  If you wish to add another, feel free. - [[User:Ihcoyc|Smerdis of Tlön]] 04:26, 22 Dec 2003 (UTC)

::The KJV is the most relevant for this page since it's the text for most musical settings in English, even up to the present day. (By the way, I believe that the King James version is technically under perpetual crown copyright and will never enter the public domain.) [[User: Doops|Doops]] | [[User_talk:Doops | talk]] 2 July 2005 19:44 (UTC)

:::Wikipedia's [[King James Version of the Bible|article]] makes it sound like that &quot;crown copyright&quot; issue is only relevant in the UK. I'm not sure what this means in terms of Wikipedia's policies, but I would guess that such a small fragment as the Magnificat is still acceptable. &amp;mdash;[[User:HorsePunchKid|&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: monospace; font-variant: small-caps;&quot;&gt;HorsePunchKid&lt;/span&gt;]]&amp;rarr;[[User talk:HorsePunchKid|&lt;span style=&quot;color: #070;&quot;&gt;&amp;#x9F9C;&lt;/span&gt;]] July 2, 2005 20:22 (UTC)
:::P.S. Thanks for the rewrite! I worked on some of the text but was never happy with how I left it. It's starting to look more like a real article now. &lt;tt&gt;:)&lt;/tt&gt; &amp;mdash;[[User:HorsePunchKid|&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: monospace; font-variant: small-caps;&quot;&gt;HorsePunchKid&lt;/span&gt;]]&amp;rarr;[[User talk:HorsePunchKid|&lt;span style=&quot;color: #070;&quot;&gt;&amp;#x9F9C;&lt;/span&gt;]] July 2, 2005 20:25 (UTC)

:I'm going to replace the KJV version with the version from the Anglican Book of Common Prayer, as that is the version that most English versions of the Magnificat (all the ones I've sung, at least) actually use. It's only slightly different, and I assume it's based on the KJV. [[User:DTOx|DTOx]]

::Good call. But I'm going to kill the colons, which are distracting and will be meaningless for most readers. [[User: Doops|Doops]] | [[User_talk:Doops | talk]] 21:07, 20 December 2005 (UTC)
:::If you must, but liturgical colons are part of the BCP and part of this version of the Magnificat. I'd leave them in. [[User:DTOx|DTOx]] 21:17, 20 December 2005 (UTC)
::::H'm. Maybe we can find a away to keep the half-verse marks but make them less visually intrusive. Make them red, perhaps? [[User: Doops|Doops]] | [[User_talk:Doops | talk]] 21:19, 20 December 2005 (UTC)
::::If you really don't like them (I'd still prefer them back in), perhaps someone could write it out so each half verse started a new line and each verse a new paragraph. [[User:DTOx|DTOx]] 14:55, 24 December 2005 (UTC)
:::::I think that whenever the (old) Book of Common Prayer uses a text that differs from the KJV, it's because they have retained texts from the [[Great Bible]].  The Psalms are from that version as well, I believe.  They are all revisions of [[William Tyndale]] in any case, so they are going to resemble one another.  Not sure which version is used in the revised books of common prayer.  [[User:Ihcoyc|Smerdis of Tlön]] 05:12, 21 December 2005 (UTC)

:Do you think we should use, rather than the NAB, the NRSV or another version more widely used than the NAB? As far as I can tell, the NAB is a Bible used only by American Catholics. Once again, I'm taking the initiative and I'm going to replace the NAB translation with the NRSV one. You can always revert my edit if you don't like it. [[User:DTOx|DTOx]] 21:04, 20 December 2005 (UTC)
::I've done it, but I can't get the indentation (as it's presented as poetry) without creating bigger line spacing. If anyone knows how to bring the lines closer together, please do it. [[User:DTOx|DTOx]] 21:13, 20 December 2005 (UTC)
::I like the NRSV version better than the NAB, but the latter is official American English translation used in most countries outside of the Commonwealth, and is the version used in the [[Liturgy of the Hours]] for those countries.  This does not mean that I want it to be changed back, though.  --[[User:Marcusscotus1|Marcusscotus1]] 22:00, 20 December 2005 (UTC)

The Commonwealth?! Did I just step into an Oscar Wilde play? [[Special:Contributions/75.48.19.237|75.48.19.237]] ([[User talk:75.48.19.237|talk]]) 01:50, 22 August 2010 (UTC)

==English translation of the Latin==
I have added Knox version of the Magnificat since it just seems incomplete when the translation present in this article (BCP &amp; NRSV) are from the Greek. It is just justifiable to present a version that is actually from the Latin. If anyone suggest the Douai Version, it is too similar to the BCP so I instead opted for another one. 31 May 2006
:Chances are the version in the BCP ''was'' translated from Latin. But this is starting to get too text-heavy. Really, we should have the Greek original, the Vulgate translation, at most two English versions, perhaps one translated from each language. ''[[User:Csernica|TCC]]'' &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Csernica|(talk)]] [[Special:Contributions/Csernica|(contribs)]]&lt;/small&gt; 03:35, 1 June 2006 (UTC)

I don't think we should include a Hebrew translation (As added March 28, 20090
[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Magnificat&amp;oldid=280279269]).  The list of translations is already longer than I would wish for the front of such an article, and those included are justified only by the historical import of those particular versions within English-speaking Christianity and the other traditions in which the Magnificat had a significant liturgical role.   It's true that Jesus' mother may have spoken this prayer in Aramaic (the common language of Palestine at the time) or even in Hebrew (still used in religious contexts among the the Jews), but the version posted is a modern translation back into Hebrew (a retroversion) or a translation into modern Israeli Hebrew.  It has no claim to antiquity or originality.  The &quot;most original&quot; Magnificat we have is still the Greek text from the gospel of Luke. It may be of interest to specialists to speculate about what sort of semitic constructs may lie behind the Greek, but that would border on &quot;Original Research&quot;, and as such probably does not belong to an Encyclopedia article.  If you think differently, do state your case below.  At the very least we should include publication information on this version (there are a dozen retroversions of the Magnificat into Hebrew), and some justification for its inclusion, being clear that this does not pretend to be an &quot;original&quot; version.  (&quot;A sample Hebrew retroversion, as translated by XYZ in 19??:&quot;)  I do admit the Hebrew translation is interesting, just not here! [[User:Beckersc0t|Beckersc0t]] ([[User talk:Beckersc0t|talk]]) 12:38, 14 April 2009 (UTC)

==Liturgical Use==
This article implied that [[Magnificat (Bach)|J.S. Bach's Magnificat]] was not intended for liturgical use.  However, the piece was performed in a liturgical setting several times during Bach's lifetime (with full orchestra).  It is still occasionally performed during worship services with full orchestra today.  I added the words &quot;most of,&quot; since perhaps later large-scale settings were not intended for liturgical use.[[User:Jkisch|Jkisch]] 17:20, 26 August 2006 (UTC)

== More words? ==

Maybe I'm missing something, but isn't there another line after &quot;Abraham et semini eus in saecula&quot; that goes like this?
&quot;Gloria Patri et Filio et Spiritui Sancto. Sicut erat in principio et nunc et semper et in saecula saeculorum. Amen.&quot;
[[User:Evin290|evin290]] 02:18, 22 March 2007 (UTC)
:Not in St. Luke's Gospel there isn't, no. Not every tradition follows the Gospel text with the doxology. As sung in the Orthodox canon, the lines alternate with the refrain, &quot;More honorable than the Cherubim, and more glorious beyond compare than the Seraphim, without corruption thou gavest birth to God the Word. True Theotokos we magnify thee.&quot; But it would be troublesome and not very informative to the reader to insert all these liturgical flourishes into the text. ''[[User:Csernica|TCC]]'' &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Csernica|(talk)]] [[Special:Contributions/Csernica|(contribs)]]&lt;/small&gt; 03:05, 22 March 2007 (UTC)
:In the interest of clarity, a less technical response to Evin290: those phrases, the [[Gloria Patri]], are added onto the end of the Magnificat, the Nunc Dimittis, and various other canticles when sung liturgically. But they're not actually part thereof. [[User: Doops|Doops]] | [[User_talk:Doops | talk]] 03:13, 22 March 2007 (UTC)

== Magnificat Booklet ==

WP:NOT#ADVERTISING That looks a lot like an advertisement to me; I'd like to see that section deleted. [[User:PatriciaT|PatriciaT]] ([[User talk:PatriciaT|talk]]) 19:49, 26 November 2007 (UTC)

Okay, I'm going ahead with removal of the thing. If you can make the case that this is not advertising, go ahead and restore it. [[User:PatriciaT|PatriciaT]] ([[User talk:PatriciaT|talk]]) 05:56, 20 January 2008 (UTC)

:I'm looking to restore your edit. If there is a car, or a watch, or whatever called Magnificat then this article should try to discuss this issue. Otherwise there should be a disambiguation page and a separate article made for each one. --[[User:CyclePat|CyclePat]] ([[User talk:CyclePat|talk]]) 19:52, 4 July 2008 (UTC)
:I've restore the booklet information and also added some interesting reference regarding trademarks. --[[User:CyclePat|CyclePat]] ([[User talk:CyclePat|talk]]) 21:39, 4 July 2008 (UTC)

This [[Magnificat]] article ought to stay focussed on the canticle. There is already a [[Magnificat (disambiguation)]] page, so you're half-way there already.  Anything non-canticle (e.g. trademarks) should be elsewhere (e.g. [[Magnificat (trademark)]]), referenced from the disambiguation page. Could you do that, CyclePat? Or I could set it up for you if you wish starting with your current material. [[User:Feline Hymnic|Feline Hymnic]] ([[User talk:Feline Hymnic|talk]]) 09:08, 6 July 2008 (UTC)

:Completed. [[User:Feline Hymnic|Feline Hymnic]] ([[User talk:Feline Hymnic|talk]]) 19:01, 11 July 2008 (UTC)
::I disagree, this is a [[WP:CFORK]]. All articles should try to talk about every aspect or POV.  We need to have at least once sentence that describes this aspect of the term Magnificat otherwise we are violating WP:Cfork. --[[User:CyclePat|CyclePat]] ([[User talk:CyclePat|talk]]) 05:24, 21 July 2008 (UTC)
::: This is not an article on the ''term'' 'Magnificat', it's an article on the Lukan text, the hymn of Mary, which went on to play such a large part in the church's liturgical tradition. Other things which take or took their name from the first word of the canticle's Latin text  do not belong in this article, except as a pointer to where they can be discussed on their own terms, and the Wikipedia idiom of a disambiguation page fulfills this function admirably.  Paintings or musical pieces whose main focus is the hymn should get a reference, since they belong to the specific historical influence of the hymn.  The publication referred to in this bullet point (Beginning: &quot;In 1998, a pocket-size monthly booklet entitled Magnificat, published in English...&quot;) is a general liturgical resource, and the web page mentions no specific ongoing tie with Mary's song as opposed to the rest of the liturgical tradition.  For this publication, &quot;Magnificat&quot; is a useful and suggestive name, but the resource is not focused around the canticle.  If you think this particular publication is notable enough for a Wikipedia article, by all means restore the information to the appropriate page, and link from the Magnificat/disambiguation page.  I have removed it. [[User:Beckersc0t|Beckersc0t]] ([[User talk:Beckersc0t|talk]]) 16:23, 16 February 2009 (UTC)

:::: I agree with the deletion performed by Beckersc0t. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 21:58, 16 February 2009 (UTC)

==What Did Gabriel Really Say?==
At no time does Gabriel inform Mary that she IS pregnant.  When Mary asks how it could be possible, he informs of what WILL happen.  Those are his last words.  According to Catholic teaching, Mary does not become pregnant until she agrees.  Mary agrees and Gabriel leaves without saying anything about her pregnancy.  I have changed the text in the article accordingly.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.123.203.164|76.123.203.164]] ([[User talk:76.123.203.164|talk]]) 16:21, 13 December 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Thank you. [[User:Willthacheerleader18|Willthacheerleader18]] ([[User talk:Willthacheerleader18|talk]]) 14:47, 23 July 2010 (UTC)

== The Magnificat sung ==

This section &quot;The Magnificat sung&quot; appeared on December 11. It doesn't seem to serve any real purpose. Shouldn't it simply be deleted?  (Or replaced with something much more substantial that analyses musical settings of the Magnificat, whilst not overlapping with the &quot;Liturgical use&quot; section.) In the absence of further significant developments, can I propose deletion of it in mid-January? [[User:Feline Hymnic|Feline Hymnic]] ([[User talk:Feline Hymnic|talk]]) 22:27, 28 December 2007 (UTC)

== Other Comments ==

I removed the account of the '''prohibition of the Magnificat in Guatemala in the 1980's''' after I failed in a concerted effort to find any support for it.  The book that was previously cited in the article only mentions the prohibition as a means of making an unrelated point and offers no further support for the story. 

The account is found very widely on the internet (in published sermons and in blogs, mostly with reference to Guatemala, sometimes Nicaragua, once even Costa Rica[!]), but never with any further support.  I could find no reference to the law itself, nor any first-hand accounts of the decree or enforcement of such a law. Of course if there was such a prohibition, the evidence should be fairly easy to find for someone close to the events, in which case we can add it back.  At the moment, I consider it a baseless assertion which we should refrain from perpetuating. [[User:Beckersc0t|Beckersc0t]] ([[User talk:Beckersc0t|talk]])

== salutari vs salvatore ==

Google stats:
&quot;in Deo salutari meo&quot;, 50,500 hits [[http://www.google.co.uk/search?hl=en&amp;q=%22in+Deo+salutari+meo%22&amp;btnG=Search&amp;meta=]] 
&quot;in Deo salvatore meo&quot;, 6,720 hits [[http://www.google.co.uk/search?hl=en&amp;source=hp&amp;q=%22in+Deo+salvatore+meo%22&amp;btnG=Google+Search&amp;meta=&amp;aq=f&amp;oq=]]

Google book stats:
&quot;in Deo salutari meo&quot;, 680 hits [[http://books.google.co.uk/books?hl=en&amp;q=%22in%20Deo%20salutari%20meo%22&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;sa=N&amp;tab=wp]] 
&quot;in Deo salvatore meo&quot;, 68 hits [[http://books.google.co.uk/books?hl=en&amp;source=hp&amp;q=%22in%20Deo%20salvatore%20meo%22&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;sa=N&amp;tab=wp]]

Quite clear.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/79.70.116.29|79.70.116.29]] ([[User talk:79.70.116.29|talk]]) 23:25, 15 November 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:No Johnny it is NOT clear. Google is not an official church authority. In fact even the Vatican website has BOTH versions, so I added both refs and the alternate form. Let the discussion end. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 23:53, 15 November 2009 (UTC)

:: No problem, but the book references given by google (10 to 1)  means that &quot;salutari&quot; is more common. [[Special:Contributions/79.70.116.29|79.70.116.29]] ([[User talk:79.70.116.29|talk]]) 00:08, 16 November 2009 (UTC)

===Official Source===
Esoglou recently revised the text to reflect the Nova Vulgata edition, which (perhaps) is the source mentioned in the references. But there is an issue. This year, the new ''Antiphonale'' was published by Solesmes, and its text differs from that printed in the breviary and Nova Vulgata. This &quot;new&quot; text does (or will?) indeed have some official standing in the Ordo Cantus Officii. As I understand it, the Magnificat now has two official texts, one for speaking and another for chanting. I believe that the chanted office could be considered the more &quot;official&quot; version, so you can tentatively count me in the &quot;salutari&quot; as opposed to &quot;savatore&quot; camp, for what it's worth. [[User:Rwflammang|Rwflammang]] ([[User talk:Rwflammang|talk]]) 12:47, 12 July 2010 (UTC)

Some scuttlebut on some liturgy blogs. These are the closest things I have to references so far. : [http://musicasacra.com/forum/comments.php?DiscussionID=2936&amp;page=2] and [http://www.newliturgicalmovement.org/2010/02/antiphonale-romanum-ii.html]. Regards [[User:Rwflammang|Rwflammang]] ([[User talk:Rwflammang|talk]]) 13:12, 12 July 2010 (UTC)

==Languages==
I agree with Esoglou's edit summary that if we open the door to other language then we will have to also have French if we have German, then Italian and eventually many more. Given that this is a long prayer I think Latin and a few English versions are enough. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 23:12, 9 March 2011 (UTC)

:Why not, though?  After all, the German (especially the Luther version) has been used (even more so than the English or the Greek, and 2nd only to the Latin) and (in many respects) is actually a truer translation of the words and meanings of the original Greek than the Latin.  Speaking of the English, I feel we should limit it to the KJV and the most current liturgical usage and (if needs be) the NIV or NRSV, not all five (as it is now).  Besides which, firstly it is '''''not''''' a prayer, but rather a '''''[[Canticle]]'''''; Secondly, there are other Canticles longer than it (the '''''[[Nunc dimittis]]''''' and certainly the '''''[[Te Deum]]''''', for example).  [[User:Dgljr5121973|Dgljr5121973]] ([[User talk:Dgljr5121973|talk]]) 16:33, 10 March 2011 (UTC)

::I like the Malayalam version. But this is the English Wikipedia. [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 16:41, 10 March 2011 (UTC)

:::I agree with Esoglou. I am sorry, given the length of the prayer, I can not agree that the German, French, Italian, Turkish, etc. need to all be here. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 16:45, 10 March 2011 (UTC)

== Italics ==

What is the general Wikipedia rule for the names of songs, canticles, hymns, and prayers?  Are they to be listed in italics or non-italics?  In this article — and others — I noticed some discrepancies.  I was not sure if the differences were intentional or erroneous.  Please advise.  Thanks!   ([[User:Joseph A. Spadaro|Joseph A. Spadaro]] ([[User talk:Joseph A. Spadaro|talk]]) 12:27, 17 May 2011 (UTC))

: I am not sure, but it seems to want them in Italics. But no big deal probably, given that so man factual errors still float around. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 13:21, 17 May 2011 (UTC)

:: Thanks for the reply.  I was just wondering if Wikipedia (in general) — or if either the [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Christianity|WikiProject Christianity]] or the [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Songs|WikiProject Songs]] — had any consistent rules or conventions for this.  Thanks.  ([[User:Joseph A. Spadaro|Joseph A. Spadaro]] ([[User talk:Joseph A. Spadaro|talk]]) 18:34, 23 May 2011 (UTC))

== Music and liturgy ==

I just added a German Magnificat for liturgical use, but wonder about starting a new section for the compositions, because some are also performed in concert. --[[User:Gerda Arendt|Gerda Arendt]] ([[User talk:Gerda Arendt|talk]]) 13:15, 27 June 2011 (UTC)

:I do not know much about its use in compositions, but I have seen your edits around and you seem to know the topic. So maybe that way I will learn it. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 13:31, 27 June 2011 (UTC)

::Ok, I see the section now. How about some references so we will not get a citation flag on it next week. Thanks. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 13:48, 27 June 2011 (UTC)

:::Nothing in it which was not there before, to be expanded. An article on the piece itself, Magnificat of Bach and Bruckner, should be a ref. My time is limited, I just came here for the new Bach cantata, but the Rutter Magnificat is also on my todolist, --[[User:Gerda Arendt|Gerda Arendt]] ([[User talk:Gerda Arendt|talk]]) 14:26, 27 June 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>342idev82y2o1zzwwoaahmnzkreu6t6</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
