<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Monotheism</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>20662</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520021739</id>
      <parentid>510259309</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-26T21:17:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BelalSaid</username>
        <id>17696835</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="43439">{{talkheader}}
{{ChristianityWikiProject|importance=Low|class=c}}
{{WPReligion|class=c|importance=Top}}

==the introduction==

please exclude &quot;advaita, dvaita and visishtadvaita&quot; out. Monotheism isn't just the belief in one God. Pantheism and Monism and several other forms of theisms also believe in &quot;one God&quot;. The word &quot;God&quot; has numerous definitions. Monotheism is characterized by Abrahamic religions. Advaita, Dvaita, Visishtadvaita are all philosophical schools of thought and none of them fall within Monotheism. Advaita is Monism, Visishtadvaita is Qualified Monism and Dvaita perhaps is arguably Monotheism. But that is not the case because within it as well there are multiple Gods and Goddesses who have a heirarchy in which Vishnu stands the Highest. These Gods and Goddesses are represented by idols. They are anthropomorphic-zoomorphic. They copulate and reproduce. They interact with each other. Sometimes engaging in fights etc. They manifest to ordinary mortals also. These are all considered to be against Monotheism. Therefore it is improper and misleading to include them. Furthermore in the Dvaita tradition, its founder, Madhvacharya, is considered to be an incarnation of Vayu or Hanuman, who is a God but subordinate to Vishnu along with others.

Monotheism is the belief in a single God. There is a strict distinction between the Creator and creation. No images are allowed. God is single, with a unity is His being, and without any likeness. Jews and Muslims speak of God, Yahweh or Allah, as a single God. A Supreme Being. And would see the aforementioned Hindu beliefs as idolatry, polytheism and heresy.

In the Puranas, the Hindu Gods and Goddesses command each other, usually the respective Deities who are central to a specific Purana being superior and the others being inferior. Like for example in the Shiva Purana, Shiva commands Brahma and Vishnu and they obediently oblige to his authority and supremacy. Whereas in the Devi Bhagavata Purana, Durga says all other Gods are created by her and are all due to her lila(divine play) etc

Therefore it is beyond any doubr that atleast these schools of thought within Hinduism do not fall under Monotheism.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/175.156.15.127|175.156.15.127]] ([[User talk:175.156.15.127|talk]]) 09:39, 6 December 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Subjective vs Objective comments==

I would stay away from comments like this:

the distinction between worshipping the divine nature of Jesus but not the human nature of Jesus can be difficult for non-Christians (and even Christian laity) to follow.

Personally, I find all the -isms confusing.  —Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/205.167.198.121|205.167.198.121]] ([[User talk:205.167.198.121|talk]]) 17:53, 9 September 2008 (UTC)&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Deaism==
Does not Deaism (as can be defined at ( http://www.mother-god.com/catechism.html ) deserve a place here somewhere? As well perhaps in other articles, such as the one for God?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/99.199.90.38|99.199.90.38]] ([[User talk:99.199.90.38|talk]]) 15:29, 24 December 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== whether to include &quot;oneness of a God&quot; in the definition ==

In [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Monotheism&amp;diff=237935945&amp;oldid=237820686 this edit], EGMichaels changed the opening definition &quot;from the belief in the existence of one [[deity]], or in the [[Oneness (concept)|oneness]] of a God&quot; to &quot;the belief that only one [[Deity]] exists&quot;, with the edit summary &quot;Corrected the meaning of the term&quot;.  But the original wording was a direct quote from the given source, Encyclopedia Brittanica.  I don't know whether Brittanica is correct, but we should either use their definition or use a different source.  --[[User:Amcbride|Allen]] ([[User talk:Amcbride|talk]]) 20:41, 30 September 2008 (UTC)

Monotheism does not deny existance of other gods, but emphasises the importance of one over all others. This should be included in your definitions. [[Special:Contributions/67.183.157.148|67.183.157.148]] ([[User talk:67.183.157.148|talk]]) 06:21, 25 May 2010 (UTC)
EDIT: Christianity, Islam, and Mosaicity (Judaism) are not monotheistic but are [[monolatrism|monolatric]]. [[Special:Contributions/67.183.157.148|67.183.157.148]] ([[User talk:67.183.157.148|talk]]) 07:41, 26 May 2010 (UTC)

== This is not a scholarly article ==

Any enclypopedia article is supposed to reflect the latest scholarly research. Here the author accepts traditionalist dating of biblical authorship, which is now comprehensively rejected by both Jewish and Christian scholars. The author betrays his literalist position with the passage 'if Deuteronomy is taken as part of the original text as it generally is by those who use it as scripture'. This is a statement of faith, not fact. Scholars date Deuteronomy centuries later. Similaraly he quotes from the prophet Isaiah to demonstrate that the Bible predates Zoroastrian monotheism. In fact Chapter 44, from which he quotes, has long been ascribed to a second author (Deutero Isaiah), who was writing after the Babylonian empire had been destroyed by Cyrus in 537 BCE. By this time Hebrew religion had been heavily influenced by Mesopotamian and Persian religion. Deutero Isaiah's hymn of joy 'Every valley shall be exalted and every mountain and hill made low' could just as well have been written by Zoroaster himself. Doubters are refered to Norman Cohn's authoratitive Cosmos, Chaos and the World to Come. Yale 2001. 

This article contrasts sharply with other scholarly Wiki offerings on religious developments in this early period.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/82.6.96.248|82.6.96.248]] ([[User talk:82.6.96.248|talk]]) 16:54, 13 May 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Zoroaster Not a Monotheist ==

I removed the demonstrably untrue statement that suggested Zoroaster could have been the first monotheist. Zoroastrianism was explicitly a dualist religion. Zurvanism is often confused with Zoroastrianism but was NOT the doctrine of the Gathas. CF Boyce *History of Zoroastrianism* [[User:Yonderboy|Yonderboy]] ([[User talk:Yonderboy|talk]]) 08:06, 14 October 2009 (UTC)

Oh PS looks like time to archive this discussion page... [[User:Yonderboy|Yonderboy]] ([[User talk:Yonderboy|talk]]) 08:06, 14 October 2009 (UTC)

== Zoroaster was a Monotheist ==

Dear people who are ignorant about the subject, please stop trying to change the facts.

There is less dualism in Zoroastrianism than in Christianism. Indeed, there is no &quot;devil&quot; in Zoroastrianism. The &quot;devil&quot; is &quot;Ahriman&quot;, which is actually an &quot;evil spirit&quot;. It faces &quot;Spenta Minyiu&quot;, which is the &quot;good spirit&quot; (but not God). So the &quot;evil spirit&quot; does not confront God. God is the only supreme Being and its aspects are represented by the seven angels and by the good spirit. Against this good spirit, there is an evil spirit, that man cultivates by doing bad things (cheating, lying, killing, etc.) Man can cultivate this spirit because God created the man free, so it's the man's role to choose between good and bad. 

Then, there is no reference to &quot;OTHER AHURAS&quot; in the Gathas. This &quot;other Ahuras&quot; should actually be translated into &quot;the ahuric rays&quot; (the 7 angels). The ONE and ONLY divinity accepted by Zoroaster was Ahura Mazda, The Only Creator. 
The sentence &quot;You are The Mightiest Ahura&quot; is actually &quot;You are the Mightiest, Ahura Mazda !&quot; exactly like Muslims say &quot;Allah Akbar&quot; saying &quot;Allah is The GreatEST&quot;. It only means that there is nothing better than God.

The word &quot;Yazata&quot; is not used one single time in the Gathas.

The &quot;fake gods&quot; is the translation of &quot;daeva&quot;, word that still exists in our current Persian (deev) meaning &quot;demon&quot;. &quot;Fake gods&quot; is a translation based on the Bible, where the idols, etc. are called &quot;fake gods&quot;.

So the one who says Zoroastrianism isn't monotheistic by bringing these irrational and incoherent arguments should also go and claim the Abrahamic religions are not monotheistic. 

&quot;Additionally, the Zoroastrian faith includes characteristics different from those found in purely monotheistic worldviews, including the acknowledgment of subordinate nature-spirits and the aspect of the fire being very holy.&quot;
Come on, most experts claim that your &quot;purely monotheistic worldviews&quot; directly come from Zoroastrianism http://www.religioustolerance.org/zoroastr.htm
http://www.buzzle.com/articles/zoroastrianism-the-foundation-of-monotheism.html

Fire is VERY holy ? No, fire is just holy because it is a symbol of light and pureness. In the later Avestan writings (Yasht), the spirit symbolizing it (Arta) is not even quoted as an &quot;angel&quot; or &quot;yazata&quot;. 
Acknowledgment of subordinate nature-spirits ? It is the opposite. Before Zoroastrianism, Iranians (Aryans) venerated nature-spirits like Anahita, etc. Zoroaster came and changed this and did not want anyone to venerate any nature-spirits anymore, it's actually them he called &quot;daevas&quot;. 

If you don't know the subject, please stop writing articles. Thank you very much and best regards.

--[[User:RaheZartosht|RaheZartosht]] ([[User talk:RaheZartosht|talk]]) 11:53, 31 October 2009 (UTC)

:I have not edited that section and I have not yet reviewed it. However, it really does not matter what editors think, what matters is what experts think and statements made supported by [[WP:RS|reliable references]]. If you have them, use them. IF you don't, then it is just bantering opinions, which is not fruitful. -&lt;sup&gt;[[user:Storm Rider|'''''&lt;font color=&quot;01796F&quot;&gt;Storm&lt;/font&gt;''''']]&lt;/sup&gt;[[User talk:Storm Rider#top|'''''&lt;font color=&quot;1C39BB&quot;&gt;Rider&lt;/font&gt;''''']] 13:07, 31 October 2009 (UTC)


:Are there better sources than http://www.religioustolerance.org/zoroastr.htm and http://www.buzzle.com/articles/zoroastrianism-the-foundation-of-monotheism.html ? Neither seem to fulfill [[WP:RS]]. [[User:Gabbe|Gabbe]] ([[User talk:Gabbe|talk]]) 09:01, 4 December 2009 (UTC)

== Source about monotheism or pantheism of Zoroaster ==
Please give a source about [[Zoroastrianism]] being pantheic or monotheic.
In the following source monotheism is evident. 

from [http://altreligion.about.com/od/importanthistoricalpeople/a/zoroaster.htm]:
: Zoroaster’s teachings were a sharp break with previous local traditions, including:
* Ahura Mazda was the only god to be worshipped. The previous tradition was polytheistic.
* Wisdom being a defining trait of the new supreme god. Traditionally, local gods were nature-gods primarily defined by strength and power.
* The new religion was to be a religion of righteousness. It specifically focused on correct living and genuine piety rather than stringent ritual aimed at placating the gods.

Please correct me if I am wrong. It seems to me that early Zoroastrianism could be different to what practised later ([[Sassanid]]s)
[[User:Sohale|Sohale]] ([[User talk:Sohale|talk]]) 22:36, 20 May 2010 (UTC)

== Hebrew Bible and monotheism ==

I shorted the first paragraph, but the entire section needs to be edited - it's far too long and diffuse. I think, if I were writing it fro scratch, I'd set out the gradual development of monotheism from polytheism, beginning with those passages in Psalms and elsewhere which are clearly polytheistic, then discussing the development of monolatry in passages such as the [[shema]], and finally the emergence of genuine monotheism in the Persian period. I'd also discuss the forces which formed this history - the original Levantine pantheon, the emergence of Yahweh as the god of Israel in the late 7th century, and the impact of the Josianic reforms and then the Bablylonian and Persian period. But perhaps the first step really is to identify sources? - Anchor Bible Dictionary, Day, that sort of thing. [[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 04:04, 5 December 2009 (UTC)

:This is someone else &quot;editing&quot; but I just want to say that this is completely true and Zorastrianism is in fact the first monotheistic religion  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/71.66.251.49|71.66.251.49]] ([[User talk:71.66.251.49|talk]]) 15:57, 6 December 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

::I believe you're probably right, but you'll need a good source to support that. By the way, there were strong elements of quasi-monotheism in ancient Egypt and elsewhere too (actually henotheism and monolatry). Plus perhaps worth mentioning that Islam doesn't regard Christianity as a monotheistic religion. All this needs to be covered. [[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 21:54, 6 December 2009 (UTC)

== Christian View? ==

At the end it say: &quot;Some groups that are self-identified as Christians eschew orthodox theology; such as the Jehovah's Witnesses, Mormonism, Oneness Pentecostals, the Unitarians, Christadelphians, Church of God General Conference (Abrahamic Faith), Socinian and some of the Radical Reformers (Anabaptists), do not teach the doctrine of the Trinity at all.&quot;
Are not all Christian groups &quot;self-identified&quot;? Why are we say that some are Christian and some are only &quot;self-identified&quot;?--[[User:Lord Don-Jam|Lord Don-Jam]] ([[User talk:Lord Don-Jam|talk]]) 02:16, 9 January 2010 (UTC)

:That does sound a great deal as if someone is writing from a particular perspective. I am going to be [[WP:BOLD|bold]] and change it to read, &quot;Some Christians eschew orthodox theology...--&lt;sup&gt;[[user:Storm Rider|'''''&lt;font color=&quot;01796F&quot;&gt;Storm&lt;/font&gt;''''']]&lt;/sup&gt;[[User talk:Storm Rider#top|'''''&lt;font color=&quot;1C39BB&quot;&gt;Rider&lt;/font&gt;''''']] 02:48, 9 January 2010 (UTC)

::I think that &quot;eschew orthodox theology&quot; may also seem to be coming from a particular perspective by some.--[[User:Lord Don-Jam|Lord Don-Jam]] ([[User talk:Lord Don-Jam|talk]]) 18:30, 11 January 2010 (UTC)

you should be even bolder and remove such obviously essayish bits. If it isn't clearly encyclopedic and clearly dealing with monotheism, it needs to go. This article is a pov-magnet as it is. --[[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|(𒁳)]]&lt;/small&gt; 13:09, 23 January 2010 (UTC)

===Is Christianity Monotheistic?===

Monotheism means believing that there is only one God. Leaving aside the question of the Trinity, if Christians believe in other spiritual powers whether good (eg angels) or evil (eg demons) how can they be said to be monotheistic? Isn't Satan a kind of evil god? Or does being a monotheist  depend on whether you worship such an entity or not, rather than believing in its existence? I find this perplexing.[[Special:Contributions/188.141.24.109|188.141.24.109]] ([[User talk:188.141.24.109|talk]]) 22:57, 20 April 2010 (UTC)
:Monotheists such as Jews and Christians believes in an Almighty God who never had and will never have any '''peer'''. [http://bible.cc/psalms/82-6.htm Psalms 82:6 is one of several scriptures which refer to angels as &quot;gods&quot; to emphasize that a mere angel (literally &quot;messenger&quot;) of the biblical God is as powerful as any of the so-called gods of the pagans.]&lt;br /&gt;--[[User:AuthorityTam|AuthorityTam]] ([[User talk:AuthorityTam|talk]]) 01:24, 21 April 2010 (UTC)
:...and yet recognises the existance of other gods. There does not exist any religion that believes that only one god '''exists'''. Insistance upon the superiority of a god should not be rewritten as belief in the existance of one god, regardless of what the lay person has been taught or believes. [[Special:Contributions/67.183.157.148|67.183.157.148]] ([[User talk:67.183.157.148|talk]]) 06:24, 25 May 2010 (UTC)
::You are confusing &quot;monotheism&quot; and [[henotheism]]. [[User:Beeswaxcandle|Beeswaxcandle]] ([[User talk:Beeswaxcandle|talk]]) 08:51, 25 May 2010 (UTC)
:::Christianity is more henotheistic than monotheistic, but still is [[monolatrism|monolatric]]. That monotheistic religions even exist is a misconception by the masses--which does not make it correct. Though common education is made avaliable today, common belief does not supercede fact. [[Special:Contributions/67.183.157.148|67.183.157.148]] ([[User talk:67.183.157.148|talk]]) 07:33, 26 May 2010 (UTC)

I also have concluded, in my unstudied manner, that modern Christianity is not monotheistic but dualistic as much (perhaps more than half) of the world's events are attributed to Satan.  One could objectively quantify this by questioning Christians not on their dogma but on their interpretation of the ultimate causes of their worlds -- I would guess that those in my childhood Nazarene church would attribute far more of the world to Satan than to God.  It seems that to modern Christians God is only the God of Good and Love, and has been separated from the terrible events of the world that the Old Testament God, and perhaps the American God-to-be-feared of only several generations ago.  As I see it, somebody has to pick up the causal slack, and once again old Lucifer is willing to do the dirty work, and so most Christians now are solidly dualistic.  I guess this argument suggests that one can define a god by duck-typing rather than questioning one's explicit belief structure in abstract terms: if it quacks like a God, walks a God, and swims like a God, it is a God.
[[Special:Contributions/75.174.90.61|75.174.90.61]] ([[User talk:75.174.90.61|talk]]) 01:38, 25 August 2011 (UTC)




== Only one faith of one God can exist? ==

Is there any truly monotheistic religion in the world, which is NOT derived from or connected to the YHWH faith? It appears that all proven unconnected faiths, like hindi, buddhism, shinto, maya, inca, australian aboriginal, etc. are all politheistic.

I would guess that jews' claim to be the one and only &quot;chosen people&quot; means, if true, that there cannot exist any monotheistic religion besides YHWH faith and its derivatives? [[Special:Contributions/91.83.16.58|91.83.16.58]] ([[User talk:91.83.16.58|talk]]) 23:10, 6 February 2010 (UTC)

Monotheism is not a &quot;faith&quot;, it is a theological position.
It is the very simple concept that the an absolute notion of a &quot;supreme being&quot; is meaningful and that it does have an application to a real being. 
What sort of &quot;faith&quot; you want to attach to that, i.e. worship, celebration, prayer, folklore, claims of incarnations, avatars, historical miracles or what have you goes beyond the theological claim. These are other aspects of religion unrelated to whether the religion under consideration is monotheistic.

So yes, there is only one kind of monotheism in the same sense that there is only one kind of proton. If you come up with another 'sort of proton', you should call it something different. While there is only a single concept of monotheism, there are of course any number of religions that are monotheistic, because any religion is much more than its mere theology. --[[User:Dbachmann|dab]] &lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Dbachmann|(𒁳)]]&lt;/small&gt; 17:52, 8 February 2010 (UTC)

::This is not an answer! The question was: did monotheism develop anywhere else in the world, in a way that had proven absolutely no connection to jews and their YHWH faith? For an absurd example, did the antarctican penguins develop monotheism millenia before any explorers arrived? It does appear there is no monotheistic religion on Earth, which is proven underived from the YWHW / Moses system!

::The thing that comes nearest, the short-lived egyptian Sun God religion, artificially created by the pharaoh to unseat the politheistic prist class, appears to be a direct copycat of the YHWH faith as practiced by the jews in egyptian captivity.

::The wikipedia article should make it very clear whether or not there exist any created-from-zero monotheistic religion, which is proven unconnected to the faith of Abraham, Isaac and Jacob. This is a totally important issue! [[Special:Contributions/91.82.34.6|91.82.34.6]] ([[User talk:91.82.34.6|talk]]) 20:30, 20 February 2010 (UTC)

:::This is an academic question, but one example of a monotheistic religion that predates the Abrahamic religions is [[Zoroastrianism]]. In fact, some scholars state very clearly that Zoroastrianism influenced the Abrahamic religion. Which was the very first monotheistic religion? You might want to read ''The Great Transformation - The Beginning of our Religious Traditions'' by Karen Armstrong. Monotheism is one of its topics. I hope this helps. --&lt;sup&gt;[[user:Storm Rider|'''''&lt;font color=&quot;01796F&quot;&gt;Storm&lt;/font&gt;''''']]&lt;/sup&gt;[[User talk:Storm Rider#top|'''''&lt;font color=&quot;1C39BB&quot;&gt;Rider&lt;/font&gt;''''']] 21:07, 20 February 2010 (UTC)

::::How does 5th century BCE predate monotheism???[[User:EGMichaels|EGMichaels]] ([[User talk:EGMichaels|talk]]) 03:29, 21 February 2010 (UTC)

There was the short-lived reform by Pharaoh [[Akhenaten]] in Egypt, who made [[Aten]] (the sun disc) the only god. It is unclear whether it predates Judaism or not, and connections between them are debated. Contrary to what the anon said, this was not fully artificially created, since the solar aspects of religion became already more and more emphasized under Akhenaten's predecessors, it's only that the solar religion reached its pinnacle under his reign. – [[User:Alensha|&lt;span style=&quot;color: #008ea1&quot;&gt;Alensha&lt;/span&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Alensha|&lt;span style=&quot;color: #008ea1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 00:03, 27 February 2010 (UTC)

:::::You will find that some scholars debate the monotheism of early Judaism. I am not reflecting my own opinion but the statements of scholars as I remember them or as I read them. --&lt;sup&gt;[[user:Storm Rider|'''''&lt;font color=&quot;01796F&quot;&gt;Storm&lt;/font&gt;''''']]&lt;/sup&gt;[[User talk:Storm Rider#top|'''''&lt;font color=&quot;1C39BB&quot;&gt;Rider&lt;/font&gt;''''']] 00:14, 27 February 2010 (UTC)

== First Monotheistic Religion &amp; History of Monotheism ==

I have two matters to bring up about this page.

The first is a question: what is the first monotheistic religion? When I was younger, I was under the impression that [[Judaism]] was the first religion to believe in only one god, or at least the first one to have any sort of broad significance (by which I mean that, although statistically Judaism has always had a relatively small percentage of followers, its derived religions [[Christianity]] and [[Islam]] have had huge influences on the world). Then I learned of [[Zoroastrianism]], which I was told had influenced many of the beliefs of Judaism. Which religion came first, Judaism or Zoroastrianism? And were they possibly preceded by a less prominent monotheistic religion?

The second issue I'd like to bring up is a suggestion: I think it would be a good idea to have a section detailing the history of monotheism. Any feedback regarding this would be nice.

--[[User:SelfDevouringSnake|The Self Devouring Snake.]] ([[User talk:SelfDevouringSnake|talk]]) 23:13, 1 May 2010 (UTC)

== Krishna ==

It should be stated that the majority of Vaishnavites believe in Vishnu as the supreme God. The post on Krishna is a purely ISKCON perspective.[[User:Domsta333|Domsta333]] ([[User talk:Domsta333|talk]]) 10:32, 26 July 2010 (UTC)

==Oneness Pentacostal under 'christianviews'==

&quot;The Oneness Pentecostals believe the doctrine of the Trinity is not orthodox theology, and they adhere to the teachings of the Apostles from the times of the New Testament writings before the Council of Nicaea, which taught that God is a Spirit and is one, and Jesus was the visible manifestation of that Spirit&quot;

This obvious POV, as well as factually in error, I am editing to something along the lines that 'Oneness Pentecostals accept the deity of the Father, the Son, and The Holy Spirit they beleive that there is one God, a singular spirit who manifests himself in many different ways, including as the Father, the Son and the Holy Spirit. This contrasts with the creedal formulation of three distinct and eternal persons in one being'. This info is off of the 1nes pentecostal intro so assume it is correct, the 'teachings of the apostles from the NT' and '''God is a spirit and is one, Jesus is a manifestation of said God''' is an interpretation, it may or may not be true, but it is an opinion. And also as for 'ante-nicaea writings' there was far from unanimity ast to the nature of the relationship with God and JC, there were theologies of every kind including proto-trinity like Origen, modalist (sim. to oneness) like sabellius, and arian with its namesake and probably a plethora of other theologies. a side note 'orthodox' is also not the best word as today it connotes 'traditional' as opposed to back then orthodox meant within acceptable range of beliefs, today unorthodox means untraditional rather than condemned. before the pertinent creeds both arianism and sabellianism were 'orthodox'[[User:Enedra|Enedra]] ([[User talk:Enedra|talk]]) 20:53, 26 September 2010 (UTC)

==Rewrite urgently required==
Parts of the article lack any syntactical structure, parsing or punctuation, rendering the overall sense of the subject-matter and intent of the author(s) opaque in the extreme.  [[Special:Contributions/86.138.117.138|86.138.117.138]] ([[User talk:86.138.117.138|talk]]) 19:18, 24 March 2011 (UTC)
:This is especially true for the section &quot;Siberian traditions&quot;. I am shocked by the fact that its first sentence, a totally uncomperehensible concatination of English words, has been virtually unchanched since the 4th of December 2010. The remainder of the section is hardly any better, consisting of completely ungrammatical sentences. Additionally, even the little bit of content that seems to be extractable from this gibberish lacks any citations and is not supported by the main article that the section links to, so that it might well completely contradict the facts too. The following section (&quot;Indigenous American tradition&quot;) consists of one uncited fact followed by one grammatically flawed sentence without any relevant content. Hence I decided to provisionally make these two sections invisible by HTML-comment brackets. They should either be completely rewritten or be permanently removed. [[User:Marcos|Marcos]] ([[User talk:Marcos|talk]]) 12:31, 6 May 2011 (UTC)

== Content from &quot;Unity&quot; ==

The following has been removed from the [[WP:COATRACK|coat-rack]] article [[Unity]]. It talks about &quot;oneness of God&quot;, a term which currently redirects here. (References have been inlined to avoid having side-effects on this talk page.) I hope someone will take the time to examine this material, extract anything that can add value, and include it in this (or another) article. -- [[User:Perey|Perey]] ([[User talk:Perey|talk]]) 14:46, 7 July 2011 (UTC)

:Within the [[Ahmadiyya]] understanding of [[Islam]], the Islamic concept of Unity of God, often referred to as ''Oneness of God'', in application to humans, inculcates in man the realisation of the oneness of the human species, and does away with all such barriers as divide man into racial, ethnic and colour denominations. This gives birth to the universal concept of equality in Islam. Hence from the vantage point of God, all human beings, wherever and in whichever age they were born, stand equal in His sight. {{cite web|url=http://www.alislam.org/books/study-of-islam/unity.html|title=THE BELIEF IN THE UNITY OF GOD|accessdate=2 September 2010}}

:The [[Qur'an]] views that in the history of mankind prophets or messengers were sent to every nation or society to guide people towards God in every age. For this reason, with support from theological study, Ahmadis recognise many of the world faiths as having divine origin and their founders as divinely appointed individuals, such as [[Zoroaster]], [[Buddha]], [[Krishna]] and [[Confucius]]. The founder of the Ahmadiyya community, [[Mirza Ghulam Ahmad]] explained how the teachings of various faiths all converged to Islam as a universal religion. {{cite web|url=http://www.alislam.org/introduction/index.html|title=An Overview|accessdate=6 September 2010}}

:Three core assertions of the [[Bahá'í Faith]], sometimes termed the &quot;three onenesses&quot;, are central in the teachings of the religion. They are the ''Oneness of God'', the ''Oneness of Religion'' and the ''Oneness of Humanity''. {{cite encyclopedia| last = Hutter | first = Manfred | editor = Ed. Lindsay Jones | encyclopedia = Encyclopedia of Religion | title = Bahā'īs | edition = 2nd ed. | year = 2005 | publisher = Macmillan Reference USA | volume = 2 | location = Detroit | id = ISBN 0-02-865733-0 | pages = 737&amp;ndash;740}}

:They are also referred to as the unity of [[God]], unity of [[religion]], and unity of [[human|mankind]].  The Bahá'í writings state that there is a single, all powerful [[deity|God]], revealing his message through a series of [[Manifestation of God|divine messengers]] or educators, regarding them as one progressively revealed [[religion]], to one single humanity, who all possess a rational [[Soul (spirit)|soul]] and only differ according to colour and culture.  This idea is fundamental not only to explaining Bahá'í beliefs, but explaining the attitude Bahá'ís have towards other religions, which they regard as divinely inspired.  The acceptance of every race and culture in the world has brought [[Bahá'í Faith#Demographics|Bahá'í demographics]] an incredible diversity, becoming the second most widespread faith in the world, and translating its literature into over 800 languages. {{cite encyclopedia | year = 1988 | title = The Bahá'í Faith | encyclopedia = Britannica Book of the Year | publisher = Encyclopaedia Britannica | location = Chicago | id = ISBN 0-85229-486-7}} {{cite web | url = http://www.bahai.us/bahai-writings | accessdate = 2006-08-03 | title=Bahá'í scripture | author = The National Spiritual Assembly of the Baha'is of the United States | publisher = bahai.us | year = 2006 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060805232229/http://www.bahai.us/bahai-writings &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-08-05}}

:In Kabbalah, unity amongst people is a method for achieving spirituality. Kabbalist [[Yehuda Ashlag]] stated in his article, &quot;Unity of Friends,&quot; that “the important thing that stands before you today is the unity of friends. Toil in that more and more, for it can compensate for all the faults.” His son, Kabbalist [[Baruch Ashlag]], also emphasized a method among friends that involved unity to reach the spiritual. {{cite web|url=http://www.kabbalah.info/eng/content/view/frame/58560?/eng/content/view/full/58560&amp;main |title=Society as a Condition for Attaining Spirituality |accessdate=2009-06-11 |last=Ashlag |first=Yehuda |work=www.kabbalah.info |publisher=Laitman Publishing }}

:In previous generations Kabbalists such as Rav [[Abraham Kook]] argued that the affirmation of [[God]] aspires to reveal unity in the world as it is the basis of all spiritual knowledge and one the highest notions which mankind can perceive. (Abraham Isaac Kook: The lights of penitence, The moral principles, Lights of holiness, essays, letters, and poems By Abraham Isaac Kook, Translated by Ben Zion Bokser, Published by Paulist)

== Was Islam a &quot;reaction&quot; to  Judaism and Christianity ? ==

In the &quot;Abrahamic religions&quot; section, the author suggested that islam was a reaction to Judaism and Christianity. However, this needs to be historically proved. &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:198.36.39.1|198.36.39.1]] ([[User talk:198.36.39.1|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/198.36.39.1|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;
:First, there are multiple authors in almost all articles.  Second, the Qur'an and traditional Islamic stories admit that Muhammed was born well after Judaism and Christianity were around, and that he was exposed to both religions before having his revelation.  Whether the reaction was human or divine, Islam came about as a response to the then-current state of Judaism and Christianity.  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 13:41, 29 September 2011 (UTC)

First of all Islam cannot be a reaction to the original Judaism and original Christianity since the source of revelation in Judaism, Christianity and Islam is one, Allah that is, according to Islamic theology. Now, speaking regardless Quran was a divine revelation or not, If the claim is that the source is one, then definitely Allah is not reacting to himself. However, according to Quran ''&quot; To thee We sent the Scripture in truth, confirming the scripture that came before it, and guarding it in safety...&quot;''(Surah 5, verse 48, Yusuf ali translation) Quran is a confirmation of the previous revelation. Indeed the Quran was responding to many issues related to the Jews and the Christians as they have corrupted the Holy Scriptures and the righteous religion, according to Islamic theology. It is also true that Muhammad was exposed to both Judaism and Christianity before the revelation of Quran. But to say that the Religion of Islam was a mere reaction to Judaism and Christianity is not a fully correct statement. Besides, The most common belief at that time among the majority of Arabs was neither Judaism nor Christianity, but paganism or Idolatry and a tremendous portion of Quran was discussing and refuting these beliefs/claims and it makes much sense to say that Quran is a reaction to Idolatry or any form of worship of multiple deities(polytheism) or any God but Allah ''&quot;(1). A. L. R. (This is) a Book, with verses basic or fundamental (of established meaning), further explained in detail,- from One Who is Wise and Well-acquainted (with all things)(2) (It teacheth) that ye should worship none but Allah...&quot;''(Surah 11, verse 1-2, Yusuf ali translation).  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/198.36.38.50|198.36.38.50]] ([[User talk:198.36.38.50|talk]]) 11:19, 1 October 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Worship of the One God in Monotheism ==

Regarding the top three religions of the world: Judaism, Christianity, and Islam.  It is clear that all three worship the Creator and not the creation.  With these three religions monotheism is not only a belief in the one uncreated God, but also a belief in only offering worship to that one uncreated God.  Judaism and Christianity are both resolute in that only the Creator is to receive  worship.&quot;Deuteronomy 4:19; Romans 1:25&quot;
  &quot;Muslims are taught to worship only the Creator and not His creations...&quot;.http://books.google.com/books?id=FbnnJxar3aMC&amp;pg=PA172&amp;lpg=PA172&amp;dq=Islam+teaches+that+only+God+is+worshiped+and+not+the+creation&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=qgX2pSlbV5&amp;sig=d1byflUky8J9bWi6rKTqiUeg9Jc&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=uSvATvaJGY2GiQKw-oy8Aw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false

Zoroastrianism however cannot be compared to Judaism, Christianity, and Isalm in regard to worship due to the Younger Avestan [[Yasht]]s clearly promoting the worship of the lesser dieties.  While Mary Boyce asserted that Zoroaster proclaimed Mazda as the one uncreated God,&quot;Zoroastrians Their Religious Beliefs and Practices&quot; in the [[Gathas]], the [[Gathas]] interpreted by the whole of the Zoroastrian scriptures allow worship of the created gods.[[User:TruthCkr|TruthCkr]] ([[User talk:TruthCkr|talk]]) 22:32, 13 November 2011 (UTC)

:Sources?  Wikipedia doesn't take [[WP:OR|original research or interpretation]].  There's also the issue of whether or not asking servants of the one God to do something for you really counts as worship, or having multiple titles for the one God really counts as polytheism.  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 22:56, 13 November 2011 (UTC)

Regarding Zoroastrianism as monotheistic.  This is an interpretation by Mary Boyce.  And I am simply stating that the three main religions of the world: Judaism, Christianity, and Islam interpret monotheism as not only a belief in the one uncreated God but also the solitary worship which is afforded to the one God.  Simply stated, monotheism from the point of view of the three largest religions of the world, is worship of the Creator and the not the created.  Zoroastrianism falls outside of this definition &quot;interpretation&quot; because it allows for the worship of the lesser created gods.[[User:TruthCkr|TruthCkr]] ([[User talk:TruthCkr|talk]]) 18:07, 15 November 2011 (UTC)
:That is your opinion, and you are not a [[WP:RS]].  Mary Boyce's work does meet [[WP:RS]], which is why her &quot;opinion&quot; (which has somehow time travelled centuries before her birth) is allowed.
:Again, there is also the issue of whether asking the servants of the one God to do something for you really counts as worship, or whether having multiple titles for the one God really counts as polytheism, which is where Zoroastrianism confounds your definition of monotheism.  The Amesha Spentas are aspects of Ahura Mazda (like the members of the Trinity in Christianity, in fact Spenta Mainyu can be translated as &quot;Holy Spirit,&quot;) and the Yazatas are treated in a manner similar to angels and saints have been treated in historical Judaism and Christianity: beings to be appealed for God's blessing.
:There's also the mistaken assumption that an outsider's modern interpretation of the scriptures is representative of the &quot;true&quot; form of that religion.  Max Muller's interpretation of the Vedas, while interesting, bears little similarity to modern Hinduism and is useless in describing modern Hinduism.  Those outside the Abrahamic religions (and some within them in competition of other Abrahamic religions) have tried to pick apart the Bible and the Quran to portray those works as inherently polytheistic, but that is not at all representative of Judaism, Christianity, or Islam.  Likewise, your personal interpretation of the Gathas is useless in describing modern Zoroastrianism, which is why we don't take original research.  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 18:32, 15 November 2011 (UTC)

== Abraham ==

The most that can be said with some degree of certainty is that the standard Hebrew text of Genesis places [[Abraham]] in the earlier part of the second millennium BCE. http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/03731a.htm
This is Middle [[Bronze age]] in the Ancient Near East.  [[Abrahamic religions]] are the monotheistic faiths emphasizing and tracing their common origin to [[Abraham]].http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/497132/philosophy-of-religion
Those primarily being Judaism, Christianity, and Islam.
[[User:TruthCkr|TruthCkr]] ([[User talk:TruthCkr|talk]]) 23:47, 26 November 2011 (UTC)

== Aspects of God: &quot;Plurality&quot; in Judaism, Christ., and Islam ==

There is no meaningful discussion on the expositions of the Logos by Philo, which is identified as the creative impulse of the one God in the writings of that Jewish sage. Also, the Memra of Rabbinic tradition, the Sephirot of Kabbala, and the Angel of the Lord, which many interpret as a theophany, are not discussed. These are all important Jewish concepts regarding the nature of God, and there are many historic views to be considered (such as those of Philo). In Islam, Allah is an absolute one, yet he has a Holy Spirit which is personal and visible (which is identified in Islamic tradition as the Angel Gabriel, but this is not explicit in the Quran).  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/69.201.173.75|69.201.173.75]] ([[User talk:69.201.173.75|talk]]) 07:48, 24 December 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
* In Islam, Angel Gabriel (Jibra'il) is just an angel, not a personal and visible part of Allah. An angel is a creation of Allah just like humans, planets and plants. Angel Gabriel (Jibra'il) is not part of Allah. He is not an extension of Allah. He is not a dimension of Allah. He is not a personality of Allah. He is one of Allah's creations. There is no Trinity in Islam.--[[Special:Contributions/98.196.233.8|98.196.233.8]] ([[User talk:98.196.233.8|talk]]) 00:39, 23 May 2012 (UTC)

== Relationship of God with Creation ==

There are many definitions of God in the article. But thre is no proper section for the relationship of god with creation. There must be a section for such a categorization.

Regarding this classification or categorization, only monism (pentheism, panentheism) is mentioned in the article. Other views are not named or mentioned in the article. Those views are mentioned without a name in various sections associaited for specific religions. But these views are not mentioned with their names in a proper section.

For example, Islam is a monotheistic religion but it is not monist. In Islam, it is believed that God and creation are not separate. Therefore there is god and there is creation (creatures, sum of created things). This view is called tawhid. So, this view is in contrast with monist views like panthiesm and panentheism.

Threfore, I suggest a section for '''Relationship of God with Creation'''--[[Special:Contributions/98.196.233.8|98.196.233.8]] ([[User talk:98.196.233.8|talk]]) 00:50, 23 May 2012 (UTC)

== Akhenaten ==

Akhenaten and the worship of Aten not mention? Is he consider to be a monotheist??

[[User:Henry123ifa|Henry123ifa]] ([[User talk:Henry123ifa|talk]]) 23:50, 2 June 2012 (UTC)

== Recent addition to lede ==

I have reverted a recent addition to the lede made by [[User:Pass a Method]] which added that Zoroastrianism was the first monotheistic religion. This might be true, depending on the definition of monotheism used, but there are more than one and I do not believe that the definition seemingly used in the source is the same one as used in this article. As per the &quot;Zoroastrianism&quot; article in the World Religions Reference Library of 2007, available on the HighBeam Research site, Zoroastrianism is called a monotheistic religion, based on the definition it gives after that word, &quot;a religion that worships one god&quot;. That however is not the same definition as the one used in this article. This article is about [[monotheism]] as a religion that believes in the existence of one god, not a religion that only worships one god. There is a difference. For this material to be included, I believe that it is incumbent upon anyone seeking to make such changes to meet [{WP:BURDEN]] requirements to have the material added to the article. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 20:15, 1 August 2012 (UTC)

== &quot;....references to Al-Lat, Al-’Uzza, and Manat which were redacted from later Korans&quot; ==

Okay, this idea is debated between non-Muslim scholars, while Muslims reject it wholly. The sentence appears as if it 100% actually happened, so I modified the sentence to include both ideas.--[[User:BelalSaid|BelalSaid]] ([[User talk:BelalSaid|talk]]) 21:17, 26 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>dwqzqss4mhsy6oyt14a5x3j1qgxuyq7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
