<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Discordianism</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>8534</id>
    <revision>
      <id>510661426</id>
      <parentid>510660526</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-03T21:38:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Majestic-chimp</username>
        <id>7428591</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* The Pentabarf */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20290">{{Talk page}}
{{WPReligion|class=B|importance=Low|NRM=yes|NRMImp=mid}}
{{WikiProject Neopaganism|class=B}}
{{archivebox|[[/Archive1]]}}

== Proposal to merge [[Discordian works]] here ==

See [[Talk:Discordian_works#Merge_proposal]]. [[User:Pohta ce-am pohtit|Pcap]] [[User_talk:Pohta ce-am pohtit|&lt;small&gt;ping&lt;/small&gt;]] 18:02, 30 November 2008 (UTC)


Agree. Merge. The content is essentially [[Anscombe's_quartet|exporatory]] in nature, it belongs here. --[[User:PlatoCantRepent|PlatoCantRepent]] ([[User talk:PlatoCantRepent|talk]]) 03:08, 7 January 2010 (UTC)

There is also [[Discordian Works]]. BTW, the assertion &quot;There is even ''[[Discordian Works#A Discordian Coloring Book|A Discordian Coloring Book]]'' is not borne out at [[Discordian Works]], where there is no such section. [[User:Bn|Bn]] ([[User talk:Bn|talk]]) 20:16, 11 January 2011 (UTC)

Link for the Discordian Coloring Book:http://s23.org/wiki/A_Discordian_Coloring_Book I'm not sure how best to describe it in the article, so I will leave that for someone else.
[[Special:Contributions/67.255.2.121|67.255.2.121]] ([[User talk:67.255.2.121|talk]]) 02:10, 10 July 2012 (UTC)

== Trivialism ==

[[Trivialism]] links here, but is not mentioned.  It should be mentioned here I say.  [[User:Mathiastck|Mathiastck]] ([[User talk:Mathiastck|talk]]) 23:46, 26 March 2009 (UTC)

== Secret Discordianism ==

A discussion here to publish this on the other side to bring to final fruition the main tenets and destiny of Discordianiam: by the addition of [[The Truth of Jehovah]] which brings the Principle of Contradiction into play by trading &quot;sweet for bitter&quot; instead of our current &quot;bitter for sweet&quot;; this being our present condition of existence as being &quot;under a spell&quot; by which &quot;evil&quot; is seen as &quot;good&quot; and &quot;good&quot; thus seen as &quot;evil&quot; ( as being the Mirror of Isis by which &quot;darkness&quot; is called &quot;light&quot;; and &quot;light&quot; is then seen as &quot;darkness&quot;); the reversing of this spell being where &quot;good&quot; is no longer seen as &quot;evil&quot;; as what was thought of as &quot;darkness&quot; formerly now becomes revealed as &quot;light&quot; presently. 
  
This is the &quot;apotheosis&quot; of Discordianism in which it &quot;finally contradicts itself once too many times&quot; and becomes the New Undisorder; having cancelled out all the opposites and found the Single Affirmation of Unity; the creation of a Principle to which there is no Contradiction: the Grail itself. 
 
Let us look at Joshua Abraham Norton: no one but the [[The Great Unknown|Great Unknown]] understood Joshua: but it has been revealed. By the City of [[St. Francis honoring]] as one who was now the least: San Francisco found Salvation: for by honoring Joshua as the least: they secretly honored Christ the Hidden One himself: as of &quot;the least of them&quot; was Joshua Abraham Norton where the Greatest was able to manifest: not just as Bummer and Lazarus; who were characters themselves; the signs and wonders of My Generation. 
  
In 1906 San Francisco was struck by the Censer: 4-18-1906: The Fire Cast to the Earth.
This can be seen at chapter 8 of Revelation verse 5; it was Gabriel who threw he Censer to the earth in 1906: 4th and April: 418 means &quot;Parcifal&quot; is Jewish gematria ( Robert Anton Wilson : &quot;Cosmic Trigger &quot;  ((Parcifal: the Great Work Accomplished&quot;))  ) 
  
The One we had Honored: as &quot;Norton I&quot;; that One Honored us: with His Prescence: and Joshua was this messenger; this gentle prophet who saw bridges: and they were made; saw tunnels: and they were built: prayed the Lord's prayer between two mobs: a Peacemaker: they went home: helped the poor find work; but now One came with His Work: Love is the Second Death: it is this Love as even the Name Christ Jesus in which Nothing can resist: for that One in the Name of Love as the Name of God: we have then the &quot;Name of God Almighty&quot;; a very powerful Name Indeed: because of what that Great City did once: for one poor man: for that: Salvation has now come to this Earth: even for that One Act: where one who was vanquished by the world: turned and Vanquished the world: that is the Ultimate Discord: Total Concordance. Harmonia Reigneth: Discord of Discord! Creates &quot;Accord&quot;!
  
Joshua: the Salvation of God; as of that Beloved City of St. Francis: who found that Child to lead them: [[Joshua Abraham Norton]]. [[User:Unicorn144|Unicorn144]] ([[User talk:Unicorn144|talk]]) 01:52, 4 October 2009 (UTC) [[User:Unicorn144|Unicorn144]] ([[User talk:Unicorn144|talk]]) 21:21, 3 October

== WTF?`==
Does anybody really think that this inconsistent babble promotes reliability of wikipedia?  --[[User:Magabund|Magabund]] ([[User talk:Magabund|talk]]) 14:19, 20 December 2009 (UTC)
:Is the article inconsistent?  To me it looks like a clear explanation of an inconsistent but real phenomenon. [[User:DenisMoskowitz|DenisMoskowitz]] ([[User talk:DenisMoskowitz|talk]]) 17:40, 20 December 2009 (UTC)
:I'm not sure whether the objection is to the subject matter or the presentation. Discordianism is real and has been influential in some circles. But the article could definitely be clearer about a lot of things. I don't know where to start, though. It's hard to write coherently about something that actively resists coherence. [[User:Zorblek|Zorbl]][[WP:ESP|&lt;span style=&quot;color: #00cc00; font-weight: bolder;&quot;&gt;e&lt;/span&gt;]][[User:Zorblek|k]] [[User talk:Zorblek|(talk)]] 21:34, 20 December 2009 (UTC)

== Vandalism ==
It has just occurred to me that what may have seemed to be a disorganised injoke on both this page, and the other discordian pages pre-merger could have actually been the work of a single group of vandals. When are Jimmy Wales and his band of thugs going to stop destroying Wikipedia?
--[[User:PlatoCantRepent|PlatoCantRepent]] ([[User talk:PlatoCantRepent|talk]]) 03:01, 7 January 2010 (UTC)
:Erm, what? Are you saying the articles have been vandalized, or that the topic itself is vandalism? Also, I don't think Jimbo has edited this article. &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Courier New;font-size:3&quot;&gt;[[User:The Wordsmith|'''The Wordsmith''']]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:The Wordsmith|Communicate]]&lt;/sup&gt; 04:13, 7 January 2010 (UTC)

== Opening paragraph ==

The first paragraph of this article (especially the first few sentences) is awfully hard to follow. I've cleaned it up a bit, but it still needs work. As an example, 77.99.7.242 misunderstood the phrase &quot;is and is not a modern religion&quot; to mean it &quot;is and is not modern&quot; rather than &quot;is and is not a religion&quot;. I changed the sentence back, but it would be better if it were re-written somehow, I think. Any suggestions would be appreciated. -[[User:Zorblek|zorblek]] [[User talk:Zorblek|(talk)]] 09:41, 11 January 2010 (UTC)
:The article should not be written in the style of the PD, or be Discordian in nature, which parts of it are at the moment. &quot;is and is not a modern religion&quot; is not instructive and I don't even know what is being aimed at there. That it is a joke religion which nonetheless people find some religious value to, possibly? [[User:Schizombie|Шизомби (Sz)]] ([[User talk:Schizombie|talk]]) 13:50, 11 January 2010 (UTC)
::I think that was the main intent, yeah.  I agree that the map need not be drawn in the same style as the territory. &amp;mdash;[[User:Chaos5023|chaos5023]] ([[User talk:Chaos5023|talk]]) 13:57, 11 January 2010 (UTC)

::Nobody really knows if its an elabourate joke disguised as a religion, or a religion disguised as an elabourate joke. &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Courier New;font-size:3&quot;&gt;[[User:The Wordsmith|'''The Wordsmith''']]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:The Wordsmith|Communicate]]&lt;/sup&gt; 16:40, 11 January 2010 (UTC)

::I like the most recent anonymous revision, which adds parentheses around &quot;and is not&quot;. I agree that the article shouldn't be written in the style of the Principia, but I think it's important to emphasize from the beginning that some Discordians take Discordianism seriously and that others do not. That &quot;serious/not serious&quot; attitude is one of the central aspects of the religion. -[[User:Zorblek|zorblek]] [[User talk:Zorblek|(talk)]] 05:10, 18 January 2010 (UTC)

:After some thought, I've removed the word &quot;modern&quot; from the first sentence. I think this makes it a little clearer, and doesn't really remove any information, since it says a few sentences later that it was founded in the '50s. -[[User:Zorblek|zorblek]] [[User talk:Zorblek|(talk)]] 05:20, 18 January 2010 (UTC)
:: Exactly. So I dared to remove the &quot;cleanup&quot; warning. --[[User:Bernd.Brincken|Bernd.Brincken]] ([[User talk:Bernd.Brincken|talk]]) 10:55, 15 March 2010 (UTC)

&quot;Zen for roundeyes&quot;? If nothing else this needs a citation, but I really doubt it should be there in the first place.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.127.200.20|76.127.200.20]] ([[User talk:76.127.200.20|talk]]) 13:40, 30 January 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Ideology rather than religion==
It seems to look more like an ideology rather than a religion to me. Maybe we could just change the vocabulary used throughout the article? [[User:SweetNightmares|SweetNightmares]] ([[User talk:SweetNightmares|talk]]) 02:10, 8 April 2010 (UTC)
:That would be [[wp:OR]].- [[User talk:Sinneed|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:grey 0.3em 0.3em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;Sinneed&lt;/span&gt;]] 02:25, 8 April 2010 (UTC)
:Hell yes it would.  And I really can't overstress the disrespectfulness inherent in telling somebody else their religion isn't one. &amp;mdash;[[User:Chaos5023|chaos5023]] ([[User talk:Chaos5023|talk]]) 03:17, 8 April 2010 (UTC)
:&quot;disrespectfulness inherent in telling somebody else their religion isn't one&quot;...and that will have nothing whatever to do with whether the content belongs in the encyclopedia or not, the entire line of argument will only make reaching [[wp:consensus]] harder.- [[User talk:Sinneed|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:grey 0.3em 0.3em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;Sinneed&lt;/span&gt;]] 04:29, 8 April 2010 (UTC)
::There's no need for consensus, the OP clearly wants us to violate [[WP:NOR]]. &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Courier New;font-size:3&quot;&gt;[[User:The Wordsmith|'''The Wordsmith''']]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:The Wordsmith|Communicate]]&lt;/sup&gt; 05:08, 8 April 2010 (UTC)

Jesus H., it was just a question... hence no changes were made. Are there really adherents? Are there Dischordian communities around the world? Because this article doesn't discuss that--rather, it talks about the religion as though it sprang out of modern literature and other media. I'm sure I wasn't the only reader to come across this and think it was yet another internet fad...[[User:SweetNightmares|SweetNightmares]] ([[User talk:SweetNightmares|talk]]) 01:51, 29 April 2010 (UTC)

: Yes there are adherents. I have Discordian selected for my religion on my dog tags :-D [[Special:Contributions/24.223.106.131|24.223.106.131]] ([[User talk:24.223.106.131|talk]]) 11:43, 5 May 2010 (UTC)

:The ''Principia'' was published in 1965. --[[User:Belg4mit|Belg4mit]] ([[User talk:Belg4mit|talk]]) 20:25, 6 May 2010 (UTC)
::Interestingly enough you can even find it at some libraries. I was looking for it when I read this wikipedia page. You can even find it at the Denver Public Library http://www.worldcat.org/title/principia-discordia/oclc/25210860&amp;referer=brief_results at this website. This is WorldCat.org. It is a library resource. I used to be a librarian. It is a real book. Though this one was written in 1991, there are others. Like this one written in 1978 earliest edition however. http://www.worldcat.org/title/principia-discordia-or-how-i-found-goddess-and-what-i-did-to-her-when-i-found-her-the-magnum-opiate-of-malaclypse-the-younger-wherein-is-explained-absolutely-everything-worth-knowing-about-absolutely-anything/oclc/213886072&amp;referer=brief_results[[Special:Contributions/174.20.153.23|174.20.153.23]] ([[User talk:174.20.153.23|talk]]) 06:41, 7 June 2010 (UTC)

:There are definitely adherents to Discordianism. Like me. And there are communities around the world. Like the cabal I'm proud to be a member of. Hope this clears things up for you ;) [[User:Frank Westerton|Frank Westerton]] ([[User talk:Frank Westerton|talk]]) 18:09, 31 May 2010 (UTC)

*Frown*[[User:Kungfukats2|Kungfukats2]] ([[User talk:Kungfukats2|talk]]) 04:09, 1 June 2010 (UTC)

OK, &quot;Discordianism&quot; is not a religion per se, but more a pop philosophy/religion satire against organised and instrumentalised religion. Its main tenet may be, don't take all that stuff that seriously or ask for the reason behind anything. Dispute (&quot;Discordia&quot;) anything. It is Post-Modernism (in the original French sense of Lyotard and Derrida). As disputes can only be held between equals, it is the antithesis to &quot;religion satires&quot; like the &quot;Flying Confetti Monstre&quot; and other such things whose intend is it for fundamentalist atheists to show practitioners that they are smarter than them.--[[Special:Contributions/129.13.186.2|129.13.186.2]] ([[User talk:129.13.186.2|talk]]) 17:30, 24 July 2011 (UTC)
: I disagree! -- [[User:MegA|megA]] ([[User talk:MegA|talk]]) 13:20, 25 March 2012 (UTC)
: Agree.  It is an essential part of the game that the participants in this collective satire insist that they are actually sincere adherents in a genuine religion and that there are legions of other similarly sincere believers.  It is part of the shtick to feign surprise and offense at the suggestion by non-participants that the satire being performed is just a satire--but that's part of the satire too.  I give you the exhibits above.  The article should not suggest that it is anything other than a satire or a game, nor should this article be hijacked by the satire's participants to further popularize it or to help them steal a march on the Spaghetti Monster people who are occupying the same terrain.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.97.218.2|24.97.218.2]] ([[User talk:24.97.218.2|talk]]) 19:20, 24 August 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
: Do either of you have a source for these bold claims of yours—claims which contradict the assertions of the Principia and Discordians—or are you partaking in a bit of Original Research of your own, I wonder?  Or perhaps to phrase this another way, on what grounds do you dispute the claims of an entire group of people concerning their own beliefs? [[User:Majestic-chimp|Majestic-chimp]] ([[User talk:Majestic-chimp|talk]]) 21:32, 3 September 2012 (UTC)

== Article tags ==

While the article has many sources, much nonsense has been added, in keeping with the principles of discordianism, or not.  There is presently no [[wp:consensus]] to remove the article tag.  I do wonder if, really, the factual accuracy and PoV tags might not be most appropriate, rather than refimprove.  It seems to me that discordian works would almost without exception (there would surely be some, again in keeping with the ideal... but maybe not) be sources on multiple sides of every issue.

I have restored the refimprove.  Any thoughts on the double-tag?- [[User talk:Sinneed|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:grey 0.3em 0.3em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;Sinneed&lt;/span&gt;]] 20:10, 31 May 2010 (UTC)
:It doesn't need consensus to remove the tag. Without a full rationale placed on the talk page the problem is undefined and the issue of whether there is a consensus either way on the problem can't even be addressed. Simply saying the article needs more references because 'much nonsense' has been added, isn't enough when there are already a healthy number of refs and citations in the article, and the 'much nonsense' hasn't been defined or even discussed. It's already been seven months since the tag was orignally placed and no more has been added to expand on the specifics of the rationale since then. 
:From the section on adding these tags;
:''In general, an editor who places a template message to indicate a problem like this should explain their rationale fully on the talkpage of the article. If the consensus of the other editors is that there is a problem or an editorial dispute that deserves such a clean-up template, then the editors should work to fix the problem as quickly and cleanly as possible so the template message can be removed. If the consensus is that there is no problem, then the message can be removed immediately.'' [[Special:Contributions/121.74.8.48|121.74.8.48]] ([[User talk:121.74.8.48|talk]]) 02:06, 6 July 2010 (UTC)

== Law of 5 ==
Of course the &quot;law of five&quot; applies to the 23 Enigma, as 2+3=5. This is '''repeatedly''' stated in the Illuminatus!-trilogy. There is NOTHING to discuss.

Instead, the term &quot;2+3=5&quot;, the first two prime numbers resulting in the 3rd, makes much of the ''reason'' of the ubiquity of the 5; you can construct almost ANY number (being the [[digit sum]] of any larger number) of combinations of 2, 3 and 5. Note that almost any decimal currency has coins / notes of 1, 2 and 5 units, because those allow easy construction of any amount.

Much of the &quot;23 Enigma&quot; and &quot;law of 5&quot; is &quot;snake oil&quot;, but it would be harder to propagate a &quot;law of 6&quot; or &quot;law of 13&quot; in the decimal system (they would collapse to 2*3 -&gt; 23 and 2*5+3 -&gt; 23 and 5). It's pure mathematics that almost any decimal number can be collapsed by applying [[Prime decomposition]] and [[Digit sum]] repeatedly into 2, 3 and 5.--[[Special:Contributions/129.13.186.2|129.13.186.2]] ([[User talk:129.13.186.2|talk]]) 17:24, 24 July 2011 (UTC)

== Dropped a citation tag. ==

Im pretty sure the idea that almost anyone would agree that chaotic individual coming together to form a group is paradoxical. The Sky Is Blue type thing. So I removed it. [[Special:Contributions/74.132.249.206|74.132.249.206]] ([[User talk:74.132.249.206|talk]]) 03:11, 9 September 2011 (UTC)

== Punctuation Change ==

&lt;blockquote&gt;Discordianism recognizes the positive aspects of chaos, discord, and dissent as valid and desirable qualities, in contrast with most religions, which idealize harmony and order.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

This is incorrectly punctuated but, since I'm not certain what it was meant to say, I can't be certain how to correct it.  I suggest the following.

&lt;blockquote&gt;Discordianism recognizes the positive aspects of chaos, discord and dissent, as valid and desirable qualities (in contrast with most religions, which idealize harmony and order).&lt;/blockquote&gt;

If no-one objects I will make that change.  

Incidentally, I'm not sure it's correct to say that &quot;most religions&quot; idealize harmony and order, at least not without a citation.  But that's a problem for another day.

== Vision in a Bowling Alley and &quot;The Big Lebovsky&quot;? ==

Is there a connection? -- [[User:MegA|megA]] ([[User talk:MegA|talk]])

:Everything is connected. -[[User:Zorblek|zorblek]] ([[User talk:Zorblek|talk]]) 11:29, 18 March 2012 (UTC)
:: Oh, I forgot. Thanks. -- [[User:MegA|megA]] ([[User talk:MegA|talk]]) 16:10, 23 March 2012 (UTC)

== The Pentabarf ==

Is there a source for the Pentabarf, III?  The article says ''&quot;A Discordian is required to, the first Friday after his illumination, Go Off Alone &amp; Partake Joyously of a Hot Dog ...&quot;'' however every version of the Principia I've read has the same text as http://www.principiadiscordia.com/book/11.php : ''&quot;A Discordian is Required during his early Illumination to Go Off Alone &amp; Partake Joyously of a Hot Dog on a Friday ...&quot;''

I don't want to step on anyone's toes by changing it, but was wondering where it came from. phluid61 06:51, 31 August 2012 (UTC)  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Phluid61|Phluid61]] ([[User talk:Phluid61|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Phluid61|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:My copy of the Principia is out of reach, but my own memory supports a vague reference to early in one's Illumination rather than the specific statement &quot;the first Friday&quot;; I suspect the author of that portion of the article was quoting from memory and erred.  Since you have a source, I'd say go ahead and change it! [[User:Majestic-chimp|Majestic-chimp]] ([[User talk:Majestic-chimp|talk]]) 21:38, 3 September 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>syjioo2965he023cuouwvte1y6y20b4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
