<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Canon law</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1456416</id>
    <revision>
      <id>451450646</id>
      <parentid>392551367</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-09-20T05:09:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bjenks</username>
        <id>1693504</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Capitalisation of pope/Pope */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6792">{{WikiProject Canon Law|class=C|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject law|class=C|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Christianity|class=C|importance=}}


I have one question, would anyone be able to give me one example of the canon law, like one of the main sections. Please help i am doing this for a school project. 
Sincerly Tiffany.

== A major piece of Canon Law ==

Check out Gratian's Decretals, he did a lot of work in pulling different things together, reconcilling apparently contradictory information, and just putting it all together for the next 800 yrs of people to use as reference to their disputes.  Hope it helps!  Good Luck with it, and God Bless!!

:Good luck indeed!  It is written in Middle Ages Latin!  Dave

== Example of Canon Law ==
This is from [http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG1104/__P2U.HTM Vatican Canon Law online].  It's on the purpose of [[baptism]], one of the seven [[sacraments]] of the Church. [[User:Kenj0418|Kenj0418]] 04:47, Apr 8, 2005 (UTC)

:BAPTISM (Cann. 849 - 878)
:
:Can.  849 Baptism, the gateway to the sacraments and necessary for salvation by actual reception or at least by desire, is validly conferred only by a washing of true water with the proper form of words. Through baptism men and women are freed from sin, are reborn as children of God, and, configured to Christ by an indelible character, are incorporated into the Church.

== correction at some point ==

It may be worth, at some point, to delinate out the time and evolution of Canon law, which began 1140's with Gratian and goes up to the current Codex Iuris Canonici.  But I am not a good enough computer guru to do it.

DAVE

== Errors ==

There are clear errors in the description of the history after 1900 - there is no mention about the CIC from 1917 - could somebody correct it? - I have no sources at hand. --[[User:Ioannes Pragensis|Ioannes Pragensis]] 07:39, 27 March 2006 (UTC)

:I caught a couple of the errors, but I don't remember all the details off hand, so I only put in teh parts that I was sure of.  Where are the other Canon law students?[[User:DaveTroy|DaveTroy]] 19:48, 9 June 2006 (UTC)

== Some changes ==

I made some signficant changes. First, why there is a peroration cheerleading for the Gregorian is beyond me. There are a lot of faculties of Canon Law. Second, it is patently untrue that almost all of the cardiunals come from the Greg. Third, the Apostolic Signatura is in no way the bar&quot; for Canon Laws -- the number of canonists who ever actually interact with the Signatura is miniscule. Cloture is a technical parliamentary term, and does not mean the same thing as &quot;closed.&quot; Gasparri was only arguable &quot;brilliant&quot; and the Pope did not merely &quot;permit&quot; the Eastern Churches to have their own system of canon law, etc.[[User:HarvardOxon|HarvardOxon]] 18:39, 5 July 2006 (UTC)



==Delineation, correction, self evident truth==
I'm going to change the intro, adding: '''The Code of Canon''' Law is properly termed ''Canon Law'', only in relation The Law governing The One true Holy Roman Catholic and Apostolic Church.  Other codes termed, ''canons'', gain some legitimacy, through the reader's association with the ''Canon Law''.  '''The Code of Canon Law''' is translated into English [[http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG0017/|here]].  This is the oldest continuously functioning body of law in the world.

:Hi, I removed it, sorry - because not all churches' canons have been codified, and those whose are, is different. Though, The Code of Canon Law is covered under the Roman Catholic Church section. Also, it is covered in this article: [[Code of Canon Law]], where there is a link to the [[Code of Canons of the Eastern Churches]]. :) --[[User:KGBarnett|KGBarnett]] ([[User talk:KGBarnett|talk]]) 18:42, 26 May 2008 (UTC)

== Circular Definition ==

Canon law is defined as an ''ecclesiastical law'', but the term ''ecclesiastical law'' redirects to ''canon law''.  Can someone who knows what either of these terms mean please explain in the lead?  Thanks.--[[Special:Contributions/85.177.150.34|85.177.150.34]] ([[User talk:85.177.150.34|talk]]) 19:52, 7 July 2008 (UTC)

==Civil ecclesiastic law==
There is a related branch of law which is structurally close to canon law, but which only becomes applied when the Roman Catholic Church and/or Eastern Orthodox Church is selected as the State religion. This has not happened in a long time, although it was the de facto situation in certain South American States until the late 1980s. This branch of law is called [[Civil ecclesiastic law]], which is roughly the Christian equivalent of Sharia and/or Halakha. There is a stub here on WP-FR [http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Droit_civil_eccl%C3%A9siastique] which might be translated into WP-EN if sufficient and correct sources on the topic can be found. [[User:ADM|ADM]] ([[User talk:ADM|talk]]) 08:46, 13 March 2009 (UTC)

==What is Canon Law?==
I've read this article, along with the specific individual articles for Anglican and Roman Catholic Canon Law, and I still have ''no'' idea what the hell Canon Law actually is.  Is it just the bylaws, so to speak, of the respective churches, that handle things like organizational structure and authorities?  Is it there a theological component?  Are the seven sacraments part of canon law? How is it established and promulgated?  And so on.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/68.48.89.183|68.48.89.183]] ([[User talk:68.48.89.183|talk]]) 23:41, 20 April 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

I have added &quot;is the body of laws and regulations made by or adopted by ecclesiastical authority, for the government of the Christian organization and its members.&quot; as definition. It is from the Catholic Encyclopedia (referenced already). It seemed to me that the old definition was incomplete and focused too much on saying churches use a form of Canon law or another rather that actually explaining what Canon law is.[[User:Amj1967|Amj1967]] ([[User talk:Amj1967|talk]]) 08:16, 8 July 2009 (UTC)

==Roma locuta est==
Regarding the phrase [[Roma locuta est]], it would be interesting if we could have well-sourced material explaining the origin of the phrase. [[User:ADM|ADM]] ([[User talk:ADM|talk]]) 09:18, 22 July 2009 (UTC)

==Church rights==
Another canonical concept that would need more explaining is [[Church rights]] (o

== Capitalisation of pope/Pope ==

The Oxford Dictionary for writers and editors says at p 296 &quot;'''pope''' cap in titles and ''the Pope''; lower case of the office and of more than one holder&quot;. The same applies generally to bishop, cardinal, etc. Cheers, [[User:Bjenks|Bjenks]] ([[User talk:Bjenks|talk]]) 05:09, 20 September 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>g9l5nzb44lte79rvja4hfp7rusdwd8c</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
