<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Tallit</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>148411</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522433204</id>
      <parentid>520137197</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-11T04:45:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>207.161.176.26</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Women */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22451">{{Double image|right|PRIESTLY_BLESSING_-BIRCAT_CHOHANIM_AT_THE_WESTERN_WALL_HOL_HAMOED_SUCCOT_derived.jpg|150|Prayer Shawl.JPG|150|A white ''tallit'' according to the [[Sephardic laws and customs|Sephardic tradition]]|A ''tallit'' with black stripes according to the Orthodox [[Ashkenazi Jews|Ashkenasic]] tradition|White tallit|Tallit with black stripes}}
A '''tallit'''{{Pronunciation-needed}}&lt;!-- as IPA --&gt; ({{lang-he-n|טַלִּית}}) ('''talet'''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=This I Believe: Documents of American Jewish Life|author=[[Jacob Rader Marcus]]|page=269|isbn=0-87668-782-6|url=http://books.google.ca/books?id=OgDXAAAAMAAJ}}&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Sephardic Hebrew]] and [[Ladino language|Ladino]]) ('''tallis''',&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Veil: Women Writers on its History, Lore, and Politics|author=Jennifer Heath|publisher=[[University of California Press]]|year=2008|page=211|isbn=0-520-25040-0|url=http://books.google.ca/books?id=kqDk3IRK-4gC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Ashkenazic Hebrew]] and [[Yiddish language|Yiddish]]) pl. '''tallitot'''{{Pronunciation-needed}}&lt;!-- as IPA --&gt; ('''talleisim''',&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Houses of Study: A Jewish Woman Among Books|author=Ilana M. Blumberg|publisher=[[University of Nebraska Press]]|year=2009|page=64|isbn=0-8032-2449-4|url=http://books.google.ca/books?id=8VOZ_1q6TEwC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; '''tallism''',&lt;ref name=Leftwich&gt;{{Cite book|title=An Anthology of Modern Yiddish Literature|author=[[Joseph Leftwich]]|publisher=[[Walter de Gruyter]]|year=1974|page=338|isbn=90-279-3001-5|url=http://books.google.ca/books?id=dkVDPlhjcn8C&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; in Ashkenazic Hebrew and Yiddish) is a [[Jewish]] [[Jewish prayer|prayer]] shawl. The tallit is worn over the outer clothes during the morning prayers ([[Shacharit]]) and worn during all prayers on [[Yom Kippur]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.myjewishlearning.com/holidays/Yom_Kippur/Overview_Yom_Kippur_Community/Prayer_Services.htm |title=My Jewish Learning — Prayer Services |accessdate=September 28, 2012 |author=Rabbi Daniel Kohn}}&lt;/ref&gt; The tallit has special [[twine]]d and [[knot]]ted [[Fringe (trim)|fringes]] known as ''[[tzitzit]]'' attached to its four corners. Most traditional tallitot are made of wool. Tallitot are often first worn by children on their [[Bar Mitzvah]]s. In [[Orthodox Judaism|orthodox]], [[Ashkenazi]] circles, a Tallit is customarily presented to a groom before marriage as part of the [[dowry]].

== Biblical commandment ==

The Bible does not command wearing of a unique prayer shawl or tallit. Instead, it presumes that people wore a garment of some type to cover themselves and instructs them to add fringes (tzitzit) to the 4 corners of these ([[Book of Numbers|Numbers]] 15:38, [[Deuteronomy]] 22:12). These passages do not specify tying particular types or numbers of knots in the fringes. Nor do they specify a gender division between men and women, or between native Israelite/Hebrew people and those assimilated by them. The exact customs regarding the tying of the tzitzit and the format of the tallit are post-Biblical and rabbinical and can vary between various Jewish communities.

Encyclopaedia Judaica, describes the prayer shawl as &quot;a rectangular mantle that looked like a blanket and was worn by men in ancient times&quot;. Also, it &quot;is usually white and made either of wool, cotton, or silk&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Second Ed., Vol. 19, Som-Tn, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

The tallit can be made of any materials except a mixture of wool and linen. Usually, the mixture of wool and linen - a combination known as [[shatnez]] - is specifically forbidden by the Torah. In the case of Talit however, this is a Rabbinic prohibition, because biblically, the mixture might be allowed for a Talit during the daytime (however at nighttime there would be a transgression on behalf of the wearer).&lt;ref&gt;[[Rambam]]: [[Mishneh Torah]], Laws of Tzizit, 3rd Chapter, #6/7 - http://www.mechon-mamre.org/i/2403.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Most traditional tallitot are made of wool.

According to the biblical commandment, a blue ([[Hebrew]] תכלת, [[tekhelet]], tək·ā'·leth) thread (Hebrew פתיל &quot;pəthiyl&quot;) known as &quot;tekhelet&quot; itself, is included in the tzitzit.&lt;ref&gt;Numbers 15:38&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tekhelet.com/ The Ptil Tekhelet Organization]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Pronunciation ==

In [[Modern Hebrew]] the word is pronounced {{IPA-he|taˈlit|}}, with the stress on the final syllable. In [[Yiddish]] it is {{IPA|[ˈtaləs]}}, with the stress on the first syllable. The plural of ''tallit'' in Hebrew is ''tallitot'', pronounced {{IPA|[taliˈtot]}}. The Yiddish plural is ''taleisim,'' pronounced {{IPA|[taˈlejsɪm]}}.

== Etymology and origin ==

Tallit is an [[Aramaic]] word from the root tll טלל meaning cover.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= [[Jastrow]] |first= Marcus |title= Dictionary of the Targumim, the Talmud etc. |publisher= [[E. Shapiro Valentine &amp; Co.]] |year= 1926 |isbn= 978-1-56563-860-0}}, page 537&lt;/ref&gt; Tallit literally means cloak or sheet but in Talmudic times already referred to the Jewish prayer shawl. The tallit is similar to the Roman pallium worn today by senior [[Roman Catholic]] priests, the Roman [[toga]] and the Arab [[keffiyeh]]. The tallit or other similar garment is suitable for the climate in [[Middle East|West Asia]]: typically the days are hot and the tallit can be draped around the body and head to provide cover from the sun or just bunched up on the shoulders for later evening use; the evenings can be dramatically cool and the tallit could be draped around the neck and shoulders like a [[scarf]] to provide warmth.

== Customs ==
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:tallit knotting2.jpg|200px|thumb|right|[[Tzitzit]]s tied onto a tallit following the correct sequence of knots]] --&gt;
In some Jewish communities a tallit is given as a gift by a father to a son, a father-in-law to a son-in-law, or a teacher to a student. It might be purchased to mark a special occasion, such as a wedding or a bar/bat mitzvah. Many parents purchase a tallit for their children at the age of 13, together with [[tefillin]]. In the egalitarian, Reform and Conservative movements, it is common for both men and women to wear a tallit. While many worshipers bring their own tallit to synagogue, there is usually a rack of shawls for the use of visitors and guests. At Jewish wedding ceremonies, a tallit is often used as a ''[[chuppah]]'' or wedding canopy. The tallit is traditionally draped over the shoulders, but during prayer, some cover their head with it.

In the [[Talmud]]ic and post-Talmudic periods the [[tefillin]] were worn by [[rabbi]]s and scholars all day, and a special tallit was worn at prayer; hence they put on the tefillin before the tallit, as appears in the order given in &quot;Seder Rabbi Amram Gaon&quot; (p.&amp;nbsp;2a) and in the [[Zohar]]. In modern practice, the opposite order is considered more &quot;correct&quot;. Based on the Talmudic principle of ''tadir v'she'ayno tadir, tadir kodem'' (תדיר ושאינו תדיר, תדיר קודם: lit., frequent and infrequent, frequent first), when one performs more than one [[mitzvot|mitzva]] at a time, those that are performed more frequently should be performed first. While the tallit is worn daily, tefillin are not worn on ''Shabbat'' and holidays.

The [[Kabbalah|Kabbalists]] considered the tallit as a special garment for the service of [[God]], intended, in connection with the [[tefillin]], to inspire awe and reverence for God at prayer.&lt;ref&gt;[[Zohar]], Exodus Toledot, p.&amp;nbsp;141a)&lt;/ref&gt;  The tallit is worn by worshipers at the [[Jewish services|morning prayer]] on weekdays, ''Shabbat'', and holy days; by the [[hazzan]] (cantor) at every prayer while before the [[ark (synagogue)|ark]]; and by the reader of [[Torah]], as well as by all other functionaries during the [[torah reading|Torah service]].

=== History ===

The use of the tallit begins in the Biblical period around 1800 BCE. The ancient Jewish tallit design was different than that known today. Originally it was a large white rectangular garment with tzitzyot in each corner and was used as a garment, bed sheet, and burial shroud.

In the book ''The Ancient Jewish Shroud At Turin'' by John N. Lupia  (Regina Caeli Press, 2010; ISBN 978-0-9826739-0-4) Lupia shows the historical development of the tallit when its design began to change during the second half of the first century CE and began to take on the forms known today beginning around 1000 CE. The long tradition of a single orthodox form of the tallit became modified in a more culturally diverse atmosphere and continued to change throughout time until it became permuted and shortened in length as the kitel, tallit katan, tallit gadol, and the more common tallit prayer shawl form know today.

=== Weddings ===

In many [[Sephardi]]c communities, the groom traditionally wears a tallit under the [[chuppah]] (wedding canopy). In [[Ashkenazi]] communities, a more widespread custom is that the groom wears a [[kittel]].

=== Burials ===

In the [[Diaspora]], Jews are buried in a plain, wooden casket. The corpse is collected from the place of death (home, hospital, etc.) by the ''[[chevra kadisha]]'' (burial committee). After a ritual washing of the body, the body of men is dressed in a ''[[kittel]]'' and then a ''tallit''. One of the ''tzitzit'' is then cut off. In the Land of Israel, burial is without a casket, and the ''kittel'' and ''tallit'' are the only coverings for the corpse. Women are buried in white shrouds only.

=== Additional occasions ===

In addition to the morning prayers of weekdays, Shabbat and holidays, a tallit is also worn for ''[[Selichos]]'' in Ashkenazic communities by the prayer leader, even though it is still night.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.ca/books?id=gISl55geRaAC&amp;pg=RA1-PA1042&amp;dq=Sephardi+tallis&amp;lr=#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false Books.google.ca]&lt;/ref&gt; A tallit is also worn at night on [[Yom Kippur]], from [[Kol Nidre]], which begins during the daylight hours until after the evening ([[Jewish services|Ma'ariv]]) service.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Tapestry of Jewish Time: A Spiritual Guide to Holidays and Life-Cycle Events |first=Nina Beth |last=Cardin |page=73 |url=http://books.google.ca/books?id=oXhBgCJjCmcC&amp;pg=PA73&amp;dq=ma%27ariv+tallit&amp;lr=#v=onepage&amp;q=ma'ariv%20tallit&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Types of tallitot ==

=== Tallit katan ===

[[File:Tzitzskatan-ch.jpg|thumb|100px| An Orthodox Jewish man wearing a Wool Tallit Katan under his shirt and vest.]]
The '''tallit katan''' (&quot;small tallit&quot;) is a fringed garment traditionally worn either under or over one’s clothing by [[Orthodox Judaism|Jewish]] males. It is a poncho-like garment with a hole for the head and special twined and knotted fringes known as [[tzitzit]] attached to its four corners. The requirements regarding the fabric and fringes of a ''tallit katan'' are the same as that of a ''tallit gadol''. Generally a ''tallit katan'' is made of wool or cotton.

Although Sephardi halakha generally maintains a distinct preference for a woolen garment as per the ruling of the Shulchan Aruch, among Ashkenazim customs are split, with the Rema ruling that all garment types are acceptable.&lt;ref name=torahorg&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.torah.org/advanced/weekly-halacha/5765/vayeitzei.html |title=Tallis Katan: Questions and Answers |first=Doniel |last=Neustadt |year=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; Whilst the Mishnah Berurah and [[Moshe Feinstein|Rabbi Moshe Feinstein]] recommend wearing a woolen garment in accordance with the Shulchan Aruch's ruling, the Chazon Ish was known to wear cotton, in accordance with the ruling of the Vilna Gaon.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://hirhurim.blogspot.com/2008/02/tzitzit-cotton-or-wool.html |first=Ari |last=Enkin |title=Tzitzit - Cotton or Wool? |publisher=Hirhurim |date= February 19, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was also the practice of Rabbi Joseph Soloveitchik, and that of German Jewry historically.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.koltorah.org/Volume%2014/23%20Ki%20Tisa.htm |title=Halacha of the Week, parshat Ki Tisa |date=February 26, 2005 |publisher=Torah Academy of Bergen County}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While all four cornered garments are required to have ''tzitzit'', the custom of specially wearing a ''tallit katan'' is based on a verse in {{bibleverse||Numbers|15:38-39|HE}} which exhorts Jews to &quot;remember[ance of] all the commandments of the Lord.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Berel |last=Wein |title=Living Jewish: Values, Practices and Traditions |page=72 |year=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wearing a ''tallit kattan'' is not mandated in Biblical law, but in Rabbinic law the practice is strongly encouraged for men, and often considered obligatory or a binding custom.&lt;ref name=torahorg /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rabbi Monique Susskind Goldberg, [http://www.schechter.edu/AskTheRabbi.aspx?ID=194 Tallit Kattan], Ask the Rabbi, The Schechter Institutes, June 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Aryeh Citron, [http://www.chabad.org/library/article_cdo/aid/927994/jewish/Laws-of-Tzitzit.htm Laws of Tzitzit], chabad.org&lt;/ref&gt;

The tallit katan is also known as ''arba kanfot'' ([[Yiddish]]/[[Ashkenazic Hebrew]]: ''arba kanfos''), literally &quot;four corners&quot;  or ''[[tzitzit]]''.

=== Tallit gadol ===

[[File:Tallit-bag.jpg|thumb|right|A typical ''tallit'' bag. The [[Hebrew]] embroidery says ''tallit''. Frequently the owner will add additional embroidery with their name.]]
The ''tallit gadol'' (traditionally known as ''tallét gedolah'' amongst Sephardim), or &quot;large&quot; ''tallit'', is worn over one's clothing resting on the shoulders. This is the ''prayer shawl'' that is worn during the morning services in [[synagogue]] by all male participants, and in many communities by the leader of the afternoon and evening prayers as well. The ''tallit gadol'' is usually woven of [[wool]] &amp;mdash; especially amongst Ashkenazim.  Some [[Spanish and Portuguese Jews]] use silk ''tallitot''. The Portuguese Jewish community in The Netherlands has the tradition of decorating the corners of the Tallit. Today some tallitot are made of [[polyester]] and cotton. ''Tallitot'' may be of any colour but are usually white with black, blue or white stripes along the edge. Sizes of tallitot vary, and are a matter of custom and preference. Some are large enough to cover the whole body while others hang around the shoulders, the former being more common amongst Orthodox Jews, the latter among Conservative, Reform and other denominations. The neckband of the tallit, sometimes woven of silver or gold thread, is called the ''[[atarah]]''. The ''tallit gadol'' is often kept in a dedicated pouch or cloth bag, which can be quite simple or ornately decorated.

The tallit gadol is typically either all white, white with black stripes, white with blue stripes, or white with twelve-colored stripes. The all-white and black-and-white varieties have traditionally been the commonest, with the blue-and-white variety becoming increasingly prevalent in recent years among non-Orthodox Jews on account of the association of blue and white with the State of Israel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Eisenberg|first=Ronald L.|title=What the Rabbis Said|year=2010|publisher=[[Greenwood Publishing Group]]|location=[[Santa Barbara, California]]|isbn=978-0-313-38450-9|url=http://books.google.co.il/books?id=18OAZvIuW3gC|accessdate=18 December 2011|page=241|chapter=Chapter 12: Synagogue and Prayer|quote=The ''tallit'' is usually white, based on the Talmudic description that God wraps Himself in a ''tallit'' (RH 17b), and &quot;His garment was as white as snow&quot; (Dan. 7:9).}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Strassfeld|first=Michael|title=A Book of Life: Embracing Judaism as a Spiritual Practice|year=2006|publisher=[[Jewish Lights Publishing]]|location=[[Woodstock, Vermont]]|isbn=1-58023-247-7|url=http://books.google.co.il/books?id=y5fa8Yn1AXwC|authorlink=Michael Strassfeld|accessdate=18 December 2011|page=198|chapter=Part Two: The Three Paths|quote=The ''tallit'' may be any combination of colors, but until recently it was most commonly white with black stripes. In modern times blue stripes have become more common. Blue and white, the colors associated with the State of Israel and its flag, actually originated as the 'Jewish colors' because of the ''tallit''.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The all-white variety is customary among Sepharadic communities, whereas among Ashkenazic communities the tendency is toward white tallitot with black stripes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Yitzhak|first=Hertzel Hillel|title=Tzel HeHarim: Tzitzit|year=2006|publisher=Tzel HeHarim|location=[[Chicago]]|isbn=1-58330-292-1|url=http://books.google.co.il/books?id=smV4tK-2BmAC|accessdate=18 December 2011|page=90|chapter=Chapter V: Color of the ''Tallit'' Garment}}&lt;/ref&gt; One explanation for the significance of the black stripes is that their black color symbolizes the destruction of the Temple in Jerusalem and the exile of the Jews from the land of Israel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Dosick|first=Wayne D.|title=Living Judaism: The Complete Guide to Jewish Belief, Tradition, and Practice|year=1995|publisher=[[Harper San Francisco]]|isbn=978-0-06-062119-3|url=http://books.google.co.il/books?id=k7DXAAAAMAAJ|accessdate=18 December 2011|page=223|quote=The ''tallit'' is sometimes decorated with black stripes, which some say is a remembrance or memorial to the destruction of the Holy Temple and the exile.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Fowler|first=Mery|title=World Religions|year=1999|publisher=[[Sussex Academic Press]]|location=[[Brighton]]|isbn=1-898723-49-4|url=http://books.google.co.il/books?id=joydUNzV5R0C|accessdate=18 December 2011|page=15|chapter=Chapter 1: Judaism}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In many Jewish communities, the tallit is worn in the synagogue by all men and boys over [[bar mitzvah]] age (and in some communities even younger). Aside from [[German Jews]] and [[Oberlander Jews]], men in most [[Ashkenazi Jews|Ashkenazi]] communities (which comprise the majority of Jews today) start wearing the tallit after their wedding.

== Women ==

According to the Talmud, and subsequently modern non-egalitarian denominations ([[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox]]), Women are not obligated to wear a ''tallit'', since they are not bound to perform positive [[mitzvah|mitzvot]] which are time-specific,&lt;ref&gt;[[Babylonian Talmud]], tractate Kiddushin 29a&lt;/ref&gt; and the obligation to wear a ''tallit'' only applies by day. Many early authorities did permit women to wear a ''tallit'', such as [[Isaac ibn Ghiyyat]] (b. 1038), [[Rashi]] (1040–1105), [[Rabbeinu Tam]] (ca 1100–1171), [[Zerachya ben Yitzhak Halevi of Lunel]] (ca. 1125–1186), [[Maimonides|Rambam]] (1135–1204), Rabbi [[Eliezer ben Yoel Halevi]] (ca 1140–ca 1225), [[Shlomo ben Aderet|Rashba]] (1235–1310), [[Aharon Halevi of Barcelona]] (b. ca 1235?), Rabbi [[Yisrael Yaaqob Alghazi]] (1680–1761), Rabbi  [[Yomtob ben Yisrael Alghazi]] (1726–1802)). There was, however, a gradual movement towards prohibition, mainly initiated by the Medieval [[Ashkenazi]] Rabbi [[Meir of Rothenburg]] (the ''Maharam''). The ''[[Moses Isserles|Rema]]'' states that while women are technically allowed to don a ''tallit'' it would appear to be an act of arrogance (''yuhara'') for women to perform this commandment&lt;ref&gt;[[Shulkhan Arukh]], [[Orah Hayyim]] 17:2 in ''Mappah''&lt;/ref&gt;). The [[Yaakov ben Moshe Levi Moelin|Maharil]]&lt;ref&gt;Sefer Maharil 7&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Targum]] [[Targum Pseudo-Jonathan|Yonatan Ben Uziel]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Book of Deuteronomy|Devarim]] 22:5&lt;/ref&gt; both view a talit as a “male garment” and thus find that a woman wearing a talit to be in violation of the precept prohibiting a woman from wearing a man’s garment.

In contemporary [[Orthodox Judaism]], there is a debate on the appropriateness of women wearing tzitzit which has hinged on whether women are allowed to perform commandments from which they are exempt. According to Rabbi [[Joseph Soloveitchik]] the issue depends on the intention with which such an act is undertaken, e.g. whether it is intended to fulfill the actual commandment, to bring a person closer to the Almighty, or for political or protest purposes. Other commentators hold that women are prohibited generally, without making an individual inquiry. The view that women donning a ''tallit'' would be guilty of arrogance is cited as applying to attempts of making a political statement as to the ritual status of the genders, particularly in the [[Modern Orthodox]] community, are generally more inclined to regard contemporary women's intentions as religiously appropriate.

[[Moshe Feinstein|Rabbi Moshe Feinstein]] wrote that permission is granted to every woman who wishes to fulfil even those ''mitzvot'' which the Torah did not obligate; and they indeed fulfil a mitzvah and receive the reward for the fulfilment of it including saying the appropriate associated blessing (as with  ''[[shofar]]'', ''[[lulav]]'' etc.). And also ''tzitzit'' are applicable for a woman who desires to wear a four cornered garment - it should be different than a man’s garment - and by attaching ''tzitzit'', she fulfils this ''mitzvah''.&lt;ref&gt;Igrot Moshe, [[Orah Hayyim]] 4:49, s.v. ibra d’ika&lt;/ref&gt;

Rabbi Yisrael Yaaqob Alghazi and Rabbi Yomtob ben Yisrael Alghazi held that the observance of this mitzvah by women was not only permitted but actually commendable, since such diligence amongst the non-obligated would inspire these women's male relatives to be even more diligent in their own observance {{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}.

Women in egalitarian movements ([[Reform Judaism|Reform]], [[Conservative Judaism|Conservative]], [[Reconstructionist Judaism|Reconstructionist]] and others) are not prohibited from wearing a tallit, and usually encouraged to do so.  Some will receive a tallit as a Bat Mitzvah gift.

== References ==
{{Reflist}}
{{Commons category|Tallit}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.tallit.com/Static/Tallit-Guide.aspx Tallit Blessing, tying, and customs]

{{Jewish life}}

[[Category:Jewish ritual objects]]
[[Category:Hebrew words and phrases]]
[[Category:Jewish religious clothing]]
[[Category:Shawls and wraps]]

[[ar:تاليت]]
[[bg:Талит]]
[[bar:Tallit]]
[[cs:Talit]]
[[da:Tallit]]
[[de:Tallit]]
[[es:Talit]]
[[eo:Talito]]
[[fa:تالیت]]
[[fr:Talit]]
[[it:Talled]]
[[he:טלית]]
[[lad:Talit]]
[[ms:Tallit]]
[[nl:Talliet]]
[[ja:タッリート]]
[[no:Tallit]]
[[nn:Tallét]]
[[pl:Talit]]
[[pt:Talit]]
[[ro:Tallit]]
[[ru:Талит]]
[[simple:Tallit]]
[[sk:Talit]]
[[fi:Tallit]]
[[sv:Tallit]]
[[ta:தலிட்]]
[[tr:Tallit]]
[[yi:טלית]]</text>
      <sha1>0lh9s0kwpnt0m4ma1ht2b5ch3wnkmo8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
