<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Tawhid</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>192520</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519346710</id>
      <parentid>519339852</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-23T07:33:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Eeekster</username>
        <id>5583074</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 519339852 by [[Special:Contributions/75.36.239.111|75.36.239.111]] ([[User talk:75.36.239.111|talk]]) unexplained national spelling change</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="51864">{{Islam|beliefs}}
'''Tawhid''' ({{lang-ar|توحيد}} ''{{transl|ar|ALA|tawḥīd&amp;#x202f;}}''; {{lang-en|doctrine of Oneness [of [[God in Islam|God]]]}}; also [[Arabic transliteration|transliterated]] ''Tawheed,'' and ''Tauhid.'') is the concept of [[monotheism]] in [[Islam]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oxfordislamicstudies.com/article/opr/t125/e2356?_hi=0&amp;_pos=2 From the article on Tawhid in Oxford Islamic Studies Online]&lt;/ref&gt; It is the religion's most fundamental concept and holds [[God]] (Arabic: [[Allah]]) is one (''{{transl|ar|ALA|wāḥid&amp;#x202f;}}'') and unique (''[[ahad|''{{transl|ar|ALA|aḥad&amp;#x202f;}}]]'').&lt;ref name=&quot;Allah in Britannica&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia| title=Allah |year=| encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Britannica Online | accessdate=2008-05-28|location=|publisher=|url=http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9005770/Allah}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Qur'an]] asserts the existence of a single and absolute truth that transcends the world; a unique, independent and indivisible being, who is independent of the entire creation.&lt;ref name=&quot;EncRel&quot;&gt;Vincent J. Cornell, Encyclopedia of Religion, Vol 5, pp.3561-3562&lt;/ref&gt; God, according to Islam, is a universal God, rather than a local, tribal, or parochial one—God is an absolute, who integrates all affirmative values and brooks no evil.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barlas96&quot;&gt;[[Asma Barlas]] (2002), p.96&lt;/ref&gt;

Tawhid constitutes the foremost article of the Muslim profession.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoI&quot;&gt;D. Gimaret, ''Tawhid'', [[Encyclopedia of Islam]]&lt;/ref&gt; The first part of the [[Shahada]] is the declaration of belief in the oneness of God.&lt;ref name=&quot;Allah in Britannica&quot;/&gt; To attribute divinity to a created entity is the only unpardonable sin mentioned in the Qur'an.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barlas96&quot;/&gt; Muslims believe that the entirety of the Islamic teaching rests on the principle of Tawhid.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tariq Ramadan 2005, p.203&quot;&gt;Tariq Ramadan (2005), p.203&lt;/ref&gt; There is an uncompromising [[monotheism]] at the heart of the [[Aqidah|Islamic beliefs]] which distinguishes Islam from other [[major religion]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Turner (2006), p.75&lt;/ref&gt;

Islamic intellectual history can be understood as a gradual unfolding of the manner in which successive generations of believers have understood the meaning and implications of professing God's Unity.
Islamic scholars have different approaches toward understanding it. Islamic [[Kalam|theology]], [[Fiqh|jurisprudence]], [[philosophy]], [[Sufism]], even to some degree the Islamic understanding of [[Islamic science|natural sciences]], all seek to explain at some level the principle of tawhid.&lt;ref&gt;Tabatabaei (1981), p.23&lt;/ref&gt;

==Tawhid in the Qur'an==
The [[Qur'an]] is the main information source for understanding the oneness of God in Islam. All Muslim authorities maintain that a true understanding of God is impossible unless He introduces Himself due to the fact that God is beyond the range of human vision and senses.&lt;ref&gt;Holy Qur'an: Chapter 112, Verse 4 - http://quran.com/112/4&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore God tells people who He is by speaking through the [[Prophets of Islam|prophet]]. According to this view the fundamental message of all of the prophets is &quot;There is no god but God.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Chittick (2006), p.47&lt;/ref&gt;

The Qur'an asserts the existence of a single, absolute truth that transcends the world; a unique being who is independent of the creation; a real being indivisible into hypostatic entities or incarnated manifestation. According to the Qur'an:&lt;ref name=&quot;EncRel&quot;/&gt;
{{Quote|&quot;Say (O Muhammad): &quot;Say: He is Allah, the One and Only; Allah, the Eternal, Absolute; He begetteth not, nor is He begotten;  And there is none like unto Him.&quot; |Qur'an, Sura 112 ([[Al-Ikhlas]]), ayat 1-4&lt;ref&gt;{{cite quran|112|1|e=4|s=ns}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

{{Quote|&quot;Thy Lord is self-sufficient, full of Mercy: if it were His will, He could destroy you, and in your place appoint whom He will as your successors, even as He raised you up from the posterity of other people.&quot;|Qur'an, Sura 6 ([[Al-An'am]]), ayat 133&lt;ref&gt;http://quran.com/6/133}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

According to the Qur'an, Tawhid, meaning literally unification or asserting the oneness of Allah (to be the only God who deserves to be worshiped in truth and confirming all attributes with which He has qualified Himself or that are attributed to Him by His Messenger), can be categorised into three tenets of theology; ''Tawhid al Rubu`biya'', ''Tawhid al `Uluhiyya'' and ''Tawheed-al-Asma was-Sifaat''.

===Tawhid al Rubu`biya===
Meaning ''Belief in the Oneness of the Lordship of Allah'', where it is to believe that there is only one Lord for all the universe, its Creator, Organizer, Planner, Sustainer, and the Giver of security and so on that is Allah. In addition to declaring Allah to be One and Unique in His work being creation, sustenance, bringing to life and causing death and so on. As Allah says in the Qur'an;

{{Quote|&quot;Allah created all things and He is the agent on which all things depend&quot;|Qur'an, Sura 39 ([[Az-Zumar]]), ayat 62&lt;ref&gt;{{cite quran|39|62|s=ns}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{Quote|&quot;And Allah created you all and whatever you do.&quot;|Qur'an, Sura 37 ([[As-Saaffat]]), ayat 96&lt;ref&gt;{{cite quran|37|96|s=ns}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{Quote|&quot;It was not you who threw, when you threw, but it was Allah who threw.&quot;|Qur'an, Sura 8 ([[Al-Anfal]]), ayat 17&lt;ref&gt;{{cite quran|8|17|s=ns}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{Quote|&quot;And no calamity strikes except by Allah’s permission.&quot;|Qur'an, Sura 64 ([[At-Taghabun]]), ayat 11&lt;ref&gt;{{cite quran|64|11|s=ns}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Tawhid al `Uluhiyya===
Meaning ''Belief in the Oneness of the Worship of Allah'', where it is to believe in total obedience to Allah, that none has the right to be worshiped  (praying, invoking, asking for help (from the unseen), swearing, slaughtering sacrifices, giving charity, fasting, pilgrimage and so on) except Allah. In addition to declaring Allah as the Only God to whom all acts of worship must be dedicated, such as Salah (prayers), Zakah, Saum (fasting), supplications, vowing and so on. This also includes emotions like love, trust, and fear all of which have degrees which should only be directed to Allah. As Allah tells the Prophet, to say to the pagans, in the Qur'an;

{{Quote|&quot;Say: ‘Who is it that gives you all sustenance from the sky and earth, governs sight and hearing, brings forth life from dead (matter) and death from the living, and plans the affairs of man?’ They will all say: ‘Allah’.&quot;|Qur'an, Sura 10 ([[Yunus]]), ayat 31&lt;ref&gt;{{cite quran|10|31|s=ns}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{Quote|&quot;If you asked them who created them, they would surely say, ‘Allah’.&quot;|Qur'an, Sura 43 ([[Az-Zukhruf]]), ayat 87&lt;ref&gt;{{cite quran|43|87|s=ns}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{Quote|&quot;If you asked them who brings down water from the sky and with it brings the earth to life after its death? They will most certainly say, ‘Allah’.&quot;|Qur'an, Sura 29 ([[Al-Ankabut]]), ayat 63&lt;ref&gt;{{cite quran|29|63|s=ns}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Tawheed-al-Asma was-Sifaat===
Meaning ''Belief in the Oneness of the Names and the Attributes of Allah'', being affirmation of all the Divine Names and Attributes of Allah in a manner that suits His Majesty, as mentioned in the Qu’ran.

{{Quote|&quot;There is nothing like unto Him, and He is the All-Hearer, the All-Seer.&quot;|Qur'an, Sura 42 ([[Ash-Shura]]), ayat 11&lt;ref&gt;{{cite quran|42|11|s=ns}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The Qur'anic passages Sura {{cite quran|34|20-24|style=nosup|expand=no}}, Sura {{cite quran|35|40|style=nosup|expand=no}} and Sura {{cite quran|46|4|style=nosup|expand=no}} provide a basic understanding of the serious nature and consequences of assigning partners or equals to God, a sin known in Islam as ''Shirk''. God will forgive any sin except a person who dies while committing Shirk. The verse {{cite quran|34|20-24|style=nosup|expand=no}} rejects the idea of the duality of God by arguing that both [[Goodness and evil|good and evil]] generate from God's creative act and that the evil forces have no creative power.&lt;ref&gt;R. Kevin Jaques, ''Shirk'', Encyclopedia of Islam and the Muslim World, pp.630-631&lt;/ref&gt;

The Qur'an relates the story of [[Abraham]] in order to provide an example of an intellectual quest for understanding God as the Cause of Causes: Related in verses {{cite quran|6|75-79|style=nosup|expand=no}}, Abraham moves progressively from worshiping the stars, the moon, and the sun to acknowledging God as the sole cause of the heavenly phenomena.&lt;ref name=&quot;EncRel&quot;/&gt;

== Names of God in Islam ==
{{Main|99 Names of God}}
In order to explain the complexity of the unity of God and of the divine nature, the Qur'an uses 99 terms referred to as &quot;Excellent Names of God&quot; (Sura 7:180). Aside from the supreme name &quot;Allah&quot; and the neologism ''al-Rahman'' (referring to the divine beneficence that creates and maintains the universe), other names may be shared by both God and human beings. According to the Islamic teachings, the latter is meant to serve as a reminder of God's immanence rather than being a sign of one's divinity or alternatively imposing a limitation on God's transcendent nature. Attribution of divinity to a created entity, ''shirk'', is considered a denial of the truth of God and thus a major sin.&lt;ref name=&quot;EncRel&quot;/&gt;

==Shirk==
{{Main| Shirk (Islam)}}
Associating others with God is known as Shirk. It is usually but not always in the form of [[idolatry]] and supplicating others than Allah, or believing that they hold the same attributes as Him in an equal or lesser degree. Shirk is divided into two categories; *Greater shirk (Shirk-al-Akbar): open and apparent * Lesser shirk (Shirk-al-Asghar): concealed or hidden. Greater Shirk consists of the above mentioned deeds. A person commits lesser shirk (Shirk-al-Asghar) or hidden polytheism when he claims to believe in God but his thoughts and actions do not reflect his belief. There are also minor forms of Shirk, they must be avoided as well; these include committing a good deed to show off, making an [[oath]] in the name of anyone except God. Within Islam, shirk is an unforgivable crime; God may forgive any sin if one dies in that state except for committing shirk, [[repentance]] is required for its forgiveness.&lt;ref&gt;http://islamqa.info/en/ref/20482&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://islamqa.info/en/ref/34171&lt;/ref&gt; This is mentioned in the Qur'an: {{quote|Allah forgiveth not that partners should be set up with Him; but He forgiveth anything else, to whom He pleaseth; to set up partners with Allah is to devise a sin most heinous indeed.| Qur'an, sura 4 ([[An-Nisa]]), [[ayat]] 48 &lt;ref&gt;{{cite quran|4|48|s=ns}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Discerning the unity of God==
Vincent J. Cornell, a scholar of [[Islamic studies]] quotes the following statement from [[Ali]]:&lt;ref name=&quot;EncRel&quot;/&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt; To know God is to know his oneness. To say that God is one has four meanings: two of them are false and two are correct. As for the two meanings that are false, one is that a person should say &quot;God is one&quot; and be thinking of a number and counting. This is false because that which has no second cannot enter into the category of number. Do you not see that those who say that God is a third of a trinity fall into this infidelity? Another meaning is to say, &quot;So-and-So is one of his people,&quot; namely, a species of this genus or a member of this species. This meaning is also false when applied to God, because it implies likening something to God, whereas God is above all likeness. As to the two meanings that are correct when applied to God, one is that it should be said that &quot;God is one&quot; in the sense that there is no likeness to him among things. Another is to say that &quot;God is one&quot; in the sense that there is no multiplicity or division conceivable in Him, neither outwardly, nor in the mind, nor in the imagination. God alone possesses such a unity.&lt;ref name=&quot;EncRel&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Arguments for the oneness of God==

===Theological arguments===
Theologians usually use reason and deduction to prove the existence, unity and oneness of God. They use a [[teleological argument]] for the existence of God as a creator based on perceived evidence of order, purpose, design, or direction—or some combination of these—in nature. Teleology is the supposition that there is a purpose or directive principle in the works and processes of nature.&lt;ref&gt;يك‌ برهان‌ لمّی نيز در اين‌ باب‌ مطرح‌ شده‌ است‌: يكدستی و يكتايی عالم‌ (خَلْق‌) از يك‌ پديدآورنده‌ و مدبّر حكايت‌ می كند. ...«ذهن‌ سليم‌ متنبه‌ میشود از شدت‌ ارتباط‌ عالَم‌، بعضی به‌ بعض‌ ديگر، بر وحدت‌ خالق [http://www.encyclopaediaislamica.com/madkhal2.php?sid=5052 توحيد در كلام] Encyclopedia Islamica&lt;/ref&gt;

Another argument which is used frequently by theologians is [[Reductio ad absurdum]]. They use it instead of positive arguments as a more efficient way to reject the ideas of opponents.&lt;ref&gt;. استدلال‌ بر توحيد، مسبوق‌ به‌ پذيرش‌ وجود خداست‌ و طبعاً در صورت‌بندی آن‌، غالباً مواجهه‌ با مدعيان‌ و معتقدان‌ به‌ دو يا چند خدا در نظر بوده‌ و نظريه‌ ثنويها و مجوس‌ و نصارا ابطال‌ میشده‌ است‌. به‌ همين‌ سبب‌ از قديمترين‌ زمان‌، متكلمان‌ برای دفاع‌ از آموزه‌ توحيد و اثبات‌ آن‌، احتجاج‌ به‌ روش‌ خُلف‌ را كارآمدتر از ارائه‌ ادله‌ اثباتی میدانسته‌اند. آنان‌ بيشترِ دلايل‌ توحيد را با اين‌ رويكرد ارائه كرده اند. [http://www.encyclopaediaislamica.com/madkhal2.php?sid=5052 توحيد در كلام] Encyclopedia Islamica&lt;/ref&gt; The Quran has also been used this way in several cases.

===God as the Cause of Causes===
{{Main|Kalam cosmological argument}}
Against the [[polytheism]] of [[pre-Islamic Arabia]], the Qur'an argues that the knowledge of God as the creator of everything rules out the possibility of lesser gods since these beings must be themselves created. For the Qur'an, God is an immanent and transcendent deity who actively creates, maintains and destroys the universe. The reality of God as the ultimate cause of things is the belief that God is veiled from human understanding because of the secondary causes and contingent realities of things in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;EncRel&quot;/&gt; Thus the belief in the oneness of God is equated in the Qur'an with the &quot;belief in the unseen&quot; (Sura {{cite quran|2|3|style=nosup|expand=no}}).&lt;ref name=&quot;EncRel&quot;/&gt; The Qur'an summarizes its task in making this &quot;unseen&quot;, to a greater or lesser degree &quot;seen&quot; so that belief in the existence of God becomes a Master-Truth rather than an unreasonable belief. The Qur'an states that God's signals are so near and yet so far,  demanding that its students listen to what it has to say with humility (Sura {{cite quran|50|33|style=nosup|expand=no}}, Sura {{cite quran|50|37|style=nosup|expand=no}}). The Qur'an aims to draw attention to certain obvious facts, turning them into &quot;reminders&quot; of God instead of providing lengthy  &quot;theological&quot; proofs for the existence and unity of God.&lt;ref&gt;Fazlur Rahman (1980), p.2&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ash'ari]] theologians rejected [[Causality|cause and effect]] in essence, but accepted it as something that facilitates humankind's investigation and comprehension of natural processes. These medieval scholars argued that nature was composed of uniform atoms that were &quot;re-created&quot; at every instant by God. The laws of nature were only the customary sequence of apparent causes (customs of God), the ultimate cause of each accident being God himself.&lt;ref&gt;Robert G. Mourison (2002)&lt;/ref&gt;

===God as the Necessary Existent===
{{See also|Cosmological argument|ontological argument}}
An [[ontological argument]] for the [[Existence of God#Arguments for the existence of God|existence of God]] was first proposed by [[Avicenna]] (965-1037) in the ''Metaphysics'' section of ''[[The Book of Healing]]''&lt;ref name=Johnson&gt;Steve A. Johnson (1984), &quot;Ibn Sina's Fourth Ontological Argument for God's Existence&quot;, ''The Muslim World'' '''74''' (3-4), 161–171.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Morewedge|first=P.|title=Ibn Sina (Avicenna) and Malcolm and the Ontological Argument|journal=Monist|volume=54|pages=234–49}}&lt;/ref&gt;  which is known as [[Contingency and necessity argument]] (''Imakan wa Wujub'').

[[Avicenna]] initiated a full-fledged inquiry into the question of [[being]], in which he distinguished between [[essence]] (''Mahiat'') and [[existence]] (''Wujud''). He argued that the fact of existence can not be inferred from or accounted for by the essence of existing things and that form and matter by themselves cannot interact and originate the movement of the universe or the progressive actualization of existing things. Existence must, therefore, be due to an [[Causality|agent-cause]] that necessitates, imparts, gives, or adds existence to an essence. To do so, the cause must be an existing thing and coexist with its effect.&lt;ref name=&quot;Islam in Britannica&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|last= |first= | authorlink= | title=Islam |year=2007| encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Britannica Online | accessdate=2007-11-27|location=|publisher=|url=http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-69190/Islam}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This was the first attempt at using the method of [[a priori (philosophy)|a priori proof]], which utilizes [[Intuition (knowledge)|intuition]] and [[reason]] alone. Avicenna's proof of God's existence is unique in that it can be classified as both a [[cosmological argument]] and an ontological argument. &quot;It is ontological insofar as ‘necessary existence’ in intellect is the first basis for arguing for a [[Necessary Existent]]&quot;. The proof is also &quot;cosmological insofar as most of it is taken up with arguing that [[contingent existents]] cannot stand alone and must end up in a Necessary Existent.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|first=Toby|last=Mayer|title=Ibn Sina's 'Burhan Al-Siddiqin'|year=2001|journal=Journal of Islamic Studies|publisher=[[Oxford Centre for Islamic Studies]], Oxford Journals, [[Oxford University Press]]|volume=12|issue=1|pages=18–39|doi=10.1093/jis/12.1.18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another argument Avicenna presented for God's existence was the problem of the [[mind-body dichotomy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Forming the Mind: Essays on the Internal Senses and the Mind/Body Problem from Avicenna to the Medical Enlightenment|publisher=[[Springer Science+Business Media]]|date=September 30, 2007|isbn=978-1-4020-6083-0|author=edited by Henrik Lagerlund.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Avicenna, the universe consists of a chain of actual beings, each giving existence to the one below it and responsible for the existence of the rest of the chain below. Because an actual infinite is deemed impossible by Avicenna, this chain as a whole must terminate in a being that is wholly simple and one, whose essence is its very existence, and therefore is self-sufficient and not in need of something else to give it existence. Because its existence is not contingent on or necessitated by something else but is necessary and eternal in itself, it satisfies the condition of being the necessitating cause of the entire chain that constitutes the eternal world of contingent existing things.&lt;ref name=&quot;Islam in Britannica&quot;/&gt; Thus his [[Ontological argument|ontological system]] rests on the conception of [[God]] as the ''Wajib al-Wujud'' (necessary existent). There is a gradual multiplication of beings through a timeless emanation from God as a result of his self-knowledge.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|last=Nasr |first=Seyyed Hossein | authorlink=Seyyed Hossein Nasr | title=Avicenna |year=2007| encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Britannica Online | accessdate=2007-11-05|location=|publisher=|url=http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9011433/Avicenna}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://inic.utexas.edu/asnic/phillips/pages/305/avicenna.html AVICENNA'S COSMOLOGICAL ARGUMENT FOR GOD'S EXISTENCE]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Indivisibility of God's sovereignty===
The Qur'an argues that there can be no multiple sources of divine sovereignty since &quot;behold, each god would have taken away what [each] had created, And some would have Lorded it over others!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Barlas96&quot;/&gt; The Qur'an argues that the stability and order prevailing throughout the universe shows that it was created and is being administered by only one God (Sura {{cite quran|28|70-72|style=nosup|expand=no}}).&lt;ref name=&quot;EoI&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;EoQP&quot;/&gt; Verses 27:60-64 for example read:&lt;ref&gt;Fazlur Rahman (1980), p.67, 6&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Quote|&quot;Who has created the heavens and the earth, and Who sends you down rain from the sky? Yea, with it We cause to grow well-planted orchards full of beauty of delight: it is not in your power to cause the growth of the trees in them. (Can there be another) god besides Allah? Nay, they are a people who swerve from justice.Or, Who has made the earth firm to live in; made rivers in its midst; set thereon mountains immovable; and made a separating bar between the two bodies of flowing water? (can there be another) god besides Allah? Nay, most of them know not. Or, Who listens to the (soul) distressed when it calls on Him, and Who relieves its suffering, and makes you (mankind) inheritors of the earth? (Can there be another) god besides Allah? Little it is that ye heed! Or, Who guides you through the depths of darkness on land and sea, and Who sends the winds as heralds of glad tidings, going before His Mercy? (Can there be another) god besides Allah?- High is Allah above what they associate with Him! Or, Who originates creation, then repeats it, and who gives you sustenance from heaven and earth? (Can there be another) god besides Allah? Say, &quot;Bring forth your argument, if ye are telling the truth!&quot;| Qur'an, Sura 27 ([[Al-Naml]]), ayat 60-64&lt;ref&gt;{{cite quran|6|60|e=64|s=ns}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} 

The Qur'an in verse 21:22 states: &quot;If there were numerous gods instead of one, [the heavens and the earth] would be in a sorry state&quot;. Later Muslim theologians elaborated on this verse saying that the existence of at least two gods would inevitably arise between them, at one time or another, a conflict of wills. Since two contrary wills could not possibly be realized at the same time, one of them must admit himself powerless in that particular instance. On the other hand, a powerless being can not by definition be a god. Therefore the possibility of having more than one god is ruled out.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoI&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;EoQP&quot;&gt;Mustansir Mir, ''Polytheism and Atheism'', [[Encyclopedia of the Qur'an]]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other arguments===
The Qur'an argues that human beings have an instinctive distaste for [[polytheism]]: At times of crisis, for example, even the [[idolatry|idolaters]] forget the false deities and call upon the one true God for help. As soon as they are relieved from the danger, they however start associating other beings with God (Sura {{cite quran|29|65|style=nosup|expand=no}}).&lt;ref name=&quot;EoQP&quot;/&gt;

Next, the Qur'an argues that polytheism takes away from human dignity: God has honored human beings and given them charge of the physical world, and yet they disgrace their position in the world by worshipping what they carve out with their own hands.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoQP&quot;/&gt;

Lastly, the Qur'an argues that monotheism is a not a later discovery made by the human race, but rather there is the combined evidence of the prophetic call for monotheism throughout human history starting from [[Adam (Bible)|Adam]]. The Qur'an suggests several causes for deviation from monotheism to polytheism: Great temporal power, regarded by the holder and his subjects as 'absolute' — may lead the holder to think that he is God-like; such claims were commonly forced upon, and accepted by, those who were subject to the ruler. Also, certain natural phenomena (such as the sun, the moon and the stars) inspire feelings of awe, wonder or admiration that could lead some to regard these [[Astrolatry|celestial bodies as deities]]. Another reason for deviation from monotheism is when one becomes a slave to his or her base desires and passions. In seeking to always satisfy the desires, he or she may commit a kind of polytheism         .&lt;ref name=&quot;EoQP&quot;/&gt;

===Atheism===
{{original research|section|date=June 2012}}
The following Qur'anic verses are sometimes cited as a Qur'an argument against atheism. The verses read: {{Quote|&quot;And they say, 'This worldly life of ours is all there is — we die and we live, and nothing but time destroys us.' But they have no knowledge of it; they are only speculating.&quot;|Qur'an, Sura 45 ([[Al-Jathiya]]), ayat 24&lt;ref&gt;{{cite quran|45|24|s=ns}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{Quote|&quot;Were they created without anyone or are they creators? Or have they created Heavens and the Earth? Actually they do not have faith.&quot;|Qur'an, Surah 52 ([[At-Tur]]), ayat 35,36}}

==Interpretations==
{{See also|Early Islamic philosophy}}
Understanding of the meaning of Tawhid is one of the most controversial issues among Muslims. Islamic scholars have different approaches toward understanding it, comprising [[Athari|textualistic approach]], [[Kalam|theological approach]], [[Islamic philosophy|philosophical approach]] and [[Sufism]] and [[Irfan]]i approach. These different approaches lead to different and in some cases opposite understanding of the issue.

===Textualistic approach===
{{Main|Athari}}
The Textualistists by reason of their conception of the divine Attributes, came to represent the divinity as a complex of names and qualifications alongside the divine essence itself. The Athari methodology of textual interpretation is to avoid delving into extensive theological speculation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Corbin 1993, p. 115&quot;&gt;Corbin (1993), p. 115&lt;/ref&gt; With regard to their belief in Tawheed-al-Asma was-Sifaat, or ''Belief in the Oneness of the Names and the Attributes of Allah'', they take a stance of affirmation of all the Divine Names and Attributes of Allah in a manner that suits His Majesty, as mentioned in the Qu’ran and the Sunnah. This tenet is further divided into four aspects regarding the affirmation that it is without tashbih (establishing likeness), takyeef (speculating as to &quot;how&quot; they are manifested in the divine), ta'teel (negating/denying their apparent meaning) and ta'weel (giving it secondary/symbolic meaning which is different from the apparent meaning). This is strongly opposed to the extremes of either speculative philosophy as was warned against by the Imams of the Salaf, chiefly Imam [[Al-Shafi'i]]&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
 | last = Ibn Abil-'Izz
 | first = 
 | title = Sharh al 'Aqeedah at-Tahaawiyyah of Ibn Abil-'Izz, (p. 75); Sharhus-Sunnah (1/218) of Imaam al-Baghawee
 | publisher = 
 | year =
 | page = 
 | quote = My ruling regarding the people of kalam is that they should be beaten with palm leaves and shoes and be paraded amongst the kinsfolk and the tribes with it being announced; This is the reward of the one who abandons the Book (Qur'aan) and the Sunnah and turns to theological rhetoric (kalaam).
 | isbn =  }}
&lt;/ref&gt; and Imam [[Ahmad ibn Hanbal]], or of anthropomorphism which was strongly refuted by Sheikh [[Ibn Taymiyyah]] in his monumental al`Aqeedat al`Wasatiyah who defined the aqeedah or 'creed' of the [[Salaf]] to be the balanced middle path far from the extremities of the various sects prevalent in the Muslim world.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
 | last = Ibn Taymiyyah
 | first = 
 | title = Sharh-Al-Aqeedat-Il-Wasitiyah
 | publisher = Dar us Salam Publications
 | year =
 | page = 
 | quote = The followers of Ahlus Sunnah wal Jama'ah occupy a moderate position between the Ahlut Ta'teel (Jahmiyyah) and Ahlut Tamtheel (Mushabbiha), and are moderate between the Jabariyah sect and the Qadariyah sect regarding the Acts of Allah, and are moderate about the Promises of Allah between the Murji'ah and the Wa'eediyah sects among Qadariyah and are moderate on matters of the Faith and names of the religion between the Harooriyah and Mu'tazilah, and between the Murji'ah and Jahmiyah and are moderate regarding the Companions of the Prophet, peace and blessings be upon him, between the Raafidah and the Khawarij.
 | url= http://www.scribd.com/doc/24706466/Sharh-Al-Aqeedat-Il-Wasitiyah
 | isbn =  }}
&lt;/ref&gt; This is generally summed and codified into the [[Athari]] school of theology.

===Theological viewpoints===
Certain theologians use the term Tawhid in a much broader meaning to denote the totality of discussion of God, his existence and his various attributes. Others go yet further and use the term to ultimately represent the totality of the &quot;principles of religion&quot;. In its current usage, the expressions &quot;Tawhid&quot; or &quot;knowledge of Tawhid&quot; are sometimes used as an equivalent for the whole Kalam, the [[Islamic theology]].&lt;ref name=&quot;EoI&quot;/&gt;

====Mu'tazili school====
{{Main|Mu'tazili}}
The Mu'tazilis liked to call themselves the ''men of the tawhid'' (ahl al-tawhid). In Maqalat al-Islamiyin, [[Abu al-Hasan al-Ash'ari]] describes the Mu'tazilite conception of the tawhid as follows&lt;ref&gt;Corbin (1993), pp. 109 and 110&lt;/ref&gt;:
&lt;blockquote&gt;God is unique, nothing is like him; he is neither body, nor individual, nor substance, nor accident. He is beyond time. He cannot dwell in a place or within a being; he is not the object of any creatural attribute or qualification. He is neither conditioned nor determined, neither engendered nor engendering. He is beyond the perception of the senses. The eyes cannot see him, observation cannot attain him, the imagination cannot comprehend him. He is a thing, but he is not like other things; he is omniscient, all-powerful, but his omniscience and his all-mightiness cannot be compared to anything created. He created the world without any pre-established archetype and without an auxiliary.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
According to [[Henry Corbin]], the result of this interpretation is the negation of the divine attributes, the affirmation of the created Quran, and the denial of all possibility of the vision of God in the world beyond.&lt;ref&gt;Corbin (1993), p. 110&lt;/ref&gt; Mu'tazilis believed that
God is deprived of all positive attributes, in the sense that all divine qualifications must be understood as being the essence itself. They resorted to [[Esoteric interpretation of the Qur'an|metaphorical interpretations of Qur'anic verses]] or Prophetic reports with seemingly [[anthropomorphic]] content, e.g., the hand is the metaphorical designation of power; the face signifies the essence; the fact that God is seated on the Throne is a metaphorical image of the divine reign, and so on.&lt;ref name=&quot;Corbin 1993, p. 115&quot;/&gt;

====Ash'ari school====
{{Main|Ash'ari}}
The solution proposed by [[Abu al-Hasan al-Ash'ari]] to solve the problems of tashbih and ta'til concedes that the divine Being possesses in a real sense the Attributes and Names mentioned in the Qur'an. Insofar as these Names and Attributes have a positive reality, they are distinct from the essence, but nevertheless they do not have either existence or reality apart from it. The inspiration of al-Ash'ari in this matter was on the one hand to distinguish essence and attribute as concepts, and on the other hand to see that the duality between essence and attribute should be situated not on the quantitative but on the qualitative level—something which Mu'tazilis thinking had failed to grasp.&lt;ref&gt;Corbin (1993), pp. 115 and 116&lt;/ref&gt;

====Twelvers theology====
{{Main|Theology of Twelvers}}
Twelvers theology is based on the [[Hadith]] which have been narrated from the Islamic prophet [[Muhammad]], [[Ali|the first]], [[Imam Baqir|fifth]], [[Jafar al-Sadiq|sixth]], [[Musa al-Kazim|seventh]] and [[Imam Reza|eighth]] [[Twelve Imams|Imams]] and compiled by Shia scholars such as [[Al-Shaykh al-Saduq]] in ''al-Tawhid''.&lt;ref&gt;Tabatabaei (19981), pp. 23 and 24&lt;/ref&gt;
According to Shia theologians, the attributes and [[99 Names of God|names of God]] have no independent and hypostatic existence apart from the being and essence of God. Any suggestion of these attributes and names being convinced of as separate is thought to entail [[polytheism]]. It would be even incorrect to say God knows by his knowledge which is in his essence but God knows by his knowledge which is his essence. Also God has no physical form and he is insensible.&lt;ref&gt;Momen (1985), p.176&lt;/ref&gt;

===Philosophical viewpoints===
{{Main|Islamic Philosophy|Avicennism}}
[[Al-Farabi]], [[Muhammad ibn Zakariya al-Razi|Al-Razi]] and especially [[Avicenna]] put forward an interpretation of Tawhid in light of reason, with the Qur'an and Hadith serving as a basis. Before Avicenna the discussions among Muslim philosophers were about the unity of God as divine creator and his relationship with the world as creation. The earlier philosophers were affected by the [[Plotinus]]' ideas.
&lt;ref&gt;
&lt;!-- نظريه‌ توحيد و راههای اثبات‌ آن‌ تا پيش‌ از ابن‌سينا غالباً بر محور ارتباط‌ خدا با جهان‌ آفرينش‌، يعنی وحدت‌ آفريننده‌ جهان‌ از جهت‌ آفرينندگی او، در نظر بوده‌ است‌. كندی (ج‌ 1، ص‌ 207) در رساله‌ای كه‌ در پاسخ‌ به‌ علیبن‌ جَهْم‌ نگاشته‌، خدا را به‌ عنوان‌ مُحدِث‌ جهان‌، واحد خوانده‌ و برای اثبات‌ اين‌ مطلب‌، به‌ اقامه‌ استدلال‌ به‌ شيوه‌ مذكور پرداخته‌ است‌. برای فارابی (1405، ص‌ 102) نيز اساس‌ تبيين‌ و اثبات‌ توحيد، همين‌ رابطه‌ آفرينندگی خدا نسبت‌ به‌ جهان‌ است‌. برای تبارشناسيِ اين‌ بذلِ توجه‌ فيلسوفان‌ مسلمان‌ به‌ رابطه‌ خدا با جهان‌ در اثبات‌ توحيد، میتوان‌ به‌ استشهاد فارابی (همانجا) به‌ اُثولوجيا اشاره‌ كرد. با توجه‌ به‌ اينكه‌ اُثولوجيا نوشته‌ فلوطين‌ * (متوفی 269 يا 270 ميلادی) است‌، شايد بتوان‌ يكی از ريشه‌های اين‌ گرايش‌ فيلسوفان‌ مسلمان‌ را انديشه‌ فلوطين‌ دانست‌. گر چه‌ فارابی (1982، ص‌ 39؛ همو، 1993، ص‌ 42، 45) بنا بر اين‌ گرايش‌، در اثبات‌ وحدت‌ خدا از برخی معانی، مانند «اول‌ بودن‌»، استفاده‌ كرده‌، لكن‌ بر خلاف‌ فلوطين‌، رابطه‌ خدا را با جهان‌ همانند رابطه‌ جزء و كل‌، و نوعی رابطه‌ درونی و حلولی ندانسته‌، بلكه‌ بر تغاير جوهری و ذاتی خدا با جهان‌ تصريح‌ نموده‌ است‌. علاوه‌ بر اين‌، از حيث‌ وجود نيز خدا را وجودی خاص‌ و متمايز و از اين‌ جهت‌ نيز «واحد» دانست --&gt;[http://www.encyclopaediaislamica.com/madkhal2.php?sid=5053 ''Tawhid in the words of Philosophers''] [[Encyclopaedia Islamica]]&lt;/ref&gt;

َWhether this view can be reconciled with [[Islam]], particularly given the question of what role is left for God's will, was to become a subject of considerable controversy within intellectual Islamic discourse.

===Sufi and Irfani viewpoint===
{{Main|Sufi cosmology|Sufi metaphysics}}
In Islamic mysticism ([[Sufism]] and [[Irfan]]), Tawhid is not only the affirmation in speech of God's unity, but also as importantly a practical and existential realization of that unity. This is done by rejecting the concepts tied to the world of multiplicity, to  isolate the eternal from the temporal in a practical way. The ideal is a radical purification from all worldliness.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carl Ernst 1984, p.29&quot;&gt;[[Carl Ernst]] (1984), p.29&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Vincent J. Cornall, it is possible to draw up a [[monist]] image of God (''see [[Sufi metaphysics]]'') by describing the reality as a unified whole, with God being a single concept that would describe or ascribe all existing things:&quot;He is the First and the Last, the Evident and the Immanent: and He has full knowledge of all things.&quot;(Sura {{cite quran|57|3|style=nosup|expand=no}})&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;EncRel&quot;/&gt; However this is in total contrast to Sunni Islam and throughout history any claim to this effect had been vigorously criticize as is directly blurring the distinction between the creator and the creature, and its incompatibility with the genuine and absolute monotheism of Islam.&lt;ref&gt;Roger S. Gottlie (2006), p.210&lt;/ref&gt; It is chiefly a lack of literary understanding of [[Classical Arabic]] which leads to misunderstanding the Theology of the Qur'an.

For Muslim mystics ([[sufis]]), the affirmation in speech of God's unity is only the first step of Tawhid. Further steps involve a spiritual experience for the existential realization of that unity. Categorizations of different steps of Tawhid could be found in the works of Muslims Sufis like [[Junayd Baghdadi]] and [[al-Ghazali]]. It involves a practical rejection of the concepts tied to the world of multiplicity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carl Ernst 1984, p.29&quot;/&gt; Al-Junayd for example &quot;distinguishes four steps, starting from the simple attestation of unicity which is sufficient for ordinary believers, and culminating in the highest rank reserved for the elite, when the creature totally ceases to exist before his Lord, thus achieving al-fanā fi al-tawhīd [annihilation in unity].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;EoI&quot;/&gt;

====Annihilation and Subsistence====
According to the concept of Annihilation and Subsistence, &quot;Man's existence, or ego, or self-hood...must be annihilated so that he can attain to his true self which is his existence and &quot;subsistence&quot; with God. All of man's character traits and habits, everything that pertains to his individual existence must become completely naughted and &quot;obliterated&quot; (mahw). Then God will give back to him his character traits and everything positive he ever possessed. But at this stage he will know consciously and actually - not just theoretically - and with a through spiritual realization, that everything he is derives absolutely from God. He is nothing but a ray of God's Attributes manifesting the Hidden Treasure.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;[[William Chittick]] (1983), p.179&lt;/ref&gt;

====Unity of Existence====
{{Main|Sufi metaphysics}}
The first detailed formulation of &quot;Unity of Existence&quot; (''wahdat al-wujud'') is closely associated to [[Ibn Arabi]]. Widely different interpretations of the meaning of the &quot;Unity of Existence&quot; have been proposed throughout the centuries by critics, defenders, and Western scholars. Ibn Arabi himself didn't use the term &quot;Unity of Existence&quot; and similar statements had been made by those before him. For example, according to [[al-Ghazali]] &quot;There is nothing in wujud [existence] except God...Wujud [Existence] only belongs to the Real One&quot;. Ghazali explains that the fruit of spiritual ascent of the Sufi is to &quot;witness that there is no existence in the world save God and that 'All things are perishing except his face' (Qur'an 28:88)&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Amin Banani, Richard G. Hovannisian, Georges Sabagh (1994), p.71&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;EoIMW&quot;&gt;[[William Chittick]], ''Wahdat Al-Wujud'', Encyclopedia of Islam and the Muslim World, p.727&lt;/ref&gt;

Many authors consider being or existence to be the proper designation for the reality of God. While all Muslims believe the reality of God to be one, critics hold that the term &quot;existence&quot; (wujud) is also used for the existence of things in this world and that the doctrine blurs the distinction between the existence of the creator and that of the creation. Defenders argued that Ibn Arabi and his followers are offering a &quot;subtle metaphysics following the line of the Asharite formula: “The attributes are neither God nor other than God.” God’s “signs” (ayat) and “traces” (athar)—the creatures—are neither the same as God nor different from him, because God must be understood as both absent and present, both transcendent and immanent. Understood correctly, wahdat al-wujud elucidates the delicate balance that needs to be maintained between these two perspectives.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;EoIMW&quot;/&gt; Shah Wali Allah of Delhi argued that the Ibn Arabi's &quot;unity of being&quot; was experiential and based on a subjective experience of illumination or ecstasy, rather than an ontological reality.&lt;ref&gt;John Esposito (1998), p.121&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--===Consensus on Tanzih===
{{main|Tanzih}}
There is consensus among Hadith, Islamic scholars, philosophers and Sufis in one important issue, which is called [[Tanzih]](transcendence).

Qur'an says &quot;There is nothing whatever like unto Him.&quot;(Sura {{cite quran|42|11|style=nosup|expand=no}}))

[[Muhammad]], the Prophet of Islam, says &quot;Didn't know the God whoever resemble him to his creatures.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;ما عرف الله من شبهه بخلقه&quot;  al-Saduq (1386), Al-Tawhid, Tehran, p. 50 &lt;/ref&gt;

 Ali, one the earliest and prominent companions, says

Avicenna who tried to posit the existence of God through philosophical way says &lt;blockquote&gt;So it's clear that [[the First]](al-Awwal) doesn't have any type, essence, quality, quantity, place, time, similar, partner and opposite, he's exalted and majestic. He doesn't have any restriction and there isn't any arguments for [or against] [[existence of God|him]].&lt;ref&gt;«فقد وضح ان الاول لا جنس له و لا ماهية له و لا كيفية له و لا كمية له و لا اين له و لا متى له و لا ندله و لا شريك له و لا ضدله، تعالى و جل‏وانه لا حد له و لا برهان عليه‏».
الشفاء، الالهيات، مقاله 8، فصل‏5(طبع مصر، صفحه 354). &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Sanai]], a Sufi poet, says

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;
بري از رنج و گدازي بري از درد و نيازي - بري از بيم و اميدي بري از چون و چرائي
نتوان وصف تو گفتن كه تو در فهم نگنجي - نتوان شبه تو جستن كه تو در وهم نيائ&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; --&gt;

==Influences on the Muslim culture==
The Islamic doctrine of Tawhid puts forth a God whose rule, will or law are comprehensive and extend to all creatures and to all aspects of the human life. Early Muslims understood religion to thus cover the domains of state, law and society.&lt;ref name=&quot;Esp24&quot;&gt;[[John Esposito]] (1998), p.24&lt;/ref&gt; It is believed that the entirety of the Islamic teaching rests on the principle of Tawhid.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tariq Ramadan 2005, p.203&quot;/&gt; In the following, we provide a few examples of the influences of Tawhid on the Muslim culture:

===Interpersonal relationship===
According to the Qur'an, one consequence of properly conceived relationship between God and man as the served and servant, is the proper relationship among humans. In order to achieve the former, the Qur'an consistently &quot;reminds&quot; men of two points: 1. That God is one; everything except God (including the entirety of nature) is contingent upon God. 2. With all His might and glory, God is essentially the all-merciful God.&lt;ref&gt;Fazlur Rahman(1980), peacep.2-3&lt;/ref&gt;

===Satanic Logic===
According to the Qur'an, Satan deviated from the oneness of God in the story of [[The Creation of Adam|creation of man]] by permitting his own hierarchical value system to supersede God's will: God asked the angels to bow to Adam, who he had created from clay. Satan refused, saying that &quot;I am better than him; you created me from fire and created him from clay&quot;. The Medieval [[List of Muslim scholars|Muslim scholar]], al-Ghazali pointing out that the only legitimate &quot;preference principle&quot; in the sight of God is piety, writes: &quot;every time a rich man believes that he is better than a poor one, or a white man believes that he is better than a black one, then he is being arrogant. He is adopting the same hierarchical principles adopted by Iblis [Satan] in his jahl [ignorance], and thus falling into shirk [opposite of Tawhid].&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Azizah Al-Hibri (2003)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Secularism and the evolution of public policy===
The modern [[secular state]] (a  by-product of European positivism) resulted from the evolution of [[Policy|public policy]] in west. Islamic scholarship has not however gone through the same process for a variety of reasons: The doctrine of Tawhid implies that the cosmos is a unified harmonious whole, centered around the omnipotent and omnipresent God. As interpreted by Muslim scholars, national sovereignty thus exclusively belonged to God and no room was left for evolution of [[nation-state]] ideas. According to Ozay Mehmet, &quot;Secularism, i.e. policies based on science and man-made rules rather than divine criteria, has been rejected as anti-Islamic. Traditionally, a Muslim is not a nationalist, or citizen of a nation-state; he has no political identity, only a religious membership in the [[Ummah|Umma]]. For a traditional Muslim, Islam is the sole and sufficient identification tag and [[nationalism]] and nation-states are 'obstacles'&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Ozay Mehmet (1990), p.57&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islamic art===
The desire to preserve the unity and transcendence of God led to the prohibition of Muslims from creating representation or visual depictions of God, or of any Prophet including Muhammad. Representations in art of the human form are a disputed matter in [[fiqh]]. The key concern is that the use of statues or images may lead to idolatry. The dominant forms of expression in the Islamic art, thus, became calligraphy and arabesque.&lt;ref name=&quot;Esp24&quot;/&gt;

==See also==
{{Islamic monotheism}}
*[[Allah]]
*[[Divine simplicity]] (the Christian concept of divine unity)
*[[Druze]]
*[[God in Islam]]
*[[Monotheism]]
*[[Names of God in the Qur'an]]
*[[Salvation#Islam|Salvation]]
*[[Shema Yisrael]]
*[[Trinity in Islam]]
*[[Taqarub]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==

;Encyclopedias
*{{cite encyclopedia | editor=P.J. Bearman, Th. Bianquis, C.E. Bosworth, E. van Donzel, W.P. Heinrichs | encyclopedia=[[Encyclopaedia of Islam]] Online | publisher=Brill Academic Publishers | issn=1573-3912}}
*{{cite encyclopedia | editor=Richard C. Martin, Said Amir Arjomand, Marcia Hermansen, Abdulkader Tayob, Rochelle Davis, John Obert Voll | encyclopedia=Encyclopedia of Islam &amp; the Muslim World | publisher=MacMillan Reference Books | year=2003 | isbn=978-0-02-865603-8}}
*{{cite encyclopedia | editor=Lindsay Jones | encyclopedia=Encyclopedia of Religion | publisher=MacMillan Reference Books | edition=2nd | year=2005 | isbn=978-0-02-865733-2}}
* {{cite encyclopedia | encyclopedia = [[Encyclopædia Britannica Online]] | publisher = Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.}}
* {{cite encyclopedia | encyclopedia = [[Encyclopaedia Islamica]] | publisher = }}
; Books
*Banani Amin, co ed.: Richard G. Hovannisian, Georges Sabagh (1994), ''Poetry and Mysticism in Islam: The Heritage of Rumi'', [[Cambridge University Press]], ISBN 0-521-45476-X
*{{cite book | last=Barlas | first=Asma |authorlink=Asma Barlas | title= Believing Women in Islam | publisher=University of Texas Press | year=2002 | isbn=0-292-70904-8}}
*{{cite book|last = Corbin|first = Henry|authorlink = Henry Corbin|coauthors = |title = History of Islamic Philosophy, Translated by Liadain Sherrard, Philip Sherrard|publisher = London; Kegan Paul International in association with Islamic Publications for The Institute of Ismaili Studies |year = 1993 (original French 1964)|isbn = 0-7103-0416-1}}
*[[William Chittick]] (1983), ''The Sufi Path of Love:The Spiritual Teachings of Rumi'', [[State University of New York]] Press, ISBN 0-87395-724-5
*[[William Chittick]] and [[Sachiko Murata]] (2006), ''The Vision of Islam'', Publisher:I.B.Tauris, ISBN 1-84511-320-9
*[[Carl Ernst|Ernst, Carl]] (1984), ''Words of Ecstasy in Sufism'', State University of New York Press, ISBN 0-87395-918-3
*{{cite book | last=Esposito | first=John | authorlink=John Esposito | year=1998 | title=Islam: The Straight Path | publisher=Oxford University Press | isbn=0-19-511233-4}}
*Gottlieb, Roger S. (2006), ''The Oxford Handbook of Religion and Ecology'', Oxford University Press, ASIN B000RKTUVS
*Johnson, Steve A.(1984), &quot;Ibn Sina's Fourth Ontological Argument for God's Existence&quot;, ''The Muslim World'' '''74''' (3-4), 161–171.
* {{cite book | last=Köchler| first=Hans | authorlink= Hans Köchler| title=The Concept of Monotheism in Islam and Christianity| publisher=Braumüller | year=1982| isbn=3-7003-0339-4}}
*Mehmet, Ozay (1990), ''Islamic Identity and Development: Studies of the Islamic Periphery'', Rutledge, ASIN: B000FBFF5Y
* {{cite book | last=Momen | first=Moojan | authorlink= | title= An Introduction to Shi`i Islam: The History and Doctrines of Twelver Shi'ism| publisher=Yale University Press | year=1985 | isbn=0-300-03531-4}}
* {{cite book | last=Nasr| first=Seyyed Hossein | authorlink= Seyyed Hossein Nasr| coauthors = [[William Chittick]]| title=The Essential| publisher=World Wisdom, Inc | year=2007| isbn=1-933316-38-1}}
*[[Fazlur Rahman|Rahman, Fazlur]] (1980), ''Major themes of the Qur'an'', Bibliotheca Islamica, ISBN 0-88297-051-8
*{{cite book | last=Ramadan | first=Tariq |authorlink=Tariq Ramadan | title= Western Muslims and the Future of Islam | publisher=Oxford University Press | year=2005 | isbn=0-19-517111-X}}
*{{Cite book|title=Forming the Mind: Essays on the Internal Senses and the Mind/Body Problem from Avicenna to the Medical Enlightenment|publisher=[[Springer Science+Business Media]]|date=September 30, 2007|isbn=978-1-4020-6083-0|author=edited by Henrik Lagerlund.}}
* {{cite book | last = Tabatabae | first = Sayyid Mohammad Hosayn | authorlink = Allameh Tabatabaei | coauthors = [[William C. Chittick]] (translator)  | title = A Shiʻite Anthology | publisher = Muhammadi Trust of Great Britain &amp; Northern Ireland| year = 1981 | isbn = 0-87395-510-2}}
*{{cite book|last = Turner|first = Colin|authorlink =  |coauthors = |title = Islam: The Basics |publisher = Routledge |year = 2006|isbn = 0-415-34105-1}}

;Journal articles
*Robert G. Mourison, ''The Portrayal of Nature in a Medieval Qur’an Commentary'', Studia Islamica, 2002
*Al-Hibri, Azizah Y. (2003). &quot;An Islamic Perspective on Domestic Violence&quot;. ''27 Fordham International Law Journal'' 195.
*{{Cite journal|first=Toby|last=Mayer|title=Ibn Sina's 'Burhan Al-Siddiqin'|year=2001|journal=Journal of Islamic Studies|publisher=[[Oxford Centre for Islamic Studies]], Oxford Journals, [[Oxford University Press]]|volume=12|issue=1|pages=18–39|doi=10.1093/jis/12.1.18}}
*{{Cite journal|last=Morewedge|first=P.|title=Ibn Sina (Avicenna) and Malcolm and the Ontological Argument|journal=Monist|volume=54|pages=234–49}}

{{Islamic philosophy}}

{{Islam topics|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Ahmadiyya beliefs and doctrines]]
[[Category:Allah]]
[[Category:Islamic theology]]
[[Category:Islamic terms]]
[[Category:Monotheism]]
[[Category:Shi'a theology]]

[[ace:Tauhid]]
[[ar:التوحيد في الإسلام]]
[[ast:Tawhid]]
[[az:Tövhid]]
[[bn:তাওহিদ]]
[[ba:Тәүхид]]
[[bg:Таухид]]
[[bs:Tewhid]]
[[ca:Tawhid]]
[[cy:Tawhid]]
[[da:Tawhid]]
[[de:Tauhīd]]
[[dv:ތައުޙީދު]]
[[es:Tawhid]]
[[eo:Tawhid]]
[[fa:توحید (اسلام)]]
[[fr:Tawhid]]
[[hi:तौहीद]]
[[id:Tauhid]]
[[it:Tawhid]]
[[jv:Tauhid]]
[[kk:Таухид]]
[[mk:Тевхид]]
[[ml:തൗഹീദ്‌]]
[[ms:Tauhid]]
[[nl:Tawhid]]
[[ja:タウヒード]]
[[ce:Товхьид]]
[[no:Tawhid]]
[[ps:توحيد]]
[[pl:Tauhid]]
[[pt:Tawhid]]
[[crh:Tevhit]]
[[ru:Таухид]]
[[sq:Tauhid-i]]
[[simple:Tawhīd]]
[[sd:توحيد]]
[[ckb:یەکتاپەرستی لە ئیسلامدا]]
[[sh:Tawhīd]]
[[fi:Tauhid]]
[[sv:Tawhīd]]
[[ta:தவ்ஹீத்]]
[[tt:Тәүхид]]
[[te:తౌహీద్]]
[[tr:Tevhid (din)]]
[[uk:Таухід]]
[[ur:توحید]]
[[zh:認主學]]</text>
      <sha1>okt7ujed8qwcagklua8wj07rxj9ae6a</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
