<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Temple in Jerusalem</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>30526</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521786194</id>
      <parentid>521784725</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T06:16:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EricEnfermero</username>
        <id>15977090</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edit(s) by [[Special:Contributions/58.169.115.67|58.169.115.67]] identified as test/vandalism using [[WP:STiki|STiki]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27061">{{Main|Solomon's Temple|Second Temple|Third Temple}}

[[File:Jerusalem Modell BW 2.JPG|thumb|275px|A model of [[Herod's Temple]] adjacent to the [[Shrine of the Book]] exhibit at the [[Israel Museum]], Jerusalem.]]
{{Jews and Judaism sidebar|history}}
{|style= &quot;float:right&quot; cellspacing= &quot;0&quot; cellpadding= &quot;0&quot;
| valign= &quot;top&quot; |
|}

The '''Temple in Jerusalem''' or '''Holy Temple''' ([[hebrew language|Hebrew]]: {{lang-he|בֵּית־הַמִּקְדָּשׁ}}, [[Modern Hebrew language|Modern]]: ''{{Unicode|Bet HaMikdash}}'', [[Tiberian vocalization|Tiberian]]: ''{{Unicode|Beṯ HamMiqdāš}}'', [[Ashkenazi Hebrew|Ashkenazi]]: ''Beis HaMikdosh''; {{lang-ar|بيت لقدس}}: ''Beit [[al-Quds]]'') was one of a series of structures which were historically located on the [[Temple Mount]] in the [[Old City (Jerusalem)|Old City of Jerusalem]], the current site of the [[Dome of the Rock]]. Historically, these successive temples stood at this location and functioned as the centre of ancient Israelite and later Jewish worship. According to classical [[Judaism|Jewish belief]], the Temple acted as the figurative &quot;footstool&quot; of [[shechina|God's presence]] and a [[The Third Temple|Third Temple]] will be built there in the [[Jewish eschatology|future]].

==Construction==
The [[Bible]] reports that the [[First Temple]] was built in 957 BCE&lt;ref&gt;New American Heritage Dictionary, entry: 'Temple'&lt;/ref&gt; by [[King Solomon]] (reigned c. 970-c. 930 BCE).&lt;ref name=&quot;ODCC self&quot;&gt;&quot;Temple, the.&quot; Cross, F. L., ed. The Oxford dictionary of the Christian church. New York: Oxford University Press. 2005&lt;/ref&gt; As the sole place of Jewish sacrifice, the Temple replaced the [[Mishkan|portable sanctuary]] constructed in the [[Sinai Desert]] under the auspices of Moses, as well as local sanctuaries, and altars in the hills.&lt;ref&gt;[[Will Durant|Durant, Will]]. Our Oriental Heritage. New York: Simon and Schuster. 1954. p. 307. See 1 Kings 3:2.&lt;/ref&gt; This temple was however sacked a few decades later by [[Sheshonk I]], [[Pharaoh]] of [[Egypt]]. Although efforts were made at partial reconstruction, it was only in 835 BCE when Jehoash, King of Judah in the second year of his reign invested considerable sums in reconstruction, only to have it stripped again for [[Sennacherib]], King of Assyria c. 700 BCE. The First Temple was totally destroyed by the [[Babylonians]] in 586 BCE when they sacked the city.&lt;ref&gt;New American Oxford Dictionary:Temple&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the [[Book of Ezra]], construction of the [[Second Temple]] was authorized by [[Cyrus the Great]] and began in 538 BCE, after the fall of the [[Babylonian Empire]] the year before. It was completed 23 years later, on the third day of Adar, in the sixth year of the reign of [[Darius the Great]] (12 March 515 BCE),&lt;ref name=&quot;Goble2003&quot;&gt;{{cite book|editor=Philip E. Goble|title=The Orthodox Jewish Bible: Tanakh and Orthodox Jewish Brit Chadasha|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=7Bg8CoRcI3AC&amp;pg=PA751|accessdate=11 March 2011|date=February 2003|publisher=AFI International Publishers|isbn=978-0-939341-04-7|page=751}}&lt;/ref&gt; dedicated by the Jewish governor [[Zerubbabel]]. Despite the fact that the new temple wasn't as extravagant or imposing as its predecessor, it still dominated the Jerusalem skyline and remained an important structure throughout the time of Persian suzerainty. The temple narrowly avoided being destroyed again in 332 BCE when the Jews refused to acknowledge the deification of [[Alexander the Great]] of Macedonia. Alexander was allegedly “turned from his anger” at the last minute by astute diplomacy and flattery. After the death of Alexander on 13 June 323 BCE, and the dismembering of his empire, the [[Ptolemies]] came to rule over Judea and the Temple. Under the Ptolemies, the Jews were given many civil liberties and lived content under their rule. However, when the Ptolemaic army was defeated at [[Battle of Panium|Panium]] by [[Antiochus III]] of the Seleucids in 198 BCE, this policy changed. Antiochus wanted to [[Hellenize]] the Jews, attempting to introduce the [[Greek pantheon]] into the temple. A rebellion ensued and was brutally crushed, but no further action by Antiochus was taken. When Antiochus died in 187 BCE at [[Luristan]], his son [[Seleucus IV Philopator]] succeeded him. However, his policies never took effect in Judea, since he was assassinated the year after his ascension. 

[[Antiochus IV Epiphanes]] succeeded his older brother to the Seleucid throne and immediately adopted his father's previous policy of universal Hellenisation. The Jews rebelled again and Antiochus, in a rage, retaliated in force. Considering the previous episodes of discontent, the Jews became incensed when the religious observances of [[Biblical Sabbath|Sabbath]] and [[Circumcision in the Bible|circumcision]] were officially outlawed. When Antiochus erected a statue of [[Zeus]] in their temple and Hellenic priests began sacrificing pigs (the usual sacrifice offered to the [[Greek gods]] in the [[Ancient Greek religion|Hellenic religion]]) their anger began to spiral. When a Greek official asked a Jewish priest to perform a Hellenic sacrifice, the priest ([[Mattathias]]) killed him. Predictably, Antiochus resorted to the same bloody reprisals. In 167 BCE the Jews rose up en masse behind Mattathias and his five sons to fight and win their freedom from Seleucid authority. Mattathias' son [[Judas Maccabeus]], now called &quot;The Hammer&quot;, re-dedicated the temple in 165 BCE and the Jews celebrate this event to this day as a major part of the festival of [[Hanukkah]].

The temple was rededicated under [[Judas Maccabaeus]] in 164 BCE.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODCC self&quot;/&gt; The temple was desecrated again in 54 BCE by [[Crassus]], only for him to die the year after at the [[Battle of Carrhae]] against [[Parthia]]. When news of this reached the Jews, they revolted again, only to be put down in 43 BCE. Around 20 BCE, the building was renovated by [[Herod the Great]], and became known as [[Herod's Temple]]. During the [[Roman Judaea|Roman occupation of Judea]], the Temple remained under control of the Jewish people. It was later destroyed by the [[Roman Empire|Romans]] in 70 CE during the [[Siege of Jerusalem (70)|Siege of Jerusalem]]. During the last revolt of the Jews against the Romans in 132–135 CE, [[Simon bar Kokhba]] and [[Rabbi Akiva]] wanted to rebuild the Temple, but bar Kokhba's revolt failed and the Jews were banned from Jerusalem (except for [[Tisha B'Av]]) by the Roman Empire.  The emperor [[Julian the Apostate|Julian]] failed to have the Temple rebuilt in 363 CE.

After the Muslim conquest of Jerusalem in the 7th century, [[Umayyad]] Caliph [[Abd al-Malik ibn Marwan]] ordered the construction of an [[Islamic]] shrine, the [[Dome of the Rock]], on the site of the Temple. The shrine has stood on the mount since 691 CE; the [[al-Aqsa Mosque]], from roughly the same period, also stands in the Temple courtyard. The mount bears significance in Islam as it acted as a sanctuary for many Hebrew prophets. Islamic tradition says that a temple was first built on the Temple Mount by [[Jacob]] and later renovated by [[Solomon]], son of [[David]]. In addition, it is considered to be the site of the Prophet [[Muhammad]]'s Night Ride {{citation needed|date=July 2012}} ([[Isra and Mi'raj]]) and his ascent into [[Heaven]] - one of the most significant events recounted in the [[Koran]].

==Recent history==
The Temple Mount, along with the entire Old City of Jerusalem, was captured from Jordan by Israel in 1967 during the [[Six-Day War]], allowing Jews once again to pray at the holy site. Israel officially unified [[East Jerusalem]], including the Temple Mount, with the rest of Jerusalem in 1980 under the [[Jerusalem Law]], though [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 478]] declared the Jerusalem Law to be in violation of international law.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Ibn Kathir|title=&quot;Stories of the Prophets&quot;, p. 164-165|year= 2008 |isbn=81-7101-558-1|edition= Translation by Rafiq Abdur Rahman, Idara Isha'at-e-diniyat publishers, India}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Muslim Waqf has administrative control of the Temple Mount.

==Etymology==
The Hebrew name given in the [[Hebrew Bible]] for the building complex is either ''Beit YHWH'' &quot;House of the {{LORD}},&quot; or simply ''Beiti'' &quot;my house&quot;, ''Beitekhah'' &quot;your house&quot; etc. The term ''[[hekhal]]'' &quot;hall&quot; or main building is often translated &quot;temple&quot; in older English Bibles. In rabbinical literature the temple is ''Beit HaMikdash'', &quot;The Sanctified House&quot;, and only the Temple in Jerusalem is referred to by this name.

==Location==
There are three theories as to where the Temple stood:
*The Temple was where the Dome of the Rock is now located.
*The Temple was located a little to the north of the Dome of the Rock (Professor [[Asher Kaufman]]).
*The Temple was located a little to the east of the Dome of the Rock (Professor Joseph Patrich of the [[Hebrew University]]).&lt;ref&gt;See article in the ''World Jewish Digest'', April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
Other theories have the Temple either to the north or to the south&lt;ref&gt;[[Ernest L. Martin]], ''The Temples that Jerusalem Forgot'', 2000&lt;/ref&gt; of the Temple Mount.

==Physical layout==
{{For|the 13 Temple gates as 13 spiritual gates in prayer|Nusach|Nusach Sefard}}
[[File:TempleStepsMay2009.JPG|thumb|250px|Remnants of the 1st century Stairs of Ascent, discovered by archaeologist [[Benjamin Mazar]], to the entrance of the Temple Courtyard. Pilgrims coming to make sacrifices at the Temple would have entered and exited by this stairway.]]
According to the [[Talmud]], the Temple had an ''Ezrat Nashim'' (Women's Court) to the east and main area to the west.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}} The main area contained the butchering area for the sacrifices and the Outer Altar on which portions of most offerings were burned. An edifice contained the ''ulam'' (antechamber), the ''[[hekhal]]'' (the &quot;sanctuary&quot;, the main building), and the [[Kadosh Hakadashim|Holy of Holies]]. The sanctuary and the Holy of Holies were separated by a wall in the First Temple and by two curtains in the Second Temple. The sanctuary contained the [[Menorah (Temple)|seven branched candlestick]], the table of [[showbread]] and the Incense Altar.

The main courtyard had thirteen gates. On the south side, beginning with the southwest corner, there were four gates:
*''Shaar Ha'Elyon'' (the Upper Gate)
*''Shaar HaDelek'' (the Kindling Gate), where wood was brought in
*''Shaar HaBechorot'' (the Gate of Firstborns), where people with first-born animal offerings entered.
*''Shaar HaMayim'' (the Water Gate), where the Water Libation entered on [[Sukkot]].

On the north side, beginning with the northwest corner, there  were four gates:
*''Shaar Yechonyah'' (The Gate of Jeconiah), where kings of the Davidic line enter and [[Jeconiah]] left for the last time to captivity
*''Shaar HaKorban'' (The gate of the [[Korban|Offering]]), where priests entered with ''kodshei kodashim'' offerings
*''Shaar HaNashim'' (The [[Role of women in Judaism|Women's]] Gate), where women entered into the ''Azara'' or main courtyard to perform offerings&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ou.org/torah/tt/5764/vayeitzei64/mikdash.htm Sheyibaneh Beit Hamikdash: Women in the Azara?]&lt;/ref&gt;
*''Shaar Hashir'' (The Gate of Song), where the [[Levites]] entered with their musical instruments

On the east side was ''Shaar Nikanor'', between the Women's Courtyard and the main Temple Courtyard, which had two minor doorways, one on its right and one on its left. On the western wall, which was relatively unimportant, there were two gates that did not have any name.

==Temple services==
{{Main|Korban|Ketoret}}
The Temple was the place where [[korban|offerings]] described in the course of the [[Hebrew Bible]] were carried out, including daily morning and afternoon offerings and special offerings on [[Biblical Sabbath|Sabbath]] and [[Jewish holidays]]. [[Levites]] recited [[Psalms]] at appropriate moments during the offerings, including the Psalm of the Day, special psalms for the [[Rosh Chodesh|new month]], and other occasions, the [[Hallel]] during major Jewish holidays, and psalms for special sacrifices such as the &quot;Psalm for the Thanksgiving Offering&quot; ([[Psalm]] 100).

As part of the daily offering, a prayer service was performed in the Temple which was used as the basis of the traditional Jewish [[Shacharit|(morning) service]] recited to this day, including well-known prayers such as the [[Shema]], and the [[Priestly Blessing]]. The [[Mishna]] describes it as follows:

{{cquote|The superintendent said to them, bless one benediction! and they blessed, and read the [[Ten Commandments]], and the [[Shema]], &quot;And it shall come to pass if you will hearken&quot;, and &quot;And [God] spoke...&quot;. They pronounced three benedictions  with the people present: &quot;True and firm&quot;, and the &quot;Avodah&quot; &quot;Accept, Lord our God, the service of your people Israel, and the fire-offerings of Israel and their prayer receive with favor. Blessed is He who receives the service of His people Israel with favor&quot; (similar to what is today the 17th blessing of the [[Amidah]]), and the [[Priestly Blessing]], and on the [[Shabbat|Sabbath]] they recited one blessing; &quot;May He who causes His name to [[Shekhina|dwell]] in this House, cause to dwell among you love and brotherliness, peace and friendship&quot; on behalf of the weekly Priestly Guard that departed.|||[[Mishna]] [[Tamid]] 5:1}}

Isaiah spoke of the importance of prayer as well as sacrifice in Temple, and of a universal purpose:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
:Even them will I bring to My holy mountain, and make joyful in My house of prayer,
:Their burnt-offerings and their sacrifices shall be acceptable upon Mine altar
:For my house shall be called a house of prayer for all peoples. (Isaiah 56:7, JPS translation).
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[File:Model of Second Temple made by Michael Osnis from Kedumim 1.jpg|thumb|right|150px| [[Replicas of the Jewish Temple|Model of Second Temple]] made by Michael Osnis from Kedumim.]]

==In the Talmud==
The [[Talmud]] (Yoma 9b) provides theological reasons for the destruction: Why was the first Temple destroyed? Because the three cardinal sins were rampant in society: idol worship, licentiousness, and murder… And why then was the second Temple – wherein the society was involved in Torah, commandments and acts of kindness – destroyed?  Because gratuitous hatred was rampant in society.  This teaches that gratuitous hatred is equal in severity to the three cardinal sins: idol worship, licentiousness, and murder.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.divreinavon.com/pdf/SinatHinam.pdf Gratuitous Hatred – What is it and Why is it so bad?]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Role in contemporary Jewish services==
{{Main|Jewish services}}
Part of the traditional Jewish [[Shacharit|morning]] service, the part surrounding the [[Shema]] prayer, is essentially unchanged from the daily worship service performed in the Temple. In addition, the [[Amidah]] prayer traditionally replaces the Temple's daily ''tamid'' and special-occasion ''Mussaf'' (additional) offerings (there are separate versions for the different types of [[sacrifices]]. They are recited during the times their corresponding offerings were performed in the Temple.

The Temple is mentioned extensively in [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox]] [[Jewish services|services]]. [[Conservative Judaism]] retains mentions of the Temple and its restoration, but removes references to the [[korban|sacrifices]]. References to sacrifices on holidays are made in the past tense, and petitions for their restoration are removed. Mentions in Orthodox Jewish services include:

*A daily recital of Biblical and Talmudic passages related to the [[korbanot]] (sacrifices) performed in the Temple ''(See korbanot in [[siddur]])''.
*References to the restoration of the Temple and sacrificial worships in the daily [[Amidah]] prayer, the central prayer in Judaism.
*A traditional personal plea for the restoration of the Temple at the end of private recitation of the Amidah.
*A prayer for the restoration of the &quot;house of our lives&quot; and the [[shekhinah]] (divine presence) &quot;to dwell among us&quot; is recited during the Amidah prayer.
*Recitation of the Psalm of the day; the [[psalm]] sung by the [[Levite]]s in the Temple for that day during the daily morning service.
*Numerous psalms sung as part of the ordinary service make extensive references to the Temple and Temple worship.
*Recitation of the special [[Jewish holidays|Jewish holiday]] prayers for the restoration of the Temple and their offering, during the [[Mussaf]] services on Jewish holidays.
*An extensive recitation of the special Temple service for [[Yom Kippur]] during the service for that holiday.
*Special services for [[Sukkot]] (Hakafot) contain extensive (but generally obscure) references to the special Temple service performed on that day.

The destruction of the Temple is mourned on the Jewish fast day of [[Tisha B'Av]]. Three other minor fasts (Tenth of [[Tevet]], 17th of [[Tammuz (Hebrew month)|Tammuz]], and Third of [[Tishrei]]), also mourn events leading to or following the destruction of the Temple. There are also mourning practices which are observed at all times, for example, the requirement to leave part of the house unplastered.

==In other religions==

===In Christianity===
{{See also|Jerusalem in Christianity}}
In addition to the [[Hebrew Bible]], the Temple is mentioned many times in the [[New Testament]]. In these scriptures, [[Jesus]] prays there ({{bibleverse||Mark|11:12–19}}) and [[Jesus and the Money Changers|chases away money changers]] and other merchants from the courtyard, turning over their tables and accusing them of desecrating a sacred place with secular ways. According to the [[New Testament]] [[Gospels]], it was to the Temple Court that Jesus was brought as a child, to be presented at the Temple (Luke 2:22) and to attend festivals (Luke 2:41). Jerusalem historian Dan Mazar reported in the Jerusalem Christian Review on the numerous archaeological discoveries made at this location by his grandfather, Prof. [[Benjamin Mazar]], which included the [[Christianity in the 1st century|1st century]] stairs of ascent, where Jesus and his [[Disciple (Christianity)|disciples]] preached, as well as the &quot;mikvaot&quot; (or baptismals) used by both [[Christian pilgrimage|Christian and Jewish pilgrims]]. The events of [[Pentecost]], which are recorded in the [[Book of Acts]], also took place at this location. At the area in which Jesus cleanses the Temple of the moneychangers, chasing various commercial traders of doves necessary for the sacrificial rituals away from the sacred precincts ([[Mark 11]]), remarkable findings were uncovered by the elder Mazar, such as a 1st century vessel with the Hebrew word &quot;[[Hebrew of Jesus#Korban .28.CE.BA.CE.BF.CF.81.CE.B2.CE.B1.CE.BD.29|Korban]]&quot;, meaning sacrifice(s). It was believed by Benjamin Mazar that inside this vessel, merchants would have stored the sacrifices sold at the Temple Court.&lt;ref&gt;By Dan Mazar published in Vol. 12 Issue 8 of Jerusalem Christian Review newspaper.&lt;/ref&gt;

Jesus predicts the destruction of the Second Temple ({{bibleverse||Matthew|24:2}}) and allegorically compares his body to a Temple that will be torn down and raised up again in three days. This idea, of the Temple as the [[body of Christ]], became a rich and multi-layered theme in medieval Christian thought (where Temple/body can be the heavenly body of Christ, the [[wikt:ecclesial|ecclesial]] body of the Church, and the Eucharistic body on the altar).&lt;ref&gt;See Jennifer A. Harris, &quot;The Body as Temple in the High Middle Ages&quot;, in Albert I. Baumgarten ed., ''Sacrifice in Religious Experience'', Leiden, 2002, pp. 233–256.&lt;/ref&gt;

===In Islam===
{{See also|Temple Denial}}

Imam [[Abdul Hadi Palazzi]], leader of Italian Muslim Assembly, quotes the Qur'an to support Judaism's special connection to the Temple Mount. According to Palazzi, &quot;The most authoritative Islamic sources affirm the Temples,&quot;. He adds that Jerusalem is sacred to Muslims because of its prior holiness to Jews and its standing as home to the biblical prophets and kings David and Solomon, all of whom he says are sacred figures also in Islam. He claims that the Qur'an &quot;expressly recognizes that Jerusalem plays the same role for Jews that Mecca has for Muslims&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;margolis&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Margolis|first=David|title=The Muslim Zionist|journal=Los Angeles Jewish Journal|date=February 23, 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This view is not universally accepted. Assertions by Muslims that Jews never inhabited the land of Israel in ancient times and therefore have no claim to live in the land today and denial of the authenticity of Jewish claims to ancient holy sites—such as the Temple Mount and the Cave of [[Machpelah]]—appear to be on the increase. In his 2007 book, ''The Fight for Jerusalem: Radical Islam, the West, and the Future of the Holy City,'' Ambassador [[Dore Gold]] calls such claims &quot;Temple Denial&quot;. Israeli intellectual [[David Hazony]] has described the phenomenon as &quot;a campaign of intellectual erasure [by Palestinian leaders, writers, and scholars] ... aimed at undermining the Jewish claim to any part of the land&quot; and compared the phenomenon to [[Holocaust denial]].&lt;ref&gt;Hazony, David. &quot;[http://www.nysun.com/article/49985 Temple Denial In the Holy City]&quot;, ''[[The New York Sun]]'', March 7, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Archaeological evidence==
[[File:To the trumpeting place.jpg|thumb|A stone (2.43×1 m) with [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] writing ''&quot;To the Trumpeting Place&quot;'' uncovered during archaeological excavations by [[Benjamin Mazar]] at the southern foot of the [[Temple Mount]] is believed to be a part of the complex of the Second Temple.]] Archaeological excavations have found dozens of [[mikvah|ritual immersion or baptismal pools]] dating to the 1st century in this area surrounding the [[Temple Mount]]. This is strong evidence that the area was considered one of the holiest sites at the time.

==Building a Third Temple==
{{Main|The Third Temple}}
Ever since the Second Temple's destruction, a prayer for the construction of a Third Temple has been a formal and, by some authorities, optional part of the thrice-daily [[Jewish prayer]] services. However, the question of whether and when to construct the Third Temple is disputed both within the Jewish community and without; groups within Judaism argue both for and against construction of a new Temple, while the expansion of [[Abrahamic religion]] since the 1st century CE has made the issue [[Religious significance of Jerusalem|contentious]] within [[Christianity|Christian]] and [[Islam]]ic thought as well. Furthermore, the complicated [[Positions on Jerusalem|political status of Jerusalem]] makes initiation of reconstruction presently difficult, while the traditional physical location of the historic Temple is presently occupied by the [[Al-Aqsa Mosque]] and the [[Dome of the Rock]].

In 363 CE, the Roman emperor [[Julian the Apostate|Julian]] ordered [[Alypius of Antioch]] to rebuild the Temple as part of his campaign to strengthen non-Christian religions.&lt;ref&gt;Ammianus Marcellinus, ''Res Gestae'', 23.1.2–3.&lt;/ref&gt;  The attempt failed, perhaps due to sabotage, an accidental fire, or an [[Galilee earthquake of 363|earthquake in Galilee]].

==See also==
*[[Jewish Temple at Elephantine]]
*[[Jewish Temple of Leontopolis]]
*First Temple or [[Solomon's Temple]]
*[[Second Temple]], later Herod's Temple
*[[Third Temple]]

==References==
;Notes
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Further reading==
*''[[Biblical Archaeology Review]]'', issues: July/August 1983, November/December 1989, March/April 1992, July/August 1999, September/October 1999, March/April 2000, September/October 2005
*[[Leen Ritmeyer|Ritmeyer, Leen]]. ''The Quest: Revealing the Temple Mount in Jerusalem.'' Jerusalem: Carta, 2006.  ISBN 965-220-628-8
* [[William J. Hamblin|Hamblin, William]] and [[David Seely]], ''Solomon's Temple: Myth and History'' (Thames and Hudson, 2007) ISBN 0-500-25133-9
* Yaron Eliav, ''God's Mountain: The Temple Mount in Time, Place and Memory'' (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2005)

==External links==
* [http://www.chabad.org/library/article_cdo/aid/148149/jewish/Seek-Out-the-Welfare-of-Jerusalem.htm Seek Out the Welfare of Jerusalem] Analytical studies by the Lubavitcher Rebbe, Rabbi [[Menachem Mendel Schneerson|Menachem M. Schneerson]] on the [[Maimonides|Rambam's]] rulings concerning the construction and the design of the Beis HaMikdosh.
* [http://www.orgreality.com/temple/videos.php?id=4 visit of the Temple Institute Museum in Jerusalem conducted by Rav Israel Ariel]
* [http://bible.ag/ezekiel.htm Video tour of a model of the future temple described in Ezekiel chapters 40–49 from a Christian perspective.]
* [https://docs.google.com/uc?id=0BwRNgbXyG_HmNzMyOWRiY2EtYWE2Zi00MDA0LTg3NjYtZjI3YjZhOWM0Y2Y2&amp;export=download&amp;hl=en  The Bible Unearthed: Archaeology’s New Vision of Ancient Israel and the Origin of Its Sacred Texts]
{{Coord|31.77765|N|35.23547|E |format=dms |region:IL_type:landmark_source:placeopedia |display=title}}
* [[Rachel Elior]], &quot;The Jerusalem Temple - The Representation of the Imperceptible&quot;, '''Studies in Spirituality''' 11 (2001): 126-143

{{Tabernacle and Jerusalem Temples}}
{{Jews and Judaism}}
{{Hanukkah Footer}}
{{New Testament places associated with Jesus}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Temple In Jerusalem}}
[[Category:History of Hanukkah]]
[[Category:Jewish history]]
[[Category:Jewish theology]]
[[Category:Tabernacle and Jerusalem Temples| ]]
[[Category:Temple Mount]]

{{Link FA|he}}
[[ar:معبد القدس]]
[[bg:Йерусалимски храм]]
[[ca:Temple de Jerusalem]]
[[cs:Jeruzalémský chrám]]
[[da:Templet i Jerusalem]]
[[de:Jerusalemer Tempel]]
[[et:Jeruusalemma tempel]]
[[es:Templo de Jerusalén]]
[[eo:Templo de Jerusalemo]]
[[eu:Jerusalemgo tenplua]]
[[fa:پرستش‌گاه اورشلیم]]
[[fr:Temple de Jérusalem]]
[[fur:Templi di Jerusalem]]
[[gl:Templo de Xerusalén]]
[[ko:예루살렘 성전]]
[[hr:Jeruzalemski hram]]
[[id:Bait Allah (Yerusalem)]]
[[it:Tempio di Gerusalemme]]
[[he:בית המקדש]]
[[ka:სოლომონის ტაძარი]]
[[sw:Hekalu la Yerusalemu]]
[[lv:Jeruzālemes templis]]
[[lt:Jeruzalės šventykla]]
[[mk:Ерусалимски храм]]
[[mzn:پرستش‌گاه اورشلیم]]
[[ms:Kuil Suci]]
[[nl:Joodse tempel]]
[[ja:エルサレム神殿]]
[[no:Tempelet i Jerusalem]]
[[nn:Tempelet i Jerusalem]]
[[pl:Świątynia Jerozolimska]]
[[pt:Templo de Jerusalém]]
[[ru:Иерусалимский Храм]]
[[sq:Tempulli i Jeruzalemit]]
[[simple:Temple in Jerusalem]]
[[sk:Jeruzalemský chrám]]
[[sr:Jerusalimski Hram]]
[[sh:Jeruzalemski Hram]]
[[fi:Jerusalemin temppeli]]
[[sv:Jerusalems tempel]]
[[tl:Templo sa Herusalem]]
[[ta:எருசலேம் கோவில்]]
[[th:วิหารแห่งเยรูซาเลม]]
[[tr:Kudüs Tapınağı]]
[[uk:Єрусалимський Храм]]
[[vi:Đền thờ Jerusalem]]
[[yi:בית המקדש]]
[[zh:耶路撒冷聖殿]]</text>
      <sha1>7x1qmjolhqicev97s6pi460md8v0jf4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
