<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Temple (Latter Day Saints)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1486485</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522019834</id>
      <parentid>521167309</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T16:12:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>75.151.7.189</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27777">&lt;!-- Note to editors, Latter-day Saint refers specifically to the largest Utah based denomination.  When referring to history shared amongst other denominations use Latter Day Saint --&gt;
[[File:Saltlaketemplehighsmith13507u.jpg|thumb|The [[Salt Lake Temple]], operated by [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]], is the best-known Mormon temple. Located in Salt Lake City, Utah, it is the centerpiece of the 10 acre (40,000 m²) [[Temple Square]].]]
In the [[Latter Day Saint movement]], a '''temple''' is a building dedicated to be a house of [[God]] and is reserved for special forms of worship. A temple differs from a church [[meeting house|meetinghouse]], which is used for [[Worship services of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints#Weekly services|weekly worship services]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |contribution= Of Chapels and Temples: Explaining Mormon Worship Services |title= News Release |date= 15 November 2007 |work= Newsroom |publisher= [[LDS Church]] |url= http://www.mormonnewsroom.org/article/of-chapels-and-temples-explaining-mormon-worship-services |accessdate= 2012-10-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Temples have been a significant part of the Latter Day Saint movement since early in its inception. Today, temples are operated by several [[Latter Day Saint]] denominations. [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] (LDS Church) has 140 operating temples worldwide to perform [[Endowment (Latter Day Saints)|Endowment ceremonies]], marriages, and other services for both the living and by proxy in behalf of dead ancestors with 28 more announced, some in planning stage and others under construction as of 6 October 2012 &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ksl.com/?sid=22446667&amp;nid=1016&amp;title=two-new-lds-temples-announced-at-oct-general-conference|KSL Two new LDS temples announced at Oct General Conference]&lt;/ref&gt;.

Although the most prolific builder of temples within the [[Latter Day Saint movement]] is The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, several other denominations have built or attempted to build temples. [[Community of Christ]] operates two temples in the [[United States]], which are open to the public and are used for worship services, performances, and religious education.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cofchrist.org/templeschool/ ''Temple School'', Community of Christ], (retrieved February 14, 2010)&lt;/ref&gt; Other denominations with temples are the [[Apostolic United Brethren]], the [[Church of Christ (Latter Day Saints)|Church of Christ]], the [[Fundamentalist Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints]] and the [[Righteous Branch of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]]. 
__TOC__
{{Clear}}

==History==
[[File:Kirtlandtemple2.jpg|thumb||The [[Kirtland Temple]], owned and maintained by the [[Community of Christ]], was the first temple of the [[Latter Day Saint movement]] and the only temple completed in the lifetime of [[Joseph Smith, Jr.]]]]
[[File:Nauvoo Temple.jpg|thumb|The [[Nauvoo Temple]]: built in 1846, destroyed soon after, and [[Nauvoo Illinois Temple|rebuilt]] in 2002]]
The [[Latter Day Saint movement]] was conceived as a restoration of practices believed to have been lost in a [[Great Apostasy]] from the true gospel of Jesus Christ.  Temple worship played a prominent role in the Bible's [[Old Testament]], and in the [[Book of Mormon]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://lds.org/ldsorg/v/index.jsp?vgnextoid=f318118dd536c010VgnVCM1000004d82620aRCRD&amp;locale=0&amp;sourceId=37690e46d0bdb010VgnVCM1000004d82620a____&amp;hideNav=1 Questions and Answers] Tambuli, July 1984, 6–10, 24–26&lt;/ref&gt;

On December 27, 1832—two years after the organization of the [[Church of Christ (Latter Day Saints)|Church of Christ]]—the church's founder, [[Joseph Smith, Jr.]], reported receiving a revelation that called upon church members to restore the practice of temple worship.  The Latter Day Saints in [[Kirtland, Ohio]] were commanded to:
:&quot;Establish a house, even a house of prayer, a house of fasting, a house of faith, a house of learning, a house of glory, a house of order, a house of God.&quot; (''[[Doctrine and Covenants]]'' 1835 VII:36, LDS 88:119, RLDS 85:36b)
More importantly, Latter Day Saints see temples as the fulfillment of a prophecy found in {{sourcetext|source=Bible|version=King James|book=Malachi
|chapter=3|verse=1}} (KJV):
:&quot;Behold, I will send my messenger, and he shall prepare the way before me; and the Lord, whom ye seek, shall suddenly come to his temple, even the messenger of the covenant, whom ye delight in:  behold, he shall come, saith the Lord of hosts.&quot;

This is believed to emphasize that when the Lord comes again, he will come &quot;to his temple.&quot;

As plans were drawn up to construct a temple in Kirtland, the decision was made to simultaneously begin work on a [[Temple Lot|second temple]] at the church's colony in [[Jackson County, Missouri|Jackson County]], [[Missouri]].  Surviving plans indicate that both temples would have the same dimensions and approximately the same appearance and both were to be at the &quot;centerplaces&quot; of cities designed according to Smith's plan for the [[Zion (Mormonism)|City of Zion]].

Conflict in Missouri led to the expulsion of the Mormons from Jackson County, preventing any possibility of building a temple there, but work on the temple in Kirtland continued.  At great cost and after great sacrifice, the Latter Day Saints finished the [[Kirtland Temple]] in early 1836.  On March 27, they held a lengthy dedication ceremony and numerous spiritual experiences and visitations were reported.

Conflict relating to the failure of the church's [[Kirtland Safety Society]] bank, caused the church presidency to leave Kirtland and move the church's headquarters to the Mormon settlement of [[Far West, Missouri]].  Far West was also platted along the lines of the City of Zion plan and in 1838 the church began construction of a new, larger temple in the center of the town.  They may also have dedicated a temple site in the neighboring Mormon settlement of [[Adam-ondi-Ahman]].  The events of the [[Mormon War (1838)|1838 Mormon War]] and the expulsion of the Mormons from Missouri left these attempts at temple-building no further progressed than excavating foundations.

In 1839, the Mormons regrouped at a new headquarters in [[Nauvoo, Illinois]].  They were again commanded to build a &quot;House of the Lord&quot; — this one even larger and greater than those that went before.  Plans for the temple in Nauvoo followed the earlier models in Kirtland and Independence with lower and upper courts, but the scale was much increased.

New conflicts arose that caused Joseph Smith, the Prophet and President of the Church, to be murdered, along with his brother Hyrum the [[Patriarch (Mormonism)|Patriarch]], at Carthage Jail on June 27, 1844.  The [[Nauvoo Temple]] stood only half finished.  Eventually, this temple was finished and dedicated.  Some temple ordinances were performed before most of the saints followed Brigham Young west across the Mississippi River.

Joseph Smith's death resulted in a [[Succession crisis (Latter Day Saints)|succession crisis]] which divided the movement into different sects.  The concept of temple worship evolved separately in many of these sects and only the LDS Church continued to build temples until April 1990 when the [[Community of Christ]], then known as the Reorganized Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints (RLDS), began to construct the [[Independence Temple]], which was officially dedicated in 1994.  The Community of Christ still owns the Kirtland Temple, which is used for worship services and special events but also open to visitors, including various Latter Day Saint denominations interested in the building's historical significance.
{{Clear}}

==Purposes==
[[File:1897 Temple Square.jpg|thumb|[[Salt Lake Temple|Temple]] in Salt Lake City on &quot;[[Temple Square]]&quot; circa 1897]]
Temples have held numerous purposes in the Latter Day Saint movement, both historically and their differing expressions today.  These purposes include:

*'''A House of the Lord ''' — Joseph Smith, Jr. reported a revelation in 1836 explaining that the recently-dedicated [[Kirtland Temple]] was built &quot;that the Son of Man might have a place to manifest himself to his people.&quot; (''[[Doctrine and Covenants]]'' LDS 109:5).  All Latter Day Saint denominations with temples still consider temples to be special houses of the Lord.
*'''A House of Learning''' — The Kirtland Temple housed the &quot;School of the Prophets.&quot;
*'''Center of the City of Zion''' — Latter Day Saints often view temples as central to the establishment of [[Zion#Latter-day Saints (Mormons)|Zionic]] communities.  Examples include:  the Kirtland Temple, the original (unfinished) Independence Temple, the (unfinished) [[Far West, Missouri|Far West]] Temple, the (unfinished) [[Adam-ondi-Ahman]] Temple, the original Nauvoo Temple, the [[Salt Lake Temple]], the [[St. George Utah Temple]], the [[Mesa Arizona Temple]], the [[{{Not a typo|Laie Hawaii Temple}}]], and others.
*'''Headquarters of the church''' — the Kirtland Temple served as the headquarters of the early church from its completion in 1836 through the end of 1837.
*'''Sacred spaces for special ordinances''' — Beginning in Nauvoo, temples were spaces in which to perform special ordinances such as the [[Endowment (Latter Day Saints)|endowment]] and [[baptism for the dead]] — ''see'' [[Ordinance (Mormonism)]].
{{Clear}}

==The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints==
[[File:Columbus Ohio Temple 2005.jpg|thumb|The [[Columbus Ohio Temple]], an example of smaller temples built under [[Gordon B. Hinckley|Hinckley's]] direction]]
[[File:MormonTemplePreston.JPG|thumb|The Preston Temple in the United Kingdom in February 2009.]]
{{Main|Temple (LDS Church)}}
{{See also|List of temples of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints}}
[[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] (LDS church) has been the most prolific builder of temples. {{LDS Temple status}} In this church, temples are not only a House of the [[Lord]], but are also where members of the Church make [[Covenant (theology)|covenants]], receive instructions, and perform sacred  [[Ordinance (Latter Day Saints)|ordinances]], such as: [[baptism for the dead]], [[washing and anointing]] (or &quot;initiatory&quot; ordinances), the &quot;[[Endowment (Mormonism)|endowment]],&quot; and [[Celestial marriage|eternal marriage]] [[Sealing (Latter Day Saints)|sealings]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |contribution= Temples |title= Topics and Background |work= Newsroom  |publisher= [[LDS Church]] |url= http://www.mormonnewsroom.org/ldsnewsroom/eng/background-information/temples |accessdate= 2012-10-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Ordinances are a vital part of the theology of the church, which teaches that they were practiced by the Lord's covenant people in all [[Dispensationalist theology|dispensations]]. Additionally, members consider the temple a place to [[Direct revelation|commune with God]], seek God’s aid, understand the will of God, and receive [[Revelation#Latter Day Saint concept of revelation|personal revelation]].

Upon completion, temples are usually open to the public for a short period of time (an &quot;Open House&quot;). During the Open House, the church conducts tours of the temple with [[Missionary (LDS Church)|missionaries]] and members from the local area serving as tour guides, and all rooms of the temple are open to the public. The temple is then dedicated as a &quot;House of the Lord,&quot; after which only members in good standing are permitted entrance, thus they are not churches but rather places of worship.

===History===
In 1832, shortly after the formation of the Church, [[Joseph Smith, Jr.]] said that the Lord desired the [[Latter-day Saints|saints]] build a temple;&lt;ref&gt;Recorded in the [[Doctrine and Covenants]], Smith wrote that the Lord commanded the Saints to &quot;establish a house, even a house of prayer, a house of fasting, a house of faith, a house of learning, a house of glory, a house of order, a house of God;&quot; (see {{lds|D&amp;C|dc|88|119|120}})&lt;/ref&gt; and they completed the [[Kirtland Temple]] in 1836. Differing from other churches in the Latter Day Saint tradition, members feel that the first endowment ceremonies were performed in Kirtland, Ohio, although the endowment performed in Kirtland differed significantly from the endowment performed by Joseph Smith in Nauvoo. The construction of the Nauvoo Temple and the teaching of the full endowment by Smith are seen as the final steps in restoring the Church founded by Jesus Christ following the [[great apostasy]]. Because it is an integral part of their worship, members, upon arriving in Salt Lake City began plans to build temples there, and built the [[Endowment House]] to allow members to receive the endowment until the temples were completed.

===Construction===
Initially, the Church constructed temples in areas where there were large concentrations of members: [[Utah]], [[Idaho]], [[Arizona]], [[Hawai'i]] (all in the USA), and [[Alberta]] ([[Canada]]). In the mid 20th century, because of the importance of temples in the theology, the Church tried to balance density with the travel requirements that attending the temple imposed upon members. Thus, temples were built in [[Europe]] ([[Switzerland]]-1955 and [[England]]-1958); the [[Pacific Islands]] ([[New Zealand]]-1958); and [[Washington, D.C.]]&amp;nbsp;(1974-first American temple East of Utah since [[Nauvoo Temple|Nauvoo]] in 1846) when membership alone might not have justified the effort.

Temple growth continued in the 1980s, [[Spencer W. Kimball]] directed the Church to build smaller temples with similar designs. Before this time, all but the Switzerland temple were at least {{convert|45000|sqft|m2|sigfig=2}}, and the average size of the first 20 temples was {{convert|103000|sqft|m2|sigfig=3}}. The new temples varied in size but were generally less than {{convert|25000|sqft|m2|sigfig=2}} allowing temples to be built where there were fewer members. As a result the first temples in [[South America]] ([[Brazil]]-1978); [[Asia]] ([[Japan]]-1980); and [[Central America]] ([[Mexico City]]-1983) were built and the number of temples doubled from 15 to 36. [[President of the Church (Latter Day Saints)#Presidents of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints|Church president]] and [[Prophet, seer, and revelator|prophet]] [[Gordon B. Hinckley]] (1910–2008) also accelerated the construction of temples through the use of an even smaller standardized base design&lt;ref&gt;Hinckley announced the use of smaller standardized temples in 1997 ({{Cite web|url=http://www.lds.org/conference/talk/display/0,5232,49-1-32-20,00.html |title=Some Thoughts on Temples, Retention of Converts, and Missionary Service |accessdate=2006-10-30 |author=Gordon B. Hinckley |authorlink=Gordon B. Hinckley |work=167th Semiannual General Conference, October 1997 }}). The base design is about {{convert|10700|sqft|m2|sigfig=2}}, and temples built from the design are generally between {{convert|10000|and|18000|sqft|m2|sigfig=2}}. These temples generally do not include a large laundry facility, do not provide members with the ability to rent temple clothing, nor provide a cafeteria for members (Almanac, 2000).&lt;/ref&gt; and set a goal to have 100 operating temples before 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.lds.org/conference/talk/display/0,5232,49-1-26-35,00.html |title=New Temples to Provide &quot;Crowning Blessings&quot; of the Gospel |accessdate=2006-10-30 |author=Gordon B. Hinckley |authorlink=Gordon B. Hinckley |work=168th Annual General Conference, April 1998 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Between the brief building period from 1998 to 2001, 38 of these standardized temples were constructed and dedicated, meeting Hinckley's goal and, during Hinckley's service as president, the number of temples more than doubled from 47 to 124.
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot;/&gt;
[[File:CommunityofChrist Independe.jpg|right|framed|[[Independence Temple]] of [[Community of Christ]] in Independence, Missouri, USA. Dedicated 1994]]


==Community of Christ==
[[Community of Christ]] (formerly the Reorganized Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints) maintains two temples. Unlike those of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, however, these temples are open to the public. Many religious functions take place including [[Sacrament (Mormonism)|Communion]] and a daily prayer for peace.

The temple built in Kirtland, Ohio is [[Kirtland Temple Suit|owned]] and maintained by Community of Christ. This was the first temple actually built (rather than merely planned) by the Latter Day Saint movement and the only temple completed in the lifetime of Joseph Smith, Jr. This temple was the first temple built by [[Latter Day Saint]]s.&lt;!--Do not change this back to &quot;Latter-day Saints&quot;, as &quot;Latter Day Saint&quot; is the correct term in this context; there is a specific &amp; important nuance to both terms.--&gt;

Additionally, during its 1994 World Conference, [[Community of Christ]] dedicated a second temple in [[Independence, Missouri]]. Community of Christ describes this temple as a house of worship and education &quot;dedicated to the pursuit of peace&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Doctrine and Covenants]], Section 156:5. See also Robinson, Kenneth N. (June 2006), [http://www.cofchrist.org/SharePeace/Jul06/Robinson-People-of-Temple.asp A People of the Temple].&lt;/ref&gt; The church holds a [[Daily Prayer for Peace]] at 1:00 p.m. Central Time in the 1,600 seat sanctuary.

[[Image:Independence - Cutlerite Church 01.jpg|thumb|left|250px|[[Cutlerite]] meetinghouse in [[Independence, Missouri]], which serves the functions of a temple for that denomination.]]
==Church of Jesus Christ (Cutlerite)==
The [[Church of Jesus Christ (Cutlerite)]] performs temple ordinances in its Independence, Missouri meetinghouse (their only chapel still in active use),&lt;ref&gt;A second meetinghouse exists in [[Clitherall, Minnesota]], but this is not currently in use.&lt;/ref&gt; though it also believes in the construction of special temple buildings such as the ones in Kirtland and Nauvoo.  Cutlerites do not designate their meetinghouse as a temple, ''per se'', but they believe that it serves precisely the same purpose, and that the ordinances performed there are just as valid as ones done in any historic (pre-1844) LDS temple.&lt;ref&gt;Shields, Steven L., ''Divergent Paths of the Restoration''.  Provo, Utah: Restoration Research, 1982, pg. 63.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cutlerites do not accept the validity of any temple ordinances performed in the LDS temples, or those of any other Latter Day Saint church.&lt;/ref&gt;  As within the LDS church, these sacred services are not open to the public, and participants are forbidden to discuss them outside the room where they are performed.

Cutlerite meetinghouses are constructed with a main-floor chapel that is always open to the public, unless baptisms for the dead are being performed; a second-floor room (closed to the public at all times) is reserved for the ordinances of the Endowment.&lt;ref&gt;Cutlerites do not use the term &quot;Endowment&quot; to refer to these rituals; they generally refer to them as &quot;The Priesthood ordinances.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;  A rectangular-shaped baptismal font is accessed through a trap door beneath the floor of the main-floor chapel, which is used for baptisms of both the living and the dead.  Eternal Marriages are not performed by the Cutlerites, as they have always rejected that particular doctrine.&lt;ref&gt;Shields, Steven L., ''Divergent Paths of the Restoration''.  Provo, Utah: Restoration Research, 1982, pg. 63.&lt;/ref&gt;
  
[[File:LDSTempleDiagram.gif|thumb|400px|This reference chart shows the relative sizes of various temples in the [[Latter Day Saint movement]]. (Note that the [[LDS Church]] has many more temples than are shown and a comparison of those Temples is found on the [[List of temples of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] page.)]]

==Other denominations with temples==
Five additional [[List of sects in the Latter Day Saint movement|Latter Day Saint denomination]]s have built temples:

*Joseph Smith's original [[Church of Christ (Latter Day Saints)|Church of Christ]] built two temples, the Kirtland and [[Nauvoo Temple|Nauvoo]] Temples.

*The [[Church of Christ (Wightite)#Later_church_service_and_Wightite_colony_in_Texas|Church of Christ (Wightite)]] built a temple near [[Zodiac, Texas]], about three miles from [[Fredericksburg, Texas|Fredericksburg]], at a colony founded by [[Lyman Wight]].  The only remaining material infrastructure of the colony is the [[Mormon Mill, Burnet County, Texas|Mormon Mill cemetery]] near Hamilton Creek, about fifty miles east by north of Fredericksburg.&lt;ref&gt;Van Wagenen, Michael. ''The Texas Republic and the Mormon Kingdom of God''. College Station: Texas A&amp;M University Press, 2002. ISBN 158544184&lt;/ref&gt;

*The [[Apostolic United Brethren]] has had a temple in [[Ozumba]], Mexico by at least the 1990s, as well as an Endowment house in Utah since sometime in the 1980s. 

*The [[Fundamentalist Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints]] (FLDS), in 2004 built a temple at their new settlement near [[Eldorado, Texas]].  The foundation of the FLDS temple roughly matches that of the original Nauvoo Temple.  

*The [[Righteous Branch of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]], a denomination founded in 1978, built a pyramid-shaped temple on a “sacred hill” near [[Modena, Utah]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Primer&quot;&gt;Utah Attorney General’s Office and Arizona Attorney General's Office. [http://attorneygeneral.utah.gov/cmsdocuments/The_Primer.pdf The Primer, Helping Victims of Domestic Violence and Child Abuse in Polygamous Communities]. Updated June 2006. Page 23.&lt;/ref&gt; This was the first time any of the [[Mormonism and polygamy|polygamous]] [[Mormon fundamentalists]] sects built a temple of their own.

&lt;gallery&gt;
file:FLDS Eldorado hi.jpg|&lt;center&gt;FLDS Temple&lt;/center&gt;
file:Righteous Branch Temple.jpg|&lt;center&gt;Righteous Branch temple&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Unsuccessful attempts at building temples==
During the life of Joseph Smith, Jr., a few years before the Kirtland temple was built, Smith dedicated a location in Independence, Missouri for the building of a special temple, which was to be the center of a [[Zion (Latter Day Saints)|New Jerusalem]]. However, hostile action by non-Mormon citizens resulted in the expulsion of all Latter Day Saints from the area in 1833, and the planned temple was never begun. As of 2011, the [[Temple Lot|lot]] for this temple is owned and maintained by the [[Church of Christ (Temple Lot)]].  The Temple Lot church endeavored to construct a temple beginning in 1929, as a result of a revelation that Apostle [[Otto Fetting]] of that organization claimed to have received from [[John the Baptist]].  A hole for the proposed temple basement was excavated, and architects' drawings were done, but no further work was completed due to a chronic lack of funding and the expulsion of Fetting and his followers (about one-third of the Temple Lot organization at the time) from the mainline Temple Lot church.  Eventually the City of Independence had the hole filled in, in 1946, and the lot today is mostly covered with grass, with the Church of Christ's meetinghouse and a few trees at the northeast corner.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.deseretnews.com/article/705312028/Jackson-County-temple-lot-saga.html?pg=all Jackson County Temple Lot Saga], ''Deseret News'', 22 June 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;  Today, the Temple Lot church has no plans to build a temple of its own, but rather sees itself as the steward of the Lot until the various Latter Day Saint factions unite around the time of Jesus Christ's [[Second Coming]].

The [[Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints (Strangite)]] endeavored to construct a temple in the mid-1840s in [[Voree, Wisconsin]], according to a rather elaborate plan devised by their prophet [[James J. Strang]].  Poverty and factional infighting among the Strangites prevented the temple from progressing beyond the planning stage.&lt;ref&gt;[http://bycommonconsent.com/2008/10/17/voree-temple/ Voree Temply] by John Hamer, in ''By Common Consent'', 17 October 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;  The church has made no attempt to build temples since Strang's death.

==Performing ordinances in other buildings==
From 1855 to 1889 [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] performed ordinances in the [[Endowment House]] to allow members to receive the endowment during construction of temples in Utah after leaving Nauvoo. Before the Endowment House was built, the [[Council House (Salt Lake City)|Council House]] was similarly used, between 1850 and 1855.

==See also==
{{Portal|Latter-day Saints}}
*[[Endowment House]]
*[[Holy of Holies (LDS Church)]]
*[[List of temples of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]]
*[[Ordinance room]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
{{ref begin|2}}
* David Buerger, &quot;[http://www.signaturebooks.com/mysteries.htm The Mysteries of Godliness: A History of Mormon Temple Worship]&quot;; [[Signature Books]]; ISBN 1-56085-176-7; (paperback)
* [[Richard O. Cowan]], ''Temples to Dot the Earth'', January 1997, ISBN 1-55517-339-X
*{{Cite journal
 | last=Kimball
 | first=Edward L.
 | author-link=Edward L. Kimball
 | title=The History of LDS Temple Admission Standards
 | journal=[[Journal of Mormon History]]
 | volume=24
 | issue=1
 | pages=135–176
 | year=1998
 | url=http://content.lib.utah.edu/u?/jmh,11342
 | postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;
 }}.
* Laurie Smith Monesees, ''The Temple: Dedicated to Peace'', [[Herald House]]: 1993. ISBN 978-0-8309-0648-2
* [[Boyd K. Packer]], ''The Holy Temple'', June 1980, ISBN 0-88494-411-5
* ''Preparing to Enter the Holy Temple'', [[Intellectual Reserve]].
* Elwin C. Robison, ''The First Mormon Temple: Design, Construction, and Historic Context of the Kirtland Temple'', Provo, Utah: [[BYU Press]], 1997. ISBN 0-8425-2333-2
* Speek, Vickie Cleverley. [http://www.signaturebooks.com/strang.htm ''&quot;God Has Made Us a Kingdom&quot; James Strang and the Midwest Mormon'']. [[Signature Books]].
* [[James E. Talmage]], ''[[The House of the Lord]]'' [[Signature Books]] (reprint of the first edition) ISBN 1-56085-114-7; (hardback)
* &quot;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/mormon/customs/temple.shtml The Temple]&quot; British Broadcasting [[BBC]], 2005-11-09. Article on Mormon temple worship from BBC Religion &amp; Ethics website, last accessed 2006-09-19.
{{ref end}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Latter Day Saint temples}}
* [http://lds.org/temples/home/0,11273,1896-1,00.html Official LDS Church site on Temples]
* [http://www.ldschurchtemples.com/ LDSChurchTemples.com]
* [http://www.mormon.org Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints] - Visitors site
* [http://mormontimes.com/around_church/temples/ Mormon Times] - [[Mormon Times]] Temple articles
* [http://www.mormonmonastery.org Topical bibliography + LDS Temple Preparation FAQ]
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PotAd3Gcgt8 Inside a Mormon Temple - Rexburg Idaho (YouTube)]
* [http://www.allaboutmormons.com AllAboutMormons.com]
* [http://www.adherents.com/largecom/com_lds.html#links Temple Geography Links]
* [http://www.historyofmormonism.com/history_mormon_temples.html History of Mormon Temples]
* [http://www.lightplanet.com/mormons/temples/ Mormon Temples]
* [http://www.ilove2seethetemple.com Many Temple photos and prints]
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mXSTO5IWtvg Joseph Smith, Jr. - The Kirtland Temple (YouTube)]
* [http://www.slate.com/id/2061977/ Latter-Day Fortresses: The spooky charisma of Mormon temples] - article at Slate online
{{LDS|hide|hide|hide|show}}

[[Category:Latter Day Saint doctrines, beliefs, and practices]]
[[Category:Latter Day Saint temples| ]]

[[da:Tempel (Sidste Dages Hellige)]]
[[de:Tempel der Kirche Jesu Christi der Heiligen der Letzten Tage]]
[[fr:Temple mormon]]
[[it:Tempio (mormonismo)]]
[[pl:Świątynie Świętych w Dniach Ostatnich]]
[[fi:Temppeli (mormonismi)]]</text>
      <sha1>a4bl99fca5ez8odd4ptwh1q3yyuzyds</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
