<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>The Bible and history</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>166080</id>
    <restrictions>move=:edit=</restrictions>
    <revision>
      <id>521705731</id>
      <parentid>521618457</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T18:38:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ckruschke</username>
        <id>7896724</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 521618457 by [[Special:Contributions/74.196.94.219|74.196.94.219]] ([[User talk:74.196.94.219|talk]]) - reverting unneeded change</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="77592">{{Bible related}}

The [[Bible]] from a [[historical]] perspective, includes numerous fields of study, ranging from [[archeology]] and [[astronomy]] to [[linguistics]] and methods of [[comparative literature]]. Studying the Bible may provide insight into ancient and modern culture, mythology, and morality. Scholars also examine the historical context of Bible passages, the importance ascribed to events by the authors, and the contrast between the descriptions of these events and historical evidence of their occurrence to learn information beyond the literal information presented in the Bible. Historical analysis of the Bible includes questioning the ''historicity of the Bible,'' whether the Bible is an accurate history of ancient Israel.

==Materials and methods==

===Manuscripts and canons===
The Bible exists in multiple manuscripts, none of them [[autograph]]s, and multiple [[Biblical canon|canons]], none of which completely agree on which books have sufficient authority to be included or their order (see [[Books of the Bible]]).

To determine the accuracy of a copied manuscript, [[Textual criticism|textual critics]] scrutinize the way the transcripts have passed through history to their extant forms. The higher the volume of the earliest texts (and their parallels to each other), the greater the textual reliability and the less chance that the transcript's content has been changed over the years. Multiple copies may also be grouped into text types (see [[New Testament#Early manuscripts|New Testament text types]]), with some types judged closer to the hypothetical original than others. Differences often extend beyond minor variations and may involve, for instance, interpolation of material central to issues of historicity and doctrine, such as the [[Mark 16#Mark 16:9–20 in the manuscripts and patristic evidence|ending of Mark 16]].

The books comprising the [[Hebrew Bible]] and the [[Old Testament]] (the two are almost, but not exactly, the same) were written largely in Hebrew, with a few exceptions in Aramaic. Today it exists in several traditions, including the [[Masoretic Text]], the [[Septuagint]] 47 books (a Greek translation widely used in the period from the 3rd century BCE to roughly the 5th century CE, and still regarded as authoritative by the Orthodox Christian churches), the [[Samaritan Torah]], the [[Westminster]] containing the modern 39 books, and others. Variations between these traditions are useful for reconstructing the most likely original text, and for tracing the intellectual histories of various Jewish and Christian communities. The very oldest fragment resembling part of the text of the Hebrew Bible so far discovered is a small silver amulet, dating from approximately 600 BCE, and containing a version of the [[Priestly Blessing]] (&quot;May God make his face to shine upon you...&quot;).

According to the dominant theory called [[Greek primacy]], the [[New Testament]] was originally written in [[Koine Greek|Greek]], of which 5,650 handwritten copies have survived in Greek, over 10,000 in Latin. When other languages are included, the total of ancient copies approaches 25,000. The next ancient text to come close to rivaling that number is [[Homer]]'s [[Iliad]], which is thought to have survived in 643 ancient copies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Komoszewski, J. Ed; Wallace, Daniel J. |title=Reinventing Jesus: What the Da Vinci Code and Other Novel Speculations Don't Tell You |publisher=Kregel Publications |location=Grand Rapids, Mich |year=2006 |isbn=0-8254-2982-X |page=70 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=GtdzmykR_XMC&amp;printsec }}&lt;/ref&gt; Recognizing this, [[F. E. Peters]] remarked that &quot;on the basis of manuscript tradition alone, the works that make up the Christians' New Testament texts were the most frequently copied and widely circulated [surviving] books of antiquity&quot;.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}} (This may be due to their preservation, popularity, and distribution brought about by the ease of seaborne travel and the many roads constructed during the time of the [[Roman Empire]]). When a comparison is made between the seven major [[Textual criticism|critical editions]] of the Greek NT verse-by-verse&amp;nbsp;– namely Tischendorf, [[The New Testament in the Original Greek|Westcott-Hort]], Von Soden, Vogels, Merk, Bover, and [[Novum Testamentum Graece|Nestle-Aland]]&amp;nbsp;– only 62.9% of verses are variant free.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Aland, Barbara; Aland, Kurt |title=The text of the New Testament: an introduction to the critical editions and to the theory and practice of modern textual criticism |publisher=W.B. Eerdmans |location=Grand Rapids, Mich |year=1995 |page=29 |isbn=0-8028-4098-1 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=2pYDsAhUOxAC&amp;printsec }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A four gospel canon (the ''Tetramorph'') was first asserted by [[Irenaeus]], ''c''. 180.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Ferguson, Everett |editors=Sanders, James; McDonald, Lee Martin |title=The Canon Debate |publisher=Hendrickson Publishers |location=Peabody, Mass |year=2002 |page=301 |chapter=Factors leading to the Selection and Closure of the New Testament Canon |isbn=1-56563-517-5 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=5kfh68uC7ycC }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[List of gospels|many other gospels]] that then existed were eventually deemed non-canonical (see [[Biblical canon]]) and suppressed. In his Easter letter of 367, [[Athanasius]], Bishop of Alexandria, gave a list of exactly the same books as what would become the [[New Testament]] canon,&lt;ref name=&quot;Lindberg 2006 15&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=A Brief History of Christianity|first=Carter|last=Lindberg|page=15|year=2006|publisher=Blackwell Publishing|isbn=1-4051-1078-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; and he used the phrase &quot;being canonized&quot; (''kanonizomena'') in regards to them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Brakke, David |title=Canon Formation and Social Conflict in Fourth Century Egypt: Athanasius of Alexandria's Thirty Ninth Festal Letter
|journal=Harvard Theological Review| volume=87|year=1994 |pages=395–419
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Council of Rome]] in 382 under the authority of [[Pope Damasus I]] issued an identical canon,&lt;ref name=&quot;Lindberg 2006 15&quot; /&gt; and his decision to commission the Latin [[Vulgate]] edition of the Bible, ''c''. 383, was instrumental in the fixation of the canon in the West.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Bruce, F. F. |title=The canon of scripture |publisher=Inter-Varsity Press|location=Leicester |year=1988 |page=225 |isbn=0-8308-1258-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; See [[Development of the New Testament canon]] for details.

===Texts===

====Hebrew Bible====
The Hebrew Bible is not a single book but rather a collection of texts, most of them anonymous, and most of them the product of more or less extensive editing prior to reaching their modern form. These texts are in many different genres, but three distinct blocks approximating modern narrative history can be made out.

''[[Torah]]: [[Book of Genesis|Genesis]] to [[Deuteronomy]]''

God creates the world; the world God creates is good, but it becomes thoroughly corrupted by man's decision to sin. God destroys all but the eight remaining righteous people in a [[deluge myth|deluge]] and shortens man's lifespan significantly. God selects [[Abraham]] to inherit the land of [[Canaan]]. The children of [[Israel]], Abraham's grandson, go into [[Egypt]], where their descendants are enslaved. The Israelites are led out of Egypt by [[Moses]] ([[Book of Exodus|Exodus]]) and receive the laws of God, who renews the promise of the land of Canaan.

''Deuteronomic history: [[Joshua]] to [[2 Kings]]''

The [[Israelites]] conquer the land of Canaan under Joshua, successor to Moses. Under the [[Book of Judges|Judges]] they live in a state of constant conflict and insecurity, until the prophet [[Samuel]] anoints [[Saul]] as king over them. Saul proves unworthy, and God selects [[David]] as his successor. Under David the Israelites are united and conquer their enemies, and under [[Solomon]] his son they live in peace and prosperity. But the kingdom is divided under Solomon's successors, Israel in the north and [[Kingdom of Judah|Judah]] in the south, and the kings of Israel fall away from God and eventually the people of the north are taken into captivity by outsiders. Judah, unlike Israel, has some kings who follow God, but many do not, and eventually it too is taken into captivity, and the [[Temple]] of God built by Solomon is destroyed.

''Chronicler's history: [[Books of Chronicles|Chronicles]] and [[Ezra]]/[[Nehemiah]]''

(Chronicles begins by reprising the history of the Torah and the Deuteronomistic history, with some differences over details. It introduces new material following its account of the fall of Jerusalem, the event which concludes the Deuteronomic history). The [[Babylonians]], who had destroyed the Temple and taken the people into captivity, are themselves defeated by the Persians under their king [[Cyrus the Great|Cyrus]]. Cyrus permits the exiles to return to Jerusalem. The Temple is rebuilt, and the Laws of Moses are read to the people.

''Other''

(Several other books of the Hebrew Bible are set in a historical context or otherwise give information which can be regarded as historical, although these books do not present themselves as histories).

The prophets [[Amos (prophet)|Amos]] and [[Hosea]] write of events during the 8th century kingdom of Israel; the prophet [[Jeremiah]] writes of events preceding and following the fall of Judah; [[Ezekiel]] writes of events during and preceding the exile in Babylon; and other prophets similarly touch on various periods, usually those in which they write.

Several books are included in some canons but not in others. Among these, [[Maccabees]] is a purely historical work that treats of the events of the 2nd century BCE. Others are not historical in orientation but are set in historical contexts or reprise earlier histories, such as [[Book of Enoch|Enoch]], an apocalyptic work of the 2nd century BCE.

====New Testament====
While the authorship of a number of the Pauline epistles is largely undisputed, there is no scholarly consensus on the authors of the other books of the New Testament, which most modern scholars acknowledge as pseudonymous autographs&lt;ref&gt;Ehrman, Bart (2011). &quot;Forged: Writing in the Name of God - Why the Bible's Authors Are Not Who We Think They Are&quot;, Harper One, ISBN 0062012614&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=r2&gt;Mack, Burton (1996), &quot;Who Wrote the New Testament?: The Making of the Christian Myth&quot;, Harper One, ISBN 0060655186&lt;/ref&gt; written more than a generation after the events they describe.

''[[Gospels]]/[[Acts]]''

[[Jesus]] is born to [[Saint Joseph|Joseph]] and [[Mary (mother of Jesus)|Mary]]; he is baptised by [[John the Baptist]] and begins a [[Ministry of Jesus|preaching and healing mission]] in [[Galilee]]; he comes up to [[Jerusalem in Christianity|Jerusalem]] to celebrate [[Passover]], is arrested, tried, condemned, and crucified. He is raised from the dead by His own power, [[Resurrection appearances of Jesus|appears before his followers]], issuing the [[Great Commission]], and ascends to Heaven, with a [[Second Coming|promise to return]]. The [[Disciple (Christianity)|followers of Jesus]], who had been fearful following the [[Crucifixion of Jesus|Crucifixion]], are encouraged by Jesus' resurrection and continue to practice and to preach his teachings. The [[Apostle Paul]] preaches throughout the eastern Mediterranean, is arrested, and appeals. He is sent to [[Rome]] for trial, and the narrative breaks off.

''[[Epistles]]/[[Revelation]]''

The epistles (literally &quot;letters&quot;) are largely concerned with theology, but the theological arguments they present form a &quot;history of theology&quot;. Revelation deals with the [[last judgement]] and the [[Christian Eschatology|end of the world]].

===Extra-biblical sources===

Prior to the 19th century, textual analysis of the Bible itself was the only tool available to extract and evaluate whatever historical data it contained. The past two hundred years, however, have seen a proliferation of new sources of data and analytical tools, including:
*Other Near Eastern texts, documents and inscriptions&lt;ref&gt;The most recent and most complete anthology of ancient Near Eastern texts, all translated into English, is ''The Context of Scripture'' (3 vols.; ed. William W. Hallo. assoc. ed. K. Lawson Younger, Jr.; Leiden: Brill, 1997-2002). Its worthy predecessor, which is still useful but lacks many texts discovered since the mid-20th century, is ''Ancient Near Eastern Texts Relating to the Old Testament'' (ed. James B. Pritchard; 3rd ed. with supplement; Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press, 1969).
The two preeminent anthologies of inscriptions of ancient Israel and its immediate neighbors such as Aram (ancient Syria), Ammon, Edom, Moab, Phoenicia, and Philistia (not Egypt or Mesopotamia) are: 1) Shmuel Ahituv, ed., ''Echoes from the Past: Hebrew and Cognate Inscriptions from the Biblical Period'' (Jerusalem: Carta, 2008) and 2) Nahman Avigad and Benjamin Sass, ''Corpus of West Semitic Stamp Seals'' (Jerusalem: Israel Academy of Sciences and Humanities, 1997). This last book has been criticized for mixing seals and seal impressions of known authenticity with unreliable seals and seal impressions of unknown origin, which could be forgeries. In general, if a known place of excavation by an archaeological team is mentioned, the discoveries should be considered reliable; otherwise not.&lt;/ref&gt;
*The material remains recovered throughout the Near East by archaeological excavation, analysed by ever more sophisticated technical and statistical apparatus&lt;ref&gt;The most extensive summary, site by site, is ''The New Encyclopedia of Archaeological Excavations in the Holy Land'' (4 vols. plus supplementary vol. 5; ed. Ephraim Stern; Jerusalem: Israel Exploration Society &amp; Carta, 1993-2008). A two-volume series which gives period-by-period coverage of archaeological discoveries and their significance is 1) Amihay Mazar, ''Archaeological of the Land of the Bible: 10,000-586 B.C.E.'' (New York: Doubleday, 1990) and 2) Ephraim Stern, ''Archaeological of the Land of the Bible, Volume II: the Assyrian, Babylonian, and Persian Periods, 732-332 B.C.E.'' (New York: Doubleday, 2001)&lt;/ref&gt;
*Historical geography, demography, soil science, technology studies, and comparative linguistics&lt;ref&gt;In historical geography, the preeminent book in English is Anson F. Rainey and R. Steven Notley, ''The Sacred Bridge: Carta's Atlas of the Biblical World'' (Jerusalem: Carta, 2006).&lt;/ref&gt;
*Anthropological and sociological modelling
*The [[Apocrypha]], or non-canonical texts

===Writing and reading history===
[[File:Albright 1957.jpg|thumb|left|W.F. Albright, the doyen of biblical archaeology, in 1957]]
The meaning of the term &quot;history&quot; is itself dependent on social and historical context. Paula McNutt, for instance, notes that the Old Testament narratives &quot;do not record 'history' ''in the sense that history is understood in the twentieth century'' ... The past, for biblical writers as well as for twentieth-century readers of the Bible, has meaning only when it is considered in light of the present, and perhaps an idealized future.&quot; (p.&amp;nbsp;4, ''emphasis added'')&lt;ref name=&quot;isbn0-281-05259-X&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=McNutt, Paula M. |title=Reconstructing the society of ancient Israel |publisher=SPCK |location=London |year=1999 |isbn=0-281-05259-X |url=http://books.google.com/?id=hd28MdGNyTYC }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Biblical history has also taken on different meanings in the modern era. The project of [[Biblical archaeology school|biblical archaeology]] associated with [[W.F. Albright]], which sought to validate the historicity of the events narrated in the Bible through the ancient texts and material remains of the [[Near East]],&lt;ref name=&quot;isbn0-8446-0003-2&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Albright, William Foxwell |title=Archaeology of Palestine |publisher=Peter Smith Pub Inc |year=1985 |page=128 |quote=Discovery after discovery has established the accuracy of innumerable details of the Bible as a source of history. |isbn=0-8446-0003-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; has little in common with the view of history described by archaeologist [[William G. Dever|William Dever]]. In discussing the role of his discipline in interpreting the biblical record, Dever has pointed to multiple histories within the Bible, including the history of theology (the relationship between God and believers), political history (usually the account of &quot;Great Men&quot;), narrative history (the chronology of events), intellectual history (ideas and their development, context and evolution), socio-cultural history (institutions, including their social underpinnings in family, clan, tribe and social class and the state), cultural history (overall cultural evolution, demography, socio-economic and political structure and ethnicity), technological history (the techniques by which humans adapt to, exploit and make use of the resources of their environment), natural history (how humans discover and adapt to the ecological facts of their natural environment), and material history (artefacts as correlates of changes in human behaviour).&lt;ref&gt;Dever, William G. (2008), &quot;[[Did God Have a Wife?]]: Archaeology and Folk Religion in Ancient Israel&quot; (Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing Company)&lt;/ref&gt;

A special challenge for assessing the historicity of the Bible is sharply differing perspectives on the relationship between narrative history and theological meaning. Supporters of [[biblical literalism]] &quot;deny that Biblical infallibility and inerrancy are limited to spiritual, religious, or redemptive themes, exclusive of assertions in the fields of history and science. We further deny that scientific hypotheses about earth history may properly be used to overturn the teaching of Scripture on creation and the flood.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;isbn1-58134-056-7&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Henry, Carl Ferdinand Howard |volume=4 |chapter=The Chicago Statement on Biblical Inerrancy |title=God, Revelation and Authority|publisher=Crossway Books |location=Wheaton, Ill |year=1999 |origyear=1979 |pages=211–219 |isbn=1-58134-056-7 |url=http://www.spurgeon.org/~phil/creeds/chicago.htm }}&lt;/ref&gt; But prominent scholars have expressed diametrically opposing views: &quot;[T]he stories about the promise given to the patriarchs in Genesis are not historical, nor do they intend to be historical; they are rather historically determined expressions about Israel and Israel's relationship to its God, given in forms legitimate to their time, and their truth lies not in their facticity, nor in the historicity, but their ability to express the reality that Israel experienced.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Thompson, Thomas |title=The Historicity of the Patriarchal Narratives: The Quest for the Historical Abraham |publisher=Trinity Press International |location=Valley Forge, Pa |year=2002 |origyear=1974 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=lwrzapZYqFAC |isbn=1-56338-389-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This apparently irreconcilable clash of views is most acute for the questions of the greatest contemporary political significance (such as the promise of land by God to Abraham) and theological import (the [[Virgin birth of Jesus|Virgin Birth]] and [[Resurrection]] of Jesus), which are also the &quot;events&quot; that have proved the least susceptible to extra-biblical confirmation.

==Challenges to historicity==

===The Hebrew Bible===
[[File:Lucas Cranach d. Ä. 035.jpg|300px|right|thumb| The Garden of Eden: from history to mythology. By [[Lucas Cranach der Ältere]](1472–1553)]]

Until the 18th century, the general belief in [[Christendom]] was that the earth was created about 4,000 - 5,500 years before the birth of [[Christ]], and that the [[Garden of Eden]], the Flood, the [[Tower of Babel]], and the stories of Abraham and the Exodus described actual events, constituting a genuine narrative history from Creation to the founding of Israel {{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}. However, there had always been a critical tradition as well, dating back to at least [[St Augustine of Hippo]] (354–430), with interpretations &quot;plainly at variance with what are commonly perceived in [[evangelicalism]] as traditional views of Genesis.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal |author=Young, Davis A |title=The contemporary relevance of Augustine's view of Creation |journal=Perspectives on Science and Christian Faith |volume=40 |issue=1 |pages=42–45 |date = March 1988|url=http://www.asa3.org/ASA/PSCF/1988/PSCF3-88Young.html |quote=But someone may ask: 'Is not Scripture opposed to those who hold that heaven is spherical, when it says, who stretches out heaven like a skin?' Let it be opposed indeed if their statement is false.... But if they are able to establish their doctrine with proofs that cannot be denied, we must show that this statement of Scripture about the skin is not opposed to the truth of their conclusions}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Jewish tradition has also maintained a critical thread in its approach to biblical primeval history. The influential medieval philosopher [[Maimonides]] maintained a skeptical ambiguity towards creation ''[[ex nihilo]]'' and considered the stories about [[Adam]] more as &quot;philosophical anthropology, rather than as historical stories whose protagonist is the 'first man'.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;isbn90-247-3439-8&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Klein-Braslavy, Sara |editor=Pines, S.; Yovel, Y. |title=Maimonides and Philosophy (International Archives of the History of Ideas / Archives internationales d'histoire des idées) |chapter=The Creation of the world and Maimonides' interpretation of Gen. i–v |publisher=Springer |location=Berlin |year=1986 |pages=65–78 |isbn=90-247-3439-8 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=SzymWqsNulMC&amp;pg }}&lt;/ref&gt; Greek philosophers, [[Aristotle]],&lt;ref&gt;''Physics'' I, 7&lt;/ref&gt; [[Critolaus]]&lt;ref&gt;Tiziano Dorandi, ''Chapter 2: Chronology'', in Algra et al. (1999) ''The Cambridge History of Hellenistic Philosophy'', page 50. Cambridge&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Proclus]]&lt;ref&gt;Lang, Helen, &quot;Introduction&quot;, p.2 in {{cite book |author=Proclus | title = On the Eternity of the World | publisher = University of California Press | location = Berkeley | year = 2001 | isbn = 0-520-22554-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt; held that the [[Eternity of the world|world was eternal]]. That belief was not uncommon among learned Christians{{Citation needed|date=May 2011|see linked article which doesn't have cites either but quite a ring of truth to it!}}.

[[Galileo]] is the name most closely associated with the first scientific assault on biblical authority, but the heliocentric universe was sufficiently peripheral to biblical ontology to be eventually accommodated. Galileo's writings were on the Catholic [[Index Librorum Prohibitorum|Index of prohibited books]]&lt;ref name=&quot;ban not lifted&quot;&gt;[[#Reference-Heilbron-2005|Heilbron (2005, p.307)]]; [[#Reference-Coyne-2005|Coyne (2005, p.347)]] The practical effect of the ban in its later years seems to have been that clergy could publish discussions of heliocentric physics with a formal disclaimer assuring its hypothetical character and their obedience to the church decrees against motion of the earth: see for example the commented edition (1742) of Newton's 'Principia' by Fathers Le Seur and Jacquier, which contains such a disclaimer ('Declaratio') before the third book (Propositions 25 onwards) dealing with the lunar theory.&lt;/ref&gt; All traces of official opposition to heliocentrism by the church disappeared in 1835 when these works were finally dropped from the Index.&lt;ref name=&quot;ban lifted&quot;&gt;[[#Reference-McMullin-2005|McMullin (2005, p.6)]]; [[#Reference-Coyne-2005|Coyne (2005, p.346)]]. In fact, the Church's opposition had effectively ended in 1820 when a Catholic canon, Giuseppe Settele, was given permission to publish a work which treated heliocentism as a physical fact rather than a mathematical fiction. The 1835 edition of the Index was the first to be issued after that year.&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless [[heliocentricism]] has been accepted by most (but not all) of today's fundamentalists. It was in fact the birth of [[geology]], marked by the publication of [[James Hutton]]'s ''Theory of the Earth'' in 1788, which set in train the intellectual revolution that would dethrone Genesis as the ultimate authority on primeval earth and [[prehistory]]. The first casualty was the Creation story itself, and by the early 19th century &quot;no responsible scientist contended for the literal credibility of the Mosaic account of creation.&quot; (p.&amp;nbsp;224)&lt;ref name=&quot;isbn0-674-34481-2&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Gillispie, Charles Coulston |title=Genesis and geology: a study in the relations of scientific thought, natural theology, and social opinion in Great Britain, 1790–1850 |publisher=Harvard University Press |location=Cambridge |year=1996 |origyear=1951 |isbn=0-674-34481-2 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=PKERMZkA9A0C }}&lt;/ref&gt; The battle between [[uniformitarianism]] and [[catastrophism]] kept the Flood alive in the emerging discipline, until [[Adam Sedgwick]], the president of the Geological Society, publicly recanted his previous support in his 1831 presidential address:&lt;blockquote&gt;We ought indeed to have paused before we first adopted the diluvian theory, and referred all our old superficial gravel to the action of the Mosaic Flood. For of man, and the works of his hands, we have not yet found a single trace among the remnants of the former world entombed in those deposits.&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in {{cite book |author=Gillispie, Charles Coulston |title=Genesis and geology: a study in the relations of scientific thought, natural theology, and social opinion in Great Britain, 1790–1850 |publisher=Harvard University Press |location=Cambridge |year=1996 |origyear=1951 |isbn=0-674-34481-2 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=PKERMZkA9A0C |pages=142–143}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
All of which left the &quot;first man&quot; and his putative descendants in the awkward position of being stripped of all historical context until [[Charles Darwin]] naturalized the Garden of Eden with the publication of ''[[The Origin of Species]]'' in 1859. Public acceptance of this scientific revolution was, and remains, uneven but the mainstream scholarly community soon arrived at a consensus, which holds today, that Genesis 1–11 is a highly schematic literary work representing [[theology]]/[[mythology]] rather than history.&lt;ref name=&quot;isbn0-8308-2551-7&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Wenham, Gordon J. |title=Exploring the Old Testament: A Guide to the Pentateuch|chapter=Genesis 1–11 |publisher=InterVarsity Press |location=Downers Grove, Ill |year=2003 |isbn=0-8308-2551-7 |oclc=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A central pillar of the Bible's historical authority was the tradition that it had been composed by the principal actors or eyewitnesses to the events described&amp;nbsp;– the Pentateuch was the work of Moses, Joshua was by Joshua, and so on. But the [[Protestant Reformation]] had brought the actual texts to a much wider audience, which combined with the growing climate of intellectual ferment in the 17th century that was the start of the [[Age of Enlightenment]] threw a harsh sceptical spotlight on these traditional claims. In Protestant England the philosopher [[Thomas Hobbes]] in his major work [[Leviathan]] denied Mosaic authorship of the Pentateuch, and identified Joshua, Judges, Samuel, Kings and Chronicles as having been written long after the events they purported to describe. His conclusions rested on internal textual evidence, but in an argument that resonates with modern debates, he noted: &quot;Who were the original writers of the several Books of Holy Scripture, has not been made evident by any sufficient testimony of other History, (which is the only proof of matter of fact).&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |author=Hobbes, Thomas |title=Leviathan|chapter=Chapter XXXIII. Of the number, antiquity, scope, authority and interpreters of the books of Holy Scripture |year=1651 |publisher=Andrew Crooke |location=Green Dragon in St. Paul's Churchyard |url=http://www.gutenberg.org/files/3207/3207-h/3207-h.htm#2HCH0033
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Simon leers.jpg|thumb|left|Title page of Simon's ''Critical history'', 1682.]]
The Jewish philosopher and pantheist [[Baruch Spinoza]] echoed Hobbes's doubts about the provenance of the historical books in his ''A Theologico-Political Treatise'' (published in 1670),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Spinoza, Baruch |title=A Theologico-Political Treatise (Part II) |chapter=Chapter VIII. Of the authorship of the Pentateuch and the other historical books of the Old Testament |year=1670 |url=http://www.gutenberg.org/dirs/etext97/2spnt10.txt}}&lt;/ref&gt; and elaborated on the suggestion that the final redaction of these texts was post-exilic under the auspices of Ezra (Chapter IX). He had earlier been effectively excommunicated by the rabbinical council of [[Amsterdam]] for his perceived [[heresies]]. The French priest [[Richard Simon]] brought these critical perspectives to the [[Catholic]] tradition in 1678, observing &quot;the most part of the Holy Scriptures that are come to us, are but Abridgments and as Summaries of ancient Acts which were kept in the Registries of the Hebrews,&quot; in what was probably the first work of biblical textual criticism in the modern sense.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Simon, Richard |title=A critical history of the Old Testament|year=1682|location=London|page=21|publisher=Walter Davis|url=http://ia341236.us.archive.org/1/items/SimonRichard1638-1712ACriticalHistoryOfTheOldTestament1682/SimonRichard1682ACriticalHistoryOfTheOldTestament.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In response [[Jean Astruc]], applying [[source criticism]] methods common in the analysis of classical secular texts to the [[Pentateuch]], believed he could detect four different manuscript traditions, which he claimed Moses himself had redacted. (p.&amp;nbsp;62–64)&lt;ref name=&quot;isbn0-8308-2551-7&quot;/&gt; His 1753 book initiated the school known as [[higher criticism]] that culminated in [[Julius Wellhausen]] formalising the [[documentary hypothesis]] in the 1870s,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Prolegomena to the History of Israel |author=Wellhausen, Julius |location=Edinburgh |publisher=Adam and Charles Black |year=1885 |url=http://www.sacred-texts.com/bib/cv/phai/index.htm
}}&lt;/ref&gt; which in various modified forms still dominates understanding of the composition of the historical narratives.

By the end of the 19th century the scholarly consensus was that the Pentateuch was the work of many authors writing from 1000 BCE (the time of [[David]]) to 500 BCE (the time of [[Ezra]]) and redacted ''c.''450, and as a consequence whatever history it contained was more often polemical than strictly factual&amp;nbsp;– a conclusion reinforced by the then fresh scientific refutations of what were at the time widely classed as biblical mythologies, as discussed above.

In the following decades [[Hermann Gunkel]] drew attention to the mythic aspects of the Pentateuch, and [[Albrecht Alt]], [[Martin Noth]] and the [[tradition history]] school argued that although its core traditions had genuinely ancient roots, the narratives were fictional framing devices and were not intended as history in the modern sense. Though doubts have been cast on the historiographic reconstructions of this school (particularly the notion of oral traditions as a primary ancient source), much of its critique of biblical historicity found wide acceptance. Gunkel's observation that &lt;blockquote&gt;if, however, we consider figures like Abraham, Issac, and Jacob to be actual persons with no original mythic foundations, that does not at all mean that they are historical figures ... For even if, as may well be assumed, there was once a man call 'Abraham,' everyone who knows the history of legends is sure that the legend is in no position at the distance of so many centuries to preserve a picture of the personal piety of Abraham. The 'religion of Abraham' is, in reality, the religion of the legend narrators which they attribute to Abraham&lt;ref name=&quot;isbn0-86554-517-0&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Gunkel, Hermann |editor=Biddle, Mark E. tr |title=Genesis |publisher=Mercer University Press |location=Macon, GA |year=1997 |origyear=1901 |page= lxviii |isbn=0-86554-517-0 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=-ZtH3hbGITkC&amp;pg }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;has in various forms become a commonplace of contemporary criticism.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[F]or not only has &quot;archaeology&quot; not proven a single event of the patriarchal tradition to be historical, it has not shown any of the traditions to be likely ... it must be concluded that any such historicity as is commonly spoken of in both scholarly and popular works about the patriarchs of Genesis is hardly possible and totally improbable.&quot; Thompson, ''op cit'', p. 328&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United States the [[biblical archaeology]] movement, under the influence of Albright, counter-attacked, arguing that the broad outline within the framing narratives was also true, so that while scholars could not realistically expect to prove or disprove individual episodes from the life of Abraham and the other [[patriarchs]], these were real individuals who could be placed in a context proven from the archaeological record. But as more discoveries were made, and anticipated finds failed to materialise, it became apparent that archaeology did not in fact support the claims made by Albright and his followers. Today, only a minority of scholars continue to work within this framework, mainly for reasons of religious conviction.&lt;ref name=&quot;isbn0-385-42590-2&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Mazar, Amihay |title=Archaeology of the land of the Bible, 10,000-586 BCE |publisher=Doubleday |location=Garden City, N.Y |year=1992 |isbn=0-385-42590-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;[Albright's] central theses have all been overturned, partly by further advances in Biblical criticism, but mostly by the continuing archaeological research of younger Americans and Israelis to whom he himself gave encouragement and momentum ... The irony is that, in the long run, it will have been the newer 'secular' archaeology that contributed the most to Biblical studies, not 'Biblical archaeology'.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.2307/3210358 |author=Dever, William |title=What Remains of the House that Albright Built?|journal=The Biblical Archaeologist |volume=56|issue=1|date=March 1993) |pages=25–35 |publisher=The Biblical Archaeologist, Vol. 56, No. 1 |jstor=3210358}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The scholarly history of the [[Deuteronomic history]] parallels that of the Pentateuch: the European [[tradition history]] school argued that the narrative was untrustworthy and could not be used to construct a narrative history; the American Albright school asserted that it could when tested against the archaeological record; and modern archaeological techniques proved crucial in deciding the issue. The test case was the book of Joshua and its account of a rapid, destructive conquest of the Canaanite cities: but by the 1960s it had become clear that the archaeological record did not, in fact, support the account of the conquest given in Joshua: the cities which the Bible records as having been destroyed by the Israelites were either uninhabited at the time, or, if destroyed, were destroyed at widely different times, not in one brief period. The most high-profile example was the &quot;fall of [[Jericho]]&quot;, when new excavations in the 1950s by [[Kathleen Kenyon]] revealed that the city had already been abandoned by the time of Joshua.&lt;ref name=&quot;isbn0-8042-0011-4&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Kenyon, Kathleen Mary; Moorey, P.R.S. |title=The Bible and recent archaeology |publisher=J. Knox Press |location=Atlanta |year=1987 |page=35 |isbn=0-8042-0011-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Thomas L. Thompson]], a leading [[biblical minimalism|minimalist]] scholar for example has written

:&quot;There is no evidence of a [[United Monarchy]], no evidence of a capital in Jerusalem or of any coherent, unified political force that dominated western Palestine, let alone an empire of the size the legends describe. We do not have evidence for the existence of kings named Saul, David or Solomon; nor do we have evidence for any temple at Jerusalem in this early period. What we do know of Israel and Judah of the tenth century does not allow us to interpret this lack of evidence as a gap in our knowledge and information about the past, a result merely of the accidental nature of archeology. There is neither room nor context, no artifact or archive that points to such historical realities in Palestine's tenth century. One cannot speak historically of a state without a population. Nor can one speak of a capital without a town. Stories are not enough.&quot;

Proponents of this theory also point to the fact that the division of the land into two entities, centered at [[Jerusalem]] and [[Shechem]], goes back to the Egyptian rule of Israel in the [[New Kingdom]]. Solomon's empire is said to have stretched from the [[Euphrates]] in the north to the [[Red Sea]] in the south; it would have required a large commitment of men and arms and a high level of organization to conquer, subdue, and govern this area. But there is little archaeological evidence of Jerusalem being a sufficiently large city in the [[10th century BCE]], and [[Kingdom of Judah|Judah]] seems to be sparsely settled in that time period. Since Jerusalem has been destroyed and then subsequently rebuilt approximately 15 to 20 times since the time of David and Solomon, some argue much of the evidence could easily have been eliminated.

The conquests of David and Solomon are also not mentioned in contemporary histories. Culturally, the [[Bronze Age collapse]] is otherwise a period of general cultural impoverishment of the whole Levantine region, making it difficult to consider the existence of any large territorial unit such as the Davidic kingdom, whose cultural features rather seem to resemble the later kingdom of [[Hezekiah]] or [[Josiah]] than the political and economic conditions of the 11th century. Moreover the biblical account makes no claim that they directly governed the areas included in their empires which are portrayed instead as tributaries{{Citation needed|date=January 2009}}. However, since the discovery of an inscription dating to the 9th or 8th century BCE on the [[Tel Dan Stele]] unearthed in the north of Israel, which may refer to the &quot;house of [[David]]&quot; as a monarchic dynast,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|jstor=1357129|author=Schniedewind WM |year=1996|title=Tel Dan Stela: New Light on Aramaic and Jehu's Revolt|journal=Bulletin of the American Schools of Oriental Research|volume=302|pages=75–90|doi=10.2307/1357129}}&lt;/ref&gt; the debate has continued.&lt;ref&gt;Dever, William G. (2002), ''[[What Did the Biblical Writers Know and When Did They Know It?]]'' Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing Company, ISBN 080282126X&lt;/ref&gt; This is still hotly disputed, as well as a heated debate extends as to whether the united monarchy, the vast empire of [[King Solomon]], and the rebellion of [[Jeroboam]] ever existed, or whether they are a late fabrication. The [[Mesha Stele]], dated to c. 840 BCE, may reference the House of David, and mentions events and names found in Kings.&lt;ref&gt;LeMaire, André. [http://jewishhistory.com/pdf/house_of_david.pdf &quot;House of David Restored in Moabite Inscription&quot;], Biblical Archaeology Review, May/June 1994.&lt;/ref&gt;

Once again there is a problem here with the sources for this period of history. There are no contemporary independent documents other than the claimed accounts of the Books of Samuel, which clearly shows too many [[anachronisms]] to have been a contemporary account. For example there is mention of late armor (1 Samuel 17:4–7, 38–39; 25:13), use of [[camels]] (1 Samuel 30:17) and cavalry (as distinct from chariotry) (1 Samuel 13:5, 2 Samuel 1:6), iron picks and axes (as though they were common, 2 Samuel 12:31), sophisticated siege techniques (2 Samuel 20:15), there is a gargantuan troop (2 Samuel 17:1), a battle with 20,000 casualties (2 Samuel 18:7), and refer to Kushite paramilitary and servants, clearly giving evidence of a date in which [[Kushites]] were common, after the [[Twenty-sixth dynasty of Egypt|26th Dynasty of Egypt]], the period of the last quarter of the 8th century BCE.&lt;ref name=&quot;isbn0-691-00086-7&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Redford, Donald B. |title=Egypt, Canaan, and Israel in ancient times|publisher=Princeton University Press |location=Princeton, N.J |year=1992 |page=305 |isbn=0-691-00086-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== New Testament ===
The historicity, teachings, and nature of Jesus are also currently debated among biblical scholars. The &quot;[[quest for the historical Jesus]]&quot; began as early as the 18th century, and has continued to this day. The most notable recent scholarship came in the 1980s and 1990s with the work of [[J. D. Crossan]],&lt;ref&gt;Crossan, J. D. &quot;The Historical Jesus: A Mediterranean Jewish Peasant,&quot; HarperOne, 1993, ISBN 0060616296&lt;/ref&gt; [[James D. G. Dunn]],&lt;ref&gt;James D. G. Dunn, &quot;Jesus Remembered: Christianity in the Making, Vol. 1, Eerdmans, 2003&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; [[John P. Meier]],&lt;ref&gt;John P. Meier, &quot;A Marginal Jew: Rethinking the Historical Jesus, 3 vols., the most recent volume from Yale University Press, 2001&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; [[E. P. Sanders]]&lt;ref&gt;Sanders, E.P. &quot;The Historical Figure of Jesus,&quot; Penguin, 1996, ISBN 0141928220&lt;/ref&gt; and [[N. T. Wright]]&lt;ref&gt;Wright, N.T. &quot;Jesus and the Victory of God: Christian Origins and the Question of God&quot;, Vol. 2, Augsburg Fortress Press, 1997, ISBN 0800626826&lt;/ref&gt; being the most widely read and discussed. The earliest New Testament texts which refer to Jesus, [[Paul of Tarsus|Paul]]'s letters, are usually dated in the 50s CE. Since Paul records very little of Jesus' life and activities, these are of little help in determining facts about the life of Jesus, although they may contain references to information given to Paul from the eyewitnesses of Jesus.&lt;ref name=&quot;A Marginal Jew&quot;&gt;[[John P. Meier]], ''[[A Marginal Jew]]'' Volume I, Doubleday, 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;

The discovery of the [[Dead Sea Scrolls]] has shed light into the context of 1st century Judea, noting the diversity of Jewish belief as well as shared expectations and teachings. For example the expectation of the coming [[messiah]], the beatitudes of the [[Sermon on the Mount]] and much else of the early Christian movement are found to have existed within apocalyptic Judaism of the period.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.ca/books?id=9d6gq_bR1AIC&amp;pg=PA28 The Dead Sea scrolls and Christian origins], [[Joseph Fitzmyer]], pp. 28ff&lt;/ref&gt; This has had the effect of centering [[Early Christianity]] much more within its Jewish roots than was previously the case. It is now recognised that [[Rabbinical Judaism]] and ''Early Christianity'' are only two of the many strands which survived until the [[First Jewish–Roman War|Jewish revolt]] of 66 to 70 CE,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E7DF1E3BF932A35757C0A96E958260 | work=The New York Times | title=BOOKS OF THE TIMES; Looking for Jesus and Jews in the Dead Sea Scrolls | first=Richard | last=Bernstein | date=April 1, 1998 | accessdate=May 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Shanks, Hershel &quot;[http://archive.org/details/understandingdea00shan Understanding the Dead Sea Scrolls: A Reader From the Biblical Archaeology Review]&quot;, archive.org&lt;/ref&gt; see also [[Split of early Christianity and Judaism]].

Most modern scholars hold that the canonical [[Gospel]] accounts were written between 70 and 100 or 110 CE,&lt;ref name=r2/&gt; four to eight decades after the crucifixion, although based on earlier traditions and texts, such as &quot;[[Q document|Q]]&quot;, [[Logia]] or ''sayings gospels'', the passion account or other earlier literature (See [[List of Gospels]]). Some scholars argue that these accounts were compiled by witnesses&lt;ref&gt;Bauckham, Richard [http://books.google.com/books?id=zcVVp_YD4w4C&amp;printsec=frontcover &quot;Jesus and the Eyewitnesses,&quot;] Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing, 2006, ISBN 0802831621&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Byrskog, Samuel [http://books.google.com/books?id=izHwuveIr4sC&amp;printsec=frontcover &quot;Story as History, History as Story,&quot;] Mohr Siebeck, 2000, ISBN 3161473051&lt;/ref&gt; although this view is disputed by other scholars.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20090305053738/http://www.holycross.edu/departments/crec/website/resurrection-debate-transcript.pdf Is There Historical Evidence for the Resurrection of Jesus? A Debate between William Lane Craig and Bart D. Ehrman], College of the Holy Cross, Worcester, Massachusetts, March 28, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; There are also [[Historicity of Jesus#Greco-Roman sources|secular references to Jesus]], although they are few and quite late. Almost all historical critics agree, however, that a historical figure named Jesus taught throughout the Galilean countryside c. 30 CE, was believed by his followers to have performed supernatural acts, and was sentenced to death by the Romans possibly for insurrection.&lt;ref name=&quot;A Marginal Jew 2&quot;&gt;Meier, John P. ''A Marginal Jew'', Vol. II, Doubleday, 1994, ISBN 0300140339&lt;/ref&gt;

Many scholars have pointed out, that the [[Gospel of Mark]] shows signs of a lack of knowledge of geographical, political and religious matters in Judea in the time of Jesus. Thus, today the most common opinion is, that the author is unknown and both geographically and historically at a distance to the narrated events&lt;ref&gt;Analecta Romana Instituti Danici, Danske selskab, Copenhagen, Denmark, 1998.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Nineham, Dennis, ''Saint Mark'', Westminster Press, 1978, ISBN 0664213448, p 193&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Bart Ehrman]], [http://archive.org/details/BartEhrman-TheNewTestament-AHistoricalIntroductionToTheEarly The New Testament. A Historical Introduction to the Early Christian Writings], p. 74 ISBN 0195154622&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McDonald, Lee Martin and Porter, Stanley. ''Early Christianity and its Sacred Literature'', Hendrickson Publishers, 2000, p. 286 ISBN 1565632664&lt;/ref&gt; although opinion varies and scholars such as [[Craig Blomberg]] accept the more traditional view.&lt;ref&gt;Strobel, Lee. ”The Case for Christ”. 1998. Chapter one, an interview with Blomberg, ISBN 0310209307&lt;/ref&gt; The use of expressions that may be described as awkward and rustic cause the Gospel of Mark to appear somewhat unlettered or even crude.&lt;ref name=&quot;hc&quot;&gt;[http://books.google.ca/books?id=ZSR_CQXQdtUC&amp;pg=PA25 Text-critical methodology and the pre-Caesarean text: Codex W in the Gospel, [[Larry W. Hurtado]]], p. 25&lt;/ref&gt; This may be attributed to the influence that [[Saint Peter]], a fisherman, is suggested to have on the writing of Mark.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/64496/biblical-literature &quot;biblical literature.&quot;] Encyclopædia Britannica. 2010. Encyclopædia Britannica Online. 02 Nov. 2010 .&lt;/ref&gt; The writers of the [[Gospel of Matthew]] and [[Gospel of Luke]] used Mark as a source, with changes and improvement to peculiarities and crudities in Mark.&lt;ref name=&quot;hc&quot;/&gt;

The absence of evidence of Jesus' life before his meeting with [[John the Baptist]] has led to many speculations. It would seem that part of the explanation may lie in the early conflict between Paul and the [[Desposyni]] [[Ebionim]], led by [[James the Just]], supposedly the brother of Jesus, that led to Gospel passages [[Rejection of Jesus|critical of Jesus' family]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bible-history.com/isbe/E/EBIONISM%3B+EBIONITES/ EBIONISM; EBIONITES in the Bible Encyclopedia - ISBE (Bible History Online)]. Bible-history.com. Retrieved on 2012-09-11.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[historical reliability of the Acts of the Apostles]], the [[primary source]] for the [[Apostolic Age]], is a major issue for biblical scholars and historians of [[Early Christianity]].

While some biblical scholars view the [[Book of Acts]] as being extremely accurate and corroborated by [[archaeology]], others view the work as being inaccurate and in conflict with the [[Pauline epistles]]. Acts portrays Paul as more inline with [[Jewish Christianity]], while the Pauline epistles record more conflict, such as the [[Incident at Antioch]], see also [[Paul of Tarsus and Judaism]].

==Schools of archaeological and historical thought==

===Overview of academic views===
An educated reading of the biblical text requires knowledge of when it was written, by whom, and for what purpose. For example, most academics would agree that the [[Pentateuch]] was in existence some time shortly after the 6th century [[Common Era|BCE]], but they disagree about when it was written. Proposed dates vary from the 15th century BCE to the 6th century BCE. One popular hypothesis points to the reign of [[Josiah]] (7th century BCE). In this hypothesis, the events of, for example, [[Book of Exodus|Exodus]] would have happened centuries before they were finally edited. This topic is expanded upon in [[dating the Bible]].

An important point to keep in mind is the [[documentary hypothesis]], which using the biblical evidence itself, claims to demonstrate that our current version was based on older written sources that were lost. Although it has been modified heavily over the years, most scholars accept some form of this hypothesis. There have also been and are a number of scholars who reject it, for example [[Egyptologist]] [[Kenneth Kitchen]]&lt;ref name=&quot;isbn0-8028-4960-1&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Kitchen, K. A. |title=On the reliability of the Old Testament |publisher=W.B. Eerdmans |location=Grand Rapids, Mich |year=2003|isbn=0-8028-4960-1 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=Kw6U05qBiXcC }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the late [[Umberto Cassuto]] and [[Gleason Archer]].

There are three loosely defined historical schools of thought with regard to the historical accuracy of the Bible,
* ''biblical minimalism'' — which holds the primacy of modern archaeological evidence, and maintains the theology and apology, and all stories within it are of a later ''[[aetiology|aetiological character]]''
* ''biblical maximalism'' — which holds that also the historical accounts of the Exodus, Judges and United Monarchy, king David and king Saul, are to be taken as largely accurate
* ''non-historical method'' of reading the Bible; the traditional religious reading of the Bible independent of archaeological evidence, assuming it to be accurate.

Note that historical opinions fall on a spectrum, rather than into tightly defined camps. Since there is a wide range of opinions regarding the historical accuracy of the Bible, it should not be surprising that any given scholar may have views that fall anywhere between these loosely defined camps.

===Maximalist – Minimalist dichotomy===
The major split of biblical Scholarship into two opposing schools is strongly disapproved by non-fundamentalist biblical scholars, as being an attempt by so-called &quot;conservative&quot; Christians to portray the field as a bipolar argument, of which only one side is correct.&lt;ref&gt;Spong, John Shelby (1992) &quot;Rescuing the Bible from Fundamentalism&quot; (Harper)&lt;/ref&gt;

Recently the difference between the Maximalist and Minimalist has reduced, however a new school started with a work, &quot;The Quest for the Historical Israel: Debating Archaeology and the History of Early Israel&quot; by [[Israel Finkelstein]], [[Amihai Mazar]], and Brian B. Schmidt.&lt;ref name=r1/&gt; This school argues that post-processual archaeology enables us to recognise the existence of a middle ground between Minimalism and Maximalism, and that both these extremes need to be rejected. Archaeology offers both confirmation of parts of the biblical record and also poses challenges to the naive interpretations made by some. The careful examination of the evidence demonstrates that the historical accuracy of the first part of the Old Testament is greatest during the reign of [[Josiah]]. Some feel that the accuracy diminishes, the further backwards one proceeds from this date. This they claim would confirm that a major redaction of the texts seems to have occurred at about that date.

===Biblical minimalism===
{{Main|Biblical minimalism}}
Biblical minimalists generally hold that the Bible is principally a [[theology|theological]] and [[apologetics|apologetic]] work, and all stories within it are of an [[aetiology|aetiological]] character. The early stories are held to have a historical basis that was reconstructed centuries later, and the stories possess at most only a few tiny fragments of genuine historical memory—which by their definition are only those points which are supported by archaeological discoveries. In this view, all of the stories about the biblical patriarchs are fictional, and the patriarchs mere legendary eponyms to describe later historical realities. Further, biblical minimalists hold that the twelve tribes of Israel were a later construction, the stories of King David and King Saul were modeled upon later Irano-Hellenistic examples, and that there is no archaeological evidence that the united kingdom of Israel, which the Bible says that David and Solomon ruled over an empire from the Euphrates to [[Eilath]], ever existed.

:&quot;It is hard to pinpoint when the movement started but 1968 seems to be a reasonable date. During this year, two prize winning essays were written in Copenhagen; one by [[Niels Peter Lemche]], the other by [[Heike Friis]], which advocated a complete rethinking of the way we approach the Bible and attempt to draw historical conclusions from it&quot;&lt;ref&gt;George Athas, 'Minimalism': The Copenhagen School of Thought in Biblical Studies, edited transcript of lecture, 3rd ed., University of Sydney, April 29, 1999.&lt;/ref&gt;

In published books, one of the early advocates of the current school of thought known as biblical minimalism is Giovanni Garbini,''Storia e ideologia nell'Israele antico'' (1986), translated into English as ''History and Ideology in Ancient Israel''(1988). In his footsteps followed [[Thomas L. Thompson]] with his lengthy ''Early History of the Israelite People: From the Written &amp; Archaeological Sources'' (1992) and, building explicitly on Thompson's book, P. R. Davies' shorter work, ''In Search of 'Ancient Israel' '' (1992). In the latter, Davies finds historical Israel only in archaeological remains, biblical Israel only in Scripture, and recent reconstructions of &quot;ancient Israel&quot; to be an unacceptable amalgam of the two. Thompson and Davies see the entire Hebrew Bible (Old Testament) as the imaginative creation of a small community of Jews at Jerusalem during the period which the Bible assigns to after the return from the Babylonian exile, from 539 BCE onward. [[Niels Peter Lemche]], Thompson's fellow faculty member at the [[University of Copenhagen]], also followed with several titles that show Thompson's influence, including ''The Israelites in history and tradition'' (1998). The presence of both Thompson and Lemche at the same institution has led to the use of the term &quot;[[The Copenhagen School (theology)|Copenhagen school]]&quot;. Although the immediate effect of biblical minimalism from 1992 onward was heated debate from several sides (not just two),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Mykytiuk, Lawrence J. |title=Strengthening Biblical Historicity vis-à-vis Minimalism, 1992–2008, Part 1: Introducing a Bibliographic Essay in Five Parts|journal=Journal of Religious and Theological Information|volume=9|issue=3–4 |year=2010|page=76|url=http://docs.lib.purdue.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1177&amp;context=lib_research|doi=10.1080/10477845.2010.526920}}&lt;/ref&gt; some calmer critiques, none of which was neutral, eventually appeared.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Brettler, Marc Z. |title=The Copenhagen School: The Historiographical Issues|journal=AJS Review|volume=27 |year=2003|pages=1–21|jstor=4131767|doi=10.1017/S0364009403000011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Biblical maximalism===
There is no scholarly controversy on the historicity of the events recounted from the [[Babylonian captivity]] in the 6th century BCE, and that the events predating the [[United Monarchy]] cannot be shown to have any historicity. The positions of &quot;maximalists&quot; vs. &quot;minimalists&quot; concern the monarchy period, spanning the 10th to 7th centuries BCE The maximalist position holds that the accounts of the United Monarchy and the early kings of Israel, [[king David]] and [[king Saul]], are to be taken as largely historical.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.livius.org/th/theory/theory-maximalists.html &quot;Maximalists and Minimalists&quot;], ''Livius.org''.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Decreasing conflict between the maximalist and minimalist schools===

In 2001, [[Israel Finkelstein]] and [[Neil Asher Silberman]] published the book ''[[The Bible Unearthed|The Bible Unearthed. Archaeology's New Vision of Ancient Israel and the Origin of Its Sacred Texts]]'' which advocated a view midway toward biblical minimalism and caused an uproar among many conservatives. The 25th anniversary issue of ''Biblical Archeological Review''(March/April 2001 edition), editor [[Hershel Shanks]] quoted several biblical scholars who insisted that minimalism was dying,&lt;ref&gt;Jack Cargill [http://www.historycooperative.org/journals/ht/34.3/cargill.html Ancient Israel in Western Civ Textbooks]. Quoting Amy Dockster Marcus about the minimalists: &quot;The bottom line is that when it comes to the big picture, they are often right. Many of their ideas, once considered far-fetched, are now solidly mainstream concepts.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; although leading minimalists deny this and a claim has been made &quot;We are all minimalists now&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20070930192250/http://ajtp.iusb.edu/Back%20Issues/January1993CompleteIssue.PDF American Journal of Theology &amp; Philosophy Vol. 14, No.1 January, 1993]&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|Apart from the well-funded (and fundamentalist) “biblical archaeologists,” we are in fact nearly all “minimalists” now.&lt;ref&gt;Philip Davies &quot;[http://www.bibleinterp.com/articles/moore1357926.shtml Beyond Labels: What Comes Next?]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;|Philip Davies|&quot;Beyond Labels: What Comes Next?&quot;}}

{{quote|The fact is that we are all minimalists -- at least, when it comes to the patriarchal period and the settlement. When I began my PhD studies more than three decades ago in the USA, the 'substantial historicity' of the patriarchs was widely accepted as was the unified conquest of the land. These days it is quite difficult to find anyone who takes this view.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In fact, until recently I could find no 'maximalist' history of Israel since Wellhausen. ... In fact, though, 'maximalist' has been widely defined as someone who accepts the biblical text unless it can be proven wrong. If so, very few are willing to operate like this, not even John Bright (1980) whose history is not a maximalist one according to the definition just given.|Lester L. Grabbe|&quot;[http://www.buaclasses.com/downloads/maltsdocs/Grabbe_RecentIssuesHistIsrael.pdf Some Recent Issues in the Study of the History of Israel]&quot;}}

In 2003, [[Kenneth Kitchen]], a scholar who adopts a more maximalist point of view, authored the book ''On the Reliability of the Old Testament''. Kitchen advocated the reliability of many (though not all) parts of the Torah and in no uncertain terms criticizes the work of Finkelstein and Silberman, to which Finkelstein has since responded.

Jennifer Wallace describes archaeologist Israel Finkelstein's view in her article ''Shifting Ground in the Holy Land,'' appearing in Smithsonian Magazine, May 2006:
:''He [Finkelstein] cites the fact – now accepted by most archaeologists – that many of the cities [[Joshua]] is supposed to have sacked in the late 13th century B.C. had ceased to exist by that time. [[Tel Hazor|Hazor]] was destroyed in the middle of that century, [[Ai (Bible)|Ai]] was abandoned before 2000 B.C. Even [[Jericho]], where Joshua is said to have brought the walls tumbling down by circling the city seven times with blaring trumpets, was destroyed in 1500 B.C. Now controlled by the Palestinian Authority, the [[Jericho]] site consists of crumbling pits and trenches that testify to a century of fruitless digging.''

However, despite problems with the archaeological record, some maximalists place Joshua in the mid second millennium, at about the time the Egyptian Empire came to rule over Canaan, and not the 13th century as Finkelstein or Kitchen claim, and view the destruction layers of the period as corroboration of the biblical account. The destruction of Hazor in the mid-13th century is seen as corroboration of the biblical account of the later destruction carried out by Deborah and Barak as recorded in the [[Book of Judges]]. The location that Finkelstein refers to as &quot;Ai&quot; is generally dismissed as the location of the biblical Ai, since it was destroyed and buried in the 3rd millennium. The prominent site has been known by that name since at least Hellenistic times, if not before. Minimalists all hold that dating these events as contemporary are [[etiology|etiological]] explanations written centuries after the events they claim to report.

For the [[United Monarchy|united monarchy]] both Finkelstein and Silberman do accept that David and Solomon were really existing persons (no kings but bandit leaders or hill country chieftains)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bol.com/nl/p/engelse-boeken/david-and-solomon/1001004002970474/index.html#product_description David and Solomon] Beschrijving. Bol.com&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Richard N. Ostling [http://www.pe.com/lifestyles/stories/PE_Fea_Daily_D_david801.407fef9.html Was King David legend or fiction?] The Associated Press&lt;/ref&gt; from Judah about the 10th century BCE&lt;ref&gt;David and Solomon: In Search of the Bible's Sacred Kings and the Roots of the Western Tradition pp20&lt;/ref&gt; - they do not assume that there was such a thing as [[United Monarchy|united monarchy]] with a capital in [[Jerusalem]].

{{quote|The Bible reports that Jehoshaphat, a contemporary of Ahab, offered manpower and horses for the northern kingdom's wars against the Arameans. He strengthened his relationship with the northern kingdom by arranging a diplomatic marriage: the Israelite princess Athaliah, sister or daughter of King Ahab, married Jehoram, the son of Jehoshaphat (2 Kings 8:18). The house of David in Jerusalem was now directly linked to (and apparently dominated by) the Israelite royalty of Samaria. In fact, we might suggest that this represented the north's takeover by marriage of Judah. Thus in the ninth century BCE—nearly a century after the presumed time of David—we can finally point to the historical existence of a great united monarchy of Israel, stretching from Dan in the north to Beer-sheba in the south, with significant conquered territories in Syria and Transjordan. But this united monarchy—a real united monarchy—was ruled by the Omrides, not the Davidides, and its capital was Samaria, not Jerusalem.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Finkelstein|first1=Israel|last2=Silberman|first2=Neil Asher|title=David and Solomon. In Search of the Bible's Sacred Kings and the Roots of the Western Tradition|accessdate=December 24, 2010|year=2006|publisher=Free Press|location=New York|isbn=978-0-7432-4363-6|page=103|chapter=3. Murder, Lust, and Betrayal|chapterurl=http://books.google.com/books?id=uH7Kg9yEc7AC&amp;pg=PA103}}&lt;/ref&gt;|Israel Finkelstein and Neil Asher Silberman|David and Solomon. In Search of the Bible's Sacred Kings and the Roots of the Western Tradition.}}

Others such as [[David Ussishkin]] argue that those who follow the biblical depiction of a [[United Monarchy|united monarchy]] do so on the basis of limited evidence while hoping to uncover real archaeological proof in the future.&lt;ref&gt;Ussishkin, David, &quot;Solomon's Jerusalem: The Texts and the Facts on the Ground&quot; in Vaughn Andrew G. and Killebrew, Ann E. eds. (2003), &quot;Jerusalem in Bible and Archaeology: The First Temple Period&quot; (SBL Symposium Series 18; Atlanta: Society of Biblical Literature)&lt;/ref&gt; Gunnar Lehmann suggests that there is still a possibility that David and Solomon were able to become local chieftains of some importance and claims that Jerusalem at the time was at best a small town in a sparsely populated area in which alliances of tribal kinship groups formed the basis of society. He goes on further to claim that it was at best a small regional centre, one of three to four in the territory of Judah and neither David nor Solomon had the manpower or the requisite social/political/administrative structure to rule the kind of empire described in the Bible.&lt;ref&gt;Lehrmann, Gunnar, &quot;The United Monarchy in the Countryside: Jerusalem, Judah, and the Shephelah during the Tenth Century BCE&quot;, in Vaughn Andrew G. and Killebrew, Ann E. eds. (2003), &quot;Jerusalem in Bible and Archaeology: The First Temple Period&quot; (SBL Symposium Series 18; Atlanta: Society of Biblical Literature)&lt;/ref&gt;

These views are strongly criticized by [[William G. Dever]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Dever|2001|p=160 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Helga Weippert]], [[Amihai Mazar]] and [[Amnon Ben-Tor]].

[[André Lemaire]] states in ''Ancient Israel: From Abraham to the Roman Destruction of the Temple''&lt;ref&gt;Shanks, Hershel (1999). ''Ancient Israel: From Abraham to the Roman Destruction of the Temple'', Pearson, p. 113 ISBN 0130853631&lt;/ref&gt; that the principal points of the biblical tradition with Solomon as generally trustworthy, as does [[Kenneth Kitchen]], who argue that Solomon ruled over a comparatively wealthy &quot;mini-empire&quot;, rather than a small city-state.

Recently Finkelstein has joined with the more conservative [[Amihai Mazar]], to explore the areas of agreement and disagreement and there are signs the intensity of the debate between the so-called minimalist and maximalist scholars is diminishing.&lt;ref name=r1&gt;{{cite book|author=Finkelstein, Israel; Mazar, Amihai and Schmidt, Brian|title=The Quest for the Historical Israel: Debating Archaeology and the History of Early Israel|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=jpbngoKHg8gC|year=2007|publisher=Society of Biblical Lit|isbn=978-1-58983-277-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; This view is also taken by Richard S. Hess,&lt;ref&gt;Hess, Richard S. (2007) &quot;Israelite Religions: An Archaeological and Biblical Survey&quot;, Baker Academic, ISBN 0801027179&lt;/ref&gt; which shows there is in fact a plurality of views between maximalists and minimalists. Jack Cargill&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historycooperative.org/journals/ht/34.3/cargill.html Jack Cargill | Ancient Israel in Western Civ Textbooks | The History Teacher, 34.3]. The History Cooperative. Retrieved on 2012-09-11.&lt;/ref&gt; has shown that popular textbooks not only fail to give readers the up to date archaeological evidence, but that they also fail to correctly represent the diversity of views present on the subject. And Megan Bishop Moore and Brad E. Kelle provide an overview of the respective evolving approaches and attendant controversies, especially during the period from the mid-1980s through 2011, in their book ''Biblical History and Israel's Past''.

==See also==
{{columns
|col1=

*[[Ancient history]]
*[[Authorship of the Bible]]
*[[Biblical archaeology school]]
*[[Biblical criticism]]
*[[Biblical inerrancy]]
*[[Biblical literalism]]
*[[Chronology of Jesus]]
*[[Dating the Bible]]
*[[Development of the New Testament canon]]
*[[Documentary hypothesis]]
*[[List of artifacts significant to the Bible]]
*[[Science and the Bible]]
*[[Religious text|List of religious texts]]
*[[Rudolf Bultmann]]
|col2=

===Historical accuracy of biblical stories===
*[[Genesis creation narrative]]
*[[Adam (Bible)#Jewish perspective on Adam|Adam]]
*[[Abraham#Historicity and origins|Historicity of Abraham]]
*[[Noah's Ark]]
*[[Flood geology]]
*[[The Exodus#Challenges to the historicity of the Exodus|The Exodus]]
*[[Plagues of Egypt]]
*[[Passage of the Red Sea]]
*[[Moses#Challenges to his historicity|Moses]]
*[[Battle of Jericho]]
*[[Historicity of the Book of Joshua|Book of Joshua]]
*[[Historicity of David]]
*[[United Monarchy#Origins and historicity of the United Monarchy|Historicity of the United Monarchy]]
|col3=
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
*[[Book of Daniel#Historical accuracy|Historical accuracy of the Book of Daniel]]
*[[Ezra#Academic view|Historicity of Ezra]]
*[[Book of Esther#Debate over historicity|Historical accuracy of the Book of Esther]]
*[[Historicity of Jesus]]
*[[Gospel of Mark]]
*[[Sanhedrin Trial of Jesus#Criticism of the Sanhedrin Trial|Sanhedrin Trial of Jesus]]
*[[Census of Quirinius]]
*[[Theudas]]
*[[Massacre of the Innocents]]
*[[Crucifixion eclipse]]
*[[Historical reliability of the Acts of the Apostles]]
}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==

*{{cite book
|last = Banks
|first = Diane
|title = Writing The History Of Israel
|year = 2006
|publisher = Continuum International Publishing Group
|url = http://books.google.com/books?id=6hnrpeC2KNAC&amp;printsec=frontcover
|ref = harv
}}
*{{cite book
|last = Brettler
|first = Mark Zvi
|title = How to Read the Bible
|year = 2005
|publisher = Jewish Publication Society
|url = http://books.google.com/books?id=39nQafdJ_ssC&amp;printsec=frontcover
|ref = harv
}}
*{{cite book
|last = Davies
|first = Philip R.
|title = In Search of 'Ancient Israel'
|year = 1995
|publisher = Continuum International Publishing Group
|url = http://books.google.com/books?id=5D5GNju1-ggC&amp;printsec=frontcover
|ref = harv
}}
*{{cite book
|last = Davies
|first = Philip R.
|title = Minimalism, 'Ancient Israel', and Anti-Semitism
|year = n.d.
|publisher = The Bible and Interpretation
|url = http://www.bibleinterp.com/articles/Minimalism.htm
|ref = harv
}}
* Davies, Philip R., ''Scribes and Schools: The Canonization of the Hebrew Scriptures'', 1998.
*{{cite book
|last = Davies
|first = Philip R.
|title = Memories of Ancient Israel
|year = 2008
|publisher = Westminster John Knox Press
|url = http://books.google.com/books?id=M1rS4Kce_PMC&amp;printsec=frontcover
|ref = harv
}}
*{{cite book
|last = Dever
|first = William G.
|authorlink = William G. Dever
|title = The Lives of Ordinary People in Ancient Israel
|year = 2012
|publisher = Eerdmans 
|url = http://books.google.com/books?id=tcksD2_amqgC&amp;printsec=frontcover
|ref = harv
}}
*{{cite book
|last1 = Finkelstein
|first1 = Israel 
|last2 = Mazar
|first2 = Amihay 
|last3 = Schmidt
|first3 = Brian B.
|title = The Quest for the Historical Israel
|year = 2007
|publisher = Society of Biblical Literature
|url = http://books.google.com/books?id=jpbngoKHg8gC&amp;printsec=frontcover
|ref = harv
}}
* Finkelstein, Israel, ''The Archaeology of the Israelite Settlement'', 1988
* Garbini, Giovanni, ''History and Ideology in Ancient Israel'', 1988 (trans from Italian).
* Halpern, Baruch, &quot;Erasing History: The Minimalist Assault on Ancient Israel&quot;, ''Bible Review'', December 1995, p26 - 35, 47.
* Lemche, Niels Peter, ''Early Israel'', 1985.
*{{cite book
|last = Lemche
|first = Niels Peter
|title = The Israelites in History and Tradition
|year = 1998
|publisher = Westminster John Knox Press
|url = http://books.google.com/books?id=JIoY7PagAOAC&amp;printsec=frontcover
|ref = harv
}}
*{{cite book
|last1 = Moore
|first1 = Megan Bishop
|last2 = Kelle
|first2 = Brad E.
|title = Biblical History and Israel's Past
|year = 2011
|publisher = Eerdmans 
|url = http://books.google.com/books?id=Qjkz_8EMoaUC&amp;printsec=frontcover
|ref = harv
}}
* Provan, Iain W., &quot;Ideologies, Literary and Critical Reflections on Recent Writing on the History of Israel&quot;, ''Journal of Biblical Literature'' 114/4 (1995), p585-606. (a critique of the Copenhagen School of Thought - with responses by Davies (above) and Thompson (below))
*{{cite book
|last = Thompson
|first = Thomas L.
|title = Early History of the Israelite People
|year = 1992
|publisher = Brill
|url = http://books.google.com/books?id=RwrrUuHFb6UC&amp;printsec=frontcover
|ref = harv
}}
*Thompson, Thomas L., &quot;A Neo-Albrightean School in History and Biblical Scholarship?&quot; ''Journal of Biblical Literature'' 114/4 (1995), p683-698. (a response to the article by Iain W. Provan - above)
* {{cite book|last=Thompson|first=Thomas L.|title=The Mythic Past: Biblical Archaeology And The Myth Of Israel|year= 1999|publisher=Basic Book|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
|last = Thompson
|first = Thomas L.
|title = A view from Copenhagen: Israel and the History of Palestine
|year = n.d.
|publisher = The Bible and Interpretation
|url = http://www.bibleinterp.com/articles/copenhagen.shtml
|ref = harv
}}
* Van Seters, John, ''[[Abraham in History and Tradition (book)|Abraham in History and Tradition]]'', 1975.
*{{cite book
|last = Whitelam
|first = Keith W.
|title = The Invention of Ancient Israel
|year = 1996
|publisher = Routledge
|url = http://books.google.com/books?id=jz3X-n8JhwUC&amp;printsec=frontcover
|ref = harv
}}
* Barenboim, Peter. &quot;Biblical Roots of Separation of Powers&quot;, Moscow : Letny Sad, 2005, ISBN 5-94381-123-0, http://lccn.loc.gov/2006400578
* Biran, Avraham. &quot;'David' Found at Dan.&quot; ''Biblical Archaeology Review'' 20:2 (1994): 26–39.
* Brettler, Marc Z., “The Copenhagen School: The Historiographical Issues,” ''AJS Review'' 27 (2003): 1–21.
* Coogan, Michael D. &quot;Canaanites: Who Were They and Where Did They Live?&quot; ''Bible Review'' 9:3 (1993): 44ff.
* Davies, Philip R. 1992, 2nd edition 1995, reprinted 2004.''In Search of 'Ancient Israel' ''. Edinburgh: T. &amp; T. Clark.
* Dawood, N.J. 1978. ''Tales from the Arabian Nights'', Doubleday, A delightful children's version translated from the original Arabic.
* Dever, William G. ''[[What Did the Biblical Writers Know and When Did They Know It?]]'', Grand Rapids: Eerdmans 2001
* Finkelstein, Israel and Silberman, Neil A. 2001 ''[[The Bible Unearthed]]''. New York: Simon and Schuster
* Garbini, Giovanni. 1988. ''History and Ideology in Ancient Israel''. Translated by John Bowden from the original Italian edition. New York: Crossroad.
* Harpur, Tom. 2004. &quot;The Pagan Christ. Recovering the Lost Light&quot; Thomas Allen Publishers, Toronto.
* Kitchen, Kenneth A. 2003 ''On the Reliability of the Old Testament''. Grand Rapids: Eerdmans.
* {{cite book|last1=Koehler |last2=Dr. Ralph D|title= Christian Bible History|isbn= 1-4208-1242-4}}
* Larsson, G. 2007. &quot;The Chronological System of the Old Testament&quot;. Peter Lang GmbH.
* Lemche, Niels P. 1998. ''The Israelites in History and Tradition'' London : SPCK ; Louisville, Ky. : Westminster John Knox Press.
* Mazar, Amihai. 1992. ''Archaeology of the Land of the Bible: 10,000–586 B.C.E.'' New York: Doubleday.
* [http://books.google.com/books?id=uDijjc_D5P0C Miller, J. Maxwell, and John Haralson Hayes, &quot;A history of ancient Israel and Judah&quot; (Westminster John Knox Press, 1986)]
* Moore, Megan Bishop and Brad E. Kelle, ''Biblical History and Israel's Past'', 2011.
* Mithraic Studies: Proceedings of the First International Congress of Mithraic Studies. Manchester U. Press, 1975.
* Mykytiuk, Lawrence J. 2010. &quot;Strengthening Biblical Historicity vis-à-vis Minimalism, 1992–2008, Part 1: Introducing a Bibliographic Essay in Five Parts,” ''Journal of Religious and Theological Information'' 9/3–4: 71-83.
* Na'aman, Nadav. 1996 .&quot;The Contribution of the Amarna Letters to the Debate on Jerusalem's Political Position in the Tenth Century B.C.E.&quot; ''BASOR''. 304: 17–27.
* [http://cojs.org/cojswiki/Cow_Town_or_Royal_Capital%3F_Nadav_Na%E2%80%99aman%2C_BAR_23:04%2C_Jul/Aug_1997. Na'aman, Nadav. 1997 &quot;Cow Town or Royal Capital: Evidence for Iron Age Jerusalem.&quot; ''Biblical Archaeology Review''. 23, no. 4: 43–47, 67.]
* Noth, Martin, &quot;Uberlieferungsgeschichtliche Studien&quot;, 1943; English translation as &quot;The Deuteronomistic History&quot;, Sheffield, 1981, and &quot;The Chronicler's History&quot;, Sheffield, 1987.
* Shanks, Hershel. 1995. ''Jerusalem: An Archaeological Biography''. New York: Random House.
*[http://cojs.org/cojswiki/Face_to_Face:_Biblical_Minimalists_Meet_Their_Challengers%2C_Hershel_Shanks%2C_BAR_23:04%2C_Jul/Aug_1997. Shanks, Hershel. 1997 &quot;Face to Face: Biblical Minimalists Meet Their Challengers.&quot; ''Biblical Archaeology Review''. 23, no. 4: 26–42, 66.]
* Smith, Mark S. ''[[The Early History of God]]'', Eerdmans, 2002 (1st edition 1990)
* Steiner, Margareet and Jane Cahill. &quot;David's Jerusalem: Fiction or Reality?&quot; ''Biblical Archaeology Review'' 24:4 (1998): 25–33, 62–63; 34–41, 63. This article presents a debate between a Biblical minimalist and a Biblical maximalist.
* Thompson, Thomas L. 1999. ''[[The Bible in History: How Writers Create a Past]]''. London.
* ________. 1992. ''The Early History of the Israelite People: From the Written and Archaeological Sources''. Leiden and New York: Brill.
* Yamauchi, Edwin, The Stones and the Scriptures. Philadelphia: J.B. Lippincott Company, 1972.

==External links==
*[http://www.dinur.org/resources/resourceCategoryDisplay.aspx?categoryID=411&amp;rsid=478 Biblical History] Portal site: The Jewish History Resource Center – Project of the Dinur Center for Research in Jewish History, The Hebrew University of Jerusalem
*[http://www.bibleinterp.com/articles/Minimalism.htm Minimalism, &quot;Ancient Israel&quot;, and Anti-Semitism] By Philip Davies.
*[http://jmm.aaa.net.au/articles/9246.htm 'Minimalism' – The Copenhagen School of Thought in Biblical Studies]
*[http://www.biblestudytools.com/history/ Bible History Tools and Resources] from BibleStudyTools.com
*[http://www.apologetics.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=165:why-i-believe-the-new-testament-is-historically-reliable&amp;catid=39:historical-apologetics&amp;Itemid=54 Why I Believe The New Testament Is Historically Reliable] by [[Gary Habermas]]
*[http://www.bib-arch.org Biblical Archaeology Society: examines discoveries and controversies about historical veracity of the Bible]
*[http://www.livius.org/th/theory/theory-maximalists.html Livius.org: Maximalism and minimalism]
*[http://jmm.aaa.net.au/articles/9246.htm Notes on minimalism by George Athas]

{{The Bible and history}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bible And History, The}}
[[Category:Biblical criticism]]
[[Category:Jewish history]]
[[Category:Historicity of religion|Bible]]

[[cs:Bible a historie]]
[[pt:A Bíblia e a história]]
[[fi:Raamatun historiallisuus]]
[[sv:Bibeln som historisk källa]]
[[tr:Ahit ve tarih]]</text>
      <sha1>ehkj545xs8o3iv79g0fg6qxhg01pc5p</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
