<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>The White Goddess</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>90167</id>
    <revision>
      <id>509108382</id>
      <parentid>508611973</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-08-25T16:33:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JackieBot</username>
        <id>7713040</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>r2.7.2) (Robot: Removing [[he:האלה הלבנה]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15005">{{for|the Greek sea goddess|Leucothea}}
{{Infobox Book 
| name          = The White Goddess
| title_orig    = 
| translator    = 
| image         = [[Image:white goddess.JPG]]
| image_caption = ''The White Goddess'' cover (Farrar Straus Giroux, 1997).
| author        = [[Robert Graves]]
| illustrator   = 
| cover_artist  = 
| country       = United Kingdom
| language      = English
| series        = 
| subject       = 
| genre         = [[Mythology]], [[Poetry]]
| publisher     = 
| release_date  = 1948
| english_release_date = 
| media_type    = 
| pages         = 
| isbn          = 
| preceded_by   = 
| followed_by   = 
}}
'''''The White Goddess: a Historical Grammar of Poetic Myth''''' is a book-length essay on the nature of poetic myth-making by author and poet [[Robert Graves]]. First published in 1948, based on earlier articles published in ''[[Wales (magazine)|Wales]]'' magazine, corrected, revised and enlarged editions appeared in 1948, 1952 and 1961. ''The White Goddess'' represents an approach to the study of [[mythology]] from a decidedly creative and idiosyncratic perspective. Graves proposes the existence of a [[Europe]]an [[deity]], the &quot;White Goddess of Birth, Love and Death,&quot; much similar to the ''[[Mother Goddess]]'', inspired and represented by the phases of the [[moon]], who lies behind the faces of the diverse goddesses of various European and [[pagan]] mythologies.

Graves argues that &quot;true&quot; or &quot;pure&quot; poetry is inextricably linked with the ancient cult-ritual of his proposed White Goddess and of her son.

== History ==
Graves first wrote the book under the title of ''The Roebuck in the Thicket'' in a three-week period during January 1944, only a month after finishing ''The Golden Fleece''. He then left the book, to focus on ''King Jesus'', a historical novel about the life of [[Jesus]]. Returning to ''The Roebuck in the Thicket'', he renamed it ''The Three-Fold Muse'', before finishing it and retitling it as ''The White Goddess''. In January 1946 he sent it to the publishers, and in May 1948 it was published in the UK, and in June 1948 in the US, as ''The White Goddess: a Historical Grammar of Poetic Myth''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hutton&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Triumph of the Moon: A History of Modern Pagan Witchcraft|publisher=Oxford University Press |location= |author=Hutton, Ronald|pages=188–189 |year=1999}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Poetry and myth ==
Graves described ''The White Goddess'' as &quot;a historical grammar of the language of [[poetry|poetic]] [[mythology|myth]].&quot; The book draws from the mythology and poetry of [[Wales]] and [[Ireland]] especially, as well as that of most of [[Western Europe]] and the ancient [[Middle East]]. Relying on arguments from [[etymology]] and the use of forensic techniques to uncover what he calls 'iconotropic' redaction of original myths, Graves argues for the worship of a single goddess under many names, an idea that came to be known as &quot;[[Matriarchal religion]]&quot; in [[feminist theology]] of the 1970s. 

In response to critics, Graves has accused literary scholars of being psychologically incapable of interpreting myth&lt;ref&gt;Inter alia - The White Goddess, Farrar Strauss Giroud, p. 224. ISBN 0-374-50493-8&lt;/ref&gt; or too concerned with maintaining their perquisites to go against the majority view. (See Frazer quote below.)

''[[The Golden Bough]]'' (1922, but begun in 1890), an early anthropological study by Sir [[James George Frazer]], is the starting point for much of Graves's argument, and Graves thought in part that his book made explicit what Frazer only hinted at.  Graves wrote: 
&lt;blockquote&gt;Sir James Frazer was able to keep his beautiful rooms at [[Trinity College, Cambridge|Trinity College]], [[University of Cambridge|Cambridge]], until his death by carefully and methodically sailing all around his dangerous subject, as if charting the coastline of a forbidden island without actually committing himself to a declaration that it existed.  What he was saying-not-saying was that [[Christian legend]], [[Christian dogma|dogma]] and [[Christian sacraments|ritual]] are the refinement of a great body of primitive and even [[barbarian|barbarous]] beliefs, and that almost the only original element in Christianity is the personality of [[Jesus]].&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Graves's ''The White Goddess'' deals with [[goddess|goddess worship]] as the prototypical [[religion]], analyzing it largely from literary evidence, in myth and poetry.

Graves admitted he was not a medieval historian, but a poet, and thus based his work on the premise that the 
&lt;blockquote&gt;language of poetic myth anciently current in the Mediterranean and Northern Europe was a magical language bound up with popular religious ceremonies in honor of the Moon-goddess, or Muse, some of them dating from the Old Stone Age, and that this remains the language of true poetry...&lt;/blockquote&gt; 
Graves concluded, in the second and expanded edition, that the male-dominant monotheistic god of [[Judaism]] and its successors were the cause of the White Goddess's downfall, and thus the source of much of the modern world's woe. He describes Woman as occupying a higher echelon than mere poet, that of the Muse Herself.  He adds &quot;This is not to say that a woman should refrain from writing poems; only, that she should write as a woman, not as an honorary man.&quot;  He seems particularly bothered by the spectre of women's writing reflecting male-dominated poetic conventions.&lt;ref&gt;Graves, The White Goddess, p. 446-447&lt;/ref&gt;

Graves openly considered poetic inspiration, or &quot;[[Analepsis]]&quot; as he termed it, a valid historical methodology.

Visual iconography was also important to Graves's conception. Graves created a methodology for reading images he called &quot;iconotropy&quot;. To practice this methodology one is required to reduce &quot;speech into its original images and rhythms&quot; and then to combine these &quot;on several simultaneous levels of thought&quot;. By applying this methodology Graves decoded a woodcut of ''[[Judgement of Paris|The Judgement of Paris]]'' as depicting a singular Triple Goddess&lt;ref&gt;Von Hendy, Andrew. ''The Modern Construction of Myth''. p.196.&lt;/ref&gt; rather than the traditional [[Hera]], [[Athena]] and [[Aphrodite]] of the narrative the image illustrates.

==&quot;Celtic Astrology&quot;==
Graves also argues that the names of the [[Ogham]] letters in the alphabet used in parts of [[Goidelic|Gaelic]] Ireland and Britain contained a calendar that contained the key to an ancient [[liturgy]] involving the [[human sacrifice]] of a [[sacred king]],  and, further, that these letter names concealed lines of [[Ancient Greek]] [[hexameter]] describing the goddess.

While Graves's &quot;Celtic Astrology&quot; has been popularized by some [[New Age]] authors, his &quot;Tree Calendar&quot; has no relation to any historical [[Celtic calendar]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| first =Peter Berresford | last =Ellis |   title=The Fabrication of 'Celtic' Astrology|journal=The Astrological Journal|volume=39|issue=issn.4|year=1997| url=http://cura.free.fr/xv/13ellis2.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;
His interpretations rather rely on the book ''Ogygia'' by the 17th-century bard [[Roderick O'Flaherty]]

Graves's &quot;Tree Zodiac&quot; includes the four cardinal points besides the twelve signs of the zodiac, resulting in a list of 16, matched to the 20 Ogham letters by attributing two letters each to winter solstice (A/I), Sagittarius (B/R), spring equinox (O/E) and Gemini (D/T):
#Winter Solstice: A/I: Spruce/Yew
#Sagittarius: B/R: Birch/Elder
#Capricorn: L: Service tree
#Aquarius: N: Ash
#Spring Equinox: O/E: Furze/Poplar
#Pisces: F: Alder
#Aries: S: Willow
#Taurus: H: Whitethorn
#Summer Solstice U: Heather
#Gemini: D/T: Oak/Holly
#Cancer: C: Hazel
#Leo: Q: Apple
#Autumnal Equinox: E/O : Poplar/Furze
#Virgo: M: Vine
#Libra: G: Ivy
#Scorpio: NG: Reed

==Criticism==
''The White Goddess'' has been seen as a poetic work where Graves gives his notion of man's subjection to women in love an &quot;anthropological grandeur&quot; and further mythologises all women in general (and several of Graves's lovers in specific) into a three-faced moon goddess model.&lt;ref&gt;Hunter, Jefferson (1983). &quot;The Servant of Three Mistresses&quot; (review of: Seymour-Smith, Martin, ''Robert Graves: His Life and Work''), in ''The Hudson Review'', Vol. 36, No. 4 (Winter, 1983-1984), pp. 733-736.&lt;/ref&gt; 
Graves's value as a poet aside, flaws in his scholarship such as poor [[philology]], misdating texts (for example, the ''[[Hanes Taliesin]]'' a 16th-18th century text which Graves believed originated centuries earlier&lt;ref name=&quot;wood&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Wood|first=Juliette|title=The Concept of the Goddess|editor=Sandra Billington, Miranda Green|publisher=Routledge|year=1999|page=12|chapter=Chapter 1, The Concept of the Goddess|isbn=0-415-19789-9, 9780415197892|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=IoW9yhkrFJoC&amp;lpg=PP10&amp;pg=PA10#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false|accessdate=2008-12-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;), and use of out-dated archeology have been criticised.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hutton|first=Ronald|title=The Pagan Religions of the Ancient British Isles: Their Nature and Legacy|publisher=[[John Wiley &amp; Sons]]|year=1993|page=320|isbn=0-631-18946-7, 9780631189466|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=wNpVJQAACAAJ}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some scholars, particularly archeologists, historians and folklorists have not received the work favourably.&lt;ref name=&quot;paganism_reader&quot;&gt;''The Paganism Reader''. p. 128.&lt;/ref&gt; Graves was disappointed that his work was &quot;loudly ignored&quot; by many Celtic scholars;&lt;ref name=&quot;White&quot;&gt;White, Donna R. ''A Century of Welsh Myth in Children's Literature''. p. 75.&lt;/ref&gt; however, it was accepted as history by many non-scholarly readers and, according to [[Ronald Hutton]], ''The White Goddess'' remains a major source of confusion about the ancient Celts and influences many un-scholarly views of Celtic paganism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hutton-Pagan&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Hutton|first=Ronald|title=The Pagan Religions of the Ancient British Isles: Their Nature and Legacy|publisher=[[John Wiley &amp; Sons]]|year=1993|page=145|isbn=0-631-18946-7, 9780631189466|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=wNpVJQAACAAJ}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hilda Ellis Davidson]] criticized Graves as having &quot;misled many innocent readers with his eloquent but deceptive statements about a nebulous goddess in early Celtic literature&quot;, and stated that he was &quot;no authority&quot; on the subject matter he presented.&lt;ref name=DAVIDSONROLESOF&gt;Davidson, Hilda Ellis (1998). ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=9IAyyYi0OC4C&amp;lpg=PA11&amp;pg=PA11#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false Roles of the Northern Goddess]'', page 11. [[Routledge]]. ISBN 0-415-13611-3&lt;/ref&gt; While Graves made the association between Goddesses and the moon appear &quot;natural,&quot; it was not so to the Celts or some other ancient peoples.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hutton-Pagan&quot; /&gt; Some Neopagans have been bemused and upset by the scholarly criticism that ''The White Goddess'' has received in recent years,&lt;ref&gt;The Pomegranate 7.1, Equinox press, (Review of) &quot;Jacob Rabinowitz, ''The Rotting Goddess: The Origin of the Witch in Classical Antiquity’s Demonization of Fertility Religion''.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; while others have appreciated its poetic insight but never accepted it as a work of historical veracity.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis, James R. ''Magical Religion and Modern Witchcraft''. p. 172.&lt;/ref&gt;

Michael W. Pharand, though quoting earlier criticisms, rebutted, &quot;Graves's theories and conclusions, outlandish as they seemed to his contemporaries (or may appear to us), were the result of careful observation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Pharand, Michael W. &quot;Greek Myths, White Goddess: Robert Graves Cleans up a 'Dreadful Mess'&quot;, in Ian Ferla and Grevel Lindop (ed), ''Graves and the Goddess: Essays on Robert Graves's The White Goddess''. Associated University Presses, 2003. p.188.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Matriarchal religion]]
*''[[The Hebrew Goddess]]''
*[[Triple Goddess (Neopaganism)]]
*[[Triple deity|Triple goddesses]]
*''[[When God Was a Woman]]''

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Bibliography==
===Editions===
*1948 - ''The White Goddess : a Historical Grammar of Poetic Myth'' (London: Faber &amp; Faber) [Corr. 2nd ed. also issued by Faber in 1948] [US ed.= New York, Creative Age Press, 1948]
*1952 - ''The White Goddess : a Historical Grammar of Poetic Myth'', Amended &amp; enl. ed.[i.e. 3rd ed.] (London: Faber &amp; Faber) [US ed.= New York: Alfred A.Knopf, 1958]
*1961 - ''The White Goddess : a Historical Grammar of Poetic Myth'', Amended &amp; enl. ed.[i.e. 4th ed.] (London: Faber &amp; Faber) [US ed.= New York, Farrar, Straus and Giroux, 1966]
*1997 - ''The White Goddess : a Historical Grammar of Poetic Myth''; edited by [[Grevel Lindop]] (Manchester: Carcanet)  ISBN 1-85754-248-7

===Critical studies===
*Bennett, Joseph, [review of Robert Graves' ''The White Goddess: a Historical Grammar of Poetic Myth''], ''Hudson Review'', vol.2 (1949), 133-138
*Davis, Robert A., 'The Origin, Evolution, and Function of the Myth of the White Goddess in the Writings of Robert Graves' (unpublished PhD, University of Stirling, 1987) [ British Library copy: BLDSC DX212513]
*Donoghue, Denis, 'The Myths of Robert Graves', ''New York Review of Books'', 43, no.6 (4 April 1996), 27-31
*''Graves and the Goddess  : Essays on Robert Graves's The White Goddess'', ed. by Ian Firla and Grevel Lindop (Selinsgrove, Pa.: Susquehanna University Press, 2003) ISBN 1-57591-055-1
*Graves, Richard Perceval, ''Robert Graves and The White Goddess, 1940-85'' (London: Weidenfeld and Nicolson, 1995)  ISBN 0-297-81534-2
*Kirkham, M.C., 'Incertitude and ''The White Goddess''', ''Essays in Criticism'', 16 (1966), 57-72
*Lindop, Grevel, 'A Crazy Book: Robert Graves and ''The White Goddess''', ''PN Review'', 24, no. 1 [117] (1997 Sept-Oct), 27-29
*Musgrove, Sydney, ''The Ancestry of 'The White Goddess'', (Bulletin No. 62, English Series, no. 11) (Auckland: Univ. of Auckland Press, 1962)
*Smeds, John. ''Statement and story : Robert Graves's myth-making'' (Åbo : Åbo Akademis Förlag, 1997) 
*Vickery, John B., ''Robert Graves and The White Goddess''  (Lincoln: Univ. of Nebraska Press, 1972)
*Vogel, Amber, 'Not Elizabeth to his Raleigh: Laura Riding, Robert Graves, and origins of ''The White Goddess''', in ''Literary Couplings: Writing Couples, Collaborators, and the Construction of Authorship'', ed. by Marjorie Stone and Judith Thompson ([[University of Wisconsin Press]], 2006), pp.&amp;nbsp;229–239, ISBN 978-0-299-21760-0

== External links ==
*[http://www.robertgraves.org/ The Robert Graves Trust]
*[http://homes.ukoln.ac.uk/~lispjh/graves/ The Robert Graves Archive]
*[http://www.serve.com/Lucius/Graves.index.html Robert Graves and ''The White Goddess'']
*[http://www.lacasaderobertgraves.com Web oficial de 'La Casa de Robert Graves' en Deià, Mallorca]. De la Fundación Robert Graves.

{{DEFAULTSORT:White Goddess, The}}
[[Category:1948 books]]
[[Category:Books by Robert Graves]]
[[Category:Comparative mythology]]
[[Category:Mythology books]]
[[Category:Wiccan books]]
[[Category:Matriarchy]]

[[it:La Dea bianca]]
[[nl:The White Goddess]]
[[pt:The White Goddess]]
[[ru:Белая Богиня]]
[[fi:The White Goddess]]</text>
      <sha1>5kfkfhy4v62y7oov4iicyn8s69fslq3</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
