<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>The Urantia Book</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>173592</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522389584</id>
      <parentid>522387922</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T21:55:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Edegonz</username>
        <id>7444714</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Criticism of its science */ I, myself, had added the word ¨commonly¨when adding the readership speculation that the Higgs boson is the ultimaton, but removed it as I realized that it was redundant when discussing modern understanding so I rephrased..</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="89577">{{Infobox book| &lt;!-- See Wikipedia:WikiProject_Novels or Wikipedia:WikiProject_Books --&gt;
| name          = The Urantia Book
| image         = [[File:The Urantia Book Cover--Urantia Foundation, Publisher.jpg|200px]]
| image_caption = Cover of 2008 edition of ''The Urantia Book'', published by the Urantia Foundation
| author        = unknown
| publisher     = Urantia Foundation, Uversa Press, others
| release_date  = October 1955
| media_type    = Print ([[Hardcover|Hardback]] &amp; [[Paperback]])
| pages         =
| isbn          = ISBN 0-911560-02-5 (Urantia Foundation), ISBN 0-9651972-3-9 (Uversa Press)
| oclc= 49687706
}}
{{Infobox book
| name          = Uversa Press Indexed Edition
| image         = 
| image_caption =
| author        = unknown
}}

'''''The Urantia Book''''' (sometimes called the '''Urantia Papers''' or '''The Fifth Epochal Revelation''') is a [[Spirituality|spiritual]] and [[Philosophy|philosophical]] book that discusses [[God]], [[Jesus]], [[science]], [[cosmology]], [[religion]], [[history]] and [[destiny]].&lt;ref name=&quot;tub&quot;&gt;[[Urantia Foundation]] (1955). ''The Urantia Book''. Urantia Foundation. ISBN 0-911560-02-5&lt;/ref&gt; It originated in [[Chicago]] sometime between 1924 and 1955. The authorship remains unverified.&lt;ref name=&quot;lewis&quot;&gt;Lewis, James R. and Hammer, Olav (2007). ''The Invention of Sacred Tradition''. Cambridge University Press. ISBN 0-521-86479-8&lt;/ref&gt;

The authors introduce the word &quot;Urantia&quot; as the name of the planet [[Earth]] and state that their intent is to &quot;present enlarged concepts and advanced truth&quot; in an &quot;endeavor to expand cosmic consciousness and enhance spiritual perception.&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/foreword#U0_0_2 |title=Foreword |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among other topics, the book expounds on the [[origin of life|origin]] and [[meaning of life]], humankind's place in the [[universe]], the relationship between [[God]] and people, and the life of [[Jesus]].

The [[Urantia Foundation]], a U.S.-based [[non-profit group]], first published ''The Urantia Book'' in 1955 in English and has since translated it into 14 other languages.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=From Urantia Foundation News Online |date=December 2010 |url=http://www.urantia.org/sites/default/files/docs/Foundation_2010_December_Newsletter.pdf |PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2001, a jury found that the English book's copyright was no longer valid after 1983.&lt;ref name=&quot;cotter&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | journal = [[California Law Review]] | volume = 91 | issue = 2 | date = March 2003 | title = Gutenberg's Legacy: Copyright, Censorship, and Religious Pluralism | author = Thomas F. Cotter | pages = 323–392 | jstor = 3481334 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;court_decision_2&quot;&gt;''[http://ca10.washburnlaw.edu/cases/2003/03/01-6347.htm Michael Foundation, Inc. v. Urantia Foundation v. Harry McMullan, III]'' US Court of Appeals affirms the jury decision that Urantia Foundation does not hold the copyright to ''The Urantia Book''&lt;/ref&gt; The English text is a [[public domain]] work in the United States,&lt;ref name=&quot;lewis&quot; /&gt; and in 2006, the international copyright on the English text expired.&lt;ref name=&quot;UFAR2006&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=2006 Urantia Foundation annual report |url=http://www.urantia.org/pub/AR2006.pdf |PDF |publisher=urantia.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Overview==
''The Urantia Book'' is 2,097 pages long and consists of an introductory foreword followed by 196 &quot;papers&quot; divided into four parts:
*The '''Foreword''' is presented as a guide to the terminology developed in greater detail in Part I, and provides an explanation for words and phrases that are &quot;in designation of Deity and certain associated concepts of the things, meanings, and values of universal reality.&quot;
*'''Part I''' consists of 31 papers that address what are considered the highest levels of creation, beginning with the [[eternity|eternal]] and [[Infinity|infinite]] &quot;Universal Father,&quot; his Trinity associates and the &quot;Isle of Paradise.&quot;
*'''Part II''' is composed of 25 papers pertaining to the origin, administration and personalities of &quot;local universes,&quot; in particular the local universe of &quot;Nebadon&quot; that is said to contain Urantia. It presents narratives on the inhabitants of local universes and their work as it is coordinated with a scheme of spiritual ascension and progression of different orders of beings, including humans.
*'''Part III''' includes 48 papers that compile a broad history of the Earth, presenting a purported explanation of the [[Creation myth|origin]], purpose, evolution and [[destiny]] of our world and its inhabitants, introducing Andon and Fonta as the first man and first woman living about 993,000 years ago, while Adam and Eve's visitation (portrayed as a mission of genetic improvement) occurring about 37,000 years ago. An additional 15 papers cover various topics such as &quot;Religion in Human Experience&quot;, the concept of the [[#God and the individual|Thought Adjuster]], &quot;Personality Survival,&quot; and &quot;The Bestowals of Christ Michael.&quot;
*'''Part IV''' is presented in 77 papers and narrates &quot;The Life and Teachings of Jesus.&quot; Included are papers about his childhood, teenage years, family life, public ministry, and the events that led to his [[crucifixion]], death, and resurrection. It continues with papers about appearances after he rose, [[Pentecost]], and finally, &quot;The Faith of Jesus.&quot; Part IV illustrates many of the concepts presented in the first three parts through the story of Jesus's life.

==Authorship==
[[Image:William S Sadler 1914.jpg|thumb|right|[[William S. Sadler]]]]
[[Image:Lena Sadler - SadlerLenaBill.jpg|thumb|right|[[Lena Sadler|Lena K. Sadler]]]]
The exact circumstances of the origin of ''The Urantia Book'' are unknown. The book and its publishers do not name a human author. Instead, it is written as if directly presented by numerous celestial beings appointed to the task of providing an &quot;epochal&quot; religious revelation. For each paper, either a named celestial being, an order of being, or a group of beings is credited as its author.&lt;ref name=&quot;gardner&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;notes_on_history&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantiabook.org/archive/history/histumov.htm |title=Notes For A History of The Urantia Movement |publisher=Urantiabook.org |date= |accessdate=2012-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sadlers_history_of_book&quot;&gt;[http://www.ubfellowship.org/archive/history/wssjr1.htm &quot;How The Urantia Book Came Into Existence&quot;] by William S. Sadler, Jr., February 18, 1962.&lt;/ref&gt;

As early as 1911, [[William S. Sadler]] and his wife [[Lena Sadler]], physicians in Chicago and well known in the community, are said to have been approached by a neighbor who was concerned because she would occasionally find her husband in a deep sleep and breathing abnormally.&lt;ref name=&quot;lewis&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;gardner&quot; /&gt; She reported that she was unable to wake him at these times. The Sadlers came to observe the episodes, and over time, the individual produced verbal communications that claimed to be from &quot;student visitor&quot; spiritual beings.&lt;ref name=&quot;lewis&quot; /&gt; This changed in early 1925 with a &quot;voluminous handwritten document,&quot; which from then on became the regular method of purported communication.&lt;ref name=&quot;lewis&quot; /&gt; The Sadlers were both respected physicians, and William Sadler was a debunker of paranormal claims, who is portrayed as not believing in the supernatural. In 1929, he published a book called ''The Mind at Mischief'', in which he explained the fraudulent methods of [[mediumship|mediums]] and how self-deception leads to psychic claims. He wrote in an appendix that there were two cases that he had not explained to his satisfaction.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sadler&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title= Sadler, William (1929). ''The Mind at Mischief''. Funk and Wagnalls. ASIN B0013WP860 |url=http://www.scribd.com/doc/23997490/William-S-Sadler-The-Mind-at-Mischief-Tricks-Deceptions-of-the-Subconscious#outer_page_302}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The other exception has to do with a rather peculiar case of psychic phenomena, one which I find myself unable to classify.... I was brought in contact with it, in the summer of 1911, and I have had it under my observation more or less ever since, having been present at probably 250 of the night sessions, many of which have been attended by a stenographer who made voluminous notes. A thorough study of this case has convinced me that it is not one of ordinary trance...In no way are these night visitations like the séances associated with spiritualism. At no time during the period of eighteen years' observation has there been a communication from any source that claimed to be the spirit of a deceased human being.... Eighteen years of study and careful investigation have failed to reveal the psychic origin of these messages... Psychoanalysis, hypnotism, intensive comparison, fail to show that the written or spoken messages of this individual have origin in his own mind... Its philosophic content is quite new, and we are unable to find where very much of it has ever found human expression... Its philosophy is consistent. It is essentially Christian and is, on the whole, entirely harmonious with the known scientific facts and truths of this age.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sadler&quot; /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In 1924, a group of Sadler's friends, former patients, and colleagues began meeting for Sunday intellectual discussions, but became interested in the strange communications when Sadler mentioned the case and read samples at their request. Shortly afterwards, a communication reportedly was received that this group would be allowed to devise questions and that answers would be given by celestial beings through the &quot;contact personality.&quot;

Sadler presented this development to the group, and they generated hundreds of questions without full seriousness, but their claim is that it resulted in the appearance of answers in the form of fully written papers. They became more impressed with the quality of the answers and continued to ask questions, until all papers now collected together as ''The Urantia Book'' were obtained. The group was known as the Forum. A smaller group of five individuals called the Contact Commission, including the Sadlers, was responsible for gathering the questions from the Forum, acting as the custodians of the handwritten manuscripts that were presented as answers, and arranging for proofreading and typing of the material.&lt;ref name=&quot;gardner&quot; /&gt;

The Sadlers and others involved, now all deceased, claimed that the papers of the book were physically materialized from 1925 until 1935 in a way that was not understood even by them, with the first three parts being completed in 1934 and the fourth in 1935. The last Forum gathering was in 1942.&lt;ref name=&quot;gardner&quot; /&gt;

After the last of Part IV was obtained in 1935, an additional period of time supposedly took place where requests for clarifications resulted in revisions. Sadler and his son William (Bill) Sadler, Jr. at one point wrote a draft introduction and were told that they could not add their introduction. The Foreword was then &quot;received.&quot; Bill Sadler is noted to have composed the table of contents that is published with the book.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Ernest P. Moyer|title=The Birth of a Divine Revelation : The Origin of the Urantia Papers|date=February 16, 2000|publisher=Moyer Pub|isbn=978-0-9678264-0-0|page=312|chapter=22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The communications purportedly continued for another two decades while members of the Forum studied the book in depth, and according to Sadler and others, permission to publish it was given to them in 1955. The [[Urantia Foundation]] was formed in 1950 as a tax-exempt educational society in Illinois,&lt;ref name=&quot;mather&quot;&gt;Mather, George A. and Nichols, Larry A. (1993). ''Dictionary of Cults, Sects, Religions and the Occult.'' Zondervan Publishing House. ISBN 0-310-53100-4&lt;/ref&gt; and through privately raised funds, the book was published under international copyright on October 12, 1955.

Only the members of the Contact Commission witnessed the activities of the sleeping subject, and only they knew his identity.&lt;ref name=&quot;lewis&quot; /&gt; The individual is claimed to have been kept anonymous in order to prevent undesirable future veneration or reverence for him. Martin Gardner states that an explanation concerning the origin of the book more plausible than celestial beings is that the Contact Commission, particularly William Sadler, was responsible. Gardner's conclusion is that a man named Wilfred Kellogg was the sleeping subject and authored the work from his subconscious mind, with William Sadler subsequently editing and authoring parts.&lt;ref name=&quot;gardner&quot; /&gt; A statistical analysis using the [[Frederick Mosteller|Mosteller]] and Wallace methods of [[stylometry]] indicates at least nine authors were involved, and by comparatively analyzing the book against Sadler's ''The Mind at Mischief'', does not indicate authorship or extensive editing by Sadler, without ruling out the possibility of limited edits.&lt;ref name=&quot;lewis&quot; /&gt;

==Copyright status==
In 1999,  Harry McMullan III and the Michael Foundation published a book, ''Jesus–A New Revelation'', which included verbatim 76 of the 196 papers included in ''The Urantia Book''.  McMullan and the Michael Foundation subsequently sought a legal declaration that the Urantia Foundation's copyright in ''The Urantia Book'' was either invalid or, alternatively, that the copyright had not been infringed upon.  Urantia Foundation's copyright was held to have expired in 1983 because the book was deemed to have been neither a composite work nor a commissioned work for hire.  These two arguments having been rejected, a U.S. court held that, since the Conduit had deceased prior to 1983, only the Conduit's heirs would have been eligible to renew the copyright in 1983 and, since they had not done so, the Urantia Foundation's copyright in the book had expired and the book had therefore passed into the public domain.  This decision was upheld on appeal.&lt;ref name=&quot;cotter&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;court_decision_2&quot;&gt;''[http://ca10.washburnlaw.edu/cases/2003/03/01-6347.htm Michael Foundation, Inc. v. Urantia Foundation v. Harry McMullan, III]'' US Court of Appeals affirms the jury decision that Urantia Foundation does not hold the copyright to''The Urantia Book''&lt;/ref&gt;  The international copyright on the English text expired in 2006.&lt;ref name=&quot;UFAR2006&quot;/&gt;

==Teachings==
{{primary sources|date=August 2012}}

===Nature of God===
According to ''The Urantia Book'', God is the creator and upholder of all reality—an [[omniscience|omniscient]],&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-3-attributes-god#U3_3_0 |title=Paper 3, &quot;The Attributes of God&quot;, omniscience |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[omnipresence|omnipresent]],&lt;ref  group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-3-attributes-god#U3_1_0 |title=Paper 3, &quot;The Attributes of God&quot;, omnipresence |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[omnipotence|omnipotent]],&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-3-attributes-god#U3_2_0 |title=Paper 3, &quot;The Attributes of God&quot;, omnipotence |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[infinity|infinite]],&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-2-nature-god#U2_1_0 |title=Paper 2, &quot;The Nature of God&quot;, infinity |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[eternity|eternal]]&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-2-nature-god#U2_2_0 |title=Paper 2, &quot;The Nature of God&quot;, eternal |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; spirit personality. The most fundamental teaching about God in the book is that he is a Father. &quot;The face which the Infinite turns toward all universe personalities is the face of a Father, the Universal Father of love.&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/en/urantia-book-standardized/paper-105-deity-and-reality#U105_1_8 |title=Paper 105, &quot;Deity and Reality&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Even during the development of numerous other themes in ''The Urantia Book'', God as a loving Father is emphasized as the central, unifying attitude of God toward the universe.

{{quote|God is inherently kind, naturally compassionate, and everlastingly merciful. And never is it necessary that any influence be brought to bear upon the Father to call forth his loving-kindness. The creature's need is wholly sufficient to insure the full flow of the Father's tender mercies and his saving grace. Since God knows all about his children, it is easy for him to forgive. The better man understands his neighbor, the easier it will be to forgive him, even to love him.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/en/urantia-book-standardized/paper-2-nature-god#U2_4_2 |title=Paper 2, &quot;The Nature of God&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

God is said to be a [[Sacred Mysteries|mystery]] though because of the infinite scope of his perfection and his attributes.

{{quote|God is not hiding from any of his creatures. He is unapproachable to so many orders of beings only because he &quot;dwells in a light which no material creature can approach.&quot; The immensity and grandeur of the divine personality is beyond the grasp of the unperfected mind of evolutionary mortals.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/en/urantia-book-standardized/paper-1-universal-father#U1_5_3 |title=Paper 1, &quot;The Universal Father&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

God, according to the book, is one Deity who functions on a range of different levels of reality, both personal and impersonal. God is taught to exist in a [[Trinity]] of three perfectly individualized persons&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-10-paradise-trinity |title=Paper 10, &quot;The Paradise Trinity&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; who are co-equal: God the Father, God the Son,&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-6-eternal-son |title=Paper 6, &quot;The Eternal Son&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; and God the Spirit.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-8-infinite-spirit |title=Paper 8, &quot;The Infinite Spirit&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; These persons are referred to by additional titles in the book, primarily as the &quot;Universal Father,&quot; &quot;Eternal Son,&quot; and &quot;Infinite Spirit.&quot; While stating that the concept of one God in three persons is difficult to fully understand, the book says that the idea &quot;in no manner violates the truth of the divine unity. The three personalities of Paradise Deity are, in all universe reality reactions and in all creature relations, as one.&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/en/urantia-book-standardized/paper-1-universal-father#U1_7_8 |title=Paper 1, &quot;The Universal Father&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Father, Son, and Spirit are considered &quot;existential&quot; persons of Deity, those in existence from the eternal past to the eternal future. In addition, three persons of Deity are described who are &quot;experiential,&quot; or incomplete and in the process of actualizing: God the Supreme,&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-117-god-supreme |title=Paper 117, &quot;God the Supreme&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; God the Ultimate,&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/foreword#U0_9_0 |title=Foreword, &quot;God the Ultimate&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; and God the Absolute.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/foreword#U0_10_0 |title=Foreword, &quot;God the Absolute&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of these three, God the Supreme, or &quot;the Supreme Being,&quot; is given the most explanation, as the person of Deity evolving in time and space to unify finite reality and the infinite. The persons of God the Ultimate and God the Absolute are considered to be remote from the possibility of comprehension and are covered on a limited basis.

Many types of celestial beings are enumerated in the book, and one of particular note is a joint &quot;offspring&quot; of the Universal Father and Eternal Son called a &quot;Creator Son.&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-21-paradise-creator-sons |title=The Paradise Creator Sons |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; A divine Creator Son is considered the full representation of the Universal Father and Eternal Son that is possible to people. [[Jesus]] of [[Nazareth]] is identified as a Creator Son who [[incarnation|incarnated]] on Earth&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-32-evolution-local-universes#U32_0_3 |title=Paper 32, &quot;The Evolution of Local Universes&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; and whose life and teachings are portrayed&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/part-iv-life-and-teachings-jesus |title=The Life and Teachings of Jesus |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; as the fullest revelation of the personality and attitude of God ever given to humanity.

The final paper states:&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/en/urantia-book-standardized/paper-196-faith-jesus##U196_1_3  |title=Paper 196, &quot;The Faith of Jesus&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|To &quot;follow Jesus&quot; means to personally share his religious faith and to enter into the spirit of the Master's life of unselfish service for man. One of the most important things in human living is to find out what Jesus believed, to discover his ideals, and to strive for the achievement of his exalted life purpose. Of all human knowledge, that which is of greatest value is to know the religious life of Jesus and how he lived it.}}

===God and the individual===
God is described as the Father of each individual, and through the direct gift of a fragment of his eternal spirit, called a Thought Adjuster,&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-107-origin-and-nature-thought-adjusters  |title=Paper 107, Origin and Nature of Thought Adjusters |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; is said to be able to guide the individual toward an increased understanding of him. The Thought Adjuster is also called a &quot;Mystery Monitor,&quot; &quot;inner voice,&quot; &quot;divine spark,&quot; and &quot;pilot light.&quot; The concept is in ways comparable to the [[Hindu]] [[Atman (Hinduism)|atman]], the ancient [[Ancient Egypt|Egyptian]] [[Egyptian soul|ka]],&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-111-adjuster-and-soul#U111_0_4  |title=Paper 111, The Adjuster and the Soul, atman and ka |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Quaker]] [[inner light]]. In relation to biblical traditions, the Thought Adjuster is described by the book as the meaning behind the phrases &quot;being made in God's image&quot; and the &quot;kingdom of God is within you&quot;:

{{quote|The Adjuster is the mark of divinity, the presence of God. The &quot;image of God&quot; does not refer to physical likeness nor to the circumscribed limitations of material creature endowment but rather to the gift of the spirit presence of the Universal Father in the supernal bestowal of the Thought Adjusters upon the humble creatures of the universes.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/en/urantia-book-standardized/paper-108-mission-and-ministry-thought-adjusters#U108_6_3  |title=Paper 108, Mission and Ministry of Thought Adjusters, Thought Adjusters as image of God  |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Each person is said to receive one such fragment at the time of his or her first independent [[morality|moral]] decision, on average around the age of five years and ten months.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-108-mission-and-ministry-thought-adjusters#U108_2_1  |title=Paper 108, Mission and Ministry of Thought Adjusters, average age of Thought Adjusters arrival |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Adjuster then serves noncoercively as a divine partner in the mind of the individual for the rest of life, and to the extent that a person consents with their [[free will]] to want to find God, it leads the person toward more mature, spiritualized thinking. Through the practice of learning how to follow the inner leadings of the Adjuster—choose &quot;God's will&quot;—the individual progresses to greater God consciousness and spiritual growth.

A person's Thought Adjuster is described as distinct from either the [[Soul (spirit)|soul]] or the [[conscience]]. In ''The Urantia Book''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s teachings, the degree to which a human mind chooses to accept its Adjuster's guidance becomes the degree to which a person's soul &quot;grows&quot; and becomes a reality that can then survive death. The soul is in essence an embryonic spiritual development, one parental factor being the divine Adjuster and the other being the human will.

The book many times links the biblical [[New Testament]] teachings of becoming like a little child&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-140-ordination-twelve#U140_10_4  |title=Paper 140, The Ordination of the Twelve, man as little child |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;  in attitude of trust and sincerity as being the stance each person should have toward God. It says the attitude of open-minded teachability facilitates spiritual growth in liaison with the work of the Thought Adjuster and invariably leads a person to love and serve other people. It also says, &quot;But you yourself are mostly unconscious of this inner ministry. You are quite incapable of distinguishing the product of your own material intellect from that of the conjoint activities of your soul and the Adjuster.&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-110-relation-adjusters-individual-mortals#U110_4_2  |title=Paper 110, Relation of Adjusters to Individual Mortals, unconscious of Adjusters ministry |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Persistently embracing [[sin]] is considered the same as rejecting the leadings of the Adjuster, rejecting the [[will (philosophy)|will]] of God. Constant selfishness and sinful choosing lead eventually to iniquity and full identification with unrighteousness, and since unrighteousness is unreal, it results in the eventual annihilation of the individual's identity. Personalities like this become &quot;as if they never were.&quot; The book says that &quot;in the last analysis, such sin-identified individuals have destroyed themselves by becoming wholly unreal through their embrace of iniquity.&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-2-nature-god#U2_3_2 |title=Paper 2, The Nature of God, sin destroys individuals &amp;#124; Urantia Book &amp;#124; Urantia Foundation |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; The concepts of [[Hell]] and [[reincarnation]]&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-94-melchizedek-teachings-in-orient#U94_2_3 |title=Paper 94 - The Melchizedek Teachings in the Orient, reincarnation &amp;#124; Urantia Book &amp;#124; Urantia Foundation |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; are not taught.

From Paper 5, &quot;God's Relation to the Individual&quot;:&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/en/urantia-book-standardized/paper-5-gods-relation-individual |title=Paper 5 - God's Relation to the Individual &amp;#124; Urantia Book &amp;#124; Urantia Foundation |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|The great God makes direct contact with mortal man and gives a part of his infinite and eternal and incomprehensible self to live and dwell within him. God has embarked upon the eternal adventure with man. If you yield to the leadings of the spiritual forces in you and around you, you cannot fail to attain the high destiny established by a loving God as the universe goal of his ascendant creatures from the evolutionary worlds of space.}}

The book says that a person ultimately is destined to fuse with his or her divine fragment and become one inseparable entity with it, if the person chooses to accept the Adjuster's leadings and become self-identified with it. The act of fusion is the moment when a human personality has successfully and unalterably won eternal life, described as typically taking place in the afterlife, but also a possibility during earthly life.&lt;ref name=&quot;fuse_on_earth&quot; group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-110-relation-adjusters-individual-mortals#U110_7_2 |title=Paper 45 - Relation of Adjusters to Individual Mortals, fusion on earth &amp;#124; Urantia Book &amp;#124; Urantia Foundation |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; The result during human life is a &quot;fusion flash,&quot; with the material body consumed in a fiery light and the soul &quot;translated&quot; to the afterlife. The Hebrew prophet [[Elijah]] being taken to heaven without death&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-45-local-system-administration#U45_4_15 |title=Paper 45 - The Local System Administration, Elijah fusion &amp;#124; Urantia Book &amp;#124; Urantia Foundation |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; in &quot;chariots of fire&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;fuse_on_earth&quot; group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; is said to be a rare example in recorded history of a person who attained fusion.

Once fused with his or her fragment of God, a person continues as an ascending citizen in the universe and travels through numerous worlds on a long, adventurous pilgrimage of growth and learning that eventually leads to God and residence on Paradise. Mortals who reach this stage are called &quot;finaliters.&quot; The book goes on to discuss the potential destinies of these &quot;glorified mortals.&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-31-corps-finality#U31_3_0 |title=Paper 112 - The Corps of the Finality &amp;#124; Urantia Book &amp;#124; Urantia Foundation |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''The Urantia Book'' places much emphasis on the idea that all individuals have the same opportunity to know God, and it says nothing can hinder a human being's spiritual progression if he or she is motivated to be spirit led.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-112-personality-survival#U112_5_6 |title=Paper 112 - Personality Survival, accidents of time &amp;#124; Urantia Book &amp;#124; Urantia Foundation |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; The book regards human life on earth as a &quot;short and intense test,&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-14-central-and-divine-universe#U14_5_1 |title=Paper 14 - The Central and Divine Universe, life on earth as short and intense test &amp;#124; Urantia Book &amp;#124; Urantia Foundation |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;is not so much a probation as an education&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-111-adjuster-and-soul#U111_3_5 |title=Paper 111 - The Adjuster and the Soul, life on earth as education &amp;#124; Urantia Book &amp;#124; Urantia Foundation |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;  and the afterlife as a continuation of training that begins in material life. The &quot;religion of Jesus&quot; is considered to be practiced by way of loving God the Father with a person's whole being, thereby learning to love each person the way Jesus loves people; that is, recognizing others as brothers and sisters and being of unselfish service to them.

===Cosmology===
The book teaches that the universe is vastly older&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-57-origin-urantia#U57_1_3 |title=Paper 57, &quot;The Origin of Urantia&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; than current scientific theories state, and that the universe is the product of intelligent and purposeful organization.&lt;ref name=&quot;gardner&quot;&gt;[[Martin Gardner|Gardner, Martin]] (1995). ''Urantia: The Great Cult Mystery.'' Prometheus Books. ISBN 0-87975-955-0&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;gooch&quot;&gt;Gooch, Brad (2002). ''Godtalk: Travels in Spiritual America''. Alfred A. Knopf. ISBN 0-679-44709-1&lt;/ref&gt;
Information about [[cosmology]] and [[astronomy]] is provided in parts I, II, and III of the book. The book discusses [[space]] and [[time]],&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-12-universe-universes#U12_1_0 |title=Paper 12, &quot;The Universe of Universes&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; describes the formation and evolution of [[galaxies]], [[stars]], and [[planets]].&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-15-seven-superuniverses#U15_5_0 |title=Paper 15, &quot;The Seven Superuniverses&quot;,&quot;The Origin of Space Bodies&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; The authors claim that the universe is teeming with intelligent life located mainly on the [[extrasolar planet|planets of extrasolar]] [[planetary systems]].&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-14-central-and-divine-universe#U14_2_1 |title=Paper 14, &quot;The Central and Divine Universe&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The book describes that at the center of the cosmos is the stationary Isle of Paradise&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-11-eternal-isle-paradise |title=Paper 11, &quot;The Eternal Isle of Paradise&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; — the dwelling place of [[God]] — with Paradise being surrounded by &quot;Havona,&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-14-central-and-divine-universe |title=Paper 14, &quot;The Central and Divine Universe&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; a created universe containing a billion perfect worlds, around which seven evolutionary &quot;superuniverses&quot; circle.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-15-seven-superuniverses |title=Paper 15, &quot;The Seven Superuniverses&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; All the [[Galaxy groups and clusters|groupings of galaxies]] of inhabited and uninhabited universes circle around the Isle of Paradise,&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-12-universe-universes#U12_1_3 |title=Paper 12, &quot;Space Levels of the Master Universe&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; the gravitational center of the universe, which some Urantia Book readers believe is located in [[Great Attractor]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=TruthBook.com - Dr. Stefan H. Tallqvist - Great Attractor|url=http://www.truthbook.com/index.cfm?linkID=98}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term &quot;universe&quot; in the book is used to denote a number of different scales of organization. A &quot;superuniverse&quot; is roughly the size of a [[galaxy]] or group of galaxies, and the seven superuniverses along with Paradise-Havona are together designated as the &quot;grand universe.&quot; A &quot;local universe&quot; is a portion of a superuniverse, with 100,000 local universes being in each superuniverse. Beyond the seven superuniverses, enormous uninhabited &quot;outer space levels&quot; are described.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-12-universe-universes#U12_1_14 |title=Paper 12, &quot;The Outer Space Levels&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term &quot;master universe&quot; refers to what in modern usage would be the total universe — all existing [[matter]] and space taken as a whole.

The physical size of a local universe is not directly stated, but each is said to have up to 10 million inhabited worlds. Urantia is said to be located in a remote local universe named &quot;Nebadon,&quot; which itself is part of superuniverse number seven, &quot;Orvonton.&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-15-seven-superuniverses#U15_14_5 |title=Paper 15, Urantia location |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The book discusses alternative explanations for the universe's origin and offers explanations for some observed astronomical phenomena. For example, the book claims that [[Hubble's law|astronomic redshift]] arises from &quot;numerous factors of error&quot; and is &quot;wholly unreliable&quot; beyond nearby galaxies, the greatest distortion being caused by the seven superuniverses revolving around Paradise in the direction opposite from the galaxies in the &quot;outer space levels.&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-12-universe-universes#U12_4_15 |title=Paper 12, redshift velocity errors |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Science===
The book attempts to synchronize religion, science and philosophy and many statements about science appear in the text. &quot;The ideal human estate is that in which philosophy, religion, and science are welded into a meaningful unity..&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-98-melchizedek-teachings-in-occident#U98_2_12 |title=Paper 98, &quot;The Melchizedek Teachings in the Occident&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Science teaches man to speak the new language of mathematics and trains his thoughts along lines of exacting precision. And science also stabilizes philosophy through the elimination of error, while it purifies religion by the destruction of superstition.&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-81-development-modern-civilization#U81_6_10 |title=Paper 81, &quot;Development of Modern Civilization&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; The book holds science in high regard, however it opposes the purely materialistic science. About conflict between science and religion the book states: &quot;In reality, true religion cannot become involved in any controversy with science; it is in no way concerned with material things.&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-195-after-pentecost#U195_6_2 |title=Paper 195, &quot;After Pentecost&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
''The Urantia Book'' debunks astrology as &quot;pseudo science of Babylon&quot; and also states: &quot;But the frank, honest, and fearless search for true causes gave birth to modern science: It turned astrology into astronomy, alchemy into chemistry, and magic into medicine.&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-81-development-modern-civilization#U81_6_10 |title=Paper 81, astrology |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Paper 101, &quot;The Real Nature of Religion,&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/en/urantia-book-standardized/paper-101-real-nature-religion |title=Paper 101 - The Real Nature of Religion &amp;#124; Urantia Book &amp;#124; Urantia Foundation |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; the authors write:
&lt;blockquote&gt;We full well know that, while the historic facts and religious truths of this series of revelatory presentations will stand on the records of the ages to come, within a few short years many of our statements regarding the physical sciences will stand in need of revision in consequence of additional scientific developments and new discoveries. These new developments we even now foresee, but we are forbidden to include such humanly undiscovered facts in the revelatory records. Let it be made clear that revelations are not necessarily inspired. The cosmology of these revelations is ''not inspired''.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-101-real-nature-religion#U101_4_2 |title=Paper 101, cosmology is not inspired |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The only apparent anticipation of science the book has made, in Gardner's opinion, is that it says the magnetic sense that [[homing pigeon]]s possess is &quot;not wholly wanting as a conscious possession by mankind.&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-34-local-universe-mother-spirit#U34_4_13 |title=Paper 34, magnetic sense |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1980, a British zoologist, Robin Baker, published evidence that humans have a limited magnetic sense.

[[Kary Mullis]] a [[Nobel Prize]] winning American [[biochemistry|biochemist]] indicates on his personal website {{Better source|date=July 2012}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Kary Mullis website |url= http://www.karymullis.com/urantia.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; a striking coincidences between a story of Adam and Eve&lt;ref name=&quot;adam_eve&quot; group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-74-adam-and-eve |title=Paper 74, &quot;Adam and Eve &quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; in ''The Urantia Book'' and the finding published in &quot;Science&quot;: 309 (2005) that a variant of a gene that regulates brain size arose roughly 37,000 years ago with a 95% [[confidence interval]] of 14,000 to 60,000 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Science 9 September |year=2005 |url=http://www.sciencemag.org/content/309/5741/1717}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to The Urantia Book: &quot;Adam and Eve arrived on Urantia, from the year A.D. 1934, 37,848 years ago&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;adam_eve&quot; group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Mark McMenamin]], a professor of [[geology]], quotes a section of the book describing a billion-year-old supercontinent that subsequently split apart, forming ocean basins where early marine life developed. He says, &quot;This amazing passage, written in the 1930s, anticipates scientific results that did not actually appear in the scientific literature until many decades later.&quot; McMenamin also states, &quot;Of course I am being selective here in my choice of quotations, and there are reams of scientifically untenable material in ''The Urantia Book''.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;McMenamin, Mark A. S. ''The Garden of Ediacara: Discovering the Earliest Complex Life Columbia''. University Press. New Ed edition (October 15, 2000) ISBN 0-231-10559-2&lt;/ref&gt;

In his book ''Supercontinent: Ten Billion Years in the Life of Our Planet'' Ted Nield comments on McMenamin's statement, saying &quot;These quotations are selective, of course, which is always the key to making the prophecies of mystics look 'uncanny' If you look at other parts of the same passage from which those quotations come, you can find a rich and colourful mixture of half-correct ideas and plain nonsense... But the trick of a successful prophet is to say enough things, and to phrase them sufficiently elliptically, so that the occasional correct hits within the general rambling leap out at the prepared mind - just like cloud patterns, or the face of the Man in the Moon.&quot; In this case, he says, both scientists and mystics &quot;apparently independently 'discovered'&quot; this supercontinent, &quot;and it was the mystics who sleepwalked there first.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Neild|first=Ted|title=Supercontinent: Ten Billion Years in the Life of Our Planet|year=2009|publisher=Harvard University Press|isbn=978-0674032453|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=3wXCrWU37uYC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=inauthor:%22Ted+Nield%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=YQmzu4gIP_&amp;sig=DIYsGE4y56ftNGGeUOhH5RZ631s&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=z3chUJHUE8Gi0QX0v4GADA&amp;redir_esc=y#v=snippet&amp;q=Urantia%20sleepwalked&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Adherents believe that there are some examples of [[Scientific foreknowledge in sacred texts|scientific foreknowledge]] ''in The Urantia Book''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Science in The Urantia Book url=http://urantiabook.org/index_science.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=History, Science and Evolution url= http://www.truthbook.com/index.cfm?linkID=6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===History and future of the world===
The book's extensive teachings about the history of the Earth include its physical development about 4.5 billion years ago,&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite wikisource|title=Paper 57, 57:5.4|wslink=The_Urantia_Book/Paper_57#U57_5_4|noicon=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; the gradual changes in conditions that allowed life to develop, and long ages of organic evolution that started with microscopic marine life and led to plant and animal life in the oceans, later on land. The emergence of humans is presented as having occurred about a million years ago from a branch of superior [[primate]]s originating from a [[lemur]] ancestor.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite wikisource|title=Paper 62, The First Human Beings|wslink=The Urantia Book/Paper 62|anchor=The First Human Beings|noicon=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''The Urantia Book'' says &quot;this story is graphically told within the fossil pages of the vast 'stone book' of world record ... the pages of this gigantic [[fossil record|biogeologic record]] unfailingly tell the truth if you but acquire skill in their interpretation.&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite wikisource|title=Paper 58, 58:7.12|wslink=The_Urantia_Book/Paper_58#Paragraph_58:7.12|noicon=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike current scientific views, evolution is said to be orderly and controlled. Primordial life is taught to have been intelligently planned, implanted, and monitored by &quot;Life Carriers,&quot; instead of arising spontaneously.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite wikisource|title=Paper 65, Life Carrier Functions|wslink=The_Urantia_Book/Paper_65|anchor=Life Carrier Functions|noicon=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; The book says that &quot;mortal man is not an evolutionary accident,&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite wikisource|title=Paper 49, 49:1.6|wslink=The_Urantia_Book/Paper_49#Paragraph_49:1.6|noicon=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that the purpose of evolution on a planet such as Urantia is to produce creatures of &quot;will dignity&quot; that can develop spiritual natures and survive material existence, going on to have eternal spiritual careers.

''The Urantia Book'' teaches not only biological evolution, but that human society and spiritual understandings evolve by slow progression, subject both to periods of rapid improvement and the possibility of retrogression. Progress is said to follow a divine plan that includes periodic gifts of revelation and ministry by heavenly teachers, which eventually will lead to an ideal world status of &quot;light and life&quot; in the far distant future.

Though there is the ideal and divine plan, it is said to be fostered and administered by various orders of celestial beings who are not always perfect. Through mistakes or deliberate rebellion, the plan can be wrecked, requiring long spans of time to recoup lost progress. Urantia is said to be a markedly &quot;dark and confused&quot; planet that is &quot;greatly retarded in all phases of intellectual progress and spiritual attainment&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite wikisource|title=Paper 50, 50:6.2|wslink=The_Urantia_Book/Paper_50#Paragraph_50:6.2|noicon=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; compared to more typical inhabited worlds, due to an unusually severe history of rebellion and default by its spiritual supervisors.

The Urantia Book describes the successive eras of biologic, intellectual, and spiritual uplifting as &quot;epochal revelations&quot; of God and his ministering agents to man. According to The Urantia Book the Lucifer Rebellion&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/en/urantia-book-standardized/paper-53-lucifer-rebellion |title=Paper 53 - The Lucifer Rebellion &amp;#124; Urantia Book &amp;#124; Urantia Foundation |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; was a disruption of God's divine plan in the history of Urantia. In the book, Lucifer is classified as a &quot;Primary Lanonandek Son&quot; and head administrator of his attending system. He proposed the concepts of personal liberty, self-autonomy, and self-assertion. These concepts were adopted on Urantia first by the head of its human affairs, Caligastia. By joining Lucifer, Caligastia caused the eventual collapse of the same fragile civilization he had come to guide as &quot;Planetary Prince&quot; of the realm.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Kelly Elstrott|title=The Fifth Revelation: A collection of key passages from The Urantia Book|year=1998|publisher=Mighty Messenger Press Pub|isbn=0-9654301-7-0|page=55}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Urantia Book emphasizes that despite its dark history, Urantia has been the beneficiary of much good. The life of [[Jesus]], designated in The Urantia Book as the &quot;fourth epochal revelation,&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite wikisource|title=Paper 92, 92:4.8|wslink=The_Urantia_Book/Paper_92#Paragraph_92:4.8|noicon=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; is said to have redeemed the planet of the blunders of rebellion. &quot;And when Jesus came down from his sojourn on Mount Hermon, the Lucifer rebellion in Satania and the Caligastia secession on Urantia were virtually settled.&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite wikisource|title=Paper 134, The Sojourn on Mount Hermon |wslink=The_Urantia_Book/Paper_134#Paragraph_134:8.9|noicon=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=God's Bible: An Epochal Revelation Sponsored by God's Angels, Part IV, Papers 120-196: The Life and Teachings of Jesus|publisher=Pathways, Inc|page=90}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Life and teachings of Jesus===
More than one third of the content of the book (Part IV) is devoted to a narrative of the life and teachings of Jesus. From his birth in Bethlehem and infancy in Alexandria, the story extends through his years of school in Nazareth and his work as a young carpenter after the death of his father Joseph,&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite wikisource|title=Paper 126, The Death of Joseph|wslink=The_Urantia_Book/Paper_126#The_Death_of_Joseph|noicon=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; in order to sustain his widowed mother and eight brothers and sisters. Topics include a girl Rebecca who fell in love with him, and Jesus's rejection of her proposal for marriage.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite wikisource|title=Paper 127, Rebecca, the Daughter of Ezra|wslink=The_Urantia_Book/Paper_127#Rebecca.2C_the_Daughter_of_Ezra|noicon=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jesus is said to have traveled around the Mediterranean Basin (Alexandria, Rome, Athens etc. ) and regions of the Middle East (Mesopotamia and Caspian Sea region) in his late 20s,&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite wikisource|title=Paper 130, On the Way to Rome|wslink=The_Urantia_Book/Paper_130|noicon=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; and after these trips, the narrative begins to parallel what is depicted in the New Testament, but with numerous extra details. John the Baptist and the twelve Apostles are people of flesh and blood with their virtues and flaws. Jesus's teachings, as presented to his apostles and followers, is exhaustive, enlarged and presented in contemporary language. The work of the Women's Evangelistic Corps appointed by Jesus is also narrated.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite wikisource|title=Paper 150, The Women's Evangelistic Corps |wslink=The_Urantia_Book/Paper_150#The_Women.27s_Evangelistic_Corps|noicon=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

As Jesus's mission on Earth, the book describes the seventh bestowal of a Creator Son.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite wikisource|title=Paper 119, The Bestowals of Christ Michael |wslink=The_Urantia_Book/Paper_119|noicon=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; Each Creator Son can rule his part of the universe – (termed the &quot;local universe&quot;) – after completing seven bestowals, the final of them is in the likeness of mortal flesh. This is the one of reasons why the Creator Son came to Earth – Urantia. The other purpose of his mission is stated in the book: &quot;A Creator Son did not incarnate in the likeness of mortal flesh and bestow himself upon the humanity of Urantia to reconcile an angry God but rather to win all mankind to the recognition of the Father's love and to the realization of their sonship with God.&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-98-melchizedek-teachings-in-occident#U98_7_1|title=Paper 98, &quot;The Melchizedek Teachings in the Occident&quot;|publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; The core of Jesus's teaching is that men are children of God and their fellows are their brethren in one big family; when Jesus is their elder brother. The idea of the kingdom of God as presented by Jesus is the spiritual rule of Heavenly Father in the hearts of men, but many of his followers misinterpret this idea as a purely earthly kingdom. The book states that today Christianity is rather a religion about Jesus instead religion of Jesus – his original teaching – which the book reinstates.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite wikisource|title=Paper 195, 195:4.4 | wslink=The_Urantia_Book/Paper_195#Paragraph_195:4.4|noicon=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Comparisons==

===Comparison to Christianity===
Of all current major world religions, ''The Urantia Book''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s teachings are most similar to those of [[Christianity]]. However, there are numerous and significant differences between it and commonly accepted Christian beliefs.

[[Jesus]] is held in high regard by ''The Urantia Book,'' as he is in the New Testament of the [[Bible]]. The following are attributed to him as in the Bible:
*He was both human and divine, a Son of God incarnate who was born to [[Mary (mother of Jesus)|Mary]], whose husband was [[Joseph the Betrothed|Joseph]].&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-120-bestowal-michael-urantia#U120_4_0 |title=Paper 120, &quot;The Incarnation — Making Two One&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*He lived a perfect life.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-140-ordination-twelve#U140_8_19 |title=Paper 140, 140:8.19 |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*He performed many of the miracles described in the Bible, such as the resurrection of [[Lazarus of Bethany|Lazarus]],&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-168-resurrection-lazarus |title=Paper 168, &quot;The Resurrection of Lazarus&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; the turning of water into wine,&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-137-tarrying-time-in-galilee#U137_4_0 |title=Paper 137, &quot;The Wedding at Cana&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; the feeding of the five thousand,&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-152-events-leading-capernaum-crisis#U152_2_0 |title=Paper 152, &quot;Feeding the Five Thousand&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; and numerous healings of the blind, diseased, and infirm.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-145-four-eventful-days-capernaum#U145_3_0 |title=Paper 145, &quot;The Healing at Sundown&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*He taught twelve apostles, most of whom went on to spread his teachings.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-140-ordination-twelve |title=Paper 140, &quot;The Ordination of the Twelve&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*He was crucified, and on the third day after his death, rose from the dead.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-189-resurrection |title=Paper 189, &quot;The Resurrection&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*He will return to the world again some day.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-176-tuesday-evening-mount-olivet#U176_4_0 |title=Paper 176, &quot;The Return of Michael&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some differences with Christianity include:&lt;ref name=&quot;gardner&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;gooch&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;house&quot;&gt;House, Dr. H. Wayne (2000). ''Charts of Cults, Sects, and Religious Movements''. Zondervan. ISBN 0-310-38551-2&lt;/ref&gt;
*God is never wrathful or angry. He is a personality entirely motivated by Fatherlike love.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-2-nature-god#U2_6_7 |title=Paper 2, &quot;The Goodness of God&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Jesus's crucifixion is not considered an [[atonement in Christianity|atonement]] for the sins of humanity.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-188-time-tomb#U188_4_0 |title=Paper 176, &quot;The Return of Michael&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; The crucifixion is taught to be an outcome of the fears of religious leaders of the day, who regarded his teachings as a threat to their positions of authority.
*Jesus is considered the human incarnation of &quot;Michael of Nebadon,&quot; one of more than 700,000 &quot;Paradise Sons&quot; of God, or &quot;Creator Sons.&quot; Jesus is not considered the second person of the [[Trinity]] as he is in Christianity.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-104-growth-trinity-concept#U104_1_11 |title=Paper 104, 104:1.11 |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; The book refers to the Eternal Son as the second person of the Trinity.
*Jesus was born on earth through natural means of conception instead of a [[Virgin birth of Jesus|virgin birth]].{{citation needed|reason=There are only statements about carrying and birth|date=September 2012}}
*Jesus did not walk on water&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-152-events-leading-capernaum-crisis#U152_4_0 |title=Paper 152, Simon Peter’s Night Vision |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; or perform some of the miracles that are attributed to him in the Bible.
*Jesus commissioned twelve women (and later more) as religious teachers, who traveled about with him and his apostles on their preaching missions.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-163-ordination-seventy-magadan#U163_7_3 |title=Paper 163, 163:7.3 |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The book states that Jesus may return to the world many times.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-176-tuesday-evening-mount-olivet#U176_4_0 |title=Paper 176, The Return of Michael |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; This contrasts with traditional [[Christian eschatology]], in which Jesus will return only once.

===Comparison to Buddhism===
''The Urantia Book'' considers [[Buddhism]] one of the &quot;great international, interracial faiths&quot; and says it &quot;has shown an adaptability to the mores of many peoples that has been equaled only by Christianity.&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-94-melchizedek-teachings-in-orient#U94_8_0 |title=Paper 194, &quot;The Buddhist Faith&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Gautama Siddhartha]] is called a real [[prophet]] whose doctrines were &quot;revolutionary and amazing&quot; for their time.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-94-melchizedek-teachings-in-orient#U94_7_0 |title=Paper 94, &quot;Gautama Siddhartha&quot; |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; He is credited with being one of the seven outstanding teachers in human history in the matter of combining contemporaneous systems of ethical and religious teachings, a group that includes [[Moses]], [[Laozi]], and the [[Apostle Paul]].&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-121-times-michaels-bestowal#U121_6_4 |title=Paper 121, 121:6.4 |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The teaching that a divine nature—the [[Buddha-nature]]—resides in all people, and that through their own endeavors people can attain a realization of this inner divinity, is cited as one of the clearest presentations of the concept of the Thought Adjuster to be found in non-revelatory religion.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-94-melchizedek-teachings-in-orient#U94_11_5 |title=Paper 94, 94:11.5 |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The book says Gautama's experience was tragic, however, in that he was an &quot;orphan prophet&quot; whose philosophy failed early on to envision the reality of a spiritual God.

Despite this, the book states: &quot;Buddhism is a living, growing religion today because it succeeds in conserving many of the highest moral values of its adherents. It promotes calmness and self-control, augments serenity and happiness, and does much to prevent sorrow and mourning. Those who believe this philosophy live better lives than many who do not.&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-94-melchizedek-teachings-in-orient#U94_9_6 |title=Paper 94,94:9.6 |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Comparison to other world religions===
Facets of other world religions are incorporated in the book, including from Islam, Taoism, Judaism, Hinduism, Shinto, and Confucianism. For example, Paper 131, &quot;The World's Religions&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/en/urantia-book-standardized/paper-131-worlds-religions |title=Paper 131 - The World's Religions &amp;#124; Urantia Book &amp;#124; Urantia Foundation |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; discusses in more depth those aspects of different religions that have commonalities with what the book claims is the &quot;religion of Jesus.&quot; There are also numerous other references to the world's major religions throughout Part III, &quot;The History of Urantia,&quot; beginning with Paper 86, &quot;Early Evolution of Religion.&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/en/urantia-book-standardized/paper-86-early-evolution-religion |title=Paper 86 - Early Evolution of Religion &amp;#124; Urantia Book &amp;#124; Urantia Foundation |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; The perspective of ''The Urantia Book'' is that all religions should be studied to take &quot;the best&quot; from each.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-92-later-evolution-religion#U92_7_3 |title=Paper 92, 92:7.3 |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Consideration as literature==
''The Urantia Book'' has been enjoyed by some as a form of [[science fiction]], [[historical fiction]] or [[fantasy]]. ''The Urantia Book'' is noted for its high level of internal consistency and an advanced writing style. Skeptic [[Martin Gardner]], in a book otherwise highly critical of ''The Urantia Book'', writes that it is &quot;highly imaginative&quot; and that the &quot;cosmology outrivals in fantasy the cosmology of any science-fiction work known to me.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gardner&quot; /&gt;

Parts I, II, and III are chiefly written in expository language. The papers are informational, matter-of-fact, and instructional. Part IV of the book is written as a biography of Jesus's life, and some feel it is a rich narrative with well-developed characters, high attention to detail, woven sub-plots, and realistic dialogue. Considered as literature, Part IV is favorably compared to other retellings of Jesus's life, such as ''[[The Gospel According to Jesus Christ]]'' by [[José Saramago]] and ''[[Behold the Man (novel)|Behold the Man]]'' by [[Michael Moorcock]]. Martin Gardner considers Part IV to be an especially &quot;well-written, impressive work,&quot; and says, &quot;Either it is accurate in its history, coming directly from higher beings in position to know, or it is a work of fertile imagination by someone who knew the New Testament by heart and who was also steeped in knowledge of the times when Jesus lived.&quot; He assesses that in his view the narrative is consistent with human authorship.&lt;ref name=&quot;gardner&quot; /&gt;

==Critical views==

===Criticisms of claims as a revelation===
In Paper 92, &quot;The Later Evolution of Religion,&quot; the authors refer to the papers as the fifth revelation of &quot;epochal significance&quot; to humankind, the fourth epochal revelation having been the life of Jesus.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-92-later-evolution-religion#U92_4_5 |title=Paper 92, 92:4.5 |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The claim of revelation in ''The Urantia Book'' has been criticized for various reasons. Skeptics such as [[Martin Gardner]] say it is a product of human efforts rather than a revelation because some of its science is flawed. Because the book does not support certain tenets of Christianity, such as the [[Atonement in Christianity|atonement doctrine]], while at the same time presenting an account of parts of Jesus's life absent in the Bible, others with a Christian viewpoint have argued it cannot be genuine.&lt;ref name=&quot;house&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;larson&quot;&gt;Larson, Bob (2004). ''Larson's Book of World Religions and Alternative Spirituality''. Tyndale House Publishers, Inc. ISBN 0-8423-6417-X&lt;/ref&gt;

Other critics have felt that at over 2,000 pages, nearly twice the length of the [[King James Bible]], it is too long, complex, and bureaucratic.&lt;ref name=&quot;mather&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;gooch&quot; /&gt;

===Criticism of its science===
Skeptics like [[Martin Gardner]] see the science in ''The Urantia Book'' as clear reflections of the views that prevailed at the time the book is said to have originated. The claim by the authors that no unknown scientific discoveries could be imparted is seen as a ruse to allow mistakes to be dismissed later. That presentation of post-1955 scientific knowledge is avoided is taken to be evidence it was written by humans and not by celestial beings with superior knowledge.

Examples of criticisms regarding the science in ''The Urantia Book'' include:&lt;ref name=&quot;gardner&quot; /&gt;
*The described formation of the [[solar system]]&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-57-origin-urantia#U57_5_0 |title=Paper 57, Origin of Monmatia — The Urantia Solar System |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; is consistent with the [[Chamberlin-Moulton planetesimal hypothesis]]. Though popular in the early part of the 20th century, by the early 1940s it was discarded by [[Henry Norris Russell|Henry Russell]]'s argument that it was incompatible with the [[angular momentum]] of planets such as [[Jupiter]]. The currently accepted scientific explanation for the origin of the solar system is based on the [[solar nebula|nebular hypothesis]].
*According to the book's descriptions, the universe is hundreds of billions of years old and periodically expands and contracts — &quot;respires&quot; — at 2-billion-year intervals. Current observations, however, suggest that the true [[age of the universe]] is approximately 13.7 billion years, and there are no cycles of expansion and contraction. The [[big bang]] theory is not supported.
*A fundamental particle called an &quot;ultimaton&quot; is proposed, with an [[electron]] being composed of 100 ultimatons.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-42-energy-mind-and-matter#U42_6_5 |title=Paper 42, 42:6.5 |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; The particle seems to be invented as it is not found in other literature prior to The Urantia Book´s publication and though the concept is not known to be supported by modern [[particle physics]] there is speculation among readers that it is the [[Higgs boson]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rajan-c-mathew.blogspot.com/2012/07/gods-particle-discovery-what-caused-our.html|title=God's Particle Discovery : What Caused Our Scientists To Be So Jubilant?}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Some [[species]] are said to have evolved suddenly from single [[mutation]]s without transitional species.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-58-life-establishment-urantia#U58_6_4 |title=Paper 58, 58:6.4 |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; The theory originated with [[Dutch people|Dutch]] botanist [[Hugo De Vries]], but was short-lived and is not now supported.
*The book says that a solar eclipse was predicted in 1808 by the [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]] prophet [[Tenskwatawa]].&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite wikisource|title=Paper 90, 90:2.9| wslink=The_Urantia_Book/Paper_90#U90_2_9|noicon=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; The eclipse was actually predicted in late April 1806 and occurred on June 16, 1806.&lt;!-- Note to editors: This item in the article has been edited sometimes to include commentary that there were 3 solar eclipses in 1808. It is true there were 3 eclipses that year; however, editors have not realized that these eclipses were only visible in extremely remote areas of the world and could not be seen by Tenskwatawa or his followers. For this and other reasons, these eclipses have not been credibly attributed to Tenskwatawa. For a more complete discussion, please see the discussion page, &quot;Archive 5,&quot; under the section titled &quot;Tenskwatawa eclipse of 1806.&quot; --&gt;
*Controversial statements about human races can be found in the book.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-52-planetary-mortal-epochs#U52_2_11 |title=Paper 52, 52:2.11 |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Supporters state that criticism has arisen mainly due to reading passages out of context. Gardner believes that [[William S. Sadler]], who wrote some [[eugenics|eugenicist]] works, had a hand in editing or writing the book, and that this is how the ideas were included.

While some adherents of the book believe that all of the information in ''The Urantia Book'' including its science is literally true, others accept the book's caveats and do not believe that the science is fully accurate.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-101-real-nature-religion#U101_4_2 |title=Paper 101, 101:4.2 |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Meredith Sprunger, a [[liberal religion|liberal]] believer in ''The Urantia Book'' and retired minister in the [[United Church of Christ]], writes, &quot;research has revealed that virtually all of the scientific material found in ''The Urantia Book'' was the accepted scientific knowledge of the period in which the book was written, was held by some scientists of that time, or was about to be discovered or recognized.&quot; He argues against its literal infallibility and that fundamentalism over the book is &quot;just as untenable as Biblical fundamentalism.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gardner&quot; /&gt;

Other believers maintain that the book has prophetically anticipated scientific advances already. They believe more of its science — if not all of it — will be proven correct in the future. Gardner evaluated many of these claims as of 1995 and found them unconvincing. Some arise because the book is said to have been indited by the revelators by 1935, but then was not published until 1955. Discoveries from science during the two intervening decades can be perceived as prophetic by believers, while skeptics think such facts were added prior to publication. For instance, the catalytic role that [[carbon]] plays in the sun's nuclear reactions is described in the book,&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-41-physical-aspects-local-universe#U41_8_0 |title=Paper 41, Solar-Energy Reactions |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; though [[Hans Bethe]]'s announcement of the discovery was not made until 1938.

Most criticism of ''The Urantia Book'' is based on Martin Gardner's book, ''Urantia: The Great Cult Mystery''. However this book has also been severely criticized. Sandra Collins, SLIS, Univ. of Pittsburg, wrote in ''Library Journal'': &quot;Given the lack of scholarly distance from the subject, the patronizing tone and the gross editorializing, it would be difficult to recommend this book to any library.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Gardner Book Review&quot; in the ''Library Journal'', April 15, 1995 Book Reviews&lt;/ref&gt; Sarah Lewis, of the Univ. of Wales, stated: &quot;Martin Gardner is one of the few people outside the Urantia Foundation who has undertaken research into the movement. His research is worth noting, although his position as a great skeptic does not allow his conclusions much academic credibility.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;lewis&quot; /&gt;

===''The Urantia Book'' and the use of published material===
''The Urantia Book'' states in its Foreword that more than one thousand &quot;human concepts representing the highest and most advanced planetary knowledge of spiritual values and universe meanings&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/foreword#U0_12_10 |title=Foreword 0:12.10 |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; were selected in preparing the papers. The authors say that they were required to &quot;give preference to the highest existing human concepts pertaining to the subjects to be presented&quot; and would &quot;resort to pure revelation only when the concept of presentation has had no adequate previous expression by the human mind.&quot; One of the authors wrote in Part IV: &quot;I well know that those concepts which have had origin in the human mind will prove more acceptable and helpful to all other human minds.&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-121-times-michaels-bestowal#U121_8_12 |title=Paper 121, 121:8.12 |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In recent years, students of the papers have found that the free use of other sources appears to be true.&lt;ref name=&quot;gardner&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;gooch&quot; /&gt; None of the material allegedly used from other sources is directly cited or referenced within the book.

In 1992, a reader of ''The Urantia Book'', Matthew Block, self-published a paper that showed nineteen possible examples of ''The Urantia Book'' utilizing material published earlier. All of the source authors identified in Block's paper were published in English between 1905 and 1943 by U.S. publishers and are typically scholarly or academic works that contain concepts and wording similar to what is found in ''The Urantia Book''. Block has since claimed to have discovered over 125 source books and articles, written by over 90 authors, which were incorporated into the papers.&lt;ref name=&quot;gardner&quot; /&gt;

The use of outside source materials was studied separately by Gardner and Gooch, and they concluded that the book did plagiarize many of the sources noted by Block.

For instance, Gardner and Block note that Paper 85 appears to have been taken from the first eight chapters of ''Origin and Evolution of Religion'' by [[Edward Washburn Hopkins]], published by [[Yale University Press]] in 1923. Each section of the paper corresponds to a chapter in the book, with several passages possibly used as direct material, and further material used in Papers 86-90 and 92. (In addition to the book's &quot;heavy indebtedness to Hopkins,&quot; Gardner discovered that Hopkins was a major reference in an earlier book authored by Sadler, adding to Gardner's view that it is more likely Sadler had a hand in writing or editing ''The Urantia Book'' than that celestial beings wrote it.) Likewise, much of ''The Urantia Book'' material relating to the evolution of mankind appears to have been directly taken from [[Henry Fairfield Osborn]], ''Man Rises to Parnassus: Critical Epochs in the Prehistory of Man'' published by [[Princeton University Press]] in 1928.

In one example cited by Block and confirmed by Gardner, the original author discusses the periodicity of the chemical elements and concludes that the harmony in the construction of the atom suggests some unspecified plan of organization. The authors of ''The Urantia Book'' assert that this harmony is evidence of the [[intelligent design]] of the universe. W. F. G. Swann writes on page 64 of ''The Architecture of the Universe'' (italics indicate edits as compared to ''The Urantia Book'', bolding indicates deletions):
{{quote|Starting from any one '''of them [i.e., chemical''' element'''s],''' ''and'' noting some property such '''as the melting point, for example,''' ''the property would change as we went along the row,'' but ''as we continued it would gradually come back to the condition very similar to that which we started'' ... The eighth element ''was in many respects like'' the first, the ninth '''like''' the second, '''the tenth like the third,''' and so on. Such a ''slate of affairs'' point[s] '''''not only''''' to ''a varied internal structure, but also to a certain harmony in that variation suggestive of some organized plan in building the atom.''}}

Contrast with ''The Urantia Book''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s version:
{{quote|Starting from any one element, ''after'' noting some ''one'' property, such ''a quality will exchange for six consecutive elements,'' but ''on reaching the eighth, it tends to reappear, that is,'' the eighth ''chemically active'' element ''resembles'' the first, the ninth the second, and so on. Such a ''fact of the physical world unmistakably'' points to ''the sevenfold constitution of ancestral energy and is indicative of the fundamental reality of the sevenfold diversity of the creations of time and space.''&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-42-energy-mind-and-matter#U42_9_3 |title=Paper 42, 42:9.3 |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

Block and other believers do not see the use of the source materials as plagiarism, but express a view instead that the quality of the way the material was borrowed is consistent with authorship by celestial beings. Meredith Sprunger, a believer and defender of ''The Urantia Book'', stated in a letter to Gardner that if humans wrote the book, the plagiarisms would indeed be disturbing, but not if it was written by supermortals.&lt;ref name=&quot;gardner&quot; /&gt;

Also Meredith Sprunger wrote:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://urantiabook.org/archive/mjs_archive/mjs_purpose_of_revelation.htm |title=Response to Martin Gardner's Urantia: The Great Cult Mystery |publisher=Urantiabook.org |date= |accessdate=2012-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;As we mentioned earlier, the authors of The Urantia Book clearly state that they have used human sources and why they are using them. The use of these human sources is often handled in such a way as to arrive at a position differing from that of the human author. To accuse the superhuman authors of plagiarism is a bit far fetched, as they are not concealing the use of human sources and they deliberately avoided reference to specific human personalities....&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Adherents==
There is no way to gauge how many adherents there may be as there is no central organization to census. Informal study groups &quot;tend to sprout, ripen, then vanish or splinter&quot; and have not been counted reliably.&lt;ref name=&quot;gooch&quot; /&gt; Readers sometimes join study groups after reading on their own for years or decades, others join them soon after developing an interest in the book, while &quot;for most, worship remains as individual as the act of reading.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gooch&quot; /&gt; Disagreements over the legal ownership of the book, its interpretation, and the reception of new revelations have led to some splintering, though these disagreements appear to have been settled to the satisfaction of most adherents.&lt;ref name=&quot;partridge&quot; /&gt; The movement generally incorporates a nonsectarian view, contending that individuals with different religious backgrounds can receive the book's teachings as an enrichment rather than as a contradiction of their faiths.&lt;ref name=&quot;melton&quot;&gt;Melton, J. Gordon. 1990. ''New Age Encyclopedia (First Edition).'' Gale Research Inc.&lt;/ref&gt;

The small movement inspired by ''The Urantia Book'' has not developed clergy or institutions such as churches, reading rooms, or temples.&lt;ref name=&quot;gooch&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;partridge&quot;&gt;Partridge, Christopher (2004). ''New Religions: A Guide'' (2nd Edition). Oxford University Press. ISBN 0-19-522042-0&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2006, the [[Urantia Foundation]] had one office in Chicago and five people on staff.&lt;ref name=&quot;UFAR2006&quot; /&gt;

Sarah Lewis notes that, &quot;The Urantia Revelation is not securing legitimacy through historically known and accepted means to any great degree, nor is it even using common language that would increase the likelihood of understanding and therefore acceptance. It introduces new concepts and a new language, and this does not make acceptance any easier.&quot; She assesses that the movement is uncontroversial compared to other ones, &quot;lacking the zealous proselytizing found within many other groups,&quot; and that it is therefore likely to remain small and unaffected by opposing views.&lt;ref name=&quot;lewis&quot; /&gt;

Urantia Foundation advocated a &quot;slow growth&quot; policy in the past and had not significantly marketed the book. Sales by Urantia Foundation went from 7,000 in 1990 to 24,700 in 1997, and steadily increased to nearly 38,000 in 2000, an &quot;upturn that seems to represent a genuine trend rather than just some spike on a sales chart,&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gooch&quot; /&gt; however in 2011 the Foundation reported worldwide annual sales of 16,000 copies and over 60,000 downloads from various sites. More than half of the books printed by Urantia Foundation are in languages other than English, particularly Spanish and Portuguese.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=From Urantia Foundation News Online |date=March 2012 |url=http://www.urantia.org/sites/default/files/docs/Foundation_2012_March_Newsletter.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since the book was determined to be in the [[public domain]] in 2001, other organizations, such as The Urantia Book Fellowship under the publishing name Uversa Press, have also published the book. Copies of ''The Urantia Book'' are on the Internet in various formats and it has been adapted to more recent platforms such as the [[Amazon Kindle|Kindle]] and the [[App Store (iOS)|iOS App Store]]. Several audio books of the text are also on the Internet.

The International Urantia Association had twenty-six reader associations worldwide as of 2002, and the Urantia Book Fellowship (formerly the Urantia Brotherhood, founded in 1955 with Urantia Foundation as the original social fraternal organization of believers) claimed roughly twelve hundred official members, with the highest concentrations in the West of the United States and the [[Sun Belt]], especially California, Colorado, Florida, and Texas.&lt;ref name=&quot;gooch&quot; /&gt; It appears an increasing number of people are forming study groups, participating in Internet discussion groups, and hosting or visiting websites about it.&lt;ref name=&quot;gooch&quot; /&gt;

==Teaching Mission==
The Teaching Mission is a group of Urantia [[Mediumship#Channeling|channellers]]. According to [[Richard Landes]], &quot;The [[Urantia Foundation|foundation]] considers them self-deluded, but they have created a schism that continues to disrupt the movement.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Landes|first=Richard|title=Encyclopedia of Millennialism and Millennial Movements|year=2000|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0415922463|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=4eVZaI20_mEC&amp;pg=PA747&amp;lpg=PA747&amp;dq=Urantia+%22Teaching+mission%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=NXxuLAFXzH&amp;sig=2gk_SGqMHgBm1OFR1xEIlWMnOQA&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=vfEgUOTdCcTS0QXFk4HwDg&amp;ved=0CFkQ6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=Urantia%20%22Teaching%20mission%22&amp;f=false|page=747}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Symbols==
[[File:Urantia three-concentric-blue-circles-on-white symbol.svg|left|80px|Paradise Trinity]]
One symbol described in ''The Urantia Book'' consists of three concentric [[Azure (color)|azure]] circles on a white background.&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-53-lucifer-rebellion#U53_5_4 |title=Paper 53, 53:5.4 |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; The circles are said to have symbolized several trinity associations in the history of humankind. The authors of ''The Urantia Book'' indicate its revealed meaning as being &quot;the infinity, eternity, and universality of the Paradise Trinity of divine maintenance and direction.&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;UB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urantia.org/urantia-book-standardized/paper-93-machiventa-melchizedek#U93_3_3 |title=Paper 93, 93:3.3 |publisher=Urantia.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Urantia logo.png|right|81px|Urantia logo]]
Urantia Foundation, the original publisher, placed the concentric circles on the cover of ''The Urantia Book'' and has a United States trademark. The circles are used to indicate other organizations affiliated with the foundation.

The Urantia Association International, one of the main readership organizations in the movement, has been licensed by Urantia Foundation to use the three azure concentric circles on a white background.

[[Image:Wiki-Urantia-BF-logo.jpg|right|80px|Urantia Book Fellowship logo]]
Some other groups use the symbol in various altered forms. The Urantia Book Fellowship, an independent reader organization established in 1955, uses a similar symbol.

==Popular culture==
*[[Stevie Ray Vaughan]] (1954–1990), American blues-rock guitarist: &quot;Stevie often brought along the book of Urantia and read Lindi passages from the strange publication.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Stevie Ray Vaughan: Caught in the Crossfire'' ISBN 978-0-316-16069-8&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Jaco Pastorius]] wrote a song that appears on Weather Report's 'Heavy Weather' named 'Havona'
*In the book ''Six Feet Under: Better Living through Death'', an in-universe companion piece to the television series ''[[Six Feet Under (TV series)|Six Feet Under]]'', ''The Urantia Book'' is highlighted in a past correspondence held by one of the main characters.
*In the 1983 book ''Angels'' by [[Denis Johnson]], one character carries around ''The Urantia Book'' and proselytizes to drug addicts.
*[[Karlheinz Stockhausen]] based his seven-opera cycle ''[[Licht]]'' on the cosmology of ''The Urantia Book''.&lt;ref name=&quot;licht&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
 |title=An Operatic Conundrum Untangled
 |author=Robin William
 |last=Robin |first=William
 |date=May 6, 2011
 |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/05/08/arts/music/sonntag-by-karlheinz-stockhausen-in-cologne.html
 |accessdate=May 29, 2011
 |newspaper=[[The New York Times]]
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References to online text of The Urantia Book==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em|group=&quot;UB&quot;}}

==See also==
{{sister
|project=wikisource
|text=[[wikisource:|Wikisource]] has original text related to: [[s:The Urantia Book|The Urantia Book]]
|position=left
}}
{{sister
|project=wikiquote
|text=[[wikiquote:|Wikiquote]] has a collection of quotations related to: [[q:The Urantia Book|The Urantia Book]]
|position=left
}}
{{sister
|project=commons
|text=[[commons:|Wikimedia Commons]] has media related to: [[commons:Category:Urantia|The Urantia Book]]
|position=left
}}

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
&lt;!--======================== {{No more links}} ============================
    | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. Wikipedia  |
    | is not a collection of links nor should it be used for advertising. |
    |                                                                     |
    |           Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.         |
    | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.  |
    |                                                                     |
    | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or   |
    | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
    | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)   |
    | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.         |
    ======================= {{No more links}} =============================--&gt;
*[http://www.urantia.org/ Urantia Foundation] the original publisher but now one of several
*[http://www.urantia-uai.org/ The Urantia Association International (UAI)]
*[http://www.ubhistory.org/ The Urantia Book Historical Society]
*[http://www.urantiabook.org/ The Urantia Book Fellowship]
*[http://ubwebsites.com/ Urantia Book Related Websites]

{{The Urantia Book}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Urantia Book, The}}
[[Category:1955 books]]
[[Category:New Age texts]]
[[Category:New religious movements]]
[[Category:Urantia Book| ]]
[[Category:UFO religions]]
[[Category:Works of unknown authorship]]
[[Category:Religious cosmology]]

[[de:Urantia]]
[[et:Urantia raamat]]
[[es:Libro de Urantia]]
[[eo:Urantio]]
[[fr:Le Livre d'Urantia]]
[[ko:유란시아]]
[[id:Buku Urantia]]
[[lt:Urantijos knyga]]
[[hu:Az Urantia könyv]]
[[nl:Het Urantia boek]]
[[pl:Księga Urantii]]
[[pt:O Livro de Urântia]]
[[ro:Urantia]]
[[ru:Книга Урантии]]
[[fi:Urantia-kirja]]</text>
      <sha1>fpx3928xwjsrwj52i9ln8d45f0qmunv</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
