<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Thealogy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>31444</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516191657</id>
      <parentid>515910649</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-05T18:39:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Dating maintenance tags: {{By whom?}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14834">{{Multiple issues|essay-like =July 2009|refimprove =April 2007|more footnotes = March 2011|copy edit = April 2012}}
{{Feminism sidebar}}

'''Thealogy''', is a relatively recent term and describes an emerging field of academic interdisciplinary study whose origin and initial use is open to debate.  Often attributed to a [[neologism]] coined by [[Isaac Bonewits]] in 1974, Patricia 'Iolana traces the early use of the term to 1976 crediting both Bonewits and [[Valerie Saiving]] in its initial use.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last= 'Iolana|first= Patricia|title= Testing the Boundaries: Self, Faith, Interpretation and Changing Trends in Religious Studies|year= 2011|publisher= Cambridge Scholars Publishing|location= Newcastle upon Tyne}}&lt;/ref&gt;  While the definition and scope of thealogy is currently being defined by the key scholars in the field, thealogy is generally understood as a [[discourse]] that reflects upon the meaning of [[Goddess]] and Her relationship to life forms. Situated in the field of theology and religious studies, it is seen as a complementary and relational field to that of [[theology]].  It is a discourse that critically engages the beliefs, wisdom, practices, questions, and values of the Goddess community, both past and present. The term suggests a [[feminist]] approach to [[theism]] and the context of [[Gender of God|God and gender]] within [[Paganism]], [[Neopaganism]], [[Goddess]] Spirituality and various nature-based religions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last= 'Iolana &amp; Hope|title= Goddess Thealogy: An International Journal for the Study of the Divine Feminine,  Vol. 1 No. 1 December|year= 2011|publisher= Institute for Thealogy and Deasophy|location= electronic}}  http://www.thealogyanddeasophy.org/GoddessThealogy_1_1_2012.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; 

The term, thealogy, increasingly appeared in feminist literature associated with the Neopagan Goddess movement during the 1980s to 1990s.  Naomi Goldenberg used the term in 1979.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last= Goldenberg|first= Naomi|title= Changing of the gods: Feminism and the end of traditional religions|year= 1979|publisher= Beacon Press|location= Boston}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Carol P. Christ]] used the term in 1987, and further defined thealogy in her 2002 essay, &quot;Feminist theology as post-traditional thealogy,&quot; as &quot;the reflection on the meaning of the Goddess&quot; (p79).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last= Christ|first= Carol P|title= Laughter of Aphrodite: Reflections on a Journey to the Goddess |year= 1987|publisher= Harper &amp; Row |location= SanFrancisco}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last= Christ|first= Carol P|title= The Cambridge Companion to Feminist Theology|year= 2002|publisher= Cambridge University Press|location= Cambridge}}&lt;/ref&gt; In her 1989 essay &quot;On Mirrors, Mists and Murmurs: Toward an Asian American Thealogy,&quot; Rita Nakashima Brock defined thealogy as &quot;the work of women reflecting on their experiences of and beliefs about divine reality&quot; (p236).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last= Brock|first= Rita Nakashima|title= Weaving the Visions: New Patterns in Feminist Spirituality, Eds Judith Plaskow and Carol P Christ |year= 1989|publisher= HarperSanFrancisco|location= SanFrancisco}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Contemporary Thealogians include [[Carol P. Christ]], Melissa Raphael, Asphodel Long, Beverly Clack, Charlotte Caron, Naomi Goldenberg, Paul Reid-Bowen, Rita Nakashima Brock, and Patricia 'Iolana.

Thealogy can be described as religiously [[Religious pluralism|pluralistic]], as thealogians come from various religious backgrounds that are often hybrid in nature. In addition to Pagans, Neopagans, and Goddess-centred faith traditions, they are also [[Christian]], [[Judaism|Jewish]], [[Buddhism|Buddhist]], [[Muslim]], [[Quakers]], etc. or define themselves as Spiritual Feminists. As such, the term ''thealogy'' has also been used by feminists within mainstream [[Monotheism|monotheistic]] religions describe in more detail the feminine aspect of a monotheistic deity or trinity, such as God/dess Herself, or the [[Heavenly Mother (Latter Day Saints)|Heavenly Mother]] of the [[Latter Day Saint movement]].

==Terminology==
{{Main|Feminist theology}}
In &quot;The Druid Chronicles (Evolved)&quot;, privately published in 1976, Isaac Bonewits used &quot;thealogian&quot; to refer to [[Wicca]]n author [[Aidan Kelly]], aka &quot;C. Taliesin Edwards&quot;.  &quot;The Druid Chronicles (Evolved)&quot; represented a three-year project starting in 1974 and finished (published) in 1976. The article referred to within &quot;The Druid Chronicles (Evolved)&quot; is dated to the summer of 1976. Moreover, this is almost certainly not the first usage; the context of &quot;thealogian&quot; appears in a work by C. Taliesin Edwards, &quot;Essays towards a Meta''thealogy'' of the Goddess&quot; [stress added].&lt;ref&gt;Paganism: An Overview, p. 91 http://www.pagancouncil.co.za/files/OVERVIEW.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; There is, however, a possibility that Bonewits altered the name of the work to fit with his terminology. Kelley himself had related to Bonewits that he couldn't remember which of the two of them said &quot;thealogy&quot; to the other first.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}} 

In the 1979 &quot;The Changing of the Gods,&quot; Naomi Goldenberg introduces the term as a future possibility with respect to a distinct discourse, highlighting the masculine nature of theology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last= Goldenberg|first= Naomi|title= Changing of the gods: Feminism and the end of traditional religions|year= 1979|publisher= Beacon Press|location= Boston}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Also in 1979, in the first revised edition of &quot;Real Magic&quot;, Bonewits defined &quot;thealogy&quot; in his Glossary as &quot;Intellectual speculations concerning the nature of the Goddess and Her relations to the world in general and humans in particular; rational explanations of religious doctrines, practices and beliefs, which may or may not bear any connection to any religion as actually conceived and practiced by the majority of its members.&quot; Also in the same glossary, he defined &quot;theology&quot; with nearly identical words, changing the feminine pronouns with masculine pronouns appropriately.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last= Bonewits|first= Isaac|title= Real Magic PEI Bonewits, Ed.|year= 1989 (reprint)|publisher= Weiser Books|location= York Beach, ME}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 1989 Ursula King notes thealogy's growing usage as a fundamental departure from traditional male-oriented theology, characterized by its privileging of symbols over rational explanation. She chronicles that:

:''most writing on the Goddess, when not historical, is either inspirational or devotional, and a systematically ordered body of thought, even with reference to symbols, is only slowly coming into existence''(King 1989, pp. 126-127).

[[Carol P. Christ|Carol Christ]] used the term more substantially in &quot;Laughter of Aphrodite&quot; (1987), acknowledging that those who create thealogy cannot avoid being influenced by the categories and questions posed in Christian and Jewish theologies (Christ 1987, p. xii). In &quot;Rebirth of the Goddess&quot;, Christ establishes some guidelines for method, suggesting that thealogy begins rooted in women's experience (Christ 1997, pp.&amp;nbsp;31–49). Christ's text &quot;Rebirth of the Goddess&quot; sets out to develop the first systematic thealogy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last= Christ|first= Carol P|title= Rebirth of the Goddess: Finding Meaning in Feminist Spirituality |year= 1997|publisher= Routledge|location= New York}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 1993, Charlotte Caron's definition of thealogy as &quot;reflection on the divine in feminine and feminist terms&quot; appeared in &quot;To Make and Make Again&quot; (Russell &amp; Clarkson 1996). By this time, the concept had gained considerable status among Goddess adherents. Mainstream religious studies scholars and theologians have contested the legitimacy of such a discourse.{{Who|date=March 2011}}

In 2000, Melissa Raphael wrote the text &quot;Introducing Thealogy: Discourse on the Goddess&quot;. Written for an academic audience, it purports to introduce the main elements of thealogy within the context of Goddess feminism. She situates thealogy as a discourse that can be engaged with by Goddess feminists—those who are feminist adherents of the Goddess who may have left their church, synagogue, or mosque, or those who may still belong to their originally established religion (Melissa Raphael 2000, p.&amp;nbsp;16)

In 2007, Paul Reid-Bowen wrote the text &quot;Goddess as Nature: Towards a Philosophical Thealogy&quot;, which can be regarded as another systematic approach to thealogy, but which integrates philosophical discourse.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last= Reid-Bowen|first= Paul|title= Goddess as Nature: Towards a Philosophical Thealogy|year= 2007|publisher= Ashgate|location= Aldershot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010, Angela Hope co-founded the &quot;Institute for Thealogy &amp; Deasophy&quot; with Patricia 'Iolana.&lt;ref&gt;http://thealogyanddeasophy.org/&lt;/ref&gt;  

In the past decade, other thealogians like Patricia 'Iolana and D'vorah Grenn have generated discourses that bridge thealogy with other academic disciplines. 'Iolana's [[Carl Jung|Jungian]] thealogy bridges analytical psychology with thealogy, and Grenn's metaformic thealogy is a bridge between matriarchal studies and thealogy.

==Interpretations==
{{prose|section|date=April 2011}}
* Bonewits, by implication, sees thealogy as the Goddess-focused variant of a thealogy/polytheology cluster viewable as subsets of the broader field of the [[philosophy of religion]].
* Christ and Reid-Bowen focus thealogy specifically on post-Christian [[Goddess]]-spirituality and as a [[discourse]] systematically conceivable with specific thealogical methods.
* Caron defines a broader field of a female worldview of the [[sacred]] that also incorporates non-feminist approaches to thealogy.
* Raphael focuses on thealogy as an embodied discourse that may or may not be approached systematically; she situates thealogy closely with the views and beliefs held by Goddess feminists.
* Goldenberg's neologism as a political stance that marks the [[androcentrism]] of historical [[theology]] that summons her reader to think about the possibilities of a post-patriarchal discourse about the Divine.{{Clarify|date=May 2011}}
* Hope's rendering situates thealogy as rooted in feminist [[epistemology]] and [[ontology]]. Similar to Raphael, she locates thealogy as a discourse involving more than just Neopagans, and including those who have not left their established religion.
* 'Iolana focuses on depth thealogy, which combines the [[depth psychology]] of [[Carl G. Jung]] with thealogy to provide a [[psychodynamic]] understanding of personal thealogical religious experience and [[Praxeology|praxis]].

Thealogy is referred to{{by whom?|date=October 2012}} as its own unique discourse separate from theology, rather than a sub-field within theology. In line with Christ and Reid-Bowen, thealogy can be conceived of in a systematic fashion with specific methods, while deasophy (a concept coined by [[Max Dashu]]) which addresses the wisdom of the Goddess tradition, may not necessarily be systematically ordered.

==See also==
*[[Gender and religion|God and gender]]
*[[Goddess movement]]
*[[Goddess movement|Goddess worship]]
*[[Matriarchal religion]]
*[[Matriarchy]]
*[[Mother goddess]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*[http://books.google.com/books?id=TMfhaRCJ79kC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;hl=pt-BR Introducing thealogy: discourse on the goddess, Melissa Raphael]
*Bonewits, Isaac (1976) &quot;The Second Epistle of Isaac&quot; in &quot;the Druid Chronicles (Evolved)&quot; Berkeley Drunemeton Press.
*Bonewits, Isaac (1989) Real Magic.  PEI Bonewits, Ed. York Beach, ME: Weiser Books.
*Caron, Charlotte (1993) To Make and Make Again: Feminist Ritual Thealogy. New York: Crossroad.
*Christ, Carol P. (1997) Rebirth of the Goddess: Finding Meaning in Feminist Spirituality. New York: Routledge
*Christ, Carol P. (2003) She Who Changes: Re-Imagining the Divine in the World. New York: Palgrave Macmillan.
*Clack, Beverly (1999) 'Thealogy and Theology: Mutually Exclusive or Creatively Independent' from Feminist Theology: The Journal of the Britain and Ireland School of Feminist Theology No. 21, May 1999 Lisa Isherwood, et al. (eds) (Sheffield: Sheffield Academic Press) p.&amp;nbsp;21-38.
*Clack, Beverly (1995) ‘The Denial of Dualism: Thealogical Reflections on the Sexual and the Spiritual’ from Feminist Theology: The Journal of the Britain and Ireland School of Feminist Theology No. 10, September 1995 Lisa Isherwood, et al. Eds. Sheffield: Sheffield Academic Press p.&amp;nbsp;102-115.
*Eller, Cynthia (1995 [1993]) Living in the Lap of the Goddess: The Feminist Spirituality Movement in America. Boston: Beacon Press.
*Goldenberg, Naomi (1979) The Changing of the Gods. [[Beacon Press]], ISBN 0-8070-1111-8
*Goldenberg, Naomi (1990) Returning Words to Flesh: Feminism, Psychoanalysis, and the Resurrection of the Body. Boston: Beacon Press.
*Grenn, D'vorah Grenn (2005)&quot;Connecting with Deity through a Metaformic Thealogy&quot; Metaformia: A Journal of Menstruation and Culture.
*Hope, Angela (2010) &quot;What is Goddess Thealogy &amp; Deasophy: Toward a Definition&quot; http://www.thealogyanddeasophy.org/defining.html
*‘Iolana, Patricia (2012) ‘The Sublime and the Profane: A Thealogical Account of Psychometric Experiences within a Sacred Space’ in Paranthropology: Journal of Anthropological Approaches to the Paranormal, Vol. 3 No. 1, Jack Hunter, Ed., January 2012, 4-8, print and electronic.  http://www.magcloud.com/browse/issue/302101
*‘Iolana, Patricia (2012) ‘Divine Immanence: A Psychodynamic Study in Women’s Experience of Goddess’ in Claremont Journal of Religion, Kile Jones, Ed.,  January 2012, 86-107, electronic.  http://claremontjournal.com/
*'Iolana, Patricia and Angela Hope (2011) &quot;Thealogy: Mapping a Fluid and Expanding Field&quot; in Goddess Thealogy: An International Journal for the Study of the Divine Feminine, p 9-22.  http://www.thealogyanddeasophy.org/defining.html
*King, Ursula (1989) Women and Spirituality. Macmillan.
*Miller, David L. (1974) The New Polytheism: Rebirth of the Gods and Goddesses. New York: Harper &amp; Row.
*Raphael, Melissa (1996) Thealogy and Embodiment: The Post-Patriarchal Reconstruction of Female Sacrality. Sheffield: Sheffield Academic Press.
*Raphael, Melissa (1997) ‘Thealogy, Redemption and the Call of the Wild’ from Feminist Theology: The Journal of the Britain and Ireland School of Feminist Theology No. 15, May 1997 Lisa Isherwood, et al. (eds) (Sheffield: Sheffield Academic Press) p.&amp;nbsp;55-72.
*Raphael, Melissa (1999) &quot;Introducing Thealogy: Discourse on the Goddess&quot; Sheffield:Sheffield Academic Press.
*[[Letty M. Russell|Russell, Letty M.]]  &amp; J Shannon Clarkson (1996) &quot;Dictionary of Feminist Theologies&quot; Mowbray.
*York, Michael (2003) Pagan Theology: Paganism as a World Religion.  New York: New York University Press.

{{DEFAULTSORT:THEALOGY}}
[[Category:Feminist theology]]
[[Category:Feminist spirituality]]
[[Category:Mother goddesses]]
[[Category:Matriarchy]]

[[pt:Tealogia]]</text>
      <sha1>lejb84bdtgzh2yfo9umc6cpje9b5fse</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
