<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Theosophy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>31480</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516140752</id>
      <parentid>514375203</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-05T12:36:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>24.123.143.74</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Theosophy in early modern Europe beginning in the 1500s */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29520">{{Theosophy}}
{{For|The Theosophical Society|Theosophical Society}}

'''Theosophy''' (from Greek θεοσοφία ''theosophia'', from θεός ''theos'', divine + σοφία ''sophia'', wisdom; literally &quot;divine wisdom&quot;), refers to systems of [[esoterism|esoteric]] philosophy concerning, or investigation seeking direct knowledge of, presumed mysteries of being and nature, particularly concerning the nature of [[divinity]].

Theosophy is considered a part of the broader field of [[esotericism]], referring to hidden knowledge or wisdom that offers the individual enlightenment and salvation. The word esoteric dates back to the 2nd century CE.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hanegraaff|2006}} p. ''336'' &lt;/ref&gt; The theosophist seeks to understand the mysteries of the universe and the bonds that unite the universe, humanity and the divine. The goal of theosophy is to explore the origin of divinity and humanity, and the end of world, life and humanity. From investigation of those topics theosophists try to discover a coherent description of the purpose and origin of the universe.

==Etymology==
The word ''theosophia'' appeared in both Greek and Latin in the works of early church fathers as a synonym for “[[theology]]”.&lt;ref name = &quot;Lobel&quot;&gt;{{cite book
  | last = Lobel 
  | first = Diane
  | title = A Sufi-Jewish Dialogue: Philosophy and Mysticism in Baḥya Ibn Paqūda's Duties of the Heart 
  | publisher = University of Pennsylvania Press
  | date = 2007
  | location = Philadelphia, PN 
  | page = 27 
  | url = http://books.google.ca/books?id=Q_UGgSxZlw4C&amp;pg=PA27&amp;dq=%22it+appears+in+works+of+both+greek+and+latin+church+fathers+as+a+synonym+for+theology%22%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=nCe3T7DHEKPs6gHz0ei9Cg&amp;ved=0CDUQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22it%20appears%20in%20works%20of%20both%20greek%20and%20latin%20church%20fathers%20as%20a%20synonym%20for%20theology%22%22&amp;f=false
  | isbn = 978-0-8122-3953-9
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The theosophoi are “those who know divine matters.” During the [[Renaissance]], use of the term diverged to refer to [[gnostic]] knowledge that offers the individual enlightenment and salvation through a knowledge of the bonds that are believed to unite her or him to the world of divine or intermediary spirits. By the 16th century the word theosophy was being used in at least one of its current meanings.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Faivre|1987}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
===Antiquity and Medieval ending c. 1450CE ===
The term theosophy was used as a synonym for theology as early as the 3rd century CE&lt;ref name = &quot;Lobel&quot; /&gt; 

Hellenistic Alexandrian culture expressed religion through a syncretism that included influences from Egypt, Chaldea, Greece etc. It became a &quot;philosophizing and systematizing&quot; culture containing mythology, theosophy and gnosis of the East. &lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Goodrick-Clarke|2008}}p. 16&lt;/ref&gt; 

The 12th c. philosopher [[Al-Shahrastānī]] (d. 548AH / 1153CE) explored theosophy in the context of Islamic thought. In the 13th century a clear distinction was made between classical philosophers, modern (to the people then) philosophers, theosophers, and theologians in the work ''Summa philosophiae'' attributed to [[Robert Grosseteste]]. In Summa theosophists were described as authors inspired by holy books while theologians were described as persons whose task was to teach theosophy. During that time the term theosopher was applied retroactively to include earlier people including [[Pseudo-Dionysius the Areopagite]], [[Ambrose]], [[Jerome]], [[Augustine of Hippo|Augustine]], and [[Origen]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Faivre|1987}} p. 465&lt;/ref&gt;

===Theosophy in early modern Europe beginning in the 1500s===
Modern theosophy arose in Germany in the 16th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Faivre|first=Antoine|title=Access to Western Esotericism|year=1994|publisher=State University of New York Press|isbn=0791421783|pages=8}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In the 16th century Johannes Arboreus’ Theosophia (volumes published 1540-1553) provided a lengthy exposition that included no mention of esotericism.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Faivre|1987}} p. 465&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast fellow Germans [[Paracelsus]] (1493-1541), Aegidius Gutmann (1490-1584), [[Valentin Weigel]] (1533-1588), [[Heinrich Khunrath]] (1560-1605), [[Johann Arndt]] (1555-1621), and Caspar Schwenckfeld (1490-1584) demonstrated an interest in theosophy. 

The 17th century philosopher and self-identified theosophist [[Jakob Boehme]] (1575-1624) produced a complete explanation of theosophy that included esotericism. Boehme’s system of philosophical speculation bases knowledge of nature upon knowledge of the divine nature. During that time the Aristotelian method had lost favor among intellectuals. Boehme presented his system as an alternative to the Aristotelian method which he believed could provide a more profound knowledge and more control of nature than the Aristotelian method did.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Faivre|1987}} p. 465 &amp; 467&lt;/ref&gt;

Other notable contributors to the theosophical literature of the 16th and 17th centuries hailed from Holland, England, and France. They included both theosophists and historians and theologians with a strong interest in theosophy. This group includes [[Jan Baptist van Helmont]] (1618-1699), [[Robert Fludd]] (1574-1637), [[John Pordage]] (1608-1681), [[Jane Leade]] (1623-1704), [[Henry More]] (1614-1687), [[Pierre Poiret]] (1646-1719), and [[Antoinette Bourignon]] (1616-1680).

Theosophists of this period often inquired into nature using a method of interpretation founded upon a specific myth or revelation, applying [[active imagination]] in order to draw forth symbolic meanings and further their pursuit of knowledge toward a complete understanding of these mysteries.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|OED|1989|}} v. XVII, p. 903.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Faivre|1987}} v. XIV &lt;/ref&gt;

====Enlightenment theosophy, 1650-1775====
In the 18th century, the word theosophy came into widespread use in philosophy. [[Johann Jakob Brucker]](1696-1770) included a long chapter on theosophy in his monumental work Historia critica philosophia (1741). He included all the theosophists in what was then a standard reference in the history of philosophy. German philosophers produced major works of theosophy during this period: Theophilosophia theoritica et practica (1710) by Samuel Richter (alias Sincerus Renatus) and Opus magocabalsticum et theosophicum (1721) by [[Georg von Welling]] (alias Salwigt, 1655-1727). Other notable theosophists of the period include [[Johann George Gichtel]] (1638-1710), [[Gottfried Arnold]] (1666-1714), [[Friedrich Christoph Oetinger]] (1702-1782), [[William Law]] (1686-1761), and [[Dionysius Andreas Freher]] (1649-1728). By the 18th century the word theosophy was often used in conjunction with panosophy, i.e., a knowledge of divine things that is acquired by deciphering the supposed hieroglyphics of the concrete universe. The term theosophy is more properly reserved for the reverse process of contemplating the divine in order to discover the content of the concrete universe.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Faivre|1987}} p. 467&lt;/ref&gt;

In France, [[Louis Claude de Saint-Martin]] (1743-1803) and Jean-Philippe Dutoit-Membrini (alias Keleph Ben Nathan, 1721-1793) contributed to a resurgence of theosophy in the late 18th century. Other theosophical thinkers of this period include [[Karl von Eckartshausen]] (1752-1803), Johann Heinrich Jung-Stilling (1740-1817), Frederic-Rodolphe Salzmann (1749-1821), Michael Hahn (1758-1819), and [[Franz von Baader]] (1765-1841). Denis Diderot gave the word theosophie a permanent place in the French language by including it in an article in his Encyclopedie, published during the French Enlightenment.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Faivre|1987}} p. 466&lt;/ref&gt;

====The nineteenth century====
The [[Parliament of the World's Religions#1893 Parliament| Parliament of the World's Religions]] in 1893 marked the first formal gathering of representatives of Eastern and Western spiritual traditions. Today it is recognized as the occasion of the birth of formal interreligious dialogue worldwide.{{fact|date=July 2012}}

During the late 19th century theosophical initiate societies emerged. Some of these reflected a fluid boundary between theosophy and occultism. In 1875 [[Helena Blavatsky]] (1831-1891) and others founded one of these theosophical initiate societies, The [[Theosophical Society]], an organization related to earlier theosophical ideas which also departed from them significantly.&lt;ref name = &quot;Martin&quot;&gt;{{cite book
  | last1 =  Martin
  | first1 = Walter R.
  | last2 =  Zacharias
  | first2 = Ravi K., ed
  | authorlink1 = Walter Ralston Martin
  | authorlink2 = Ravi Zacharias
  | coauthors = 
  | title = The kingdom of the cults
  | publisher = Bethany House, Baker Publishing Group
  | edition = revised
  | date = 2003 ), (1965,1977,1985,1997
  | location = Bloomington, Minnesota
  | pages = 265-281 (digital) 
  | url = http://books.google.ca/books?id=Yra4KhlMBYQC&amp;pg=PA265&amp;dq=%22The+Theosophical+Society+%28Gnosticism%29+Theosophy+as+a+cult+system+derives+its+name+from+the+Greek+term+theosophia,+meaning+literally,+divine+wisdom.%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=ieadT9zLDauI6AHq3qShDw&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22The%20Theosophical%20Society%20%28Gnosticism%29%20Theosophy%20as%20a%20cult%20system%20derives%20its%20name%20from%20the%20Greek%20term%20theosophia%2C%20meaning%20literally%2C%20divine%20wisdom.%22&amp;f=false
  | isbn = 978-0-7642-2821-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Meanwhile outside of the initiate societies others such as the Martinist Order founded by Papus in 1891 followed a prior theosophical current which was closely linked to the Judeo-Christian-Islamic tradition and Western esotericism. Theosophists outside of the initiate societies included people such as [[Vladimir Solovyov (philosopher)|Vladimir Solovyov]] (1853-1900). According to the Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy, Solovyov thought, “Although empiricism and rationalism (= idealism) rest on false principles, their respective objective contents, external experience, qua the foundation of natural science, and logical thought, qua the foundation of pure philosophy, are to be synthesized or encompassed along with mystical knowledge in 'integral knowledge,' what Solovyov terms 'theosophy.'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iep.utm.edu/solovyov Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy, Vladimir Solovyov]&lt;/ref&gt;

====The twentieth century to present====
Several organizations developed from the popularization of Blavatsky's ideas and are considered new religious movements.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Santucci|2004}} p. 259 &lt;/ref&gt; Theosophical Society lodges also continue to exist in many places. [[Anthroposophy]] was founded by [[Rudolf Steiner]] (1861-1925) as a schism of the Theosophical Society.&lt;ref name = &quot;Greer&quot; &gt;{{Citation
  | last = Greer 
  | first = John Michael
  | title = The New Encyclopedia of the Occult 
  | place = St. Paul, MN 
  | publisher = Llewellyn Publications
  | year = 2004 
  | edition = 1st
  | chapter = Anthroposophical Society entry
  | chapterurl = http://books.google.ca/books?id=xAmMNnJlfnoC&amp;pg=PA25&amp;dq=%22Anthroposophical+Society.+The+organization+created+by+Austrian+occultist+rudolf+Steiner%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=_Yy3T8i8EI7qgQeT-8C4Cg&amp;ved=0CDkQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Anthroposophical%20Society.%20The%20organization%20created%20by%20Austrian%20occultist%20rudolf%20Steiner%22&amp;f=false
  | page = 25
  | url = http://books.google.ca/books?id=xAmMNnJlfnoC
  | isbn = 1-56718-336-0 
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Theosophical concepts can be seen in the work of [[Sergei Bulgakov]] (1877-1945), [[Nikolai Berdyaev]] (1874-1945), Leopold Ziegler (1881-1958), [[Valentin Tomberg]] (1901-1973), Auguste-Edouard Chauvet (1885-1955), [[Wassily Kandinsky]] (1866-1944), [[Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan]] (1888-1975) and [[Henry Corbin]] (1903-1978).&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Faivre|2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Common characteristics==
The use of the term theosophy has changed over time. As such, the use of the term in antiquity, or even using a strictly etymological definition, is not common in the academy. Theosophy actually designates a specific flow of thought, current, stream or tradition within the modern study of esotericism. Thus it follows the path starting from the more modern period of the 15th century onward (e.g. neo-Alexandrian, hermeticism, Christian Kaballah, Rosicrucianism, Alchemy etc.).  The usage here is not intended to be inclusive of the concept as used in The Theosophical Society.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Faivre|2006}} p. ''259'' &lt;/ref&gt;  

Theosophists engage in analysis of the universe, humanity, divinity, and the reciprocal effects of each on the other. The starting point for theosophists may be knowledge of external things in the world or inner experiences and the aim of the theosophist is to discover deeper meanings in the natural or divine realm. [[Antoine Faivre]] notes, “the theosophist dedicates his energy to inventing (in the word’s original sense of ‘discovering’) the articulation of all things visible and invisible, by examining both divinity and nature in the smallest detail.”&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Faivre|1987}}&lt;/ref&gt; The knowledge that is acquired through meditation is believed to change the being of the meditator.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | last = Williamson
  | first = Lola
  | title = Transcendent in America: Hindu-Inspired Meditation Movements (HIMM) as New Religion
  | publisher = New York University Press 
  | date = 2010
  | location = New York, NY
  | page = 31 
  | url = http://books.google.ca/books?id=OxD1SYaelLAC&amp;pg=PA31&amp;dq=theosophy,+%22until+one+attains+liberation%22,+%22through+meditative+practices%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=BTe3T8unIJKcgQeA87TWCg&amp;ved=0CDsQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=theosophy%2C%20%22until%20one%20attains%20liberation%22%2C%20%22through%20meditative%20practices%22&amp;f=false 
  | isbn = 978-0-8147-9449-4
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Antoine Faivre]] successfully created a taxonomy approach as a means to comparing the various traditions.  He proceeded by taking the concordance of neoplatonism, Hermeticism, Kaballah, astrology, alchemy, magic etc. and deduced six fundamental characteristics of esoteric spirituality. &lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Goodick-Clarke|2008}} p. ''9-10'' &lt;/ref&gt; He discovered that the first four characteristics of esotericism are always present, while the latter two are sometimes present.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hanegraaff|2006}} p. ''340'' &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Goodick-Clarke|2008}} p. ''6-10'' &lt;/ref&gt;  Along with these six characteristics of esotericism, he identified three characteristics of theosophy.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Faivre|2000}} p. 7, 8 &lt;/ref&gt; 

''[[Esotericism]]'':
#Correspondence: Everything in Nature is a sign. The signs of Nature can be read. The microcosm and macrocosm interplay. Synchronicity exists, and can be found as signs from Nature and may lead to the understanding of the divine.
# Nature is Alive: It is not just correlations between pieces of matter. It is a living entity that will, and does, surge and evolve through its expanding self, replete with dynamic flows of energy and light.
#Imagination and mediations: Imaginations as a power that provides access to worlds and levels of reality intermediary between the material world and the divine.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hanegraaff|2006}} p. ''340'' &lt;/ref&gt;
#Experience of Transmutation: The Gnosis and illuminations of self and mind performing a transmutation of consciousness. The birth of an awareness, a second new life becomes born.
#Practice of Concordance: Primordial Tradition. Studying traditions, religions etc. seeking the common one Root from which all esoteric knowledge grows.
#Transmission: Master-Disciple, master-Initiate, initiation into the Occult.

The three characteristics of theosophy are listed below.

''Theosophy'':
#Divine/Human/Nature Triangle: The inspired analysis which circles through these three angles. The intradivine within; the origin, death and placement of the human relating to Divinity and Nature; Nature as alive, the external, intellectual and material. All three complex correlations synthesize via the intellect and imaginative processes of Mind.   
#Primacy of the Mythic: The creative Imagination, an external world of symbols, glyphs, myths, synchronicities and the myriad, along with image, all as a universal reality for the interplay conjoined by creative mind.
#Access to Supreme Worlds: The awakening within, inherently possessing the faculty to directly connect to the Divine world(s). The existence of a special human ability to create this connection. The ability to connect and explore all levels of reality; co-penetrate the human with the divine; to bond to all reality and experience a unique inner awakening.

==Blavatskyan Theosophy and the Theosophical Society==
In 1875 [[Helena Blavatsky]], [[Henry Steel Olcott]], and [[William Quan Judge]] co-founded The [[Theosophical Society]]. Blavatsky combined Eastern religious traditions with Western esoteric teachings to create a synthesis she called the ''Perennial Religion''. She developed this in in ''Isis Unveiled'' (1877) and ''The Secret Doctrine'' (1888), her major works and exposition of her Theosophy. 

Eventually the Theosophical Society became virtually synonymous with Theosophy in the vernacular sense. There are many differences between traditional Western theosophy and the Theosophical movement begun by Helena Blavatsky, though the differences &quot;are not important enough to cause an insurmountable barrier.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Faivre|2000}} p. 5. Faivre quotes and agrees with Jean-Louis Siémons.&lt;/ref&gt; When referring to the ideas related to Blavatsky and the Theosophical Society, the word &quot;Theosophy&quot; is capitalized; otherwise it is not. 

===Overview of Blavatsky's teachings===
The three fundamental propositions expounded in ''The Secret Doctrine'' are:&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Sellon|1987}} v. II, p. 245-246 &lt;/ref&gt;
#That there is an omnipresent, eternal, boundless, and immutable reality of which spirit and matter are complementary aspects.
#That there is a universal law of periodicity or evolution through cyclic change.
#That all souls are identical with the universal oversoul which is itself an aspect of the unknown reality.

Helena Blavatsky taught that Theosophy is neither revelation nor speculation.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Blavatsky|1889}} p. 3-4, 7-12, 87&lt;/ref&gt; Blavatsky stated that Theosophy was an attempt at a gradual, faithful reintroduction of a hitherto hidden science called The [[Occult science]] in Theosophical literature. According to Blavatsky Occult science provides a description of reality not only at a physical level but also on a metaphysical one. Blavatsky said [[Occult science]] had been preserved and practiced throughout history by carefully selected and trained individuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Blavatsky|1888}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The Theosophical Society believes its precepts and doctrinal foundation will be verified when a Theosophist follows prescribed disciplines to develop metaphysical means of knowledge that transcend the limitations of the senses.{{Citation needed|reason=reliable source needed for the whole sentence|date=May 2012}}

===Criticisms of Helena Blavatsky and The Theosophical Society===
====Helena Blavatsky's skeptics====
[[René Guénon]] wrote a detailed critique of Theosophy titled ''Theosophism: history of a pseudo-religion'' (1921). In the book Guenon claimed that Blavatsky had acquired all her knowledge naturally from other books not from any supernatural masters. Guenon points out that Blavatsky spent a long time visiting a library at New York where she had easy access to the works of [[Jacob Boehme]], [[Eliphas Levi]], the [[Kabbalah|Kabbala]] and other [[Hermeticism|Hermetic]] treatises. Guenon also wrote that Blavatsky had borrowed passages taken from a translation of extracts from the ''Kanjur'' and ''Tanjur'' published in 1836 in the twentieth volume of the ''Asiatic Researchers of Calcutta'' by [[Sándor Kőrösi Csoma]] an eccentric orientalist.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | first1=René |last1= Guénon |translator= Alvin Moore, Jr. and Cecil Bethell | title = Theosophy: history of a pseudo-religion | year=2004 | pages= 82–89 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[K. Paul Johnson]] suggests in his book ''The Masters Revealed: Madam Blavatsky and Myth of the Great White Brotherhood'' that the Masters that Madam Blavatsky claimed she had personally met are idealizations of certain people she had met during her lifetime.&lt;ref&gt;Johnson, K. Paul. ''The Masters Revealed: Madam Blavatsky and Myth of the Great White Brotherhood'', Albany, New York: State University of New York Press, 1994.&lt;/ref&gt;

Also see the article “Talking to the Dead and Other Amusements” by Paul Zweig ''New York Times'' October 5, 1980, which maintains that Madame Blavatsky's revelations were fraudulent.&lt;ref&gt;Zweig, Paul. “Talking to the Dead and Other Amusements”, ''The New York Times'', 5 October 1980.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Robert Todd Carroll]] in his book ''The skeptic's dictionary'' (2003) wrote that Blavatsky used trickery into deceiving others into thinking she had paranormal powers. Carroll wrote that Blavatsky had faked a materialization of a tea cup and saucer as well as written the messages from her masters herself.&lt;ref&gt;Carroll, Robert Todd. ''The skeptic's dictionary'', 2003, p. 376.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Blavatsky's Theosophy connected to antisemitism, racism====
[[Jackson Spielvogel]] and David Redles of the Simon Wiesenthal Center's Museum of Tolerance analyze  Blavatsky's racial ideas in her book ''Secret Doctrine''. According to Spielvogel and Redles Blavatsky labeled some races superior and others inferior. They clarify that Blavatsky did not advocate &quot;domination of one race over another&quot; and that she was against violence. They comment that Blavatsky's work &quot;helped to foster antisemitism, which is perhaps one of the reasons her esoteric work was so rapidly accepted in German circles.&quot; They state Blavatsky &quot;sharply differentiated Aryan and Jewish religion&quot; and believed &quot;The Aryans were the most spiritual people on earth.&quot; They quote Blavatsky's writing in ''Secret Doctrine'' as stating Aryans used religion as an &quot;everlasting lodestar&quot; in contrast to Judaism which Blavatsky claimed was based on &quot;mere calculation&quot; while characterizing it as a &quot;religion of hate and malice toward everyone and everything outside itself.&quot;&lt;ref name = &quot;Spielvogel&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | last1 = Spielvogel 
  | first1 = Jackson
  | last2 = Redles
  | first2 = David
  | authorlink1 = Jackson Spielvogel 
  | title = Hitler's Racial Ideology: Content and Occult Sources
  | work = The Museum of Tolerance Online Multimedia Learning Center
  | publisher = The Simon Wiesenthal Center
  | date = 1997
  | url = http://motlc.wiesenthal.com/site/pp.asp?c=gvKVLcMVIuG&amp;b=395043#45
  | accessdate = 2012-May-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Post-Blavatskyan Theosophy and New Religious Movements== 
Notes: Reasons regarding to the division of traditional theosophy from the Theosophical Society {{clarification needed|date=May 2012|reason=Not sure what this sentence is saying}}&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hanegraaff|2006}} p. ''x-xii'' &lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref name=Goodrick-Clarkes&gt;{{cite book|last=Goodrick-Clarke|first=Claire and Nicholas|title=G. R. S. Mead and the Gnostic Quest|year=2005|publisher=North Atlantic Books|isbn=155643572X|pages=7 and 32}}&lt;/ref&gt;

G.R.S. Mead was an early Theosophist. In 1909 he resigned from the Theosophical Society which was Orientalist. Prior to his break from the Society Mead had already begun emphasizing sources from the Western esoteric tradition in his writing. Mead was among the first Theosophists to explicate a &quot;'Western' theosophy deriving from Alexandrian and Hellenistic sources in the early centuries A.D.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Goodrick-Clarkes 2&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Goodrick-Clarke|first=Claire and Nicholas|title=G. R. S. Mead and the Gnostic Quest|year=2005|publisher=North Atlantic Books|isbn=155643572X|pages=9, 19 and 32}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See Also==
*[[Grace F. Knoche]]
*[[James A. Long]]
*[[Jakob Böhme]]
*[[Wouter Hanegraaff]]
*[[Antoine Faivre]]
*[[Nicholas Goodrick-Clarke]]
*[[Alice Bailey]]
*[[Rudolf Steiner]]
*[[Anthroposophy]]
*[[Guy Ballard]]
*[[Theosophical Society Pasadena]]
*[[Halcyon, California|Halcyon, California (Temple of the People)]]
*[[Lomaland]]
*[[Sunrise (magazine)]]
*[[New Age]]
*[[New Thought]]
*[[Church Universal and Triumphant]]
*[[Valentin Tomberg]]
*[[Henry Corbin]]
*[[Edmonton Theosophical Society]]
*[[Arthur Versluis]]

==References==

===Citations===


{{Reflist|2}}

===Bibliography===


*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Faivre|first=Antoine|authorlink=Antoine Faivre|title=''“Theosophy” in'' The Encyclopedia of Religion;'' Mircea Eliade, Charles J Adams, et al''|year=1987|publisher=Macmillan|location=New York}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Hanegraaff|first=Wouter J.|authorlink=Wouter J. Hanegraaff|title=''“Esotericism” in'' The Dictionary of Gnosis and Western Esotericism;'' Wouter J. Hanegraaff, Editor''|year=2006|publisher=Brill Academic Publishers|location=The Netherlands}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Santucci|first=James A.|title=''“The Theosophical Society” in'' Controversial New Religions;'' James R. Lewis, Jesper Aagaard Petersen''|year=2004|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=USA}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Sellon|first=Emily|title=''“Blavatsky, H. P.” in'' The Encyclopedia of Religion;'' Mircea Eliade, Charles J Adams, et al''|year=1987|publisher=Macmillan|location=New York}} 
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Faivre|first=Antoine|authorlink=Antoine Faivre|title=Theosophy, Imagination, Tradition: Studies in Western Esotericism|year=2000|publisher=SUNY|location=Albany, NY}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Goodrick-Clarke|first=Nicholas|authorlink=Nicholas Goodrick-Clarke|title=The Western Esoteric Traditions|year=2008|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=New York}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Godwin|first=Joscelyn|authorlink=Joscelyn Godwin|title=The Theosophical Enlightenment|year=1994|publisher=SUNY|location=Albany, NY}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=OED|title=Oxford English Dictionary|year=1989|publisher=Oxford University Press}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last= Blavatsky|first=Helena|title=The Secret Doctrine: The Synthesis of Science, Religion, and Philosophy|year=1888|publisher=The Theosophical Publishing Company|location=London}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last= Blavatsky|first=Helena|title=The Key to Theosophy |year=1889|publisher=The Theosophical Publishing Company|location=London}}

===Online Sources===


*{{cite book
 | last = Ellwood
 | first = Robert S.
 | title = Theosophy: A Modern Expression of the Wisdom of the Ages
 | publisher = Theosophical Publishing House
 | date = 1986
 | location = Wheaton, IL
 | pages = 237
 | language =
 | url = http://books.google.ca/books?id=_-mfy2EaKWwC
 | isbn = 0-8356-0607-4}}

*{{cite book
 | last = Hammer
 | first = Olav
 | authorlink = Olav Hammer
 | title = Claiming Knowledge: Strategies of Epistemology from Theosophy to the New Age
 | publisher = Brill
 | series = Studies in the history of religions
 | volume = Volume 90
 | edition = reprint
 | date = 2004
 | location = Leiden, Netherlands
 | pages = 550
 | url = http://books.google.ca/books?id=EZYsPQgBNioC
 | isbn = 97890041136380 {{Please check ISBN|reason=Invalid length.}}}}

*{{cite book
 | last = Judge
 | first = William Q.
 | authorlink = William Q. Judge
 | title = The Ocean of Theosophy
 | publisher = Theosophical University Press online edition
 | edition = Second
 | date = 1893
 | location = Pasedena, CA
 | url = http://www.theosociety.org/pasadena/ocean/oce-hp.htm
 | isbn = 978-1-55700-034-7}}

*{{cite book
 | last1 = Antes
 | first1 = Peter
 | last2 = Geertz
 | first2 = Armin W.
 | last3 = Warne
 | first3 = Randi Ruth, editors
 | title = New Approaches to the Study of Religion: Regional, critical, and historical approaches
 | publisher = Walter de Gruyter
 | volume = 1
 | date = 2004
 | location = Berlin, Germany
 | pages = 559
 | url = http://books.google.ca/books?id=OYsk8ZtJaMIC&amp;dq=%22the+white+buddhist%22%2C+theosophy&amp;q=theosophy#v=snippet&amp;q=theosophy&amp;f=false
 | isbn = 978-3-11-017698-8}}

==External links==
*[http://www.esswe.org/# European Society for the Study of Western Esotericism]
*[http://centres.exeter.ac.uk/exeseso/# Exeter Centre for the Study of Esotericism]
*[http://www.aseweb.org/ Association for the Study of Esotericism]
*[http://www.theohistory.org/ Theosophical History]
*[http://www.esoteric.msu.edu/ Esoterica]
*[http://www.amsterdamhermetica.nl/# Western Esotericism in the Academy]
*[http://www.mutaaliah.com/Home Transcendental Theosophy Institute]
*[http://meta-religion.com/index.html Meta religion]


[[Category:Esotericism]]
[[Category:Theosophy]]
[[Category:Religious philosophy]]
[[Category:Philosophy of religion]]
[[Category:Religious philosophical concepts]]

[[ar:الثيوصوفية]]
[[az:Teosofiya]]
[[bg:Теософия]]
[[ca:Teosofia]]
[[cs:Teosofie]]
[[da:Teosofi]]
[[de:Theosophie]]
[[et:Teosoofia]]
[[el:Θεοσοφία]]
[[es:Teosofía]]
[[eo:Teozofio]]
[[fr:Théosophie]]
[[gl:Teosofía]]
[[ko:신지학]]
[[hr:Teozofija]]
[[io:Teozofio]]
[[id:Teosofi]]
[[ia:Theosophia]]
[[it:Teosofia]]
[[he:האגודה התאוסופית#תאוסופיה]]
[[ka:თეოსოფია]]
[[ky:Теософия]]
[[lt:Teosofija]]
[[hu:Teozófia]]
[[mk:Теозофија]]
[[mn:Теософи]]
[[nl:Theosofie]]
[[ja:神智学]]
[[no:Teosofi]]
[[pl:Teozofia]]
[[pt:Teosofia]]
[[ro:Teosofie]]
[[ru:Теософия (Блаватская)]]
[[stq:Theosophie]]
[[si:පරමවිඥානාර්ථවාදය]]
[[sk:Teozofia]]
[[sl:Teozofija]]
[[sr:Теозофија]]
[[sh:Teozofija]]
[[fi:Teosofia]]
[[sv:Teosofi]]
[[tr:Teozofi]]
[[uk:Теософія]]
[[ur:حکمت یزدانی]]
[[zh:神智学]]</text>
      <sha1>4laoseng4zc25917q5wtffgqibhlcmr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
