<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Torah study</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>142703</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521697618</id>
      <parentid>521697192</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T17:43:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bbb2007</username>
        <id>5465311</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edit(s) by [[Special:Contributions/24.51.214.106|24.51.214.106]] identified as test/vandalism using [[WP:STiki|STiki]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18461">{{refimprove|date=June 2009}}
'''Torah study''' is the study by [[Jewish]] people of the [[Torah]], [[Tanakh|Hebrew Bible]], [[Talmud]], [[responsa]], [[rabbinic literature]] and similar works, all of which are [[Judaism]]'s religious texts.  According to Rabbinic beliefs the study is ideally done for the purpose of the [[mitzvah]] (&quot;commandment&quot;) of Torah study itself.

This practice is present to an extent in all religious branches of Judaism and is considered of paramount importance among religious Jews. Torah study has evolved over the generations, as lifestyles changed and also as new texts were written.

==Traditional view of Torah study==
In rabbinic literature, the highest ideal of all Jewish men is Torah study, women being exempt from Torah study. This literature teaches an eagerness for such study and a thirst for knowledge that expands beyond the text of the Tanakh to the entire [[Oral Torah]]. According to many historians, this carried over into the general characteristics of Jewish society, both religious and non-religious, down to the present. Some examples of traditional religious teachings:

* The study of Torah is considered to outweigh a number of mitzvot, such as visiting the sick, honouring one's parents, and bringing peace between people (Shabbat 127a). This paragraph was incorporated in the daily prayer service.
* A number of Talmudic rabbis consider Torah study as being greater than the rescue of human life, than the building of the [[Temple in Jerusalem]], and than the honor of father and mother (Megilah 16b), provided that the individual's life will be saved by someone else.{{Citation needed|date=October 2008}}
* According to R. Meir, when one studies Torah for its own sake (''Torah Lishma'' - תורה לשמה) the [the creation of] entire world is worthwhile for him alone, and he brings joy to G-d ([[Avot]] [http://www.chabad.org/library/article_cdo/aid/2122/jewish/Chapter-Six.htm 6:1]).
* As the child must satisfy its hunger day by day, so must the grown man busy himself with the Torah each hour (Yerushalmi, Berakhot ch. 9).
* Torah study is of more value than the offering of daily sacrifice (Eruvin 63b).
* A single day devoted to the Torah outweighs 1,000 [[Korban|sacrifices]] (Tractate Shabbat 30a; comp. Tractate Menachot 100a).
* The fable of the Fish and the Fox [http://www.sacred-texts.com/jud/tgm/tgm20.htm], in which the latter seeks to entice the former to dry land, declares Israel can live only in the Law as fish can live only in the ocean (Babylonian Talmud, Berakhot 61b).
* Whoever learns Torah at night is granted grace during the day and whoever neglects it will be fed burning coals in the World to Come. ([[Avodah Zarah (tractate)|Avodah Zarah]] 3b).
* God weeps over one who might have occupied himself with Torah study but neglected to do so (Tractate Hagigah 5b).
* The study must be unselfish: one should study the Torah with self-denial, even at the sacrifice of one's life; and in the very hour before death one should devote himself to this duty (Tractate Shabbat 83b).
* All, even lepers and the ritually unclean, are required to study the Torah (Tractate Berakhot 22a).
* It is the duty of everyone to read the entire weekly portion twice (the law of [[shnayim mikra ve-echad targum]], Tractate Berakhot 8a).
* According to R. Meir, a [[Gentile]] who studies the Torah (for the purpose of finding out about the [[Noachide Laws]]) is as great as the [[kohen|High Priest]] (Tractate Avodah Zarah 3a).
* According to R. Yehudah, God Himself studies the Torah for the first three hours of every day. (Tractate Avodah Zarah 3b).

==Origins==
Torah study is counted amongst the [[613 mitzvot]] (&quot;[Biblical] commandments&quot;), finding its source in the verse ([[Deuteronomy]] 6:7): &quot;And you shall teach it to your children,&quot; upon which the Talmud comments that &quot;Study is necessary in order to teach.&quot; The importance of study is attested to in another Talmudic discussion (Kiddushin 40b) about which is preferred: study or action. The answer there, a seeming compromise, is &quot;study that leads to action.&quot;
Although the word &quot;Torah&quot; refers specifically to the [[Humash|Five Books of Moses]], in Judaism the word also refers to the [[Tanakh]] ([[Hebrew Bible]]), the [[Talmud]] and other religious works, even including the study of [[Kabbalah]], [[Hasidic Judaism|Hasidism]], [[Mussar movement|Mussar]] and much more.

==Forms of traditional Jewish Torah study==
The Talmud (Tractate Kiddushin 30a) defines the objective of Torah study: &quot;That the words of Torah shall be clear in your mouth so that if someone asks you something, you shall need not hesitate and then tell it to him, rather you shall tell it to him immediately.&quot; In [[yeshiva]]s (&quot;[[Talmud]]ical schools&quot;), rabbinical schools and [[kollel]]s (&quot;[post-graduate] Talmudical schools&quot;) the primary ways of studying Torah include study of:
* The [[weekly Torah portion]] with its [[Rabbinic literature|Meforshim]] (&quot;Rabbinic commentators&quot;)
* [[Talmud]]
* Ethical works

Other less universally studied texts include the [[Nevi'im]] and [[Ketuvim]], other rabbinic literature (such as [[midrash]]) and works of religious [[Jewish philosophy]].

Orthodox Jews can study the text of the Torah on any of four levels as described in the [[Zohar#Pardes and Biblical exegesis|Zohar]]:
* ''[[Peshat]]'', the plain (simple) or literal reading;
* ''Remez'', the allegorical reading through text's hint or allusion
* ''Derash'', the metaphorical reading through a (rabbinic sermon's) comparison/illustration ([[midrash]])
* ''Sod'', the hidden meaning reading through text's secret or mystery ([[Kabbalah]]).

The initial letters of the words '' '''P'''eshat'', '' '''R'''emez'', '' '''D'''erash'', '' '''S'''od'', forming together the [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] word [[Pardes (Jewish exegesis)|'''P'''a'''RD'''e'''S''']] (also meaning &quot;orchard&quot;), became the designation for the four-way method of studying Torah, in which the mystical sense given in the [[Kabbalah]] was the highest point.

In some traditional circles, most notably the [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox]] and [[Haredi Judaism|Haredi]], Torah study is a way of life for males. Women do not study Torah, but gain merit for facilitating Torah study for the men. In some communities, men forgo other occupations and study Torah full-time. 

Haredi Israelis often choose to devote many years to Torah study, often studying at a [[Kollel]]. National Religious Israelis often choose to devote time after high school to Torah study, either during their army service at a [[Hesder]] yeshiva, or before their service at a [[Mechina]].

==Study cycles==

Apart from full-time Torah study as engaged in at schools and ''yeshivot'' or for the purpose of rabbinic training, there is also held to be an obligation on individuals to set aside a regular study period to review their knowledge.  Examples of programmes of study are as follows.
* [[Shnayim mikra ve-echad targum]]: study of the [[weekly Torah portion]] together with the Aramaic [[Targum]]
* ''[[Chok l'Yisrael|Ḥoq le-Yisrael]]'', a programme founded by Rabbis [[Hayyim ben Joseph Vital]] and [[Chaim Joseph David Azulai]] in which, every week, one studies extracts from the [[Mishnah]], the [[Zohar]] and other works in addition to the [[Weekly Torah portion|portion for that week]]: the relevant passages are often printed in book form in a multivolume set.
* The ''[[Seder ha-Mishmarah]]'', used by some Jews of Near and Middle Eastern origin, in which each weekly Torah portion is studied together with sections from [[Neviim]] and [[Ketuvim]] and the [[Mishnah]] so that all these works are read in full in the course of the year: this too has been published in book form under the title ''Ḥoq le-Ya'akob''.  In some countries it was customary for groups to gather in the synagogue each Shabbat afternoon and read out the ''mishmarah'' passages for the following Shabbat.
* The [[Daf Yomi]] programme, founded in 1923 by Rabbi [[Meir Shapiro]]: one page of the Talmud is studied each day, on a rota to ensure that Jews round the world are studying the same passage at the same time (more recently, there have been similar programmes for the [[Jerusalem Talmud]] and other works).
* The [[Amud Yomi]], similar to Daf Yomi, but only one side of a page per day.
*''[[Mishneh_Torah#Study|Mishneh Torah]]'' - daily study (1 or 3 year cycle)
*''[[Mishnah Berurah]] Yomit'' - daily study (2.5 or 5 year cycle)
*''[[Shlomo_Ganzfried#Kitzur_Shulchan_Aruch|Kitzur Shulchan Aruch]] Yomi'' - daily study (1 year cycle)
*''[[Halacha Yomit]]'' ([[Shulchan Aruch]]) - daily study (4 year cycle)
*''[[Tanya]]'' - daily study (1 year cycle)

==D'var Torah==

A ''D'var Torah'' (Heb: דבר תורה) (Plural: ''Divrei Torah'') is a talk on topics relating to a section ([[parashah]]) of the [[Torah]] – typically the [[weekly Torah portion]]. In respect to its place in [[synagogue]]s, rabbis will often give their D'var Torah after the [[Torah reading|Torah service]]. Divrei Torah can range in length, depending on the rabbi and the depth of the talk. In most congregations, it will not last much longer than fifteen minutes, but in the case of [[Rebbe]]s or special occasions, a Dvar Torah can last all afternoon.  

It is extremely likely that a D'var Torah will carry a life lesson, backed up by passages from certain Jewish texts like the [[Talmud]] or [[Mishnah]].  

It is also known as a ''Drasha'' in [[Ashkenazi Jews|Ashkenazic]] communities.

There are many Torah sites on the web that contain Divrei Torah to help people learn Torah. One of these sites provides users the ability to post their own Dvar Torah to help others who are learning Torah.

==Torah study by Jewish denominations==

Like [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox Jews]], other [[Jewish denominations]] may use any or all of the traditional areas and modes of Torah study. They study the [[weekly Torah portion|Parsha]], the Talmud, ethical works, and more. They may study simply the ''peshat'' of the text, or they may also study, to a limited extent, the ''remez'', ''derash'' and ''sod'', which is found in ''Etz Hayyim: A Torah Commentary'' (Rabbinical Assembly), used in many Conservative congregations. It is common in Torah study among Jews involved in [[Jewish Renewal]]. Some level of ''PaRDeS'' study can even be found in forms of Judaism that otherwise are strictly rationalist, such as [[Reconstructionist Judaism]]. However, non-Orthodox Jews generally spend less time in detailed study of the classical Torah commentators, and spend more time studying modern Torah commentaries that draw on and include the classical commentators, but which are written from more modern perspectives. Furthermore, works of rabbinic literature (such as the [[Talmud]]) typically receive less attention than the [[Tanakh]].

Before the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]], virtually all Jews believed that the Torah was dictated to Moses by God.&lt;ref&gt;Mishnah, Sanhedrin 11:1&lt;/ref&gt;{{Better source|date=September 2012}} They also believed that as many parts of the Torah, specifically the laws and commandments, are written in unspecific terms, Moses also received an interpretation of the Torah that was transmitted through the generations in oral form till it was finally put in writing in the [[Mishnah]] and later, in greater detail, the [[Talmud]].&lt;ref&gt;Maimonodies, Introduction to Commentary on Mishnah, also, Maimonodies, Commentary on Mishnah, Sanhedrin 11:1&lt;/ref&gt; After the Enlightenment, many Jews began to participate in wider European society, where they engaged in study related to critical methods of textual analysis, including both [[Lower criticism|lower]] and [[higher criticism]], the modern historical method, [[hermeneutics]], and fields relevant to Bible study such as near-Eastern [[archaeology]] and [[linguistics]]. In time the [[documentary hypothesis]] emerged from these studies. Formulated primarily by non Jews,{{citation needed|date=September 2012}} the documentary hypothesis holds that the Torah was not written by Moses, but was simply written by different people who lived during different periods of Israelite history. Some Jews adapted the findings of these disciplines. Consequently, biblical study primarily focused on the intentions of these people, and the circumstances in which they lived. This type of study depends on evidence external to the text, especially archeological evidence and comparative literature.

Today, [[Reform Judaism|Reform]], [[Conservative Judaism|Conservative]], and [[Reconstructionist Judaism|Reconstructionist]] [[rabbi]]s draw on the lessons of modern critical Bible scholarship as well as the traditional forms of Biblical exegesis. Orthodox, [[Sephardi]]m, a majority of Israeli Jews&lt;ref&gt;Jerusalem Center for Public Affairs, Daniel Elazar Papers Index, Israel: Religion and Society [http://jcpa.org/dje/articles2/howrelisr.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; and other Jews, including many whom are not observant, reject critical Bible scholarship and the documentary hypothesis, holding to the opinion that it is contradicted by the Torah in Deuteronomy 31:24,25 and 26, and the Talmud ([[Gittin]] 60a, [[Bava Basra]] 15b), which state that Moses wrote the Torah, as well as by the [[Mishnah]],&lt;ref&gt;Sanhedrin 11:1&lt;/ref&gt; which asserts the divine origin of the Torah as one of the essential tenets of Judaism.

Humanistic Jews value the Torah as a historical, political, and sociological text written by their ancestors.  They do not believe 'that every word of the Torah is true, or even morally correct, just because the Torah is old.' The Torah is both disagreed with and questioned. Humanistic Jews believe that the entire Jewish experience, and not only the Torah, should be studied as a source for Jewish behavior and ethical values.&lt;ref&gt;http://oradam.org/OAC/FAQ&lt;/ref&gt;

==Non-religious Torah study==
According to Ruth Calderon, there are currently almost one hundred non-halakhic Torah study centers in Israel. Whilst influenced by methods used in the yeshiva and in the university, non religious Torah study includes the use of new tools that are not part of the accepted hermeneutic tradition of the exegetic literature. These include Feminist, and post-modernist criticism, historic, sociological and psychological analyses, and literary analysis.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.culturaljudaism.org/ccj/articles/26&lt;/ref&gt; Among these institutions is the Alma Centre for Hebrew Studies in Tel Aviv.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.alma.org.il/content.asp?pageid=8&amp;lang=en&lt;/ref&gt;

==Torah study in Israel==

Devoting a year to Torah study in the modern Land of Israel is a common practice among [[United States|American]], and, to a lesser extent, [[Europe]]an, [[History of the Jews in South Africa|South African]], South American, and Australian [[Modern Orthodox Judaism|Modern Orthodox]] Jews. Young adults spend a year studying Torah in the [[Land of Israel]]. It is common both among males and females, with the boys normally going to a [[yeshiva]] and the girls to a [[midrasha]] (often called ''seminary'' or ''seminaria''). Common Yeshivot with year-in-Israel programs include: [[Yeshivat Har Etzion]], [[Yeshivat HaMivtar]], [[Machon Meir]], [[Aish HaTorah]]. Common seminaries or midrashot include: [[Midreshet HaRova]] [[Midreshet Lindenbaum]], [[Migdal Oz]], [[Nishmat]], [[Bnos Chava]], Michlalah [http://www.machal.michlalah.edu/], and many many others. [[Chasidic]] and [[Charedi]] boys from abroad often spend many years studying in the Land of Israel.  Bnei Akiva offers a number of options to spend a year of study in Israel, as part of their Hachshara programs.

==See also==
* [[Menachem Cohen (scholar)]]
* [[Judaism]]
* [[Kollel]]
* [[Mechina]]
* [[Midrasha]]
* [[Yeshiva]]
* [[Torah]]
* [[Torah reading]]
* [[Weekly Torah portion]] and links to articles on individual Torah portions found there

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
*[http://www.tzorichiyun.wordpress.com Tzorich Iyun]
*[http://www.torahanytime.com TorahAnytime.com]
*[http://www.partnersintorah.org Partners in Torah free phone study program]
*[http://www.torah.org/learning/halacha-overview/chapter3.html in the Mishneh Torah]
*[http://www.torah.org/advanced/shulchan-aruch/classes/chapter18.html in Shulkhan Arukh, Yoreh De'ah]
*[http://www.chassidus.org.ru/chabadlibrary.org/admur_hazoken/shulchan_oruch/yore_dea/talmud_tora_1.htm in Shulkhan Arukh haRav]
*[http://www.shemayisrael.co.il/publicat/schwartz/a33.htm The importance of Torah Study]
*[http://ReturntoG-d.blogspot.com Torah`s Studies]
*[http://www.kitzur.net/main.php?siman=27 in Kitzur Shulchan Aruch], (site follows the Kitzur Yomi schedule; fully searchable)
*[http://www.shiur.com/ Weekly Torah Portion]
*http://www.torahframework.org
;Recommended Reading
* [http://www.torahandisrael.com/recommended_reading.html Recommended Reading] by TorahAndIsrael
* [http://www.aish.com/jl/sp/ns/48971206.html Essential Jewish Library] by Aish HaTorah
* [http://www.aish.com/jl/48969561.html Recommended Books] by Aish HaTorah
* [http://ohr.edu/4284 Recommended Reading] by Ohr Somayach (extensive)

==Bibliography==
*A Practical Guide to Torah Learning, D. Landesman, Jason Aronson 1995. ISBN 1-56821-320-4

==Wikimedia Torah study projects==
Text study projects at '''[[:s:Wikisource|Wikisource]]'''. Please note that in many instances, these projects proceed much faster in Hebrew than in English!
*'''[[Mikraot Gedolot]]''' (Rabbinic Bible) in '''[[:s:he:מקראות גדולות|Hebrew]]''' [[:s:he:מ&quot;ג איכה א א|(sample)]] and '''[[:s:Mikraot Gedolot|English]]''' [[:s:MG Numbers 1:1|(sample)]].
*'''[[Cantillation]]''' at the '''&quot;Vayavinu Bamikra&quot; Project''' in '''[[:s:he:ויבינו במקרא|Hebrew]]''' (lists nearly 200 recordings!) and '''[[:s:Vayavinu Bamikra|English]]'''.
*'''[[Mishnah]]''' in '''[[:s:he:משנה|Hebrew]]''' [[:s:he:ברכות פרק א משנה א|(sample)]] and '''[[:s:Mishnah|English]]''' [[:s:Mishnah/Seder Zeraim/Tractate Berakhot/Chapter 1/1|(sample)]].
*'''[[Shulchan Aruch]]''' in '''[[:s:he:שולחן ערוך|Hebrew]]''' and '''[[:s:Shulchan Aruch|English]]''' (Hebrew text with English translation).

{{Jewish life}}
{{Orthodox Judaism}}
{{Weekly Torah Portions}}

&lt;!--Categories--&gt;
[[Category:Jewish texts]]
[[Category:Jewish law and rituals]]
[[Category:Biblical studies]]
[[Category:Torah]]

&lt;!--Other languages--&gt;
[[fr:Étude de la Torah]]
[[it:Studio della Torah]]
[[he:תלמוד תורה (מצווה)]]</text>
      <sha1>64ykfxhkz3ip1wcvj55lvb8pbwqe53j</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
