<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Transubstantiation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>30907</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521658774</id>
      <parentid>521621296</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T12:06:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Esoglou</username>
        <id>11289927</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>the first time the term is known to have been *used*; no evidence that it had become a *usage*</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="56146">[[File:Blessed Sacrament Chapel interior.jpg|thumb|262px|Adoration is shown to Christ believed to be [[Real presence of Christ in the Eucharist|really present]] in [[sacramental bread]] whose reality has been changed into that of his body]]
{{Eucharist}} 

In [[Roman Catholic theology]], '''transubstantiation''' (in [[Latin language|Latin]], ''transsubstantiatio'', in [[Greek language|Greek]] μετουσίωσις [[metousiosis]]) is the [[doctrine]] that, in the [[Eucharist]], the [[Substance theory|substance]] of the bread and the wine used in the [[sacrament]] is changed into the substance of the [[Body of Christ|Body]] and the [[Blood of Christ|Blood]] of [[Jesus]],&lt;ref&gt;According to Catholic theology, the body of the living Christ, into which the bread is changed, is necessarily accompanied by his blood, his soul and his divinity, and similarly his body, his soul and his divinity are present &quot;by [http://www.catholicculture.org/culture/library/dictionary/index.cfm?id=32692 concomitance]&quot; where his blood is.&lt;/ref&gt; while all that is accessible to the senses (the appearances - ''species'' in [[Latin]]) remains as before.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P44.HTM Catechism of the Catholic Church, 1413]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The conversion of the whole substance of the bread and wine into the whole substance of the Body and Blood of Christ, only the accidents (i.e. the appearances of the bread and wine) remaining&quot; (Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church - Oxford University Press 2005 ISBN 978-0-19-280290-3 - article ''Transubstantiation''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/603196/transubstantiation Encyclopaedia Britannica].&lt;/ref&gt; 

The [[Eastern Orthodox Church]], [[Oriental Orthodoxy|Oriental Orthodox Church]], and [[Church of the East]] have sometimes used the term &quot;transubstantiation&quot; (''metousiosis''); however, terms such as &quot;divine mystery&quot;, &quot;trans-elementation&quot; (μεταστοιχείωσις ''metastoicheiosis''), &quot;re-ordination&quot; (μεταρρύθμισις ''metarrhythmisis''), or simply &quot;change&quot; (μεταβολή) are more common among them.

==History==
The earliest known use of the term &quot;transubstantiation&quot; to describe the change from bread and wine to body and blood of Christ that was believed to occur in the Eucharist was by [[Hildebert de Lavardin]], Archbishop of Tours (died 1133), in the eleventh century and by the end of the twelfth century the term was in widespread use.&lt;ref name=ODCC/&gt; The [[Fourth Council of the Lateran]], which convened beginning November 11, 1215,&lt;ref&gt;{{Catholic|prescript=|wstitle=Fourth Lateran Council (1215)}}&lt;/ref&gt; spoke of the bread and wine as &quot;transubstantiated&quot; into the body and blood of Christ: &quot;His body and blood are truly contained in the sacrament of the altar under the forms of bread and wine, the bread and wine having been ''transubstantiated'', by God's power, into his body and blood&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.papalencyclicals.net/Councils/ecum12-2.htm#Confession of Faith ''Fourth Lateran Council: 1215''], 1. Confession of Faith, retrieved 2010-03-13.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Protestant Reformation]], the doctrine of transubstantiation was heavily criticised as an [[Aristotle|Aristotelian]] &quot;pseudo-philosophy&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Luther, M. The Babylonian Captivity of the Christian Church. 1520. Quoted in, McGrath, A. 1998. Historical Theology, An Introduction to the History of Christian Thought. Blackwell Publishers: Oxford. p. 198.&lt;/ref&gt; imported into Christian teaching and jettisoned in favor of [[Martin Luther]]'s doctrine of [[sacramental union]], or in favor, per [[Huldrych Zwingli]], of the Eucharist as memorial.&lt;ref&gt;McGrath, op.cit. pp. 198-99&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Council of Trent]] in its thirteenth session ending October 11, 1551, defined transubstantiation as &quot;that wonderful and singular conversion of the whole substance of the bread into the Body, and of the whole substance of the wine into the Blood – the [[species (Christianity)|species]] only of the bread and wine remaining – which conversion indeed the Catholic Church most aptly calls Transubstantiation&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;history.hanover.edu&quot;&gt;[http://history.hanover.edu/early/trent/ct13ce.htm Council of Trent, The Thirteenth Session]&lt;/ref&gt; This council officially approved use of the term &quot;transubstantiation&quot; to express the Catholic Church's teaching on the subject of the conversion of the bread and wine into the body and blood of Christ in the Eucharist,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.1911encyclopedia.org/Transubstantiation Encyclopaedia Britannica, 11th ed. (1911), vol 27, page 186]&lt;/ref&gt; with the aim of safeguarding Christ's presence as a literal truth, while emphasizing the fact that there is no change in the empirical appearances of the bread and wine.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/603196/transubstantiation Encyclopaedia Britannica: article ''transubstantiation'']&lt;/ref&gt; It did not however impose the Aristotelian theory of substance and accidents: it spoke only of the [[species (Christianity)|species]] (the appearances), not the philosophical term &quot;accidents&quot;, and the word &quot;substance&quot; was in ecclesiastical use for many centuries before Aristotelian philosophy was adopted in the West,&lt;ref name=Sophia&gt;[http://www.springerlink.com/content/p306w5884w107537/ Charles Davis: ''The Theology of Transubstantiation'' in ''Sophia'', Vol. 3, No. 1 / April 1964]&lt;/ref&gt; as shown for instance by its use in the [[Nicene Creed]] which speaks of Christ having the same &quot;οὐσία&quot; (Greek) or &quot;substantia&quot; (Latin) as the [[God the Father|Father]].

===Patristic period===
The belief that the Eucharist conveyed to the believer the body and blood of Christ appears to have been widespread from an early date, and the elements were commonly referred to as the body and the blood by early Christian writers.  The early Christians who use these terms also speak of it as the flesh and blood of Christ, the same flesh and blood which suffered and died on the cross.  

The short document known as the Teaching of the Apostles or [[Didache]], which may be the earliest Christian document outside of the [[New Testament]] to speak of the Eucharist, says, &quot;Let no one eat or drink of the Eucharist with you except those who have been baptized in the Name of the Lord,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/0714.htm &quot;The Didache&quot;, 9:1]&lt;/ref&gt; for it was in reference to this that the Lord said, &quot;Do not give that which is holy to dogs.&quot; Matthew 7:6  

A letter by Saint [[Ignatius of Antioch]] to the Romans, written in AD 106 says:  &quot;I desire the bread of GOD, which is the flesh of Jesus Christ.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/0107.htm &quot;Epistle to the Romans&quot;, 7]&lt;/ref&gt;   

Writing to the Christians of Smyrna, in about AD 106, Saint [[Ignatius of Antioch|Ignatius]] warned them to &quot;stand aloof from such heretics&quot;, because, among other reasons, &quot;they abstain from the Eucharist and from prayer, because they confess not the Eucharist to be the flesh of our Savior Jesus Christ, which suffered for our sins, and which the Father, of His goodness, raised up again.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/0109.htm ''Epistle to the Smyrnaeans'', 7]&lt;/ref&gt;

In about 150, [[Justin Martyr]] wrote of the Eucharist: &quot;Not as common bread and common drink do we receive these; but in like manner as Jesus Christ our Savior, having been made flesh by the Word of God, had both flesh and blood for our salvation, so likewise have we been taught that the food which is blessed by the prayer of His word, and from which our blood and flesh by transmutation are nourished, is the flesh and blood of that Jesus who was made flesh.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.earlychristianwritings.com/text/justinmartyr-firstapology.html First Apology, LXVI]&lt;/ref&gt;

Justin Martyr wrote, in Dialogue with Trypho, ch 70: &quot;Now it is evident, that in this prophecy to the bread which our Christ gave us to eat, in remembrance of His being made flesh for the sake of His believers, for whom also He suffered; and to the cup which He gave us to drink, in remembrance of His own blood, with giving of thanks.&quot;

In about 200 AD, Tertullian wrote (Against Marcion IV. 40): &quot;Taking bread and distributing it to his disciples he made it his own body by saying, 'This is my body,' that is a 'figure of my body.'  On the other hand, there would not have been a figure unless there was a true body.&quot;

The [[Apostolic Constitutions]] (compiled c. 380) says: &quot;Let the bishop give the oblation, saying, The body of Christ; and let him that receiveth say, Amen. And let the deacon take the cup; and when he gives it, say, The blood of Christ, the cup of life; and let him that drinketh say, Amen.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/anf07.ix.ix.ii.html Book VIII, section II, XIII]&lt;/ref&gt;

Saint [[Ambrose]] of Milan (d. 397) wrote:
:Perhaps you will say, &quot;I see something else, how is it that you assert that I receive the Body of Christ?&quot; ... Let us prove that this is not what nature made, but what the blessing consecrated, and the power of blessing is greater than that of nature, because by blessing nature itself is changed. ... For that sacrament which you receive is made what it is by the word of Christ. But if the word of Elijah had such power as to bring down fire from heaven, shall not the word of Christ have power to change the nature of the elements? ... Why do you seek the order of nature in the Body of Christ, seeing that the Lord Jesus Himself was born of a Virgin, not according to nature? It is the true Flesh of Christ which was crucified and buried, this is then truly the Sacrament of His Body. The Lord Jesus Himself proclaims: &quot;This is My Body.&quot; Before the blessing of the heavenly words another nature is spoken of, after the consecration the Body ''is signified''. He Himself speaks of His Blood. Before the consecration it has another name, after it is called Blood. And you say, Amen, that is, It is true. Let the heart within confess what the mouth utters, let the soul feel what the voice speaks.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/3405.htm On the Mysteries, 50-54]&lt;/ref&gt;

Other fourth-century Christian writers say that in the Eucharist there occurs a &quot;change&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Cyril of Jerusalem, ''Cat. Myst.,'' 5, 7 (Patrologia Graeca 33:1113): {{lang|grc|μεταβολή}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;transelementation&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Gregory of Nyssa, ''Oratio catechetica magna'', 37 (PG 45:93): {{lang|grc|μεταστοιχειώσας}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;transformation&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;John Chrysostom, Homily 1 on the betrayal of Judas, 6 (PG 49:380): {{lang|grc|μεταρρύθμησις}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;transposing&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Cyril of Alexandria, On Luke, 22, 19 (PG 72:911): {{lang|grc|μετίτησις}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;alteration&quot;&lt;ref&gt;John Damascene, On the orthodox faith, book 4, chapter 13 (PG 49:380): {{lang|grc|μεταποίησις}}&lt;/ref&gt; of the bread into the body of Christ.

In AD 400, Augustine quotes Cyprian (AD 200): &quot;For as Christ says 'I am the true vine,' it follows that the blood of Christ is wine, not water; and the cup cannot appear to contain His blood by which we are redeemed and quickened, if the wine be absent; for by the wine is the blood of Christ typified, ...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Augustine, On Christian Doctrine, book 4, ch 21, quoting Cyprian.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Middle Ages===
In the eleventh century, [[Berengar of Tours]] denied that any material change in the elements was needed to explain the Eucharistic Presence, thereby provoking a considerable stir.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODCC&quot;/&gt; Berengar's position was never diametrically opposed to that of his critics, and he was probably never excommunicated. But the controversy that he aroused forced people to clarify the doctrine of  the Eucharist.&lt;ref&gt;Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church (Oxford University Press 2005 ISBN 978-0-19-280290-3), article ''Berengar of Tours''&lt;/ref&gt;

The earliest known use of the term &quot;transubstantiation&quot; to describe the change from bread and wine to body and blood of Christ was by [[Hildebert de Lavardin]], [[Archbishop of Tours]] (died 1133), in about 1079,&lt;ref&gt;Sermones xciii; PL CLXXI, 776&lt;/ref&gt; long before the Latin West, under the influence especially of [[Thomas Aquinas]] (c. 1227-1274), accepted [[Aristotelianism]].

Although it was only in the West that Aristotelian philosophy prevailed,&lt;ref&gt;Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church (Oxford University Press 2005), article ''Aristotle''&lt;/ref&gt; the objective reality of the Eucharistic change is also believed in by the Eastern Orthodox Church and the other ancient Churches of the East (see [[metousiosis]]).

In 1215, the [[Fourth Lateran Council]] used the word ''transubstantiated'' in its profession of faith, when speaking of the change that takes place in the Eucharist. It was only later in the thirteenth century that Aristotelian metaphysics was accepted and a philosophical elaboration in line with that metaphysics was developed, which found classic formulation in the teaching of Saint Thomas Aquinas.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ODCC&quot;&gt;Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church (Oxford University Press 2005 ISBN 978-0-19-280290-3), article ''Transubstantiation''&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1551 the [[Council of Trent]] officially defined, with a minimum of technical philosophical language,&lt;ref name=&quot;ODCC&quot;/&gt; that &quot;by the consecration of the bread and wine there takes place a change of the whole substance of the bread into the substance of the body of Christ our Lord and of the whole substance of the wine into the substance of his blood. This change the holy Catholic Church has fittingly and properly called transubstantiation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://history.hanover.edu/texts/trent/ct13.html Session XIII], chapter IV; cf. canon II)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Protestant criticisms===
[[Image:De-captivitate-Babylonica.jpg|thumb|Title page of [[Martin Luther]]'s ''[[On the Babylonian Captivity of the Church|De Captivitate Babylonica Ecclesiae]]'']]
In the [[Protestant Reformation]], the doctrine of transubstantiation became a matter of much controversy. [[Martin Luther]] held that &quot;It is not the doctrine of transubstantiation which is to be believed, but simply that Christ really is present at the Eucharist&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;McGrath, op.cit., p197.&lt;/ref&gt; In his &quot;[[On the Babylonian Captivity of the Church]]&quot; (published on 6 October 1520) Luther wrote: 

:Therefore it is an absurd and unheard-of juggling with words, to understand &quot;bread&quot; to mean &quot;the form, or accidents of bread,&quot; and &quot;wine&quot; to mean &quot;the form, or accidents of wine.&quot; Why do they not also understand all other things to mean their forms, or accidents? Even if this might be done with all other things, it would yet not be right thus to emasculate the words of God and arbitrarily to empty them of their meaning.

:Moreover, the Church had the true faith for more than twelve hundred years, during which time the holy Fathers never once mentioned this transubstantiation — certainly, a monstrous word for a monstrous idea — until the pseudo-philosophy of Aristotle became rampant in the Church these last three hundred years. During these centuries many other things have been wrongly defined, for example, that the Divine essence neither is begotten nor begets, that the soul is the substantial form of the human body, and the like assertions, which are made without reason or sense, as the Cardinal of Cambray himself admits.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ctsfw.edu/etext/luther/babylonian/babylonian.htm A Prelude by Martin Luther on the Babylonian Captivity of the Church, 2:26 &amp; 2:27]&lt;/ref&gt;

In his 1528 [[Confession Concerning Christ's Supper]] he wrote:
:Why then should we not much more say in the Supper, &quot;This is my body&quot;, even though bread and body are two distinct substances, and the word &quot;this&quot; indicates the bread? Here, too, out of two kinds of objects a union has taken place, which I shall call a &quot;sacramental union&quot;, because Christ's body and the bread are given to us as a sacrament. This is not a natural or personal union, as is the case with God and Christ. It is also perhaps a different union from that which the dove has with the Holy Spirit, and the flame with the angel, but it is also assuredly a sacramental union.&lt;ref&gt;''Weimar Ausgabe'' 26, 442; ''Luther's Works'' 37, 299-300.&lt;/ref&gt;

What Luther thus called a &quot;[[sacramental union]]&quot; is often called [[consubstantiation]] by non-Lutherans.

In &quot;On the Babylonian Captivity&quot; Luther upheld belief in the Real Presence of Jesus and in his 1523 treatise [[The Adoration of the Sacrament]] defended adoration of the body and blood of Christ in the Eucharist.

[[Huldrych Zwingli]] taught that the sacrament is purely symbolic and memorial in character, arguing that this was the meaning of Jesus' instruction: &quot;Do this in remembrance of me&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|11:23-26||}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Thirty-nine articles]] of religion in the Church of England declare: &quot;Transubstantiation (or the change of the substance of Bread and Wine) in the Supper of the Lord, cannot be proved by holy Writ; but is repugnant to the plain words of Scripture, overthroweth the nature of a Sacrament, and hath given occasion to many superstitions&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;[[Thirty-Nine Articles]], article 28&lt;/ref&gt; and made [[Mass (liturgy)|Mass]] illegal.&lt;ref&gt;[http://writ.news.findlaw.com/books/reviews/20050107_leavitt.html The Literature of Persecution and Intolerance]; [http://www.worldwideschool.org/library/books/relg/historygeography/HistoryoftheCatholicChurchfromtheRenaissancetotheFrenchRevolutionVolume2/chap8.html James MacCaffrey, vol. 2]; [http://www.tanbooks.com/doct/margaret_martyr.htm St. Margaret Clitherow]&lt;/ref&gt;

==In Roman Catholic theology==
{{see|Substance theory}}
&quot;Substance&quot; here means what something is in itself. A hat's shape is not the hat itself, nor is its colour, size, softness to the touch, nor anything else about it perceptible to the senses. The hat itself (the &quot;substance&quot;) ''has'' the shape, the color, the size, the softness and the other appearances, but is distinct from them.&lt;ref&gt;This illustration is given in [http://books.google.com/books?ei=DfqWTNTxIpHBswb30Yxb&amp;ct=result&amp;id=4cU9AAAAIAAJ&amp;dq=Catholic+Evidence+Training+Outlines&amp;q=hat#search_anchor Maisie Ward and F. J. Sheed, ''Catholic Evidence Training Outlines'' (Sheed &amp; Ward, third edition 1935), p. 240.]&lt;/ref&gt; While the appearances, which are referred to by the philosophical term [[accident (philosophy)|accidents]], are perceptible to the senses, the substance is not.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The word 'substance' as here used is not a technical philosophical term, such as might be found in the philosophy of Aristotle.  It was used in the early Middle Ages long before the works of Aristotle were current.  'Substance' in common-sense usage denotes the basic reality of the thing, i.e., what it is in itself.  Derived from the Latin root 'sub-stare', it means what stands under the appearances, which can shift from one moment to the next while leaving the subject intact.  Appearances can be deceptive.  You might fail to recognize me when I put on a disguise or when I become seriously ill, but I do not cease to be the person that I was; my substance is unchanged.  There is nothing obscure, then, about the meaning of 'substance' in this context&quot; ([http://www.30giorni.it/us/articolo.asp?id=9352 [[Avery Dulles]]: Christ's Presence in the Eucharist: True, Real and Substantial).]&lt;/ref&gt;

Consider the [[Classical antiquity|classic example]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Plato]], [[Aristotle]], [[Augustine]], [[Plotinus]], [[Thomas Aquinas]], [[Duns Scotus]], [[Bonaventure]], et al.  ''For more detailed treatment and bibliographical links and references see'' [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/11090c.htm The Catholic Encyclopedia, ''&quot;Nominalism, Realism, and Conceptualism&quot;''], [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/universals-medieval/ Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy, ''&quot;The Medieval Problem of Universals&quot;''], and [http://www.friesian.com/universl.htm &quot;Meaning and the Problem of Universals, ''A Kant-Friesian Approach''&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; of the [[Human nature|human body]].  All of the separate chemical compounds, minerals and water—which when piled together constitute the sum total of the actual physical matter of the human body—are not of themselves a human body, however much they may be physically compounded and mixed and rearranged in the laboratory, since they are still only a pile of organic chemicals, minerals and water in a particular complex configuration.  If this has never been alive it is not a human body.  If they are ''[[composition (logical fallacy)#Modo hoc fallacy|participant]]'' in the integral physical expression of a living human being who has absorbed and metabolized them, or if they are now the physical remains of a once-living human being, the substance of what they actually are is human, hence, a human body.  The substantial reality of what is before us is human. The ''substance'' (substantial reality) of what is seen is not solely that of a complex organization of organic chemical compounds, but is (or has been) someone.  The chemical elements of the food a person eats become in a few hours part of that person's human body and are no longer food but have been turned into the human flesh and blood and bone of that person, yet the physical chemical elements of what was once food remain the same (calcium, copper, salt, protein, sugars, fats, water, etc.).  The ''substance'' of any matter that has become an integral part of any human being has ceased to be the ''substance'' or ''reality'' of ''food'' and has become incorporated as an integral part of the physical manifestation or expression of that ''human person''.  To touch that matter now is not to touch a batch of chemical compounds or food but to touch that [[Human nature#Spiritual versus nature|person]].&lt;ref&gt;''see also'' [[Moderate realism]] ''and'' [[Ontologism]] ''for influences found within the specifically Catholic interpretation of the reality of the human person underlying the outward physical appearance that is the human body.  see also ''[[Soul (spirit)|soul]]'' and ''[[incarnation]].&lt;/ref&gt;

When at his [[Last Supper]], [[Jesus]] said: &quot;This is my body&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Matthew|26:26}}, {{bibleverse||Mark|14:22}}, {{bibleverse||Luke|22:19||}}, {{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|11:24}}&lt;/ref&gt; what he held in his hands still had all the ''appearances'' of bread: these &quot;accidents&quot; remained unchanged. However, the Roman Catholic Church believes that, when Jesus made that declaration,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P41.HTM ''Catechism of the Catholic Church, 1356-1381,'' number '''1376''']&lt;/ref&gt; the ''underlying reality'' (the &quot;substance&quot;) of the bread was converted to that of his body. In other words, it ''actually was'' his body, while all the appearances open to the senses or to scientific investigation were still those of bread, exactly as before. The Catholic Church holds that the same change of the substance of the bread and of the wine occurs at the [[consecration]] of the Eucharist&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P41.HTM ''Catechism of the Catholic Church, 1356-1381,'' number '''1377''']; ''and'' [http://www.30giorni.it/us/articolo.asp?id=9352 Christ's Presence in the Eucharist: True, Real and Substantial]&lt;/ref&gt; when the [[Words of Institution|words]] are spoken &quot;This is my body ... this is my blood.&quot;  In Orthodox confessions, the change is said to take place during the [[Epiklesis]].

Believing that [[Christ]] is risen from the dead and is alive, the Catholic Church holds that when the bread is changed into his body, not only his body is present, but Christ as a whole is present (i.e. body and blood, soul and divinity.) The same holds for the wine changed into his blood.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P44.HTM ''Catechism of the Catholic Church, 1406-1409,'' number '''1413''']&lt;/ref&gt; This belief goes beyond the doctrine of transubstantiation, which directly concerns only the transformation of the bread and wine into the body and blood of Christ.

In accordance with this belief that Christ is really, truly and substantially present under the remaining appearances of bread and wine, and continues to be present as long as those appearances remain, the Catholic Church preserves the consecrated elements, generally in a [[church tabernacle]], for administering Holy Communion to the sick and dying, and also for the secondary, but still highly prized, purpose of [[Eucharistic adoration|adoring Christ present in the Eucharist]].

The Roman Catholic Church considers the doctrine of transubstantiation to be concerned with ''what'' is changed, and not ''how'' the change occurs; it teaches that the [[accident (philosophy)|accidents]] that remain are real, not an illusion, and that Christ is &quot;really, truly, and ''substantially'' present&quot; in the Eucharist.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P41.HTM ''Catechism of the Catholic Church, 1356-1381,'' number '''1374''']&lt;/ref&gt;  To touch the smallest particle of the [[Sacramental bread|host]] or the smallest droplet from the [[chalice]] is to touch Jesus Christ himself, as when one person touches another on the back of the hand with only a fingertip and in so doing touches not merely a few skin cells but touches the whole person:  &quot;Christ is present whole and entire in each of the species and whole and entire in each of their parts, in such a way that the breaking of the bread does not divide Christ.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P41.HTM ''Catechism of the Catholic Church, 1356-1381,'' number '''1377'''], '''''Cf.''''' [[Council of Trent]]: DS 1641:  &quot;Nor should it be forgotten that Christ, whole and entire, is contained not only under either species, but also in each particle of either species.  ''Each,'' says St. Augustine, ''receives Christ the Lord, and He is entire in each portion.  He is not diminished by being given to many, but gives Himself whole and entire to each.''&quot; (Quoted in Gratian, p. 3, dist. ii. c. 77; Ambrosian Mass, Preface for Fifth Sunday after Epiph.)  —''[[Roman Catechism|The Catechism of the Council of Trent]] for Parish Priests, issued by order of Pope Pius V, translated into English with Notes by John A. McHugh, O.P., S.T.M., Litt. D., and Charles J. Callan, O.P., S.T.M., Litt. D.'', © 1982 by TAN Books and Publishers, Inc., Rockford, Illinois 61105, p. 249 &quot;Christ Whole and Entire Present in Every Part of Each Species&quot; {{cite book |isbn=978-0-89555-185-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In the arguments which characterised the relationship between Roman Catholicism and Protestantism in the 16th century, the [[Council of Trent]] declared subject to the ecclesiastical penalty of [[Anathema#Roman Catholic Church|anathema]] anyone who: 
:&quot;'''denieth''', that, in the sacrament of the most holy Eucharist, are contained truly, really, and substantially, the body and blood together with the soul and divinity of our Lord Jesus Christ, and consequently the whole Christ; '''but saith''' that He is only therein as in a sign, or in figure, or virtue&quot; and anyone who &quot;'''saith''', that, in the sacred and holy sacrament of the Eucharist, the substance of the bread and wine remains conjointly with the body and blood of our Lord Jesus Christ, '''and denieth''' that wonderful and singular conversion of the whole substance of the bread into the Body, and of the whole substance of the wine into the Blood - the species only of the bread and wine remaining - which conversion indeed the Catholic Church most aptly calls Transubstantiation, let him be anathema.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;history.hanover.edu&quot;/&gt;

Protestant denominations have not generally subscribed to belief in transubstantiation or [[consubstantiation]].

As already stated, the Roman Catholic Church insists that the &quot;accidents&quot; that remain are real. In the sacrament these are the ''signs'' of the reality that they efficaciously signify.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P3Z.HTM ''Catechism of the Catholic Church, 1333-1344,'' numbers '''1333-1336'''] ''under the heading'' &quot;'''III. The Eucharist in the Economy of Salvation'''  The signs of bread and wine&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; And by definition [[sacrament]]s are &quot;efficacious signs of grace, instituted by Christ and entrusted to the Catholic Church, by which divine life is dispensed to us.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P35.HTM ''Catechism of the Catholic Church, 1131-1134,'' number '''1131''']&lt;/ref&gt;

==Interpretations of Biblical evidence==
[[Image:Codex Bruchsal 1 28r.jpg|thumb|The [[Last Supper]] (upper image) and preparatory washing of feet (lower image) in a 1220 manuscript in the Badische Landesbibliothek]]
Those who believe that in the Eucharist the bread and wine become instead the body and blood of Christ see this as plainly indicated in the [[New Testament]], both in the Eucharistic discourse given by [[Jesus Christ|Christ]] in John 6, and in 1st Corinthians 11, where St. Paul several times equates the body and blood of Jesus with the &quot;bread&quot; and &quot;cup of benediction&quot; used in the Eucharist. Christians who deny that there is such a change (transubstantiation) deny that the New Testament teaches it. Some of them even see the New Testament as contradicting it.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

Eastern Orthodox, Oriental Orthodox, and Roman Catholics, who together constitute the [[List of Christian denominations by number of members|majority of Christians]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adherents.com/adh_branches.html Major Branches of Religions Ranked by Number of Adherents]&lt;/ref&gt; hold that the consecrated elements in a valid celebration of the Eucharist indeed become the body and blood of Christ. This belief is held also by some Reform and Protestant Christian churches, Lutherans and Anglicans,&lt;ref&gt;[http://anglicanhistory.org/england/cps/black.html Transubstantiation and the Black Rubric]; and see [[Anglican Eucharistic theology]]&lt;/ref&gt; though they generally deny transubstantiation.

While there is a large body of theology noting the many Scriptural supports for transubstantiation, in general, Orthodox and Catholics consider it unnecessary to &quot;prove&quot; from texts of Scripture a belief that they see as held by Christians without interruption from the earliest, apostolic times.  They point out that the Church and its teaching existed before it assembled and canonized the New Testament, and even before any individual part of the New Testament was written.&lt;ref&gt;See, for instance, '''''Eastern Orthodoxy:'''''  [http://www.goarch.org/ourfaith/ourfaith7065 The Twelve Apostles], [http://www.goarch.org/ourfaith/ourfaith8032 Introduction: What is the Greek Orthodox Church?], [http://www.goarch.org/ourfaith/ourfaith8131 Unity and Autocephaly: Mutually Exclusive?], [http://www.goarch.org/ourfaith/ourfaith8038 The Dogmatic Tradition of the Orthodox Church]'''; ''Catholicism:''''' [http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__PJ.HTM Catechism of the Catholic Church, 74], [http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__PK.HTM 75-79], [http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__PL.HTM 80-83].&lt;/ref&gt; They also point out that [[Early Christianity|early Christians]] such as [[Ignatius of Antioch]], [[Justin Martyr]], and [[Clement of Rome]] (who were much closer to the event than those who have later proposed a figurative interpretation of the Eucharist), described the Eucharist as truly the body and blood of Christ.
They see nothing in Scripture that in any way contradicts this age-old Christian belief that the reality beneath the visible signs in the Eucharist is the body and blood of Christ and no longer bread and wine. Instead, they see this teaching as the same teaching in the Bible's reports of what Christ himself and [[Paul the Apostle]] taught.

As the scriptural support required by their [[sola scriptura]] position, Protestants who believe that in the Eucharist the bread and wine become the body and blood of Christ turn to the words of Jesus himself at his [[Last Supper]], as reported in the [[Synoptic Gospels]]&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Mark|14:22-24}}; {{bibleverse||Matthew|26:26-28}}; {{bibleverse||Luke|22:19-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Saint Paul's [[First Epistle to the Corinthians]].&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|11:23-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; In that context, Jesus said of what to all appearances were bread and wine: &quot;This is my body … this is my blood&quot; or, in the case of what appeared to be wine, &quot;… this cup is the new covenant in my blood&quot;.

Many Protestants reject a literal interpretation of these words. They compare them to non-literal expressions by Jesus such as &quot;I am the door&quot;, &quot;I am the vine&quot;, &quot;You are the salt of the earth ... You are the light of the world&quot; ({{bibleverse||Matthew|5:13-14}}),&quot;Beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and the Sadducees&quot; ({{bibleverse||Matthew|16:6-12}}). In this last example, the disciples thought that the reason Jesus said it was because they had brought no bread; but Jesus explained that he was referring to the ''teaching'' of the Pharisees and the Sadducees.  

These Protestants add that &quot;eating and drinking&quot; is sometimes used metaphorically, as of Jeremiah &quot;eating&quot; God's words ({{bibleverse||Jeremiah|15:16}}), or David speaking of water as blood, since it was obtained at the risk of the lives of his men ({{bibleverse|2|Samuel|23:17}}).
 
Those who hold that Jesus' words, &quot;This is my body&quot;, &quot;This is my blood&quot;, were not metaphorical claim that there is a marked contrast between metaphorical figurative expressions, which of their nature have a symbolic meaning, and what Jesus said about concrete things such as the bread and wine. 

In the phrase &quot;This is my body&quot;as expressed in the original Greek (Τοῦτό ἐστιν τὸ σῶμά μου), the word &quot;τοῦτο&quot; (&quot;this&quot; or &quot;this thing&quot;) is a grammatically neuter pronoun, and so of the same grammatical gender as  the noun &quot;σῶμα&quot; (body), but of a different grammatical gender from that of the word &quot;ἄρτος&quot; (bread), which is a masculine noun. Some claim that this is an indication of the change of the reality from bread (ἄρτος) to body (σῶμα).&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=GiQQAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA7&amp;dq=%22come+hither%22+%22rule+of+syntax%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=zxo5Tu37C8-xhQfysfmzAg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false ''Come Hither'' (London: Wertheim, Macintosh, and Hunt 1863), p. 7]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;tbo=1&amp;q=%22institution+touto%22+George+Huntston+Williams&amp;btnG= George Huntston Williams, ''The Radical Reformation'' (Truman State University Press 1992 ISBN 978-0-940474-15-4)]&lt;/ref&gt;

As indications that the bread and wine are indeed changed to the body and blood of Christ, appeal is made to expressions used by Saint Paul in his [[First Epistle to the Corinthians]], in particular his rhetorical question, &quot;The cup of blessing that we bless, is it not a participation in the blood of Christ? The bread that we break, is it not a participation in the body of Christ?&quot; ({{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|10:16|ESV}}), and his statement, &quot;Whoever, therefore, eats the bread or drinks the cup of the Lord in an unworthy manner will be guilty concerning the body and blood of the Lord.&quot; ({{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|11:27|ESV}}).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ethiopianorthodox.org/english/dogma/sacaracommunion.html The Sacrament of the Holy Communion]&lt;/ref&gt; Protestant commentators, such as [[Matthew Henry]] (1662–1714) say that use of the word &quot;bread&quot; shows there has been no change.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=snJAAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA112&amp;dq=matthew+henry+commentary+corinthians&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=XF_7TcnYForLhAfOpsmZAw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CDQQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Matthew Henry, ''A Commentary upon the Holy Bible'' (Religious Tract Society, London 1835), p.. 155]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblestudytools.com/commentaries/matthew-henry-complete/1-corinthians/11.html?p=5 Online version]&lt;/ref&gt;

Paul's subsequent recommendation, &quot;Let a person examine himself, then, and so eat of the bread and drink of the cup. For anyone who eats and drinks without discerning the body eats and drinks judgment on himself&quot; ({{bibleverse|2|Corinthians|11:28-29}}), has likewise been interpreted either as indicating the reality of the disputed change or as implying no such change. Marvin R. Vincent, in particular, objected to what he called the mistaken [[King James Version]] translation  of κρῖμα in verse 29 as &quot;damnation&quot;, rather more literally as &quot;judgment&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sacred-texts.com/bib/cmt/vws/co1011.htm Vincent's Word Studies]&lt;/ref&gt;

It has been noted that Paul wrote: &quot;Whoever, therefore, eats the bread ''or'' drinks the cup of the Lord in an unworthy manner will be guilty concerning the body ''and'' blood of the Lord&quot; (emphases added).&lt;ref&gt;The King James Version translators wrote: &quot;Wherefore whosoever shall eat this bread, ''and'' drink this cup of the Lord, unworthily, shall be guilty of the body and blood of the Lord ({{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|11:27|KJV}}, emphasis added), but the word in the original Greek text is ἤ (or), not καί (and).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.drbo.org/chapter/53011.htm Note on verse 27]&lt;/ref&gt; This has been interpreted as stating that unworthy participation of either the bread or the cup of the Lord involves guilt concerning both the body and blood of the Lord, an indication of the  presence of Christ in each of the two cases.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.veritasbible.com/drb/compare/haydock/1_Corinthians_11:27 Haydock's Commentary]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catholicapologetics.info/apologetics/general/Christ.htm The Holy Eucharist]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://oce.catholic.com/index.php?title=Utraquism Utraquism]&lt;/ref&gt;

Another Scripture text that Catholics generally understand as related to the Eucharist is the [[Gospel of John]]'s account of Jesus as saying: &quot;Unless you eat the flesh of the [[Son of Man]] and drink his blood you have no life in you … he who eats my flesh and drinks my blood abides in me and I in him&quot; ({{bibleverse-nb||John|6:53-56}}), a statement that he did not tone down when, as a result, many of his [[Disciple (Christianity)|disciples]] then abandoned him ({{bibleverse-nb||John|6:66}}), shocked at the idea.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catholic-convert.com/2009/05/12/the-eucharist-the-flesh-profits-nothing/ The Eucharist: the Flesh Profits Nothing]&lt;/ref&gt; Protestants tend to interpret this passage in connection with {{bibleverse||John|6:63}}, where Jesus says &quot;the flesh profits nothing, the words that I speak unto you, they are spirit, and they are life&quot;, which they say means that the redeemed live by faith. Some also invoke {{bibleverse||John|6:57|NIV}}, &quot;Just as the living Father sent me and I live because of the Father, so the one who feeds on me will live because of me&quot;,  describing how one &quot;lives&quot;.

==Views in other churches==
===Eastern Christianity===
The [[Eastern Rite Catholic Churches|Eastern Catholic]], [[Oriental Orthodoxy|Oriental Orthodox]] and [[Eastern Orthodox Church]]es, along with the [[Assyrian Church of the East]], agree that in a valid [[Divine Liturgy]] bread and wine truly and actually become the body and blood of Christ. They have in general refrained from philosophical speculation, and usually rely on the status of the doctrine as a &quot;Mystery,&quot; something known by divine revelation that could not have been arrived at by reason without revelation. Accordingly, they prefer not to elaborate upon the details and remain firmly within Holy Tradition, than to say too much and possibly deviate from the truth. However, there are official church documents that speak of a &quot;change&quot; (in [[Greek language|Greek]] {{lang|grc|μεταβολή}}) or &quot;[[metousiosis]]&quot; ({{lang|grc|μετουσίωσις}}) of the bread and wine. &quot;Μετ-ουσί-ωσις&quot; (''met-ousi-osis'') is the Greek word used to represent the Latin word &quot;''trans-substanti-atio''&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/creeds1.v.vii.html The Synod of Jerusalem and the Confession of Dositheus, A.D. 1672]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Holy Orthodox Church at the Synod of Jerusalem (date 1643 A.D.) used the word metousiosis--a change of ousia--to translate the Latin Transubstantiatio&quot; ([http://anglicanhistory.org/england/cps/black.html Transubstantiation and the Black Rubric).]&lt;/ref&gt; as Greek &quot;μετα-μόρφ-ωσις&quot; (''meta-morph-osis'') corresponds to Latin &quot;''trans-figur-atio''&quot;. Examples of official documents of the Eastern Orthodox Church that use the term &quot;μετουσίωσις&quot; or &quot;transubstantiation&quot; are the [http://www.pravoslavieto.com/docs/eng/Orthodox_Catechism_of_Philaret.htm Longer Catechism of The Orthodox, Catholic, Eastern Church] (question 340) and the declaration by the Eastern Orthodox [[Synod of Jerusalem]] of 1672:
:&quot;In the celebration of [the Eucharist] we believe the Lord Jesus Christ to be present. He is not present typically, nor figuratively, nor by superabundant grace, as in the other Mysteries, nor by a bare presence, as some of the Fathers have said concerning Baptism, or by [[impanation]], so that the Divinity of the Word is united to the set forth bread of the Eucharist hypostatically, as the followers of Luther most ignorantly and wretchedly suppose. But [he is present] truly and really, so that after the consecration of the bread and of the wine, the bread is ''transmuted, transubstantiated, converted and transformed'' into the true Body Itself of the Lord, Which was born in Bethlehem of the ever-Virgin, was baptized in the Jordan, suffered, was buried, rose again, was received up, sits at the right hand of the God and Father, and is to come again in the clouds of Heaven; and the wine is converted and transubstantiated into the true Blood Itself of the Lord, Which as He hung upon the Cross, was poured out for the life of the world.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cresourcei.org/creeddositheus.html Confession of Dositheus] (emphasis added) The Greek text is quoted in an [http://www.constantinosa.gr/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=149:2010-06-04-10-24-07&amp;catid=2:2010-05-27-14-43-36&amp;Itemid=8 online extract] from the 1915 book &quot;Μελέται περί των Θείων Μυστηρίων&quot; (Studies on the Divine Mysteries/Sacraments) by Saint Nektarios.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Anglicanism===
During the reign of King [[Henry VIII of England]], the official teaching was identical with the Roman Catholic Church's doctrine before and after Henry's break with Rome by declaring that the Pope had no jurisdiction in England.  A decade before the break the king wrote a book in defence of Catholic doctrine for which the Pope rewarded him with the title of [[Fidei defensor|Defender of the Faith]], a title revoked by the Pope following Henry's break with Rome but still claimed and held by English and, after 1707, British monarchs after being bestowed on the monarch by Parliament.  Under Henry's son, [[Edward VI of England|Edward VI]], the [[Church of England]] began to accept some aspects of Protestant theology and rejected transubstantiation. [[Elizabeth I of England|Elizabeth I]], as part of the [[Elizabethan Religious Settlement]], gave royal assent to the [[Thirty-Nine Articles]] of Religion, which sought to distinguish Anglican from Roman Church doctrine.  The Articles declared that &quot;Transubstantiation (or the change of the substance of Bread and Wine) in the Supper of the Lord, cannot be proved by holy Writ; but is repugnant to the plain words of Scripture, overthroweth the nature of a Sacrament, and hath given occasion to many superstitions.&quot; Indeed for many years it was illegal in Britain to hold public office whilst believing in transubstantiation, as under the [[Test Act|Test Act of 1673]]. Archbishop [[John Tillotson]] decried the &quot;real barbarousness of this Sacrament and Rite of our Religion&quot;, considering it a great [[impiety]] to believe that people who attend [[Eucharist|Holy Communion]] &quot;verily eat and drink the natural flesh and blood of Christ.  And what can any man do more unworthily towards a Friend?  How can he possibly use him more barbarously, than to feast upon his living flesh and blood?&quot; (''Discourse against Transubstantiation'', London 1684, 35). 

Anglicans generally consider no teaching binding that, according to the Articles, &quot;cannot be found in Holy Scripture or proved thereby&quot;, and are not unanimous in the interpretation of such passages as John, Chapter 6, and 1 Corinthians 11. Consequently, some Anglicans (especially [[Anglo-Catholics]] and some other [[High Church]] Anglicans) accept transubstantiation while most Anglicans do not.  In any case, nowadays even [[Church of England]] clergy are only required to assent that the [[Thirty-nine Articles]] have borne witness to the Christian faith.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cofe.anglican.org/worship/liturgy/commonworship/texts/books/mv/preface.html The Declaration of Assent]&lt;/ref&gt; 

In some Anglican churches other than the Church of England even this is not required. 

Official writings of the churches of the [[Anglican Communion]] have consistently upheld belief in the Real Presence, a term that includes transubstantiation as well as several other eucharistic theologies such as [[consubstantiation]], [[transignification]], and the purely spiritual presence affirmed by the [[Thirty Nine Articles]]. {{Citation needed|date=January 2009}}  Some recent Anglican writers explicitly accept the doctrine of transubstantiation&lt;ref&gt;[http://anglicanhistory.org/england/cps/black.html Transubstantiation and the Black Rubric] by the [http://anglicanhistory.org/england/cps/index.html Catholic Propaganda Society] within the [[Church of England]]&lt;/ref&gt; or, while avoiding the term &quot;transubstantiation&quot;, speak of an &quot;objective presence&quot; of Christ in the Eucharist. The term &quot;objective presence&quot; includes a belief in transubstantiation but does not limit belief to transubstantiation.  

Theological dialogue with the Roman Catholic Church has produced common documents that speak of &quot;substantial agreement&quot; about the doctrine of the Eucharist: the ARCIC Windsor Statement of 1971,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.prounione.urbe.it/dia-int/arcic/doc/e_arcic_eucharist.html Pro Unione Web Site - Full Text ARCIC Eucharist&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and its 1979 Elucidation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.prounione.urbe.it/dia-int/arcic/doc/e_arcic_elucid_euch.html Pro Unione Web Site - Full Text ARCIC Elucidation Eucharist&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Remaining arguments can be found in the Church of England's pastoral letter: ''The Eucharist: Sacrament of Unity''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cofe.anglican.org/info/ccu/england/catholics/eucharist.pdf Eucharist 2&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lutheranism===
Luther explicitly rejected transubstantiation, believing that the bread and wine remained fully bread and fully wine while also being fully the body and blood of Jesus Christ.  Luther instead emphasized the [[sacramental union]] (not exactly the [[consubstantiation]], as it is often claimed). Lutherans believe that within the Eucharistic celebration the body and blood of Jesus Christ are objectively present &quot;in, with, and under the forms&quot; of bread and wine (cf. [[Book of Concord]]). They place great stress on Jesus' instructions to &quot;take and eat&quot;, and &quot;take and drink&quot;, holding that this is the proper, divinely ordained use of the sacrament, and, while giving it due reverence, scrupulously avoid any actions that might indicate or lead to superstition or unworthy fear of the sacrament.

===Other Protestants===
Many Protestant denominations believe that the Lord's Supper is a merely symbolic act done in remembrance of what Christ has done for them on the cross. For example, according to the Official Creed of the Assemblies of God - an Evangelical Protestant church - Holy Communion, or &quot;The Lord's Supper, consisting of the elements--bread and the fruit of the vine--is the symbol expressing our sharing the divine nature of our Lord Jesus Christ ({{bibleverse|2|Peter|1:4}}); a memorial of His suffering and death, and a prophecy of His suffering and death ({{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|11:26}}); and is enjoined on all believers &quot;till He come!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bible.ca/cr-assemblies-of-god.htm Official Creed of Assemblies of God]&lt;/ref&gt; He commanded the [[Twelve Apostles|apostles]]: &quot;This do in remembrance of me&quot;, after &quot;he took bread, and gave thanks, and broke it, and gave unto them, saying, This is my body which is given for you&quot; ({{bibleverse||Luke|22:19}}, {{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|11:24}}). Therefore they see it as a symbolic act done in remembrance and as a declaration ({{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|11:26}}) of faith in what they consider Christ's ''finished'' ({{bibleverse||John|19:30}}) work on the cross. They see the historical Last Supper as being not a literal event as Catholics do where Jesus; that is, Jesus humanly present in flesh and blood simultaneously shared out his sacramental Body and Blood under the appearances of bread and wine to his disciples, but as a prophetic act: in stating &quot;This is my body&quot;, &quot;This is the cup of my blood&quot;, Jesus was giving a figure of the sacrifice he would make upon the Cross the following day. Other Protestants also reject the idea that a priest, acting, he believes, in the name of Christ, not in his own name, can transform bread and wine into the actual body and blood of God incarnate in Jesus Christ, and many of them see the doctrine as a problem because of its connection with practices such as [[Eucharistic adoration]], which they believe may be [[idolatry]].&lt;ref&gt;According to Boswell's [http://andromeda.rutgers.edu/~jlynch/Texts/BLJ/b424.html Life of Johnson], [[Samuel Johnson]] responded to such views:  &quot;Sir, there is no idolatry in the Mass. They believe GOD to be there, and they adore him.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; They base their criticism of the doctrine of transubstantiation (and also of the [[Real Presence]]) on a number of verses of the Bible, including {{bibleverse||Exodus|20:4-5}}, and on their interpretation of the central message of the Gospel. Scripture does not explicitly say &quot;the bread was transformed&quot; or &quot;changed&quot; in any way, and therefore they consider the doctrine of transubstantiation to be unbiblical from more than one approach. As already stated above, they also object to using [[early Christian]] writings to support belief that the bread of the Lord's Supper is more than a metaphor for Christ's body, because such writings are not Scripture nor writings that were able to be verified by any prophet or apostle, especially when they believe such doctrines contradict inspired Scripture.  

Protestant denominations, such as [[Methodists]] and some [[Presbyterian]]s, profess belief in the Real Presence, but offer explanations other than transubstantiation. Classical Presbyterianism held the Calvinist view of &quot;pneumatic&quot; presence or &quot;spiritual feeding.&quot; However, when the [[Presbyterian Church (USA)]] signed &quot;[http://archive.elca.org/ecumenical/fullcommunion/formula/official_text.html A Formula for Agreement]&quot; with the [[Evangelical Lutheran Church in America]], both affirmed belief in the Real Presence. [[John Calvin]] &quot;can be regarded as occupying a position roughly midway between&quot; (McGrath) the doctrines developed by Martin Luther on the one hand and Huldrych Zwingli, on the other: &quot;Believers ought always to live by this rule: whenever they see symbols appointed by the Lord, to think and be convinced that the truth of the thing signified is surely present there. For why should the Lord put in your hand the symbol of his body, unless it was to assure you that you really participate in it? And if it is true that a visible sign is given to us to seal the gift of an invisible thing, when we have received the symbol of the body, let us rest assured that the body itself is also given to us.&quot; (Calvin); that is, &quot;the thing that is signified is effected by its sign&quot; (McGrath).&lt;ref&gt;McGrath, op.cit., p.199.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Latter-day Saints ===
[[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] does not believe in literal transubstantiation, but rather that the bread and wine (or bread and water, as is used in modern LDS churches) are simply symbolic of Jesus Christ's sacrificial [[Atonement in Christianity|Atonement]] for mankind.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.lds.org/manual/gospel-principles?lang=eng Gospel Principles]'', (Salt Lake City: The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, 2011), 133.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Conceptual art==
''[[An Oak Tree]]'' is a [[conceptual art]] installation in the [[Tate Modern]], consisting of a glass of water, which the artist, [[Michael Craig-Martin]], declared he had turned into &quot;a full-grown oak tree&quot;, &quot;without altering the accidents of the glass of water&quot;.&lt;ref name =CMtext&gt;[http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/~ig206/oak_tree.html Artist's Text]&lt;/ref&gt; The text he included as part of his work states: &quot;It's not a symbol. I have changed the physical substance of the glass of water into that of an oak tree. I didn't change its appearance. The actual oak tree is physically present, but in the form of a glass of water.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;CMtext&quot;/&gt; In a [[Richard Dimbleby Lecture]], on 23 November 2000, [[Sir Nicholas Serota]] said: &quot;We may not 'like' Craig-Martin's work, but it certainly reminds us that the appreciation of all art involves an act of faith comparable to the belief that, through transubstantiation, the bread and wine of Holy Communion become the body and blood of Christ.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.independent.co.uk/opinion/commentators/theres-no-need-to-be-afraid-of-the-present-625001.html | location=London | work=The Independent | title=There's no need to be afraid of the present | date=2000-11-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Consubstantiation]]
*[[Eucharistic Miracle]]
*[[Host desecration]]
*[[Impanation]]
*[[Memorialism]]
*[[New Covenant]]
*[[Nominalism]]
*[[Real presence of Christ in the Eucharist]]
*[[Sacramental union]]
*[[Transignification]]

==References==
;Notes
{{Reflist|2}}

;Bibliography
* Burckhardt Neunheuser, &quot;Transsubstantiation.&quot; ''Lexikon für Theologie und Kirche'', vol. 10, cols. 311-14.
* Miri Rubin, ''Corpus Christi: The Eucharist in Late Medieval Culture'' (1991), pp.&amp;nbsp;369–419.
* Otto Semmelroth, ''Eucharistische Wandlung: Transsubstantation, Transfinalisation, Transsignifikation'' (Kevelaer: Butzon &amp; Bercker, 1967).
* Richard J. Utz and Christine Batz, &quot;Transubstantiation in Medieval and Early Modern Culture and Literature: An Introductory Bibliography of Critical Studies,&quot; in: ''Translation, Transformation, and Transubstantiation'', ed. Carol Poster and Richard Utz (Evanston: IL: Northwestern University Press, 1998), pp.&amp;nbsp;223–56.&quot;

==External links==
*[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/05573a.htm#3 &quot;Transubstantiation&quot; in ''Catholic Encyclopedia'']
*[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/paul_vi/encyclicals/documents/hf_p-vi_enc_03091965_mysterium_en.html Pope Paul VI: Encyclical ''Mysterium Fidei'']
*[http://www.ewtn.com/library/papaldoc/p6credo.htm Pope Paul VI: ''Credo of the People of God'']
*[http://www.bringyou.to/apologetics/num31.htm Eastern Orthodox Church statements on transubstantiation/metousiosis]
*[http://www.catholicculture.org/culture/library/view.cfm?recnum=1192 The Antiquity of the Doctrine of Transubstantiation]

&lt;!--spacing--&gt;

{{Christian theology|collapsed}}
{{Roman Catholic Theology|collapsed}}
{{CatholicMass|collapsed}}

[[Category:Roman Catholic Eucharistic theology]]
[[Category:Catholic theology and doctrine]]
[[Category:Eucharist]]
[[Category:Eucharist (Catholic Church)]]
[[Category:Doctrines and teachings of Jesus]]
[[Category:Christian miracle narrative]]
[[Category:Belief]]
[[Category:Theology]]
[[Category:Religion and science]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]

[[ca:Transsubstanciació]]
[[cs:Transsubstanciace]]
[[de:Transsubstantiation]]
[[es:Transubstanciación]]
[[eo:Transsubstancigo]]
[[fr:Transsubstantiation]]
[[ko:성변화]]
[[hr:Pretvorba (transupstancijacija)]]
[[id:Transubstansiasi]]
[[ia:Transubstantiation]]
[[it:Transustanziazione]]
[[he:טרנסובסטנציאציה]]
[[la:Transubstantiatio]]
[[hu:Transzszubsztanciáció]]
[[ml:പദാർത്ഥാന്തരീകരണം]]
[[nl:Transsubstantiatie]]
[[ja:聖変化]]
[[no:Transsubstansiasjon]]
[[nn:Transsubstansiasjon]]
[[pl:Transsubstancjacja]]
[[pt:Transubstanciação]]
[[ru:Пресуществление]]
[[simple:Transubstantiation]]
[[sh:Transupstancijacija]]
[[fi:Transsubstantiaatio]]
[[sv:Transsubstantiation]]
[[uk:Пресуществління]]</text>
      <sha1>ralrcjfmjukruplg9yjofwo9407tk2z</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
