<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Unitarian Universalist Association</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>31903</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518113862</id>
      <parentid>517678701</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-16T12:54:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Naraht</username>
        <id>230475</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>link [[Boy Scouts of America]] using [[User:Edward/Find link|Find link]]-</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22594">{{Redirect|UUA}}
{{Infobox Organization
|name         = Unitarian Universalist Association of Congregations in North America
|image        = UUA_Logo.svg
|size         =
|caption      = The official logo of the UUA, based upon the [[flaming chalice]] motif.
|abbreviation = UUA
|formation    = May 1961
|extinction   =
|type         = [[Religious organization]]
|purpose      = To serve Unitarian Universalist congregations primarily in the
[[United States]]
|headquarters = [[Boston]], [[Massachusetts]], United States
|location     = United States
|affiliations = [[International Council of Unitarians and Universalists]]
|membership   = 162,796  (adult members)&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;[http://www.uuworld.org/news/articles/183612.shtml]&lt;/ref&gt;
|language     =
|leader_title = President
|leader_name  = [[Peter Morales]]
|key_people   =
|num_staff    =
|budget       =
|website      = [http://www.uua.org www.uua.org]
}}

[[File:Sepulveda Unitarian Universalist Society Sanctuary.PNG|thumb|right|Sepulveda Unitarian Universalist Society Sanctuary &quot;The Onion&quot;, in the [[San Fernando Valley]].]]

'''Unitarian Universalist Association''' ('''UUA'''), in full the '''Unitarian Universalist Association of Congregations in North America''', is a [[Liberal religion|liberal]] religious association of [[Unitarian Universalism|Unitarian Universalist]] congregations formed by the consolidation in 1961 of the [[American Unitarian Association]] and the [[Universalist Church of America]]. Both of these predecessor organizations began as [[Christianity|Christian]] [[Unitarianism|Unitarian]] and [[Christianity|Christian]] [[Universalism#Christianity|Universalist]] denominations.  However, modern Unitarian Universalists do not limit themselves to [[Christianity|Christian]] beliefs or affinities.  Rather, they define themselves as non-[[creed]]al, and draw wisdom from various religions and philosophies in addition to Christianity, including [[Humanism]], [[Hinduism]], [[Buddhism]], [[Judaism]], and [[Neopaganism|Earth-centered spirituality]]. Thus, the UUA qualifies as a form of [[Postchristianity|''post-Christian'']] liberal religion with [[syncretism|syncretistic]] leanings.

==Congregations==
[[Image:UnitarianUniversalistChurchsignRochesterMN.JPG|thumb|left|Sign on a UU church in the United States.]]
Most of the member congregations of the UUA are in the [[United States]] and [[Canada]], but the UUA has also admitted congregations from [[Australia]], [[New Zealand]], the [[Philippines]] and [[Pakistan]] (although UUA policy appears at present to be against admitting any new congregations from outside [[North America]], rather having them form their own national bodies and having these bodies join the [[International Council of Unitarians and Universalists]]{{Or|date=September 2010}}). Until 2002, almost all member congregations of the [[Canadian Unitarian Council]] (CUC) were also members of the UUA and most services to CUC member congregations were provided by the UUA. However, after an agreement between the UUA and the CUC, since 2002 most services have been provided by the CUC to its own member congregations, with the UUA continuing to provide ministerial settlement services and as well as a minimal amount of youth (12–20) and young adult (18–35) programming and services. Since 2002, some Canadian congregations have continued to be members of both the UUA and CUC while others are members of only the CUC.

The [[Church of the Larger Fellowship]] (CLF) is a member church of the Unitarian Universalist Association providing denominational services to persons unable to attend a physical congregation because of distance or mobility, or who wish to belong to a congregation other than their local congregation. Many of these are Unitarian Universalists in other countries, members of the military, prisoners or non-mobile elderly.

==Organization==
The UUA is headquartered at 25 [[Beacon Street]] on historic [[Beacon Hill, Boston, Massachusetts]], the historical center of [[Unitarianism|Unitarian]] [[Christianity]] in America.  As of 2009, the UUA comprised 19 [[Districts of the Unitarian Universalist Association|Districts]], 1,041 congregations with 164,656 certified members and 61,795 church school enrollees served by 1,623 ministers.[http://www.uua.org/aboutuua/statistics.html] 
However, as of 2011 the UUA had 162,796 certified members and 54,671 church school enrollees. This shows a decline of 1,860 members and 7,124 enrollees in church school since 2008. The UUA has, for the first time, also reported decline in average weekly attendance to 100,693 people. This is a drop of 1.5% on the 2010 reported figure.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

===Corporate status===
The UUA was given corporate status in May 1961 under special acts of legislature of The Commonwealth of Massachusetts and the State of New York. See Chapter 148 of the acts of 1960 of the Massachusetts legislature and Chapter 827 of the Acts of 1960 of the New York legislature. Copies of said Acts are attached to the minutes of the organizing meeting of the Association held in Boston, Massachusetts in May 1961 and also are printed in the 1961-62 Directory of the Association.

===Decentralized association===
The UUA is not a [[religious denomination|denomination]] in the traditional sense; the UUA is an [[Voluntary association|association]] of congregations with no one organization able to speak authoritatively for the whole. It is the congregations that have authority over the larger body, through the annual General Assembly of the Unitarian Universalist Association. Since the general public understands ''denomination'' much more readily than ''association of congregations'', the distinction is generally elided in conversation. Because of this relationship between the congregations and the association, [[Unitarian Universalism|Unitarian Universalist]] congregations have a [[Congregationalist church governance|congregational polity of governance]]. However, for the more day-to-day decisions, there is a Board of Trustees that is elected by [[Districts of the Unitarian Universalist Association|Districts]] and at General Assembly.

In its role as a national organization representing the congregations, the UUA is a member of various organizations, both religious and secular.

===Principles and purposes===
The UUA does not have a central creed in which members are required to believe, but they have found it useful to articulate their common values in what has become known as the ''Principles and Purposes''. The first version of the principles was adopted in 1960, and the modern form was adopted in 1984 (including the 7th principle).  They were amended once again in 1995 to include the 6th source.  Both of these were added to explicitly include members with [[Neopagan]], [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Native American]], and other [[natural theist]] spiritualities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uuworld.org/ideas/articles/3643.shtml?lj uuworld.org : how the uu principles and purposes were adopted&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The principles as published in church literature and [http://www.uua.org/aboutuua/principles.html on the UUA website] :

:'''The Principles and purposes of the Unitarian Universalist Association'''

:''&quot;We, the member congregations of the Unitarian Universalist Association, covenant to affirm and promote&quot;''
:*The inherent worth and dignity of every person;
:*Justice, equity and compassion in human relations;
:*Acceptance of one another and encouragement to spiritual growth in our congregations;
:*A free and responsible search for truth and meaning;
:*The right of conscience and the use of the democratic process within our congregations and in society at large;
:*The goal of world community with peace, liberty, and justice for all;
:*Respect for the interdependent web of all existence of which we are a part.

:''&quot;The living tradition which we share draws from many sources:&quot;''
:*Direct experience of that transcending mystery and wonder, affirmed in all cultures, which moves us to a renewal of the spirit and an openness to the forces which create and uphold life;
:*Words and deeds of prophetic women and men which challenge us to confront powers and structures of evil with justice, compassion, and the transforming power of love;
:*Wisdom from the world's religions which inspires us in our ethical and spiritual life;
:*Jewish and Christian teachings which call us to respond to God's love by loving our neighbors as ourselves;
:*Humanist teachings which counsel us to heed the guidance of [[reason]] and the results of science, and warn us against idolatries of the mind and spirit.
:*Spiritual teachings of earth-centered traditions which celebrate the sacred circle of life and instruct us to live in harmony with the rhythms of nature.

:''&quot;Grateful for the religious pluralism which enriches and ennobles our faith, we are inspired to deepen our understanding and expand our vision. As free congregations we enter into this covenant, promising to one another our mutual trust and support.&quot;''

:'''The Purposes of the Unitarian Universalist Association'''

:The Unitarian Universalist Association shall devote its resources to and exercise its corporate powers for religious, educational and humanitarian purposes. The primary purpose of the Association is to serve the needs of its member congregations, organize new congregations, extend and strengthen Unitarian Universalist institutions and implement its principles.

:The Association declares and affirms its special responsibility, and that of its member societies and organizations, to promote the full participation of persons in all of its and their activities and in the full range of human endeavor without regard to race, color, sex, disability, affectional or sexual orientation, age, or national origin and without requiring adherence to any particular interpretation of religion or to any particular religious belief or creed.

:Nothing herein shall be deemed to infringe upon the individual freedom of belief which is inherent in the Universalist and Unitarian heritages or to conflict with any statement of purpose, covenant, or bond of union used by any society unless such is used as a creedal test.

===General Assembly===
{{Main|General Assembly (Unitarian Universalist Association)}}
General Assembly ([http://www.uua.org/ga/ GA]) is held every year in June in a different city in the USA. Member congregations (and three associate member organizations) send delegates and conventioneers to participate in the [[plenary session]]s, workshops, district gatherings, and worship services.

===Finances and membership fees===
The UUA requests annual contributions from its member congregations.  The requested contribution, known as Fair Share, is calculated for each congregation by multiplying an annually determined membership fee times the number of registered members of that congregation.   The UUA also has alternative modes of raising funds.  In order for congregations to participate in certain programming, they will pay a nominal fee.  Some funds are earned through charitable gifts or estate planning.  Additionally, the UUA pools together investment funds from congregations or other constituents and manages them for a small percentage.

==Related organizations==
Three non-congregational organizations belong to the UUA as Associate Member organizations. Associate Member organizations are esteemed as inherently integral to the work of the UUA and its member congregations, and are accorded two voting delegates each to the annual General Assembly. The Associate Member organizations are the [[Unitarian Universalist Service Committee]] (UUSC), which is active in social change actions; the Unitarian Universalist Women's Federation, which provides education and advocacy on women's issues; and the Unitarian Universalist United Nations Office, which is a center of information and action at the [[United Nations]].

The UUA also recognizes many organizations as Independent Affiliate organizations. These organizations are created by Unitarian Universalists as needed to meet the special needs of the diversity within Unitarian Universalism. These groups provide specialized spiritual support, work for specific [[social justice]] issues, provide support for religious professionals, etc.

The UUA owns [[Beacon Press]], a nationally known publisher of both fiction and non-fiction books. [[Skinner House Books]] publishes books primarily of interest to Unitarian Universalists.

The UUA also participates in interfaith organizations such as the [[Interfaith Center on Corporate Responsibility]].

==Presidents==
The president of the UUA is its [[CEO]] and the religious leader of Unitarian Universalism in the [[United States]].  The delegates at [[General Assembly (Unitarian Universalist Association)]] elect the president to a four-year term and a president may be re-elected once.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uua.org/aboutus/bylaws/articleviii/7006.shtml Bylaws §8.3. Term of Office.]&lt;/ref&gt;  The Rev. [[Peter Morales]] was elected at General Assembly in 2009.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!Name||Elected
|-
|Rev. [[Dana McLean Greeley]]||1961
|-
|Rev. Robert West||1969
|-
|Rev. Paul Carnes||1977
|-
|Rev. O. Eugene Pickett||1979*
|-
|Rev. [[William F. Schulz|William Schulz]]||1985
|-
|Rev. [[John A. Buehrens]]||1993
|-
|Rev. [[William G. Sinkford]]||2001
|-
|Rev. [[Peter Morales]]||2009
|}

&lt;nowiki&gt;*&lt;/nowiki&gt;Rev. Pickett was elected president by the Board of Trustees upon the death of Rev. Paul Carnes. He was subsequently elected to a four-year term by the General Assembly.

==Moderators==
The moderator of the UUA is the [[chair]] of the Board of Trustees of the Unitarian Universalist Association and is the presiding officer at the [[General Assembly (Unitarian Universalist Association)]]. The moderator is the highest UUA position traditionally held by [[laity]]. General Assembly delegates elect the moderator to a four-year term and a moderator may be re-elected once. Moderator Gini Courter (2003*) ran unopposed and was elected to a second full four-year term at General Assembly in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uua.org/events/generalassembly/2009/ga2009/144316.shtml GA2009 Plenary VI: Moderator's Report]&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!Name||Elected
|-
|Marshall E. Dimock||1961
|-
|[[Joseph L. Fisher]]||1964*
|-
|Sandra M. Caron||1977
|-
|Natalie Gulbrandsen||1985
|-
|Denise Davidoff||1993
|-
|Diane Olson||2001
|-
|Gini Courter||2003*
|}

&lt;nowiki&gt;*&lt;/nowiki&gt;Fisher and Courter were each elected moderator by the Board of Trustees upon the resignations of their predecessors and subsequently elected by General Assembly to full four-year terms.

==Boy Scouts of America controversy==
{{Further2|[[Boy Scouts of America]] membership controversies and [[Religious emblems programs (Boy Scouts of America)]]}}

The Religion in Life [[Religious emblems programs|religious emblems program]] of UUA is no longer recognized by the [[Boy Scouts of America]] (BSA). The UUA published statements opposing the BSA's policies on [[Boy Scouts of America membership controversies#Position on homosexuals|homosexuals]], [[Boy Scouts of America membership controversies#Position on atheists and agnostics|atheists, and agnostics]] in 1992; and in 1993, the UUA updated Religion in Life to include criticism of these BSA policies.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://archive.uua.org/news/scouts/faith.html |title=The Boy Scouts, a Battle and the Meaning of Faith |accessdate=2007-05-09 |author=Gustav Niebuhr |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= 1999-05-22|work= |publisher=New York Times |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1998, the BSA withdrew recognition of Religion in Life, stating that such information was incompatible with BSA programs.  The UUA removed the material from their curriculum and the BSA renewed their recognition of the program.  When the BSA found that the UUA was issuing supplemental material with the Religion in Life workbooks that included statements critical of discrimination on the basis of sexual orientation or personal religious viewpoint, the BSA again withdrew recognition.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Isaacson |first=Eric Alan |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=2007 |month= |title=Traditional Values, or a New Tradition of Prejudice?  The Boy Scouts of America vs. the Unitarian Universalist Association of Congregations |journal=George Mason University Civil Rights Law Journal |url=http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Mason_University_Civil_Rights_Law_Journal|volume=17 |issue=1 |pages= |id= |DUPLICATE DATA: url=http://law.bepress.com/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=6200&amp;context=expresso |accessdate=2007-06-24 |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Unitarian Universalist Scouters Organization (UUSO) created the Living Your Religion program in May 2005 as a parallel award for [[Unitarian Universalism|Unitarian Universalist]] youth.&lt;ref name=&quot;UUSO&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.uuscouters.org/ |title=Unitarian Universalist Scouters Organization |accessdate=2007-04-11 |author= |authorlink= |coauthors= |date=March 5, 2006 |format= |work= |publisher= |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt; The program was promoted at the [[2005 National Scout Jamboree]] and shown as having BSA approval in the UUSO membership brochure and the Living Your Religion Guidebook.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| url=http://www.praypub.org/Publications/BSQ1_05.htm |title= P.R.A.Y. Boy Scout News Bulletin |accessdate=2007-07-08 |author= |authorlink= |coauthors= |date=First Quarter 2005 |work= |publisher= |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.uuscouters.org/documents/UUSO2005JamboreeWorship.pdf |format=PDF|title= Unitarian Universalist Worship Service |accessdate=2007-07-07 |author= |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=2006 |work= |publisher=Unitarian Universalist Scouters Organization |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.uuscouters.org/documents/2006_UUSO_MembershipBrochure.pdf |format=PDF|title=2006 UUSO Membership Brochure |accessdate=2007-07-08 |author= |authorlink= |coauthors= |date=March 5, 2006 |work= |publisher=Unitarian Universalist Scouters Organization |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.uuscouters.org/documents/UUSO-LivingYourReligionGuidebook2005-02.pdf |format=PDF|title=Living Your Religion: A Unitarian Universalist Religious Award Program for Boy Scouts and Venturers |accessdate=2007-07-08 |author= |authorlink= |coauthors= |date=February 1, 2005 |work= |publisher=Unitarian Universalist Scouters Organization |pages= |language= |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070927051556/http://www.uuscouters.org/documents/UUSO-LivingYourReligionGuidebook2005-02.pdf &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-09-27 |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The UUA has stated that the UUSO is not recognized as an affiliate organization.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title= UUA and the Scouts: Statement from the Unitarian Universalist Association |url=http://archive.uua.org/news/scouts/050316_statement.html |accessdate=2007-07-08 |author= |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= March 16, 2005 |work= |publisher=Unitarian Universalist Association |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.scouting.org/awards/religious/awards/index.html |title=Religious Emblems Programs Available to Members of the Boy Scouts of America |accessdate=2007-07-08 |author= |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |work= |publisher=Boy Scouts of America |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt; As of March 2006, the UUSO has a stated goal to create a set of awards that are recognized by the UUA and BSA.&lt;ref name= &quot;UUSO&quot; /&gt;

===Alternative UU-friendly scouting organizations===
In the wake of this controversy, a number of [[SpiralScouts International]] circles have formed within congregations of the UUA, despite having no official affiliation with the UUA.&lt;ref name=&quot;uuworld.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.uuworld.org/news/articles/45487.shtml uuworld.org : scouting alternatives draw uu youth&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Boy Scout Troop 103 was sponsored by All Souls Unitarian Church in [[New York City]]. The BSA policies that excluded the UUA caused the congregation to terminate its charter and sever ties with the BSA. The volunteers who formerly led the troop later founded [[Navigators USA]],&lt;ref name=&quot;uuworld.org&quot;/&gt; which its founders describe as &quot;...committed to providing a quality scouting experience that is inclusive and available to all children and families regardless of gender, race, religion, economic status, sexual orientation and social background.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.navigatorsusa.org Navigators&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; There are currently 4 chapters in the metropolitan New York City area, one in upper New York state, three in Massachusetts, three in California, and one each in [[Durham, North Carolina]], [[Fort Collins, Colorado]], [[Norman, Oklahoma]], [[Fayetteville, Arkansas]], [[Olympia, Washington]], and [[Alpena, Michigan|Alpena, MI]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://navigatorsusa.ning.com/page/startachapter-1 START-A-CHAPTER - Navigators USA]&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to SpiralScouts and Navigators USA, the UUA website also suggests [[Camp Fire]] as an alternative scout-like organization that comports with UU principles.

==See also==
{{Portal|Religion}}
*[[Districts of the Unitarian Universalist Association]]
*[[Unitarian Universalism]]
*[[United and uniting churches]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.uua.org/ Official Website Of The Unitarian Universalist Association]
*[http://www.uua.org/CONG Official List Of Unitarian Universalist Association Member Churches]
*[http://www.thearda.com/Denoms/D_1403.asp Profile of the UUA at the Association of Religion Data Archives website]
*[http://www.uuworld.org/ UU World Magazine]

{{Unitarian, Universalist and Unitarian Universalist topics}}

[[Category:Unitarian Universalist organizations]]
[[Category:Religious organizations based in the United States]]
[[Category:Religious organizations based in Boston, Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Religion in the United States]]
[[Category:Religious organizations established in 1961]]
[[Category:Supraorganizations]]
[[Category:United and uniting churches]]

[[ca:Associació Unitària Universalista]]
[[de:Unitarian Universalist Association]]
[[es:Asociación Unitaria Universalista]]
[[fr:Association universaliste unitarienne]]
[[pt:Associação Unitária Universalista]]</text>
      <sha1>guglkwwu64ql7vkmf3rdkxsjxz2s2mb</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
