<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Unitarian Universalism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>32059</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522302452</id>
      <parentid>520534477</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T08:29:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mcc1789</username>
        <id>12965382</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Unitarianism */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="64891">'''Unitarian Universalism''' is a [[theologically]] [[liberal religion]] characterized by support for a &quot;free and responsible search for [[truth]] and [[meaning of life|meaning]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;(The 4th principle of Unitarian Universalism)[http://www.uua.org/visitors/6798.shtml UUA.org Seven principles]&lt;/ref&gt; Unitarian Universalists do not share a [[creed]]; rather, they are unified by their shared search for [[spiritual growth]] and by the understanding that an individual's theology is a result of that search and not obedience to an authoritarian requirement. Unitarian Universalists draw on many different theological sources and have a wide range of [[Religious belief|beliefs]] and practices.

Contemporary Unitarian Universalism espouses a pluralist approach to religious belief, whereby members may describe themselves as [[atheist]], [[agnostic]], [[deist]], [[monotheist]], [[pantheism|pantheist]], [[polytheist]], [[neopaganism|pagan]], or assume no label at all. As of 2006, fewer than about 20% of Unitarian Universalists identified themselves as Christian.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last =Ford| first =James Ishmael| title =Zen Master Who?| publisher =[[Wisdom Publications]]| year =2006| url =| id = |page=187| isbn = 0-86171-509-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Unitarian Universalist Association]] (UUA) was formed in 1961, a consolidation of the [[American Unitarian Association]], established in 1825, and the [[Universalist Church of America]], established in 1866. It is headquartered in [[Boston]], [[Massachusetts]], and serves churches mostly in the [[United States]]. The [[Canadian Unitarian Council]] became an independent body in 2002.&lt;ref&gt;CUC-UUA Tradition. Canadian Unitarian Council [http://cuc.ca/who_we_are/cuc-uua_transition.htm Growing Vital Religious Communities In Canada]&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{refimprove section|date=June 2011}}
Unitarian Universalism was formed from the merger in 1961 of two historically Christian denominations, the [[Universalist Church of America]] and the [[American Unitarian Association]], both based in the [[United States]]. At the time of the North American merger, the theological significance of these terms had expanded beyond the traditional Christian understanding. Unitarian Universalists today draw from a variety of religious traditions. Individuals may or may not self-identify as Christians or subscribe to Christian beliefs.&lt;ref name=&quot;surveys&quot;/&gt; Unitarian Universalist congregations and fellowships tend to retain some Christian traditions, such as Sunday worship with a sermon and the singing of hymns. The extent to which the elements of any particular faith tradition are incorporated into personal spiritual practice is a matter of personal choice for congregants, in keeping with a creedless, non-dogmatic approach to spirituality and faith development.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

New England Unitarians evolved from the Pilgrim fathers' [[Congregational]] Christianity, which was originally based on a literal reading of the [[Bible]]. Liberalizing Unitarians rejected the [[Trinitarianism|Trinitarian]] belief in the tri-partite godhead: Father, Son, and Holy Ghost/Spirit. Instead, they asserted a unitary notion of God.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

New England [[Universalists]] rejected the Puritan forefathers' emphasis on the select few, the Elect, who were reportedly saved from eternal damnation by a just God. Instead Universalists asserted that 'all were universally saved'. Universalists rejected the [[Fire and brimstone|hellfire and damnation]] of the evangelical preachers, who tried to revive the [[Religious fundamentalism|fundamentalist]] Christianity of the early Pilgrim fathers.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

===Universalism===
{{Main|Universalism}}
Universalism broadly refers to a theological belief that all persons and creatures are related to a [[god]] or the divine and will be reconciled to (a) god (Universal Salvation).{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

====Christian Universalism====
{{Main|Christian Universalism}}
Proponents of [[Christian Universalism]] claim a long history, beginning with [[Origen]] and [[Gregory of Nyssa]], although both of these are questioned by modern scholarship and Orthodox scholars.&lt;ref&gt;Westminster Origen Handbook&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ludlow, Morwenna. (2000). &quot;Universal Salvation: Eschatology in the thought of Gregory of Nyssa and Karl Rahner&quot;. New York; Oxford University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stone, Darwell. (1903). &quot;Outline of Christian Dogma&quot;. p 341 New York: Longmans, Green &amp; Co. [http://books.google.com/books?id=P0kQAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA341&amp;dq=%22gregory+of+nyssa%22+universalism&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=fMLETJfrHo-gsQPAyeykDA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CCwQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt;

It is based upon the doctrine of universal salvation through Christ ([[universal reconciliation]]) and an interpretation of the &quot;restitution of all things&quot; ([[apocatastasis]]). In 1793, Universalism emerged as a particular denomination of Christianity in the United States, eventually called the [[Universalist Church of America]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uua.org/visitors/ourhistory/6904.shtml UUA: Universalism]{{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Early American advocates of [[Universal Salvation]] such as [[Elhanan Winchester]], [[Hosea Ballou]] and [[John Murray (minister)|John Murray]] taught that all souls would achieve salvation, sometimes after a period resembling [[purgatory]].&lt;ref&gt;William Latta McCalla ''Discussion of universalism'' 1825 Page 105 &quot;THIRD UNIVERSALIST ARGUMENT. As it is a fact that many Universalists advocate a sort of purgatory, a concise notice will be taken of those texts which are erroneously thought to countenance that doctrine.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; [[Christian Universalism]] denies the doctrine of everlasting [[damnation]], and proclaims belief in an entirely loving [[God in Christianity|God]] who will ultimately [[Salvation#Redemption|redeem]] all human beings.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

===Unitarianism===
{{Main|Unitarianism}}
Historically, '''[[Nontrinitarianism]]''' consisted of dissenting factions within Christianity.  The term may refer to any belief about the nature of [[Jesus]] [[Christ]] that affirms [[God]] as a singular entity and rejects the doctrine of the [[Trinity]] and is usually distinguished from [[Arianism]], which was rejected by [[Nicene Creed|mainstream Christianity]], a consensus of Christian bishops at the [[First Council of Nicaea]] in 325. This resurfaced later in Church history, especially during the theological turmoils of the [[Protestant Reformation]]. A Spanish physician, [[Michael Servetus]], studied the Bible and concluded that the concept of the Trinity, as traditionally conceived, was not biblical. His books ''On the Errors of the Trinity'' and ''Christianismi Restitutio'' caused much uproar. Servetus was eventually arrested, convicted of heresy, and burned at the stake in [[Geneva]] in 1553 when [[John Calvin]] was leading the Reformation there.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.miguelservet.org/servetus/biography.htm |title=Michael Servetus Institute; Times that Servetus lived |publisher=Miguelservet.org |date= |accessdate=2011-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term '''Unitarian''' entered the English language via [[Henry Hedworth]] in relation to the teachings of [[Laelio Sozzini]] and the Polish [[Socinians]]. Unitarian churches were formally established in [[Transylvania]] and [[Poland]] (by the [[Socinianism|Socinians]]) in the second half of the 16th Century.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harris&quot;&gt;Harris, MW. Unitarian Universalist Origins: Our Historic Faith&lt;/ref&gt; The early Unitarian church not only rejected the Trinity, but also the [[pre-existence of Christ]] as well, in many cases, [[predestination]] and [[original sin]] as put forward by [[Augustine of Hippo]], and the [[substitutionary atonement]] of Christ developed by [[Anselm of Canterbury]] and John Calvin. There were several different forms of [[Christology]] in the beginnings of the Unitarian movement; ultimately, the variety that became prevalent was that Jesus was a man, but one with a unique relationship to God. These Unitarian thinkers and groups have gone by many names, including [[Anti-trinitarianism]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

====Britain====
{{main|History of Unitarianism}}
[[Samuel Clarke]] (1675–1729) revised the [[Book of Common Prayer]], removing the Trinitarian [[Nicene Creed]] and references to [[divinity of Jesus|Jesus as God]].&lt;ref name=Clarke&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.americanunitarian.org/fisherhistory.htm |title=Chris Fisher, '&amp;#39;A Brief History of Unitarian Christianity'&amp;#39;, retrieved July 18, 2008 |publisher=Americanunitarian.org |date= |accessdate=2011-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Theophilus Lindsey]] also revised the Book of Common Prayer to allow a more Unitarian interpretation. Neither cleric was charged under the [[Blasphemy Act 1697]] that made it an ''offence for any person, educated in or having made profession of the Christian religion, by writing, preaching, teaching or advised speaking, to deny the [[Holy Trinity]]''. The [[Act of Toleration 1689|Act of Toleration]] (1689), the long title being ''An Act for Exempting their Majestyes Protestant Subjects dissenting from the Church of England from the Penalties of certaine Lawes'', gave relief to [[English Dissenters]], but excluded Unitarians. The efforts of Clarke and Lindsey met with substantial criticism to stifle attempts at reform, from the more conservative laity, priests and bishops who held substantial power within the [[Church of England]]. In response, in 1774, Lindsey applied for registration of the [[Essex Street Chapel|Essex House]] as a ''Dissenting place of worship'' with the assistance of [[barrister]] Mr. [[John Lee (Attorney-General)|John Lee]].  On the Sunday following the registration &amp;mdash; April 17, 1774 &amp;mdash; the first true Unitarian congregation discreetly convened in the provisional Essex Street Chapel. In attendance were Mr. Lee, [[Joseph Priestley]] and the agent of the Massachusetts Colony, Mr. [[Benjamin Franklin]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web 
|url= http://www.unitarian.org.uk/support/doc-EssexHall2.shtml
|title= The History of Essex Hall
|author= |last= Rowe |first= Mortimer
|year= 1959
|work=  Chapter 2 &amp;ndash; Lindsey's Chapel
|publisher= Lindsey Press
|accessdate= ...in the early months of 1774 a little group of persons-Lindsey and his chiefpledged supporters -turned the corner out of the Strand into Essex Street and stood looking at a building near the top of the street, a building which alone kept alive the proud name 'Essex House'}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Priestley also founded a reform congregation, but, after his home was burned down in the [[Priestley Riots]], fled with his wife to America, where he became a leading figure in the founding of the church on American soil.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://www.portal.state.pa.us/portal/server.pt?open=512&amp;objID=4277&amp;&amp;PageID=443569&amp;level=4&amp;css=L4&amp;mode=2
|title= Joseph Priestley 
|accessdate= 2011-09-24
|last=Silverman
|first=  Sharon Hernes 
|date= modified September 24, 2011
|work= History &gt;  Pennsylvania History  &gt; People &gt;
|publisher= [[Pennsylvania Historical and Museum Commission]]
|quote= ...eleven homes and two chapels in Birmingham were destroyed ... on April 8, 1794, Joseph and Mary Priestley set sail for America ... his 1796 lectures on &quot;Evidences of Revelation&quot; led to the formation of the First Unitarian Church in Philadelphia
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Once laity and clergy relaxed their vehement opposition to the [[Doctrine of the Trinity Act 1813]] (sometimes called the ''Trinitarian Act 1812'' and also variously known as the ''Trinity Act'', ''Unitarian Relief Act'' and ''Unitarian Toleration Bill'') that amended the Blasphemy Act 1697 in respect of its Trinitarian provisions, the [[British and Foreign Unitarian Association]] was founded in 1825. It has its headquarters in Essex Hall, successor to Lindsey's Essex House.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

During the late 19th Century there was tension between the &quot;[[Biblical Unitarianism]]&quot; of [[Robert Spears]] and [[Samuel Sharpe (scholar)|Samuel Sharpe]] and those such as [[James Martineau]] as Unitarians began to move away from belief in scripture.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

Unitarian congregations in Britain today meet under the auspices of the [[General Assembly of Unitarian and Free Christian Churches]]. Two that have been significant in national life are the [[Cross Street Chapel]] in [[Manchester]] and [[Newington Green Unitarian Church]] in [[north London]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

====United States====
{{main|History of Unitarianism}}
In the United States, the Unitarian movement began primarily in the [[Congregational church|Congregational]] [[parish]] churches of [[New England]], which were part of the [[state church]] of Massachusetts.&lt;ref&gt;Paul Erasmus Lauer, [http://books.google.com/books?id=2J8TAAAAYAAJ&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s ''Church and state in New England''] (Johns Hopkins Press, 1892) p. 105. Retrieved September 20, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; These churches, whose buildings may still be seen today in many New England town squares, trace their roots to the division of the [[Puritan]] colonies into parishes for the administration of their religious needs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uunashua.org/sermons/sampson.shtml Bob Sampson, Seventy-three Years In the Unitarian-Universalist Church of Nashua, July 16, 2006]. Retrieved July 18, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; In the late 18th century, conflict grew within some of these churches between Unitarian and Trinitarian factions. In 1805,  Unitarians gained key faculty positions at [[Harvard University#Religion and philosophy|Harvard]]. In 1819 [[William Ellery Channing]] preached the [[ordination]] sermon for [[Jared Sparks]] in [[Baltimore]], outlining the Unitarian position. The [[American Unitarian Association]] was founded as a separate denomination in 1825.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://americanunitarian.org/fisherhistory.htm
|title= A Brief History of Unitarian Christianity
|accessdate= 2011-09-24
|author= 
|last= Fisher
|first= Chris 
|date= modified September 1, 2004
|work=  The 19th Century
|publisher= [[American Unitarian Conference]]
|archiveurl= 
|archivedate= 
|quote= Many churches that were Congregationalist split off and became Unitarian. In 1825, the movement grew large enough that an organization, the American Unitarian Association, was formed
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
By coincidence and unknown to both parties, the AUA was formed on the same day &amp;mdash; May 26, 1825 &amp;mdash; as the [[British and Foreign Unitarian Association]]
&lt;ref&gt;Rowe, Ch. 3: '' Thus was brought to birth, triumphantly, in 1825, The British And Foreign Unitarian Association. [ By a happy coincidence, in those days of slow posts, no transatlantic telegraph, telephone or wireless, our American cousins, in complete ignorance as to the details of what was afoot, though moving towards a similar goal, founded the American Unitarian Association on precisely the same day - May 26, 1825.''&lt;/ref&gt;

===Integration 1825–1961===
After the [[Schism (religion)|schism]], some of those churches remained within the Congregational fold, while others voted to become Unitarian. In the aftermath of their various historical circumstances, some of these churches became member congregations of the Congregational organization (later the [[United Church of Christ]]), others became Unitarian and eventually became part of the [[UUA]]. Universalist churches in contrast followed a different path, having begun as independent congregations beyond the bounds of the established [[Puritan]] churches entirely. Today, the UUA and the United Church of Christ cooperate jointly on [[social justice]] initiatives such as the Sexuality Education Advocacy Training project.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://www.uua.org/reproductive/education/index.shtml
|title= Comprehensive Sexuality Education
|accessdate= 2011-09-24
|date= August 23, 2011
|work= » Social Justice » Reproductive Justice »
|publisher= Unitarian Universalist Association of Congregations 
|archiveurl= 
|archivedate= 
|quote= The Unitarian Universalist Association has long been an advocate of age-appropriate, medically accurate, comprehensive sexuality education
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 19th century, under the influence of [[Ralph Waldo Emerson]] (who had been a Unitarian minister)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.harvardsquarelibrary.org/UIA%20Online/97emerson.html Ralph Waldo Emerson]. Harvardsquarelibrary.org. Retrieved on 2010-09-29.&lt;/ref&gt; and other [[transcendentalists]], Unitarianism began its long journey from [[Liberal Christianity|liberal Protestantism]] to its present more pluralist form.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

Unitarians and Universalists often have had common interests and communication between them. In the often-quoted words of [[Thomas Starr King]], pastor of the [[San Francisco, California|San Francisco]] Unitarian Church at the beginning of the [[American Civil War|Civil War]]: &quot;The Universalists believe that God is too good to damn them, and the Unitarians believe they are too good to be damned!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sias&quot;&gt;Sias, John. [http://www.uunashua.org/100q/100questions.pdf 100 Questions that Non-Unitarians Ask About Unitarian Universalism]&lt;/ref&gt; Mergers of local congregations and use of the term &quot;Unitarian-Universalist&quot; in printed publicity date from 1932 or earlier.&lt;ref&gt;''The Universalist leader'' Volume 35  18 1932 &quot;... merged church will bear the legal name of the First Unitarian Church, the term &quot;Unitarian-Universalist&quot; will be used in all printed publicity. The membership rolls have been united and both churches are represented on the board of {{Clarify|date=February 2012}}.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1961, the [[American Unitarian Association]] (AUA) was consolidated with the [[Universalist Church of America]] (UCA), thus forming the [[Unitarian Universalist Association]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Sias&quot;/&gt; In the same year, the [[Canadian Unitarian Council]] (CUC) formed.&lt;ref name=&quot;CUCHistory&quot;&gt;[http://www.cuc.ca/governance/archival/History.htm Accord History]. Cuc.ca. Retrieved on 2010-09-29.&lt;/ref&gt; The Unitarian Universalist Association (UUA) was also given corporate status in May 1961 under special acts of legislature of the [[Commonwealth of Massachusetts]] and the [[State of New York]].{{Citation needed|date=June 2008}}

In 1998, the CUC and UUA dissolved their financial accord, although they continue to cooperate in many ways.{{Clarify|date=February 2012}}&lt;ref name=&quot;CUCHistory&quot;/&gt;

==Beliefs==
{{refimprove section|date=June 2011}}
There is no single unifying belief that all Unitarian Universalists (UUs) hold, aside from complete and responsible [[freedom of speech]], [[Freedom of thought|thought]], [[Freedom of religion|belief, faith]], and [[disposition]]. Unitarian Universalists believe that each person is free to search for his or her own personal truth on issues, such as the existence, nature, and [[meaning of life]], deities, [[Creation myth|creation]], and [[afterlife]]. UUs can come from any religious background, and hold beliefs and adhere to [[moral syncretism|morals]] from a variety of [[culture]]s or [[religion]]s.

Concepts about [[deity]] are diverse among UUs. Some are [[monotheistic]]. Some have no belief in any gods ([[atheism]]); others believe in many gods ([[polytheism]]). Some believe that the question of the existence of any god is most likely unascertainable or unknowable ([[agnosticism]]). Some believe that [[God]] is a metaphor for a transcendent reality. Some believe in a female god ([[goddess]]), an [[Abrahamic religions|Abrahamic god]], or a god identified with nature or the universe ([[pantheism]]). Still others may hold with the [[Deism|Deist]] notion that a creator God exists, but does not [[Miracle|intervene in the world]] or [[Revelation|reveal itself]], and can only be apprehended (if at all) through the use of [[reason]]. Many UUs reject the idea of deities and instead speak of the &quot;spirit of life&quot; that binds all [[biosphere|life on earth]]. UUs support each person's search for truth and meaning in concepts of spirituality.

===Seven ''Principles and Purposes''===
Deliberately without an official creed or dogma (per the principle of freedom of thought), many Unitarian Universalists make use of the [[Unitarian Universalist Association#Principles and purposes|Principles and Purposes]] as a definition of what UUs believe.  These &quot;Principles and Purposes&quot; are taken from the by-laws which govern the [[Unitarian Universalist Association]]. While these were written to govern congregations, not individuals, many UUs use them as guides for living their faith.  The &quot;Seven Principles&quot; were created in committee and affirmed democratically by a vote of member congregations at an annual General Assembly (a meeting of delegates from member congregations). Adopted in 1960, the full [[Unitarian Universalist Association#Principles and purposes|Principles, Purposes and Sources]] can be found in the article on the [[Unitarian Universalist Association#Principles and purposes|Unitarian Universalist Association]]. The Principles are as follows:

&lt;blockquote&gt;We, the member congregations of the Unitarian Universalist Association, covenant to affirm and promote

* The inherent worth and dignity of every person;
* Justice, equity and compassion in human relations;
* Acceptance of one another and encouragement to spiritual growth in our congregations;
* A free and responsible search for truth and meaning;
* The right of conscience and the use of the democratic process within our congregations and in society at large;
* The goal of world community with peace, liberty and justice for all;
* Respect for the interdependent web of all existence of which we are a part.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.uua.org/aboutuua/principles.html
| title = The Principles of the Unitarian Universalist Association
| accessdate = 2007-02-24
| publisher = [[Unitarian Universalist Association]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Unitarian Universalism is often referred to by its members as a ''living tradition'', and the principles and purposes have been modified over time to reflect changes in spiritual beliefs among the membership. Most recently, the last principle, adopted in 1985 and generally known as the ''Seventh Principle'', &quot;Respect for the interdependent web of all existence of which we are a part&quot;, and a sixth source (adopted in 1995), &quot;Spiritual teachings of earth-centered traditions which celebrate the sacred circle of life and instruct us to live in harmony with the rhythms of nature&quot; were added to explicitly include members with [[Neopaganism|Neopagan]], [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Native American]], and [[Pantheism|pantheist]] spiritualities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.uuworld.org/ideas/articles/3643.shtml?lj
| title = Shared values: How the UUA’s Principles and Purposes were shaped and how they’ve shaped Unitarian Universalism
| accessdate = 2007-02-24
| author = Warren R. Ross
| year = 2000
| month = November/December
| work = UUWorld
| publisher = [[Unitarian Universalist Association]] of Congregations}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Unitarian Universalists tend to promote beliefs of a person that are based on their individual thoughts, and can range from strict monotheistic belief to less credal or more inclusive views.

===Six ''Sources''===
Unitarian Universalists place emphasis on spiritual growth and development. Unitarian Universalism is a creedless religion. The Unitarian Universalist Association affirms seven principles:&lt;ref name=&quot;uua.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.uua.org/visitors/6798.shtml Principles]. UUA (2010-09-09). Retrieved on 2010-09-29.&lt;/ref&gt; The official statement of Unitarian Universalist principles describes the &quot;sources&quot; upon which current practice is based:&lt;ref name=&quot;uua.org&quot;/&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
* Direct experience of that transcending mystery and wonder, affirmed in all cultures, which moves us to a renewal of the spirit and an openness to the forces which create and uphold life;
* Words and deeds of prophetic women and men which challenge us to confront powers and structures of evil with justice, compassion, and the transforming power of love;
* Wisdom from the [[Major religious groups|world's religions]] which inspires us in our ethical and spiritual life;
* [[Jewish]] and [[Christian]] teachings which call us to respond to God's love by loving our neighbors as ourselves;
* [[Humanism|Humanist]] teachings which counsel us to heed the guidance of reason and the results of science, and warn us against idolatries of the mind and spirit.
* Spiritual teachings of [[Earth religion|earth-centered traditions]] which celebrate the sacred circle of life and instruct us to live in harmony with the rhythms of nature.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Diversity among Unitarian Universalists===
Unitarian Universalists hold many different beliefs, but have no creedal test of membership. Unitarian Universalist congregations almost always contain members of a variety of different beliefs and religious practices.  Some congregations emphasize this diversity and use it to enrich individuals' search for their own truths.  Other congregations specialize in a particular theology or religious practice (UU Christian Churches in New England, for instance, or congregations which focus on the spiritual practice of justice and service).  All congregations are open to any person, regardless of their beliefs or practices. 

===Theologies/Philosophies===
In spite of this freedom and diversity, there seem to be some basic theological/philosophical ideas which form a core of UU identity.  UUs are often hesitant to articulate these basic beliefs because they don't want to form or imply a &quot;defacto creed.&quot;  However phenomena such as the uncanny accuracy of the [[Beliefnet.com|Beliefnet]] religious survey in identifying UUs and potential UUs, and the number of people who call themselves UUs although they do not belong to UU churches suggests that there is a core of belief.  Here is one attempt to formulate that:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
1. The universe is a beautiful, intricate, complex place, the foundations of which are a Mystery. The &quot;whole truth&quot; is too large, and our minds/knowledge/intuitions are too small to grasp it all. Therefore, we cherish and learn from diversity. 
2. If the Universe can be said to have a purpose, its purpose is for us, not against us, and it is for, not against, us all. 
3. Given how little we can know for sure, our focus should be on this earth and life; beauty, justice, love. 4. We claim the rational, eschew the irrational,(contrary to reason) and question the non-rational (that which is neither provable nor disprovable by reason alone, i.e. life after death).
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Poetically, this might be stated, &quot;We come from One origin, we are headed to One destiny, but we cannot know completely what these are, so we are to focus on making this life better for all of us, and we use reason when we can, to find our way. &quot;

===Diversity of Practices and Heritages===
Unitarian Universalists believe that the divine can be found in all people and in many faiths. Unitarian Universalists draw inspiration from a variety of other faith traditions. Many Unitarian Universalist churches celebrate observances associated with other religious traditions, including Buddhist-style meditation groups, Jewish [[Passover Seder|Seder]], Yom Kipur and Passover dinners, ''[[iftaar]]'' meals (marking the breaking of Ramadan fast for Muslims), and Christmas Eve/[[Winter Solstice#Observances|Winter Solstice]] services. Children's and youth's religious education classes teach about the divinity of the world and the sanctity of world religions. One of its more popular curricula, Neighboring Faiths (formerly Church Across the Street), takes middle and high school participants to visit the places of worship of many faith traditions including a Hindu temple, a Reform or Orthodox synagogue, and a Catholic church.
Many Unitarian Universalists consider themselves [[humanism|humanists]], while others hold to [[Christian]], [[Buddhist]], [[Jew]]ish, [[natural theology|natural theist]], [[Atheism|atheist]], [[agnostic]], [[Absurdism|absurdist]], [[pantheist]], [[Paganism|pagan]], [[Taoism|Taoist]], and other beliefs. Most choose to attach no particular theological label to their beliefs. This diversity of views is considered a strength in the Unitarian Universalist movement. The emphasis remains on the individual search for meaning among its members rather than adherence to any particular doctrine. Many UU congregations have study groups that examine the traditions and spiritual practices of [[Neopaganism]], [[Christianity]], [[Buddhism]], [[Judaism]], [[Islam]], [[Pantheism]], and other faiths. Some UU ministers, such as the Reverend [[James Ishmael Ford]], are also ordained [[Zen]] teachers. Other UU ministers, such as the Reverend David Miller, are [[atheist]]s. There are [[Buddhist meditation]] teachers, [[Sufi]] teachers, as well as [[gnostic]] and [[episcopi vagantes]] clerics. Some view their Jewish heritage as primary, and others see the concept of God as unhelpful in their personal spiritual journeys. While Sunday services in most congregations tend to be spiritual in nature (as different from theological), it is not unusual for a part of a church's membership to attend pagan, Buddhist, or other spiritual study or worship groups as an alternative means of worship.

In several surveys,&lt;ref name=&quot;surveys&quot;&gt;John Dart, ed. [http://www.uua.org/news/011205.html Surveys: 'UUism' unique Churchgoers from elsewhere]. ''Christian Century''&lt;/ref&gt; Unitarian Universalists in the United States most often identified themselves as [[humanism|humanists]], while smaller numbers identified themselves as [[Earth-centered religion|earth-centered]], [[agnostic]], [[theism|theistic]], [[atheism|atheistic]], [[Buddhist]], [[Christian]], or [[pagan]].

There is great variety among Unitarian Universalist congregations, with some favoring particular religious beliefs or forms of worship over others, with many more home to an eclectic mix of beliefs. Regardless of their orientation, most congregations are fairly open to differing beliefs, though not always with various faith traditions represented to the same degree.

There is also a wide variety in how congregations conceive of themselves. Congregations call themselves &quot;churches,&quot; &quot;societies,&quot; &quot;fellowships,&quot; &quot;congregations,&quot; or eschew the use of any particular descriptor (e.g. &quot;Sierra Foothills Unitarian Universalists&quot;). Whether a congregation is a 'fellowship' or a 'church' sometimes hinges on whether it is led by one (or more) minister(s): those without ministers being fellowships, those with ministers being churches. Many use the name &quot;Unitarian Universalist,&quot; (and a few &quot;Universalist Unitarian&quot;), having gradually adopted this formulation since consolidation in 1961. Others use names that reflect their historic roots by keeping simply the designation &quot;Unitarian&quot; or &quot;Universalist&quot; (e.g. &quot;Community Unitarian Church at White Plains&quot;). A few congregations use neither. For some congregations, the name can be a clue to their theological orientation. For others, avoidance of the word &quot;church&quot; indicates a desire to distance itself from traditional Christian theology. Sometimes the use of another term may simply indicate a congregation's lay-led or relatively new status. However, some UU congregations have grown to appreciate alternative terms such as ''fellowship'' and retained them even though they have grown much larger or lost features sometimes associated with their use (such as, in the case of fellowships, a traditionally lay-led worship model).&lt;ref&gt;See for examples: [http://www.uufellowship.org Unitarian Universalist Fellowship of Northern Westchester] and [http://www.uuathensga.org/ Unitarian Universalist Fellowship of Athens].&lt;/ref&gt;

Also of note is that there are many more people who identify as UU on surveys than those who attend UU churches (by a factor of four in a recent survey),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adherents.com/rel_USA.html Largest Religious Groups in the United States of America], Adherents.com&lt;/ref&gt; reflecting those who have never joined (and lapsed members) but nonetheless consider themselves part of the UU movement.

===Approach to sacred writings===
A Unitarian Universalist approach to the Christian [[Bible]] and other sacred works is given in ''Our Unitarian Universalist Faith: Frequently Asked Questions'', published by the UUA:

&lt;blockquote&gt;We do not, however, hold the Bible – or any other account of human experience – to be either an infallible guide or the exclusive source of truth. Much biblical material is mythical or legendary. Not that it should be discarded for that reason! Rather, it should be treasured for what it is. We believe that we should read the Bible as we read other books – with imagination and a critical eye. We also respect the sacred literature of other religions. Contemporary works of science, art, and social commentary are valued as well. We hold, in the words of an old liberal formulation, that &quot;revelation is not sealed.&quot; Unitarian Universalists aspire to truth as wide as the world – we look to find truth anywhere, universally.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In short, Unitarian Universalists respect the important religious texts of other religions. UUs believe that all religions can coexist if viewed with the concept of love for one's neighbor and for oneself. Other church members who do not believe in a particular text or doctrine are encouraged to respect it as a historically significant literary work that should be viewed with an open mind. It is intended that in this way, individuals from all religions or spiritual backgrounds could live peaceably.

===Elevator speeches===
In 2004, ''UU World'' magazine asked for contributions of &quot;[[elevator pitch|elevator speeches]]&quot; explaining Unitarian Universalism.&lt;ref&gt;UU World Magazine. Unitarian Universalist Association. July/August 2004. http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa4071/is_200407/ai_n9458199/&lt;/ref&gt; These are short speeches that could be made in the course of an elevator ride to those who knew nothing of the religion. Here are examples of the speeches submitted:

{{quote | In Unitarian Universalist congregations, we gather in community to support our individual spiritual journeys. We trust that openness to one another's experiences will enhance our understanding of our own links with the divine, with our history, and with one another. | Rev. Jonalu Johnstone, Oklahoma City, OK&lt;ref name=affirmations&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.uuworld.org/2003/06/affirmations.html
| title = Affirmations: Elevator speeches
| accessdate = 2007-02-24
| work = uuaworld.org
| publisher = [[Unitarian Universalist Association]]}}
&lt;/ref&gt;}}

{{quote | Most Unitarian Universalists believe that nobody has a monopoly on all truth, or ultimate proof of the truth of everything in any one belief.  Therefore, one's own truth is unprovable, as is that of others. Consequently, we should respect the beliefs of others, as well as their right to hold those beliefs. Conversely, we expect that others should respect our right to our own beliefs. Several UU's then, would likely hold as many different beliefs. Other beliefs they may hold in common are a respect for others, for nature, and for common decency, leading to a particular caring for the poor, the weak and the downtrodden. As a result, issues of justice, including social justice are held in common among most. | Gene Douglas, Harrah, OK&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.uuduluth.org/newsletters/nov06news.html
| title = Dear Ones
| accessdate = 2007-02-24
| author = Rev. Karen Johnson Gustafson
| year = 2006
| month = November
| work = Unitarian Universalist Congregation of Duluth Newsletter}} {{Dead link|date=November 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Worship and ritual==
As in theology, Unitarian Universalist [[worship]] and [[ritual]] are often a combination of elements derived from other faith traditions alongside original practices and symbols. In form, church services might be difficult to distinguish from those of a Protestant church, but they vary widely among congregations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sias&quot;/&gt;

===Symbols===
[[Image:UUA Logo.svg|250px|thumb|The version of the [[flaming chalice]] currently used as the logo of the [[Unitarian Universalist Association]].]]
The most common symbol of Unitarian Universalism is the [[flaming chalice]], often framed by two overlapping rings that many interpret as representing Unitarianism and Universalism (the symbol has no official interpretation). The chalice itself has long been a symbol of liberal religion, and indeed liberal Christianity (the [[Christian Church (Disciples of Christ)|Disciples of Christ]] also use a chalice as their denomination symbol&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web 
| url = http://www.disciples.org/AboutTheDisciples/TheChalice/tabid/70/Default.aspx 
| title = The Chalice 
| accessdate = 2012-01-21 
| publisher = [[Christian Church (Disciples of Christ)]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;). The flaming chalice was initially the logo of the Unitarian Service Committee during the Second World War. It was created by Austrian artist Hans Deutsch, inspired by &quot;the kind of chalice which the Greeks and Romans put on their altars. The holy oil burning in it is a symbol of helpfulness and sacrifice.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.uua.org/aboutuu/chalice.html
| title = The History of the Flaming Chalice
| accessdate = 2007-02-24
| author = Adapted from the pamphlet &quot;The Flaming Chalice&quot; by Daniel D. Hotchkiss
| publisher = [[Unitarian Universalist Association]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Nevertheless, other interpretations have been suggested, such as the chalice used by the followers of Czech [[Jan Hus]] {{Citation needed|date=June 2008}}, or its vague resemblance to a cross in some stylized representations. Many UU congregations light a chalice at the beginning of worship services. Other symbols include a slightly off-center [[cross]] within a circle (a Universalist symbol associated with the Humiliati movement in the 1950s, a group of reformist, liturgically minded clergy seeking to revive Universalism).

Other symbols include a pair of open hands releasing a [[dove]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://archive.uua.org/CONG/chalices/
| title = UU Chalices and Clip Art
| accessdate = 2008-04-12
| author = Steve Bridenbaugh
| publisher = [[Unitarian Universalist Association]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Services of worship===
Religious services are usually held on Sundays and most closely resemble the form and format of Protestant worship in the Reformed tradition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sias&quot;/&gt; Services at a vast majority of congregations utilize a structure that focuses on a sermon or presentation by a minister, a lay leader of the congregation, or an invited speaker.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.uua.org/worshipweb/commonworship/vogt.html
| title = Common Worship: How and Why; The contribution of Von Ogden Vogt
| accessdate = 2007-02-24
| author = Commission on Common Worship
| year = 1983
| work = Leading Congregations in Worship: A Guide
| publisher = [[Unitarian Universalist Association]] |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070217132901/http://www.uua.org/worshipweb/commonworship/vogt.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-02-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sermons may cover a wide range of topics. Since Unitarian Universalists do not recognize a particular text or set of texts as primary or inherently superior, inspiration can be found in many different religious or cultural texts as well as the personal experiences of the minister.

The service also includes hymn-singing, accompanied by organ, piano, or other available instruments, and possibly led by a song leader or choir. The most recent worship songbook published by the denomination, ''Singing the Journey''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|isbn=1-55896-499-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; contains 75 songs and is a supplement to the older ''Singing the Living Tradition'' which contains readings as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|isbn=1-55896-260-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hymns typically sung in UU services come from a variety of sources – traditional [[hymn tune]]s with new or adapted lyrics, spirituals, folk songs from various cultures, or original compositions by Unitarian Universalist musicians are just a few. Instrumental music is also a common feature of the typical worship service, including preludes, offertory music, postludes, or music for contemplation.
 
Pastoral elements of the service may include a time for sharing Joys and Sorrows/Concerns, where individuals in the congregation are invited to [[Ceremonial use of lights|light a candle]] and/or say a few words about important events in their personal lives. Many UU services also include a time of [[meditation]] or [[prayer]], led by the minister or service leader, both spoken and silent. Responsive readings and stories for children are also typical.

Many UU congregations no longer observe the Christian sacraments of [[baptism]], [[Eucharist|communion]], or [[confirmation]], at least in their traditional forms or under their traditional names. Congregations that continue these practices under their more traditional names are often federated churches or members of the Council of Christian Churches within the Unitarian Universalist Association (CCCUUA), or may have active chapters associated with the [[Unitarian Universalist Christian Fellowship]] or similar covenant groups.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.liveoakuu.org/christian04.htm Christians 2004]{{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Child dedications&quot; often replace more traditional infant baptisms (though it should be noted that such &quot;dedications&quot; are sometimes practiced even in &quot;orthodox&quot; Christian communities that do not baptize infants for theological reasons). Annual celebrations of [[Water Communion]] and [[Flower Communion]] may replace or supplement Christian-style communion (though many pluralist and Christian-oriented congregations may celebrate or otherwise make provisions for communion on Christian holy days).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.westhartforduu.org/sermons/my_neighbor.html
| title = Who is My Neighbor? A Homily for World Wide Communion Sunday
| accessdate = 2007-02-24
| author = Rev. Jan K. Nielsen
| date = October 6, 2002 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070311025551/http://www.westhartforduu.org/sermons/my_neighbor.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-03-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Confirmation may be replaced by a &quot;[[Coming of Age (Unitarian Universalism)|Coming of Age]]&quot; program, in which teenagers explore their individual religious identity, often developing their own credo. After they have completed exploring their spiritual beliefs, they write a speech about it which they then personally deliver to the congregation.

==Politics==
{{Unreferenced section|date=January 2010}}

===Historical politics of Unitarians===
{{main|Unitarianism}}
In the 19th century, Unitarians and Universalists were active in [[abolitionism]], the [[women's movement]], the [[temperance movement]], and other [[social reform]] movements. The [[National Women's Rights Convention|second woman's rights convention]] was held at the [[First Unitarian Church of Rochester|First Unitarian Church of Rochester, New York]].

===Historical politics of Universalists===
{{main|Universalist Church of America}}

===Politics of UUs===
[[Image:Civil marriage is a civil right.JPG|right|thumb|250px|A Unitarian Assembly in [[Louisville, Kentucky]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.firstulou.org/ |title=First Unitarian Church of Louisville |publisher=Firstulou.org |date= |accessdate=2011-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Historically, Unitarian Universalists have often been active in political causes, notably the [[civil rights]] movement,&lt;ref&gt;Smith, Amanda, [http://www.gainformer.com/files/Unitarian%20Universalists.htm Unitarian Universalist Church Has Rich Civil Rights History]&lt;/ref&gt; the [[gay rights movement]], the [[social justice]] movement, and the [[feminist movement]].

[[Susan B. Anthony]], a Unitarian and [[Quaker]], was extremely influential in the women's [[suffrage]] movement. Unitarian Universalists and Quakers still share many principles, notably that they are creedless religions with a long-standing commitment to social justice. It is therefore common to see Unitarian Universalists and Quakers working together.

UU's were and are still very involved in the fight to end [[racism]] in the United States. [[John Haynes Holmes]], a Unitarian minister and social activist at The Community Church of New York—Unitarian Universalist was among the founders of both the [[National Association for the Advancement of Colored People]] (NAACP) in 1909 and the [[American Civil Liberties Union]] (ACLU), chairing the latter for a time. [[James J. Reeb]], a minister at [[All Souls Church, Unitarian (Washington, D.C.)|All Souls Church, Unitarian]], in [[Washington, D.C.]] and a member of the [[Southern Christian Leadership Conference]], was clubbed in [[Selma, Alabama]] on March 8, 1965, and died two days later of massive head trauma. Two weeks after his death, [[Viola Liuzzo]], a Unitarian Universalist civil rights activist, was murdered by white supremacists after her participation in the protest march from Selma to Montgomery, Alabama. The [[Selma to Montgomery marches]] for voting rights are best known as [[Bloody Sunday (1965)|Bloody Sunday]], although technically that refers only to March 7, the most violent day of the three.

The past head of the Unitarian Universalist Association 2001–2009, Rev. [[William G. Sinkford]], is [[African-American]], making Unitarian Universalism one of the first traditionally white denominations to be headed by a member of a racial minority.&lt;ref&gt;Maxwell, Bill; 11 April 2008; &quot;Leading the Unitarian Universalist Association, a faith without a creed&quot;; St. Petersburg Times&lt;/ref&gt;

While [[Modern liberalism in the United States|political liberals]] make up a clear majority of Unitarian Universalists, the UU movement aspires to diversity, and officially welcomes congregants regardless of their political views. Politically conservative Unitarian Universalists point out that neither religious liberalism nor the Principles and Purposes of the UUA require liberal politics. Like the beliefs of Unitarian Universalists, politics are decided by individuals, not by congregations or the denomination.

Several congregations have undertaken a series of organizational, procedural and practical steps to become acknowledged as a &quot;[[Welcoming Congregation]]&quot;: a congregation which has taken specific steps to welcome and integrate gay, lesbian, bisexual &amp; transgender (GLBT) members. UU ministers perform [[same-sex unions]] and now [[same-sex marriages]] where legal (and sometimes when not, as a form of civil protest). On June 29, 1984, the Unitarian Universalists became the first major church &quot;to approve religious blessings on homosexual unions.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E0DB1539F93AA15755C0A962948260 &quot;Unitarians Endorse Homosexual Marriages&quot;], UPI, ''New York Times'', 29 June 1984.&lt;/ref&gt; Unitarian Universalists have been in the forefront of the work to make same-sex marriages legal in their local states and provinces, as well as on the national level. Gay men and lesbians are also regularly [[ordained]] as ministers, and a number of gay and lesbian ministers have, themselves, now become legally married to their partners. In May 2004, [[Arlington Street Church (Boston)|Arlington Street Church]] was the site of the first state-sanctioned same-sex marriage in the United States. The official stance of the UUA is for the legalization of same-sex marriage—&quot;Standing on the Side of Love.&quot; In 2004 UU Minister Rev. Debra Haffner of [[The Religious Institute on Sexual Morality, Justice, and Healing]] published An Open Letter on Religious Leaders on Marriage Equality to affirm same-sex marriage from a multi-faith perspective. In December 2009, Washington, DC Mayor [[Adrian Fenty]] signed the bill to legalize same-sex marriage for the [[District of Columbia]] in [[All Souls Church, Unitarian (Washington, D.C.)]].  

Many congregations are heavily involved in projects and efforts aimed at supporting environmental causes and [[sustainability]]. These are often termed &quot;seventh principle&quot; activities because of the seventh principle quoted above.

==Controversies==
===External===
====Lack of formal creed====
The lack of formal creed has been a cause for criticism among some who argue that Unitarian Universalism is thus without religious content. In May 2004, [[Texas]] [[Comptroller]] [[Carole Keeton Strayhorn]] ruled that Unitarian Universalism was not a &quot;religion&quot; because it &quot;does not have one system of belief,&quot; and stripped the Red River Unitarian Universalist Church in [[Denison, Texas]], of its tax-exempt status. However, within weeks, Strayhorn reversed her decision.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.window.state.tx.us/news/40524church.html |title=News Release From Carole Keeton Strayhorn |publisher=Window.state.tx.us |date=2004-05-24 |accessdate=2011-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Confusion with other groups====
There are separate movements and organizations of Christians who hold to classical Unitarian or [[Christian Universalist]] theology and do not belong to the Unitarian Universalist Association or consider themselves UUs. The [[American Unitarian Conference]] and the [[Christian Universalist Association]] are the two most significant organizations representing these theological beliefs today. Christians who hold these beliefs tend to consider themselves the true Unitarians or Universalists and heirs of the theological legacy of the original [[American Unitarian Association]] or [[Universalist Church of America]], and they do not wish to be confused with UUs and UUism. The [[Unity Church]] is another denomination that is often confused with Unitarian Universalism.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.americanunitarian.org/voicearticle.htm &quot;Why the American Unitarian Conference Had to Be Formed&quot;] and [http://www.christianuniversalist.org/articles/unitarian.html &quot;What Is the Difference between Christian Universalism and Unitarian Universalism?&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Internal===
====Language of reverence====
During the presidency of the Rev. William Sinkford, debate within the UU movement has roiled over his call to return to or create an authentic UU &quot;language of reverence.&quot; Sinkford has suggested that UUs have abandoned traditional religious language, thereby abandoning words with potential power to others who will then dictate their meanings in the public sphere. He has suggested that Unitarian Universalists regain their proper seat at the interfaith table by making this language their own. Others have reacted to this call by believing it to be part of an effort to return UU congregations to more orthodox Christian worship patterns. Sinkford has denied this, citing the words of UU humanists as examples of what he means by the &quot;language of reverence.&quot; The debate seems{{Or|date=November 2010}} part and parcel of an attendant effort at increasing biblical literacy amongst Unitarian Universalists, including the publication of a book by the UUA's Beacon Press written by former UUA President John Buehrens.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Buehrens |first=John A. |url=http://www.beliefnet.com/story/132/story_13272_1.html |title=Past Unitarian Universalist Association President John A. Buehrens on why even humanists should read the Bible – |publisher=Beliefnet.com |date= |accessdate=2011-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The book is titled ''Understanding the Bible: An Introduction for Skeptics, Seekers, and Religious Liberals'',&lt;ref&gt;ISBN 0-8070-1053-7&lt;/ref&gt; and is meant as a kind of handbook to be read alongside the Bible itself. It provides interpretative strategies, so that UUs (among others) might be able to engage in public debate about what the Bible says from a liberal religious perspective, rather than relinquishing to religious conservatives, and other more literal interpretations, all control over the book's contents and significance in matters of public and civic import. Also an important work by Rev. Buehrens, along with Forrest Church, is ''A Chosen Faith: An Introduction to Unitarian Universalism'',&lt;ref&gt;ISBN 0-8070-1617-9&lt;/ref&gt; in which the authors explore the many sources of the living tradition of their chosen faith.

====Borrowing from other religions====
The &quot;borrowing&quot; of religious rituals from other faith traditions by Unitarian Universalists was discussed at the UU General Assembly in 2001 during a seminar titled Cultural Appropriation: Reckless Borrowing or Appropriate Cultural Sharing by the Religious Education Dept, UUA.&lt;ref name=&quot;CulturApp&quot;&gt;[http://www.uua.org/ga/ga01/2038.html Cultural Appropriation: Reckless Borrowing or Appropriate Cultural Sharing] Reported for the Web by Dwight Ernest, July 24, 2001, Unitarian Universalist Association&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uua.org/leaders/leaderslibrary/leaderslibrary/interconnections/45522.shtml When Worship Becomes Cultural Misappropriation], September 15, 2007, UU Interconnections&lt;/ref&gt; Of particular discussion was the borrowing rituals and practices that are sacred to specific tribes or using spiritual practices without real context.

{{Quotation|When UUs pick and choose from these things, it trivializes their spiritual practices. The specificity [of their use] is so complete, that visiting Native Americans do not participate in another tribe's rituals, and to do so would be perceived as foolish. I would not even practice the rituals of my own tribe, because I am not an elder or spiritual leader. If this is true of her own people, then the use of these things by others who share no cultural context is seen not only as particularly foolish and inappropriate.

Not all of this usage is inappropriate, though. Some taped music, written prayers, that kind of thing, might be alright, but it's not right to fool around with it. If it's not in context, if the user is not walking with us, if the user is not part of our struggle, then it is presumptuous.|Reverend Danielle Di Bona|2001 General Assembly&lt;ref name=&quot;CulturApp&quot;/&gt;}}

==Organizations==
*The [[Unitarian Universalist Association]] (UUA) of [[Wiktionary:congregation|Congregations]] is the largest association of Unitarian, Universalist, and Unitarian Universalist congregations in the world, and the most well-known. It operates mainly within the United States. A few Unitarian and UU congregations in other countries, such as San Miguel de Allende (Mexico), Puerto Rico,&lt;ref&gt;[http://uupuertorico.org/ Congregation Unitarian Universalist]. Uupuertorico.org. Retrieved on 2010-09-29.&lt;/ref&gt; Auckland (New Zealand),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unitarian.org.nz/auckland/ |title=Welcome! |publisher=Unitarian.org.nz |date= |accessdate=2011-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a few others are also members of the UUA. Currently, the UUA represents 1,078 member congregations[11] that collectively include more than 217,000 members.
*The [[Canadian Unitarian Council]] (CUC) split off from the Unitarian Universalist Association in 2002 and serves Unitarian, Universalist, and Unitarian Universalist congregations in [[Canada]].
*[[Young Religious Unitarian Universalists]] (YRUU) is the youth organization within the Unitarian Universalist Association and the Canadian Unitarian Council. It was created in 1981 and 1982, at two conferences, Common Ground 1 &amp; 2. Common Ground was called to form a UUA-controlled replacement for [[Liberal Religious Youth]] (LRY), the youth organization that preceded YRUU. LRY was dissolved by the Unitarian Universalist Association, and its assets absorbed by the UUA.
*[[Continental Unitarian Universalist Young Adult Network]] (C*UUYAN) is the Continental (US &amp; Canada) Unitarian Universalist Young Adult Network, an organization by and for Unitarian Universalist young adults (age 18–35, inclusive).
*Unitarian, Universalist and Unitarian Universalist churches worldwide are represented in the [[International Council of Unitarians and Universalists]] (ICUU). The UUA and CUC are both members of this organization.
*The [[Unitarian Universalist Service Committee]] is a [[nonsectarian]] organization devoted to promoting human rights and social justice worldwide.
*[[Promise the Children]] is a 501(c)(3) nonprofit. Promise the Children's mission is to help Unitarian Universalists advocate for and with children and youth. Promise the Children is also an Independent Affiliate of the [[Unitarian Universalist Association]].
*The [[Covenant of Unitarian Universalist Pagans]] (CUUPS) is an association of Unitarian Universalists who define themselves as Pagans or Neopagans.
*The [[Unitarian Universalist Christian Fellowship]] (UUCF) is an association of Unitarian Universalists who define themselves as Christians.
*The [[Church of the Larger Fellowship]] (CLF) exists to serve UUs remote from any physical congregation.
*The [[Church of the Larger Fellowship#Church of the Younger Fellowship|Church of the Younger Fellowship]] (CYF) is the web based Young Adult Ministry of CLF.
*[[Religious Youth Empowerment, Inc.]] (RYE) is a 501(c)(3) nonprofit. RYE is a nonprofit created by bridged YRUUers whose goals are to empower and fund the youth and help network between youth of different districts as well as between youth and young adults. RYE is currently not yet affiliated with the [[Unitarian Universalist Association]].

==Number of members==
As of February 2011, congregations in the United States totaled 1,018, and 1,046 when including two congregations in the [[U.S. Virgin Islands]], 19 in Canada, six in other countries{{which?|date=September 2011}}, plus 28 multi-denominational congregations affiliated with the UUA: 17 in [[Massachusetts|Mass.]], four in [[Illinois|Ill.]], three in [[New Hampshire|N.H.]], two in [[Vermont|Vt.]], and one each in [[Maine|Me.]]  and [[District of Columbia|D.C.]]. Seven of the ten US states with the most congregations are also among the most populous states; the state with the most congregations and members is the fourteenth most populous state, Massachusetts; Vermont is No. 1 relative to its total population. A map using [[2010 United States Census|2010 U.S. Census]] data showing the relative number of congregations per 1 million people is posted here.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://www.uuworld.org/ideas/articles/186525.shtml?utm_source=n
|title= Unitarian Universalist congregations by state
|accessdate= September 24, 2011
|author= 
|last= Walton
|first= Christopher L.
|coauthors= Todd, Kathy 
|date= Fall 2011 8.15.11
|work= weekly web magazine 
|publisher= Unitarian Universalist Association of Congregations
|quote= Map includes 1,018 UUA member congregations in the United States using data collected by the UUA through February 2011, but does not include the [[Church of the Larger Fellowship]] (which is headquartered in Mass. but serves a geographically dispersed community. The map does include multidenominational congregations affiliated with the UUA
}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

At the time of the merger between Universalists and Unitarians, membership was perhaps half a million. Membership rose after the merger but then fell in the 1970s.

In 1956, Sam Wells wrote that &quot;Unitarians and Universalists are considering merger which would have total U.S. membership of 160,000 (500,000 in world)&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author = Wells, Sam, ed.| title = The World's Great Religions V.3 Glories of Christiandom| location = New York|publisher = Time Incorporated|year = 1957|page = 205}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1965 Conkin wrote that &quot;In 1961, at the time of the merger, membership [in the United States] was 104,821 in 651 congregations, and the joint membership soared to its historically highest level in the mid-1960s (an estimated 250,000) before falling sharply back in the 1970s [...]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author = Conkin, Paul K.|title = American Originals: Homemade Varieties of Christianity|publisher = The University of North Carolina Press|location = Chapel Hill, NC|year = 1997|page = 95|ISBN=0-8078-4649-X }}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the 2008 ''Yearbook of American &amp; Canadian Churches'', the Unitarian Universalist Association of Congregations claimed 214,738 members in 2002.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author = Lindner, Eileen W., ed.| title = Yearbook of American &amp; Canadian Churches 2008| location = Nashville|publisher = Abingdon Press|year = 2008|page = 381}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Estimates from the 1990s put world membership between 120,000 and 600,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adherents.com/Na/Na_642.html |title=Adherents.com |publisher=Adherents.com |date= |accessdate=2011-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United States, the American Religious Identification Survey reported 629,000 members describing themselves as Unitarian Universalist in 2001, an increase from 502,000 reported in a similar survey in 1990.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gc.cuny.edu/faculty/research_briefs/aris/key_findings.htm |title=The Graduate Center, CUNY |publisher=Gc.cuny.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The highest concentrations are in [[New England]] and around [[Seattle, Washington]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Unitarians as a Percentage of All Residents|url=http://www.valpo.edu/geomet/pics/geo200/religion/unitarian.gif|work=Glenmary Research Center|publisher=Religious Congregations and Membership in the United States, 2000|accessdate=23 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The U.S. Religious Landscape Survey, conducted in 2007 by the Pew Forum on Religion and Public Life and featuring a sample size of over 35,000, puts the proportion of American adults identifying as Unitarian Universalist at 0.3%.&lt;ref name=r1&gt;{{cite web|url=http://religions.pewforum.org/affiliations |title=U.S. Religious Landscape Survey |publisher=Religions.pewforum.org |date= |accessdate=2011-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While the 2001 Canadian census done by Statistics Canada put Canadian Unitarians at 17,480,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www12.statcan.ca/english/census01/products/standard/themes/RetrieveProductTable.cfm?Temporal=2001&amp;PID=55822&amp;APATH=3&amp;GID=431515&amp;METH=1&amp;PTYPE=55440&amp;THEME=56&amp;FOCUS=0&amp;AID=0&amp;PLACENAME=0&amp;PROVINCE=0&amp;SEARCH=0&amp;GC=0&amp;GK=0&amp;VID=0&amp;FL=0&amp;RL=0&amp;FREE=0 97F0022XCB2001002]. 2.statcan.ca (2010-03-09). Retrieved on 2010-09-29.&lt;/ref&gt; the latest membership statistics from the Canadian Unitarian Council show as of September 1, 2007 they had 5,150 &quot;official&quot; members.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cuc.ca/whos_who/Admin/phil/InfoTopics2008February.pdf |title=Membership – The more it changes, the more it stays the same |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2011-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable members==
{{details|List of Unitarians, Universalists, and Unitarian Universalists}}

==Notable congregations==
{{Main|List of Unitarian, Universalist, and Unitarian Universalist churches}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Religion}}
*[[Congregationalist polity]]
*[[Post-Christian]]
*[[Religious humanism]]
*[[United and uniting churches]]
*[[United Church of Christ]]
*[[Free Christian]]ity

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*''Religion among the Unitarian Universalists; converts in the stepfathers' house'' by Robert B. Tapp, New York: Seminar Press, 1973, ISBN 0-12-914650-1
*''A Chosen Faith: An Introduction to Unitarian Universalism'' (Revised edition) by [[John A. Buehrens]] and [[Forrest Church]], 1998, [[Beacon Press]], ISBN 0-8070-1617-9.
*''To Re-Enchant the World: A Philosophy of Unitarian Universalism'' by Richard Grigg, 2004
*''Unitarian Universalism: A Narrative History'' by David E. Bumbaugh, 2001

==External links==
{{Wiktionary}}
*[http://uuyan.org Continental Unitarian Universalist Young Adult Network] (C*UUYAN)
*[http://www.uuworld.org/ UU World Magazine]
*[http://www.unitarianuniversalism.tv/ Unitarian Universalism TV] (UU TV)
*[http://www.uuism.net/uuwiki/index.php/Main_Page Unitarian Universalist Wiki] (UUWiki)
*[http://www.hds.harvard.edu/library/bms/merger_timeline_1900s.html Unitarian-Universalist Merger Timeline] from [[Harvard Divinity School]]'s website.
*{{dmoz|Society/Religion_and_Spirituality/Unitarianism_and_Universalism/|Unitarianism and Universalism}}
*[http://unitarian-universalist.wetpaint.com/ Unitarian-Universalist Encyclopedia]
*[http://www.DiscoverUU.com DiscoverUU]

{{Unitarian, Universalist and Unitarian Universalist topics}}
{{Religion topics}}

[[Category:Unitarian Universalism| ]]
[[Category:Peace churches]]

[[ar:توحيدية عالمية]]
[[es:Unitarismo universalista]]
[[eo:Unitaria Universalismo]]
[[fa:جهان‌گرایی توحیدگرا]]
[[fr:Universalisme unitarien]]
[[id:Unitarian Universalisme]]
[[it:Unitariani Universalisti]]
[[he:אוניברסליזם יוניטריאני]]
[[nl:Unitaristisch Universalisme]]
[[ja:ユニテリアン・ユニヴァーサリズム]]
[[pl:Uniwersalizm unitariański]]
[[pt:Unitário-Universalismo]]
[[sco:Unitarian Universalism]]
[[simple:Unitarian Universalism]]
[[sl:Univerzalni unitarizem]]
[[fi:Unitaariuniversalismi]]
[[tr:Üniteryan Üniversalizm]]
[[zh:一神普救派]]</text>
      <sha1>fw3y90gj97ee1y13ath7lzw22lno081</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
