<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Uposatha</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7646521</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520279537</id>
      <parentid>514244500</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-28T16:01:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Zeeyanketu</username>
        <id>16772875</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted [[WP:AGF|good faith]] edit(s) by [[Special:Contributions/198.108.80.10|198.108.80.10]] using [[WP:STiki|STiki]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25255">{{Buddhism}}
The '''Uposatha''' ({{lang-sa|Upavasatha}}) is [[Buddhism|Buddhist]] day of observance, in existence from the Buddha's time (500 BCE), and still being kept today in [[Buddhism|Buddhist]] countries.&lt;ref&gt;For a description of the contemporary practice of the Uposatha in Thailand, see Khantipalo (1982a), which is also excerpted in this article below. 
Kariyawasam (1995), ch. 3, also underlines the continuity of the ancient ''uposatha'' practice in Sri Lanka: &quot;The ''poya'' [Sinhala for ''uposatha''] observance, which is as old as Buddhism itself, has been followed by the Sinhala Buddhists up to the present day, even after the Christian calendar came to be used for secular matters. Owing to its significance in the religious life of the local Buddhists, all the full-moon days have been declared public holidays by the government.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The uposatha day is sometimes likened to the Judeo-Christian notion of the Sabbath.  Pali English dictionaries that define &quot;Uposatha&quot; as &quot;Sabbath,&quot; are Buddhadatta (2002), p. 63, and, and PED(Rhys-Davids &amp; Stede,1921-25), p. 151. 
For an example of the Uposatha being equated with Sabbath by a modern Buddhist master, see Mahasi (''undated''), p. 2, where he writes: &quot;For lay people, these rules [of discipline] comprise the [[The Eight Precepts|eight precepts]] which Buddhist devotees observe on the Sabbath days (uposatha) and during periods of meditation.&quot;  Harvey (1990), p. 192, also refers to the ''uposatha'' as &quot;sabbath-like.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The Buddha taught that the Uposatha day is for &quot;the cleansing of the defiled mind,&quot; resulting in inner calm and joy.&lt;ref&gt;Thanissaro (1997b); Anguttara Nikaya 3.70: Muluposatha Sutta.&lt;/ref&gt; On this day, lay [[upasaka|disciples]] and [[bhikkhu|monks]] intensify their practice, deepen their knowledge and express communal commitment through millennia-old acts of lay-monastic reciprocity.

==Observance days==

Depending on the culture and time period, uposatha days have been observed from two to six days each lunar month.

===Theravada countries===

In general, Uposatha is observed about once a week in [[Theravada Buddhism|Theravada]] countries&lt;ref&gt;, with the full moon being the most important one, followed by the new moon. Each lunar month has eight days after both the new moon and full moon Uposatha days and then either six or seven days after the other two quarter moon Uposatha days. Thus, in relation to the [[Gregorian calendar]]'s seven-day week, sometimes there are two uposatha days in a week (such as occurred the week of August 17, 2006, when uposatha days fell on August 17 and August 23, 2006) and sometimes there are none (such as occurred the week of January 15, 2006, which fell between uposatha days on January 14 and January 22, 2006).  Nonetheless, there are four uposatha days a month and the average solar month's week has one uposatha day.&lt;/ref&gt; in accordance with the four [[lunar phases|phases]] of the moon: the [[new moon]], the [[full moon]], and the two quarter moons in between.&lt;ref&gt;More specifically, using a [[Buddhist calendar|Buddhist lunar calendar]], Uposatha is observed on the following four days of the lunar month (PTS, 1921-25, pp. 151-2): 
*first ([[new moon]])
*eighth (first quarter or waxing moon)
*fifteenth ([[full moon]])
*twenty-third (last quarter or waning moon)
According to the ''Pali English Dictionary'' (Rhys Davids and Stede, 1921-25, pp. 16, 152), the lunar month's eighth day (that is, the eighth day after the new moon) and twenty-third day (which is the eighth day after the full moon) are called in Pali ''atthama,'' which literally means the &quot;eighth,&quot; that is, the eighth day of the lunar half-month.&lt;/ref&gt; In some communities, such as in Sri Lanka, only the new moon and full moon are observed as uposatha days.&lt;ref&gt;Nyanaponika &amp; Bodhi (1999), pp. 24, 307 ''n''. 26.  Nyanaponika &amp; Bodhi refers to the quarter-moon days as &quot;semi-Uposatha.&quot; Harvey (1990), p. 192, states that the ''uposatha'' is observed &quot;at the full-moon, new-moon and, less importantly, two half-moon days.&quot;  He goes on to state: &quot;Except at times of major festivals, observance [''uposatha''] days are attended only by the more devout, who spend a day and night at their local monastery.&quot; [http://www.accesstoinsight.org/lib/authors/kariyawasam/wheel402.html#ch3 Kariyawasam (1995), ch. 3], makes a similar observation in regards to modern Sinhalese society: &quot;The popular practice is to observe [the Eight Precepts] on full-moon days, and, among a few devout lay Buddhists, on the other phases of the moon as well.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;  

In [[Burma]], Uposatha (called {{my|ဥပုသ်}} ''ubot nei'') is observed by more pious Buddhists on the following days: waxing moon ({{my|လဆန်း}} ''la hsan''), full moon ({{my|လပြည့်နေ့}} ''la pyei nei''), waning moon ({{my|လဆုတ်}} ''la hsote''), and new moon ({{my|လကွယ်နေ့}} ''la kwe nei'').&lt;ref name=&quot;spiro&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Buddhism and Society: A Great Tradition and its Burmese Viscittudes |last=Melford |first=Spiro |year=1970 |publisher=Harper and Row |isbn= |pages=214–228 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The most common days of observance are the full moon and the new moon. In pre-colonial Burma, the Uposatha day (commonly rendered as the Buddhist Sabbath in English) was a legal holiday that was observed primarily in urban areas, where secular activities like business transactions came to a halt.&lt;ref name=&quot;spiro&quot;/&gt; However, since colonial rule, Sunday has replaced the Uposatha day as the legal day of rest. All major Burmese [[Buddhist holiday]]s occur on Uposatha days, namely [[Thingyan]], the beginning of the Buddhist lent (beginning in the full moon of Waso, around July to the full moon of Thadingyut, around October). During this period, Uposatha is more commonly observed by Buddhists than during the rest of the year. During Uposatha days, Buddhist monks at each monastery assemble and recite the [[Patimokkha]] (a concise compilation of the [[Vinaya]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Buddhism: An Illustrated Review|publisher=Hanthawaddy Printing Works|location=Rangoon, Burma|date=1905|volume=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For a 2012 calendar of Thai uposatha days, see John Bullitt's [http://www.accesstoinsight.org/ptf/dhamma/sila/uposatha2012.html &quot;Calendar of Uposatha Days.&quot;]

===Mahayana countries===

In [[Mahayana]] countries that use the [[Chinese calendar]], the Uposatha days are observed six times a month, on the 8th, 14th, 15th, 23rd and final two days of each lunar month.  In Japan, these six days are known as the {{nihongo|'''roku sainichi'''|六斎日|Six Days of Fasting}}.

=== Names of Full Moon Uposatha Days ===
The Pali names of the uposatha days are based on the Sanskrit names of the ''[[Nakshatra|nakśatra]]'' (Pali: ''nakkhatta''), the constellations or lunar mansions through which the moon passes within a lunar month.&lt;ref&gt;See [[Nakshatra]], [[Hindu calendar]], ''Sanskrit English Dictionary'' by Monier Williams, s.v. 'nakśatra'.&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;margin:auto;&quot;
|+'''Full Moon Uposatha Day Names'''
|-
! Associated Month
! Pali 
! Sanskrit
! Burmese 
! Sinhala 
! Thai 
|-
| January
| Phussa
| [[Pushya|Puṣya]]
| Pyatho
| Duruthu 
| Pusaya (ปุศยะ)
|-
| February
| Māgha
| [[Maghā]]
| Tabodwe
| Navam
| Makha (มาฆะ)
|-
| March
| Phagguṇa 
| [[Pūrva Phalgunī|Phalgunī]]
| Tabaung
| Medin (Maedhin) 
| Pholkuni (ผลคุณี)
|-
| April
| Citta
| [[Nakshatra|Chitrā]]
| Tagu
| Bak 
| Chittra (จิตรา)
|-
| May
| Visākhā
| [[Viśākhā]]
| Kason
| [[Vesak]] 
| Visakha (วิสาขา)
|-
| June
| Jeṭṭhā
| [[Jyeshtha|Jyeṣṭha]]
| Nayon 
| Poson
| Chetta (เชษฐา)
|-
| July
| Āsāḷhā
| [[Pūrva Ashādhā|Aṣāḍhā]]
| Waso
| Esala (Aesala)
| Asarnha (อาสาฬหะ) 
|-
| August
| Sāvana
| [[Śrāvaṇa]]
| Wagaung
| Nikini
| Savana (สาวนะ)
|-
| September
| Poṭṭhapāda
| [[Pūrva Bhādrapadā|Bhādrapadā]]
| Tawthalin
|  Binara 
| Phattarapratha (ภัทรปทา)
|-
| October
| Assayuja
| [[Ashvinī|Aśvinī]] 
| Thadingyut
| Vap
| Assavani (อัศวนี)
|-
| November
| Kattikā
| [[Kṛttikā]]
| Tazaungmon
| Il 
| Krittika (กฤติกา)
|-
| December
| Māgasira
| [[Mrigashīrsha|Mṛgaśiras]]
| Natdaw
| Unduvap 
| Maruekasira (มฤคศิระ)
|}

== History ==

The word &quot;uposatha&quot; is derived from the [[Sanskrit]] word &quot;upavasatha,&quot; which refers to the pre-Buddhistic fast day that preceded Vedic sacrifices.&lt;ref&gt;Khantipalo (1982a); Ñanavara (1993), question No.&amp;nbsp;1 [http://www.accesstoinsight.org/lib/authors/nanavara/uposatha.html#qa]; and the Pali English Dictionary(Rhys-Davids &amp; Stede,1921-25, p. 151).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Khantipalo (1982a) also translates &quot;uposatha&quot; as literally meaning &quot;entering [a monastery] to stay&quot; but no other source supports this.&lt;/ref&gt;  

In the Buddha's time, some ascetics used the new and full moon as opportunities to present their teachings.  The Uposatha Day was instituted by the [[Gautama Buddha|Buddha]] at the request of King [[Bimbisara]], and the Buddha instructed the monks to give teachings to the laypeople on this day, and told the monks to recite the [[Patimokkha]] every second Uposatha day.&lt;ref&gt;Rhys Davids &amp; Oldenberg (1881), pp. 240-41. Also see Khantipalo (1982a) and Pali English Dictionary(Rhys Davids &amp; Stede, 1921-25, p. 152).&lt;/ref&gt;

== Practice ==
=== Lay practice ===

On each uposatha day, [[upasaka|devout lay people]] practice the [[Eight Precepts]].&lt;ref&gt;See, for instance, Kariyawasam (1995), Khantipalo (1982b), Ñanavara &amp; Kantasilo (1993) and Thanissaro (1997b).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Perhaps echoing the Buddha's teaching that laypeople should &quot;imitate&quot; arahants on Uposatha days (see, for instance, &quot;The Uposatha Observance Discourse&quot; in Nyanaponika &amp; Bodhi, 1999, pp. 216-18 or, using comparable wording, in Nanavara &amp; Khantasilo, 1993), Nyanaponika &amp; Bodhi (1999), p. 307, ''n''. 26, mention: &quot;... The Eight Precepts are modelled after the [[Five Precepts#Ten_Precepts|Ten Precepts]] observed by [[samanera|novice monks]], except that the seventh and eighth precepts for the novices are combined, the ninth novice precept becomes the eighth, and the tenth novice precept (non-acceptance of gold and silver, use of money) is excluded as being impracticable for a lay person.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;  

For lay practitioners who live near a [[Vihara|monastery]], the uposatha is an opportunity for them to visit a local [[Vihara|monastery]], make [[Offering (Buddhism)|offerings]], listen to Dhamma talks by monks and participate in [[Buddhist meditation|meditation]] sessions.

For lay practitioners unable to participate in the events of a local monastery, the uposatha is a time to intensify one's own meditation and Dhamma practice,&lt;ref&gt;Bullitt (2005); and, Khantipalo (1982a).&lt;/ref&gt; for instance, meditating an extra session or for a longer time,&lt;ref name=&quot;Khantipalo 1982a&quot;&gt;Khantipalo (1982a).&lt;/ref&gt; reading or [[Buddhist chant|chanting]] special [[suttas]],&lt;ref&gt;Khantipalo (1982a), for instance, suggests reading one of the following:
*Visakhuposatha Sutta (&quot;Discourse to Visakha on the Uposatha with the Eight Practices,&quot; AN 8.43) (Khantipalo, 1982b).
*[[Metta Sutta|Karaniya-metta Sutta]] (&quot;Discourse on Loving-kindness,&quot; [[Sutta Nipata|Sn]] 1.8) (Piyadassi, 1999a).
*[[Mangala Sutta|Maha-mangala Sutta]] (&quot;Discourse on Blessings,&quot; Sn 2.4) (Narada, 1985).
*[[Ratana Sutta]] (&quot;Jewel Discourse,&quot; Sn 2.1) (Piyadassi, 1999b).
*[[Dhammacakkappavattana Sutta]] (&quot;Discourse on Setting the Wheel of Dhamma in Motion,&quot; [[Samyutta Nikaya|SN]] 56.11) (Thanissaro, 1993).&lt;/ref&gt; [[anussati|recollecting]]&lt;ref&gt;See, for instance, the &quot;Muluposatha Sutta&quot; (AN 3.70) (Thanissaro, 1997b) regarding Uposatha-specific recollections and Thanissaro (1999) for the general Buddhist practice of recollections.  In the Muluposatha Sutta, the Buddha recommends practicing recollection of the [[Three Jewels]] as well as of one's own virtue (''[[Śīla|sila]]'') and of the wholesome qualities that leads to rebirth as a [[Deva (Buddhism)|deva]].  In this sutta, if one spends the Uposatha engaged in such a recollection, then that Uposatha acquires the name of the recollection, such as Dhamma-Uposatha or virtue-Uposatha.&lt;/ref&gt; or [[dana|giving]] in some special way.&lt;ref name=&quot;Khantipalo 1982a&quot;/&gt;

=== Monastic practice ===

On the new-moon and full-moon uposatha, in monasteries where there are four or more [[bhikkhu]]s,&lt;ref&gt;Rhys Davids &amp; Oldenberg (1881), p. 281.&lt;/ref&gt; the local Sangha will recite the [[Patimokkha]]. Before the recitation starts, the monks will confess any violations of the disciplinary rules to another monk or to the [[Sangha]].&lt;ref&gt;See, for instance, Buddhadatta (2002), p. 63, and Bullitt (2005).&lt;/ref&gt; Depending on the speed of the Patimokkha chanter (one of the monks), the recitation may take from 30 minutes to over an hour. Depending on the monastery, lay people may or may not be allowed to attend.&lt;ref name=&quot;Khantipalo 1982a&quot;/&gt;

=== Communal reciprocity ===

Describing his experience of Uposatha day in Thailand, Khantipalo (1982a) writes:

&quot;Early in the morning lay people give almsfood to the bhikkhus who may be walking on almsround, invited to a layman's house, or the lay people may take the food to the monastery. Usually lay people do not eat before serving their food to the bhikkhus and they may eat only once that day.... Before the meal the laity request the Eight Precepts [from the bhikkhus] ..., which they promise to undertake for a day and night. It is usual for lay people to go to the local monastery and to spend all day and night there.... [In monasteries where] there is more study, [lay people] will hear as many as three or four discourses on Dhamma delivered by senior bhikkhus and they will have books to read and perhaps classes on Abhidhamma to attend....  In a meditation monastery ..., most of their time will be spent mindfully employed – walking and seated meditation with some time given to helping the bhikkhus with their daily duties. So the whole of this day and night (and enthusiastic lay people restrict their sleep) is given over to Dhamma....&quot;

== Special uposatha days ==

In Thailand five full-moon uposatha days are of special significance and are called ''puja'', 'days of worship', :&lt;ref&gt;Bullitt (2005). Bullitt orders these special uposatha days in accordance with the Gregorian calendar, where Magha Uposatha thus starts the calendar year.  However, in accordance with Asian lunar calendars, where the new year starts in mid April, Visakha Uposatha is the first special uposatha day of the year.  The lunar calendar ordering of these days is maintained in this article for primarily two reasons: Visakha Uposatha is the most important of the uposatha festivals; and, ordering these uposatha days in this manner (i.e., Visakha Uposatha [Buddha Day], Asalha Uposatha [Dhamma Day], Magha Uposatha [Sangha Day]) celebrates the [[Triple Gem]] (Buddha, Dhamma, Sangha) in the order in which it is traditionally enumerated.  Also see [http://www.accesstoinsight.org/lib/authors/kariyawasam/wheel402.html#ch3 Kariyawasam, ch. 3, &quot;Poya Days,&quot;] where he identifies the relevance of all twelve full-moon uposatha days in contemporary Sinhala culture.&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Visakha Puja or Visakha Uposatha '''&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[[Vaisakha|Vesākha]]&quot; (Pali) is the second month of the Buddhist lunar year, usually occurring in the [[Gregorian calendar]]'s February. In Thailand this day is called 'Visakha Puja.' The word ''puja'' means &quot;veneration&quot; or &quot;offering&quot; and in Thailand is suffixed to all Uposatha days. (Pali month names are from the ''Pali English Dictionary'' (Rhys Davids &amp; Stede,1921-25, p. 531 s.v. &quot;māsa&quot;).&lt;/ref&gt; or '''[[Vesak]]''' (&quot;Buddha Day&quot;):
is the most sacred Buddhist holiday. It is the anniversary of the Buddha's birth, awakening and [[parinibbana]].&lt;ref&gt;For Mahayana Buddhists, the celebration of the [[Buddha's Birthday|Buddha's birthday]] is independent of recognitions of his awakening and parinibbana and is celebrated on the waxing moon of the fourth Chinese lunar month.&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''[[Asalha Puja]]''' or Asalha Uposatha. &lt;ref&gt;&quot;[[Aashaadha|Āsālha]]&quot; (Pali) is the fourth lunar month, usually around July.&lt;/ref&gt; (&quot;Dhamma Day&quot;):
:anniversary of the Buddha's delivering his first discourse, &quot;[[Dhammacakka Sutta]].&quot;  The three-month-long [[Vassa|Rains Retreat]] residence starts the following day.
* '''[[Pavarana|Pavarana Day]]''':&lt;ref&gt;Pavarana Day is in the seventh lunar month of [[Asvina|Assayuja]] (Pali), usually in October.&lt;/ref&gt;
:the end of the Rains Retreat residence during which time each monk atones before the Sangha for any offense they may have committed.&lt;ref&gt;Rhys Davids &amp; Oldenberg (1881), pp. 329-30.&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Anapanasati Day''':&lt;ref&gt;Anapanasati Day is the eighth lunar month of Kattika (Pali), usually in November.&lt;/ref&gt;
Anniversary of the Buddha's delivering the &quot;[[Anapanasati Sutta]].&quot; This event is not connected to an Uposatha (Poya) day in Sri Lanka and perhaps is particular to Thailand.&lt;ref&gt;The Anapanasati Sutta (&quot;Mindfulness of Breathing Discourse,&quot; [[Majjhima Nikaya|MN]] 118) (Thanissaro, 2006) opens on Pavarana Day in the town of Savatthi where the Buddha declares to an assembly of monks that he is so happy with the assembly's practice that he would stay in Savatthi another month.  After that month passes, the Buddha delivers the core instructions of the Anapanasati Sutta, instructions which have guided lay people and monastics to higher achievement for millennia.  Thus, given this canonical chronology,  Anapanasati Day is celebrated a lunar month after Pavarana Day. &lt;/ref&gt;
* '''[[Magha Puja]]''' or Magha Uposatha.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[[Maagha|Māgha]]&quot; (Pali) is the eleventh lunar month, usually around February.&lt;/ref&gt; (&quot;Sangha Day&quot;):
Anniversary of the assembling of 1250 monks in the Buddha's presence during which time he delivered the &quot;Ovada-Patimokkha Gatha.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;The three-line Ovada-Patimokkha Gatha (Pali: &quot;Patimokkha Exhortation Verse&quot;) (translated in [http://www.accesstoinsight.org/lib/authors/dhammayut/chanting.html#ovada Dhammayut Order in the United States of America, 1994)] includes the Buddha's famous dictum: &quot;Not doing any evil, doing what is skillful, purifying one's own mind, this is the Buddha's teaching.&quot;  This verse is familiar to many Westerners because it is rehashed in the widely popular [[Dhammapada]], chapter XIV, verses 183-85 [http://www.accesstoinsight.org/tipitaka/kn/dhp/dhp.14.than.html#dhp-183 (Thanissaro, 1997a)].&lt;/ref&gt;

In Sri Lanka three full moon Uposatha or [[Poya]] days are of special significance.&lt;ref&gt;See http://www.accesstoinsight.org/lib/authors/kariyawasam/wheel402.html#ch3 Kariyawasam, ch. 3, &quot;Poya Days.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Vesak Poya''', which is described above.
* '''Poson Poya''' corresponds to the Jeṭṭhā uposatha, which falls in June. It is of special significance in Sri Lanka because the [[Mahinda|arahant Mahinda]], King Asoka's son, officially introduced Buddhism to Sri Lanka on this day in the 3rd century B.C. 
* '''Esala Poya''' corresponds to Asalha (Āsāḷhā) uposatha, the full moon of July, and is described above. This day has special significance in Sri Lanka because it was the day that 56 nobles, headed by Prince Arițțha, became the first Sri Lankans to be fully ordained as a Buddhist monks ([[bhikkhu]]) at Cetiyagiri in [[Mihintale]] by Mahinda Thera and his companions. It therefore marks the founding of the local Sri Lankan Buddhist monastic Bhikkhu Sangha.&lt;ref&gt;See http://www.accesstoinsight.org/lib/authors/kariyawasam/wheel402.html#ch3 Kariyawasam, ch. 3, &quot;Poya Days.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
*[[Buddhist calendar]]
*[[Dhammika Sutta]]
*[[Householder (Buddhism)]]
*[[Poya]] (Sri Lankan full-moon holiday)
*[[Puja (Buddhism)]]
*[[Thai lunar calendar]]
*[[Vassa]]

== Notes ==
&lt;references/&gt;

== References ==

*[[A. P. Buddhadatta Mahathera|Buddhadatta Mahathera, A. P.]] (2002). ''Concise Pali-English Dictionary''. Delhi:Motilal Banarsidass. ISBN 81-208-0605-0.

*[[Access to Insight|Bullitt, John T.]] (2005). ''Uposatha Observance Days''.  Available on-line at http://www.accesstoinsight.org/ptf/dhamma/sila/uposatha.html.

*Dhammayut Order in the United States of America (1994). ''A Chanting Guide.'' Available on-line at http://www.accesstoinsight.org/lib/authors/dhammayut/chanting.html.

*Harvey, Peter (1990). ''An introduction to Buddhism: Teachings, history and practices''. Cambridge: Cambridge University. ISBN 0-521-31333-3.

* Kariyawasam, A.G.S. (1995). ''Buddhist Ceremonies and Rituals of Sri Lanka'' (The Wheel Publication No. 402/404). Kandy, Sri Lanka: Buddhist Publication Society. Retrieved 2007-10-22 from &quot;Access to Insight&quot; (1996 transcription) at http://www.accesstoinsight.org/lib/authors/kariyawasam/wheel402.html.

*Khantipalo, Bhikkhu (1982a). ''Lay Buddhist Practice: The Shrine Room, Uposatha Day, Rains Residence'' (The Wheel No. 206/207). Kandy, Sri Lanka:Buddhist Publication Society. Also transcribed (1995) and available on-line at http://www.accesstoinsight.org/lib/authors/khantipalo/wheel206.html.

*Khantipalo, Bhikkhu (trans.) (1982b). ''Visakhuposatha Sutta: The Discourse to Visakha on the Uposatha with the Eight Practices'' [AN 8.43]. Available on-line at http://www.accesstoinsight.org/tipitaka/an/an08/an08.043.khan.html.

*[[Mahasi Sayadaw]] (''undated''). ''Practical Vipassana Exercises''.  Buddha Dharma Education Association.  Available on-line at http://www.buddhanet.net/pdf_file/mahasit1.pdf.

*Ñanavara Thera (Somdet Phra Buddhaghosacariya) &amp; Bhikkhu Kantasilo (trans.) (1993). ''Uposatha Sila: The Eight-Precept Observance''. Thailand:The Office of the Secretary of the Supreme Patriarch. Available on-line at http://www.accesstoinsight.org/lib/authors/nanavara/uposatha.html.

*[[Narada Maha Thera|Narada Thera]] (trans.) (1985). ''Maha-mangala Sutta: Blessings'' [Sn 2.4]. Available on-line at http://www.accesstoinsight.org/tipitaka/kn/snp/snp.2.04.nara.html.

*[[Nyanaponika Thera]] and [[Bhikkhu Bodhi]] (trans. and ed.) (1999). ''Numerical Discourses of the Buddha: An Anthology of Suttas from the Anguttara Nikaya''.  Walnut Creek, CA: Altamira Press. ISBN 0-7425-0405-0.

*[[Piyadassi Thera]] (trans.) (1999a). ''Karaniya Metta Sutta: The Discourse on Loving-kindness'' [Sn 1.8]. Available on-line at http://www.accesstoinsight.org/tipitaka/kn/snp/snp.1.08.piya.html.

*Piyadassi Thera (trans.) (1999b). ''Ratana Sutta: The Jewel Discourse'' [Sn 2.1]. Available on-line at http://www.accesstoinsight.org/tipitaka/kn/snp/snp.2.01.piya.html.

*[[Thomas William Rhys Davids|Rhys Davids]],T.W. &amp; Hermann Oldenberg (trans.) ([1881]). ''Vinaya Texts (Part I)''. Oxford:Clarendon Press.  Available on-line at http://www.sacred-texts.com/bud/sbe13/sbe1313.htm.  The chapter on the Uposatha, &quot;Second Khandhaka (The Uposatha Ceremony, and the Pâtimokkha),&quot; is available at http://www.sacred-texts.com/bud/sbe13/sbe1313.htm.  The chapter on Pavarana Day, &quot;Fourth Khandhaka (The Parâvanâ Ceremony),&quot; is available at http://www.sacred-texts.com/bud/sbe13/sbe1315.htm.

* Rhys Davids, T.W., and William Stede, ''The Pali Text Society's Pali-English Dictionary'', 1921–25. [[Pali Text Society]], London : Chipstead. The entry on &quot;Uposatha&quot; is available on-line at http://dsal.uchicago.edu/cgi-bin/philologic/getobject.pl?c.0:1:4011.pali. A general on-line search engine for the PED is available at http://dsal.uchicago.edu/dictionaries/pali/.

*[[Thanissaro Bhikkhu]] (trans.) (1993). ''Dhammacakkappavattana Sutta: Setting the Wheel of Dhamma in Motion'' [SN 56.11]. Available on-line at http://www.accesstoinsight.org/tipitaka/sn/sn56/sn56.011.than.html.

*Thanissaro Bhikkhu (trans.) (1997a). ''Buddhavagga: Awakened'' [ [[Dhammapada|Dhp]] XIV]. Available on-line at http://www.accesstoinsight.org/tipitaka/kn/dhp/dhp.14.than.html.

*Thanissaro Bhikkhu (trans.) (1997b). ''Muluposatha Sutta: The Roots of the Uposatha'' [AN 3.70]. Available on-line at http://www.accesstoinsight.org/tipitaka/an/an03/an03.070.than.html.

*Thanissaro, Bhikkhu (trans.) (1999). ''The Ten Recollections: A Study Guide''. Available on-line at http://www.accesstoinsight.org/lib/study/recollections.html.

*Thanissaro, Bhikkhu (trans.) (2006). ''Anapanasati Sutta: Mindfulness of Breathing'' [MN 118]. Available on-line at http://www.accesstoinsight.org/tipitaka/mn/mn.118.than.html.

== External links ==
*[http://www.buddhanet.net/festival.htm &quot;Buddhist Ceremonies: Festivals and Special Days&quot;], on www.buddhanet.net
*[http://www.accesstoinsight.org/ptf/dhamma/sila/uposatha2011.html &quot;Calendar of Uposatha Days&quot; (2011)], [http://www.accesstoinsight.org/ptf/dhamma/sila/uposatha2010.html (2010)], [http://www.accesstoinsight.org/ptf/dhamma/sila/uposatha2009.html (2009)] on www.accesstoinsight.org.
*[http://www.buddhistgateway.com/library/rituals/ &quot;The Rituals and Festivals of the Buddhist Life&quot;], by Robert C. Lester (1987), on buddhistgateway.com.

{{LayTheravadaPractices2}}
{{Buddhism topics}}

[[Category:Buddhist festivals]]
[[Category:Festivals in India]]
[[Category:Buddhist holidays]]

[[cs:Upósatha]]
[[de:Uposatha]]
[[es:Uposatha]]
[[fr:Uposatha]]
[[ko:포살]]
[[id:Uposatha]]
[[it:Uposatha]]
[[my:ဥပုသ်]]
[[nl:Uposatha]]
[[ja:六斎日]]
[[th:วันพระ]]
[[zh:布薩]]</text>
      <sha1>5ald1q88lggxywvxgigyyu23b2295zm</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
