<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Veneration</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>185441</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522419732</id>
      <parentid>522419175</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-11T02:27:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Splashen</username>
        <id>13134842</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* See also */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="19026">[[Image:Heiligenverehrung.jpg|thumb|Veneration in Noto [[Conrad of Piacenza|St Conrad of Piacenza]] (San Corrado)]]
'''Veneration''' ([[Latin]] ''veneratio'', [[Greek language|Greek]] [[wikt:δουλεία|δουλεία]], ''douleia''), or '''veneration of saints''', is a special act of honoring a [[saint]], a person who has been identified as having a high degree of sanctity or holiness.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomson&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Thomson Gale Encyclopedia of Religion|editor=Lindsay Jones|publisher=Macmillan Reference USA|year=2005|edition=Second|volume=Sainthood|pages=8033|language=TG}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Angel]]s are shown similar veneration in many religions. [[Philology|Philologically]], to venerate derives from the [[Latin]] [[verb]], ''venerare'', meaning to regard with reverence and respect. Veneration of saints is practiced, formally or informally, by adherents of some branches of all major religions, including Christianity, Judaism,&lt;ref name=&quot;Ben-Ami1998&quot;&gt;&quot;Veneration of saints is a universal phenomenon. All monotheistic and polytheistic creeds contain something of its religious dimension... &quot; {{cite book|author=Issachar Ben-Ami|title=Saint Veneration Among the Jews in Morocco|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Hk9wCuiT7bEC&amp;pg=PA13|accessdate=7 September 2012|year=1998|publisher=Wayne State University Press|isbn=978-0-8143-2198-0|page=13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hinduism,&lt;ref name=&quot;Stark1966&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Werner Stark|title=Sociology of Religion|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=sUgVAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA367|accessdate=7 September 2012|year=1966|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|page=367|id=GGKEY:ZSKE259PDZ9}}&lt;/ref&gt; Islam,&lt;ref name=&quot;Pohl2010&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Florian Pohl|title=Modern Muslim Societies|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=n4Eye4ilLVkC&amp;pg=PA294|accessdate=7 September 2012|date=1 September 2010|publisher=Marshall Cavendish|isbn=978-0-7614-7927-7|pages=294–295}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Buddhism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomson&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stark1966&quot;/&gt;

Within Christianity, veneration is practiced by groups such as the [[Orthodox Church|Eastern Orthodox Church]], the [[Catholic Church|Roman Catholic]], and [[Eastern Catholic Churches]], all of which have varying degrees of [[canonization]] or [[glorification]] procedures. In some Christian denominations, veneration is shown outwardly by respectfully bowing or making the [[sign of the cross]] before a saint's [[icon]], [[relic]]s, or statue, or by going on [[pilgrimage]] to sites associated with saints. The practice of veneration is deemed heretical by [[iconoclasm|iconoclastic]] denominations.

In Judaism, there is no classical or formal recognition of saints, but there is a long history of reverence shown toward biblical heroes and martyrs. In some regions, for example within Judaism in Morocco, there is a long and widespread tradition of saint veneration.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomson&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ben-Ami1998&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stark1966&quot;/&gt;

Hinduism has a long tradition of veneration of saints, expressed toward various [[guru]]s and teachers of sanctity, both living and dead. Branches of Buddhism include formal liturgical worship of saints, with [[Mahayana Buddhism]] classifying degrees of sainthood.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomson&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stark1966&quot;/&gt;

In Islam, veneration of saints is practiced by sects such as the [[Shia Islam|Shi'a]] and [[Sufi]], and in many parts of Southeast Asia, along with &quot;[[Folk_religion#Folk_Islam|folk Islam]]&quot;, which often incorporates local beliefs and practices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Sufi Islam |url=http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/intro/islam-sufi.htm |quote=Although frequently characterized as the mystical component of Islam, there are also &quot;Folklorist&quot; Sufis, and the &quot;Traditional&quot; Sufis...Sufism is characterized by the veneration of local saints and by brotherhoods that practice their own rituals.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.economist.com/node/12792544|title=Of saints and sinners: The Islam of the [[Taliban]] is far removed from the popular Sufism practised by most South Asian Muslims |date=December 18, 2008 |publisher=[[The Economist]] |quote=In its popular form, Sufism is expressed mainly through the veneration of saints...South Asia is littered with the tombs of those saints. They include great medieval monuments, like the 13th-century shrine of Khwaja [[Moinuddin Chishti|Moinuddin Chisti]], founder of South Asia’s pre-eminent Sufi order, in [[Ajmer]]. But for every famous grave, there are thousands of roadside shrines, jutting into Delhi’s streets, or sprinkled across the craggy deserts of southern Pakistan.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other sects, such as [[Sunni Islam|Sunnis]] and [[Wahhabi]]sts, abhor the practice&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://articles.latimes.com/2003/may/08/news/war-saudis8 |title=Saudi Shiites Take Hope From Changes Next Door |date=2003-05-08 |author=Kim Murphy |published=Los Angeles Times |quote=while most Sunnis view them as fellow, though possibly misguided, Muslims, Shiites are regarded as infidels by the Saudi religious establishment, which adheres to the ultraconservative and austere variation of Sunni faith known as Wahhabism. Saudi religious leaders see the Shiite veneration of saints and shrines, celebration of the prophet Muhammad's birthday and other rituals as sinful.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Christianity==
Veneration towards those who were considered holy began in early Christianity, with the [[martyr]]s first being given special honor. Official church commemoration of saints in Rome beginning as early as the third century. Over time, the honor also began to be given to those Christians who lived lives of holiness and sanctity. Various denominations venerate and determine saints in different ways, with some having a formal canonization or glorification process.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomson&quot; /&gt;

===Roman Catholic, Orthodox===
In Roman Catholic, and Orthodox theology, veneration is a type of honor distinct from the [[worship|adoration]] due to God alone. According to Deacon Dr. Mark Miravelle, of [[Franciscan University of Steubenville]], the English word &quot;worship&quot; has been associated with both veneration and adoration:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Adoration, which is known as [[latria]] in classical theology, is the worship and homage that is rightly offered to God alone. It is the acknowledgement of excellence and perfection of an uncreated, divine person. It is the worship of the Creator that God alone deserves.

Veneration, known as dulia in classical Catholic theology, is the honor due to the excellence and a created person. This refers to the excellence exhibited by the created being who likewise deserves recognition and honor. We see a general example of veneration in events like the awarding of academic awards for excellence in school, or the awarding of the Olympic medals for excellence in sports. There is nothing contrary to the proper adoration of God when we offer the appropriate honor and recognition that created persons deserve based on achievement in excellence.

Here a further clarification should be made regarding the use of the term &quot;worship&quot; in relation to the categories of adoration and veneration. Some schools of theology use the term &quot;worship&quot; to introduce both adoration and veneration. They would distinguish between &quot;worship of adoration&quot; and &quot;worship of veneration.&quot; The word &quot;worship&quot; (in the same way the theological term &quot;cult&quot; is traditionally used) in these classical definitions was not at all synonymous with adoration, but could be used to introduce either adoration or veneration. Hence Catholic writers will sometimes use the term &quot;worship&quot; not to indicate adoration, but only the worship of veneration given to Mary and the saints.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chnetwork.org/journals/mary/mary_4.htm ]{{dead link|date=January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Church theologians have long adopted the terms ''[[latria]]'' for the type of worship due to God alone, and ''dulia'' for the veneration given to saints and icons. Catholic theology also includes the term ''hyperdulia'' for the type of veneration specifically paid to [[Mary, mother of Jesus]], in Catholic tradition. This distinction is spelled out in the [[dogma]]tic conclusions of the [[Seventh Ecumenical Council]] (787), which also decreed that [[iconoclasm]] (forbidding icons and their veneration) is a [[heresy]] that amounts to a denial of the [[incarnation]] of [[Jesus]].

Now, the Roman Catholic tradition has a well established philosophy for the veneration of the Virgin Mary via the field of [[Mariology]] with Pontifical schools such as the [[Marianum]] specifically devoted to this task.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mariologicalsocietyofamerica.us |title=Mariological Society of America |publisher=Mariologicalsocietyofamerica.us |date= |accessdate=2012-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.servidimaria.org/en/attualita/promotori2/promotori2.htm ]{{dead link|date=January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Publisher’s Notice in the Second Italian Edition (1986), reprinted in English Edition, [[Gabriel Roschini]], O.S.M. (1989). ''The [[Virgin Mary]] in the Writings of [[Maria Valtorta]]'' (English Edition). Kolbe's Publication Inc. ISBN 2-920285-08-4&lt;/ref&gt;

===Protestant view of veneration as idolatry===
In [[Protestantism|Protestant]]  churches, veneration is sometimes considered to amount to the heresy of [[idolatry]], and the related practice of [[canonization]] amounts to the heresy of [[apotheosis]]. [[Protestant]] theology usually denies that any real distinction between veneration and [[worship]] can be made, and claims that the practice of veneration distracts the Christian soul from its true object, the worship of God.  In his ''[[Institutes of the Christian Religion]]'', [[John Calvin]] writes that &quot;(t)he distinction of what is called ''dulia'' and ''latria'' was invented for the very purpose of permitting divine honours to be paid to angels and dead men with apparent impunity.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.reformed.org/books/institutes/books/book1/bk1ch12.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Judaism==
While orthodox and organized Judaism doesn't countenance the veneration of saints, veneration and pilgrimage to holy sites associated with saints were an ancient part of the tradition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharot&quot;&gt;&quot;....the veneration of, and pilgrimages to, saints were part of an ancient Jewish tradition.&quot;  {{cite book|last=Sharot|first=Stephen|title=Judaism: A Sociology|publisher=Holmes &amp; Meier Publishers|location=New York|year=1976|pages=42}}&lt;/ref&gt; That tradition is still strong in the few Jewish communities that were not uprooted over the years, the declining communities in Iran, Morocco and Tunisia.&lt;ref name=&quot;De Lange&quot;&gt;&quot;The life of these, mainly Sephardi, communities is marked by an unself-conscious and unquestioning commitment to deeply rooted values, where legalism often yields to common sense, and mystical piety plays an integral part, visible in such practices as veneration of tombs of patriarchs and saints, often associated with pilgrimage.&quot; {{cite book|last=De Lange|first=Nicholas|title=An Introduction to Judaism|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Cambridge, England|year=2000|pages=69}}&lt;/ref&gt; The tradition is particularly strong among Morocco Jews, who have a comprehensive list of 656 saints, including 25 women. As with some other religions, the practice of veneration of saints and the making of saints, mostly expressed in Morocco Judaism but not only there, is by popular sentiment rather than formal canonization.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomson&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ben-Ami1998&quot; /&gt;

==Hinduism==
Hinduism has a longstanding and living tradition of reverence toward saints, with the line often blurring between humanity and divinity with some Hindu deities. The [[bhakti]] movements helped to popularize the veneration of saints and [[guru]]s as models showing the way to liberation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomson&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stark1966&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cybelle Shattuck, Hinduism (London: Routledge, 1999), page 61, http://www.questia.com/read/103395975.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Buddhism==
Both main branches of Buddhism, [[Theravada]] and [[Mahayana]], recognize those who have achieved a high degree of enlightenment as an [[Arhat (Buddhism)|Arhat]]. Mahayana Buddhism particularly gives emphasis to the power of saints to aid ordinary people on the path to enlightenment. Those who have reached enlightenment, and have delayed their own complete enlightenment in order to help others, are called [[Bodhisattva]]s. Mahayana Buddhism has formal liturgical practices for venerating saints, along with very specific levels of sainthood. Tibetan Buddhist venerate especially holy lamas, such as the [[Dalai Lama]], as saints.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomson&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stark1966&quot;/&gt;

==Islam==
Veneration of saints in Islam is especially common in the [[Sufi]] branch, though there are many local customs in different parts of the world, especially in southeast Asia, where saints are honored and venerated. Islam has no formal process of canonization—it is typically done through popular acclaim and local custom.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomson&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pohl2010&quot; /&gt; Muslim saints who are venerated include the women Sufi mystic [[Rabia Basri]], and Sufi saints [[Habib al-Ajami]], and [[Saint Nuri]].

Many Islamic sects condemn veneration of icons associated with saints.  [[Destruction of sites associated with early Islam|Destruction of historical Islamic sites]], which are [[Holiest sites in Islam (Shia)|holy to Shi'ite Muslims]], in Saudi Arabia were instigated by [[Wahhabi]]s and the Saudi royal family, most notably the shrines and tombs in the [[Al-Baqi']] cemetery in 1925.&lt;ref&gt;Laurence Louėr (2008), [http://books.google.com/books?id=1vcfDuatockC&amp;pg=PA22&amp;dq=shia+holy+baqi+destroyed+wahhabi&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=P2UYTo3YA8r2sgbzhbXMDw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCgQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=shia%20holy%20baqi%20destroyed%20wahhabi&amp;f=false ''Transnational Shia politics: religious and political networks in the Gulf''], p.22&lt;/ref&gt; In 2001, the 6th century monumental statues called the [[Buddhas_of_Bamiyan#Dynamiting_and_destruction.2C_March_2001|Buddhas of Bamiyan]] in [[Afghanistan]] were destroyed by the [[Taliban]]. In 2006, a bombing by [[al-Qaeda]] resulted in the destruction of the [[Al-Askari Mosque]] in [[Iraq]].&lt;ref&gt;Karen Dabrowska, Geoff Hann, (2008), [http://books.google.com/books?id=DhJ3lRnXyXcC&amp;pg=PA239&amp;dq=askari+mosque+bomb+2006&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=UGgYTvueE8zHsgagrOiZDw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=askari%20mosque%20bomb%202006&amp;f=false ''Iraq Then and Now: A Guide to the Country and Its People''], p.239&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2012 [[Ansar Dine]], a strict Islamic sect, demolished mausoleums of the saints in [[Timbuktu]], the &quot;City of 333 ([[Sufism|Sufi]]) Saints&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/07/03/uk-mali-crisis-timbuktu-idUSLNE86202G20120703
|title=Timbuktu tomb destroyers pulverise Islam's history
|quote=Over the last three days, Islamists of the Ansar Dine rebel group which in April seized Mali's north along with Tuareg separatists destroyed at least eight [[Timbuktu]] mausoleums and several tombs, centuries-old shrines reflecting the local Sufi version of Islam in what is known as the &quot;City of 333 Saints&quot;.
|accessdate=2012-07-05
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and desecrated the [[Sidi Yahya Mosque]].&lt;ref&gt;|url=http://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2012/07/these-600-year-old-world-heritage-sites-might-be-rubble-by-august/259360/
|title=These 600-Year Old World Heritage Sites Might Be Rubble by August
|date=JUL 3 2012, 4:30 PM ET
|quote=Ansar Dine, which has seized Timbuktu, destroyed (Sidi Yahya's) tomb. They declared that the burial site made Yahya a false idol, threatening to continue their destruction of Timbuktu's historic sites
&lt;/ref&gt; In August 2012, [[Salafi]] zealots bulldozed several Sufi sites in and near [[Tripoli]] &lt;ref&gt;{{citation web
|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/08/25/us-libya-islamists-idUSBRE87O08Y20120825
|title=Fighters bulldoze Sufi mosque in central Tripoli
|publisher=[[Reuters]]
|author=Taha Zargoun
|date=Sat Aug 25, 2012 4:41pm EDT
|quote=Attackers bulldozed a mosque containing Sufi Muslim graves in the center of Tripoli in broad daylight on Saturday, in what appeared to be Libya's most blatant sectarian attack since the overthrow of Muammar Gaddafi. Government officials condemned the demolition of the large Sha'ab mosque and blamed an armed group who, they said, considered its graves and shrines to Sufi figures un-Islamic.
It was the second razing of a Sufi site in two days. Ultra-conservative Islamists wrecked Sufi shrines with bombs and another bulldozer and set fire to a mosque library in the city of Zlitan in the early hours of Friday, an official said....A Reuters reporter saw the bulldozer level the Sha'ab mosque as police surrounded the site and prevented people from approaching and did not stop the demolition... Salafis have formed a number of armed brigades in Libya. They reject as idolatrous many Sufi devotions - which include dancing and the building of shrines to venerated figures. Conservative Muslims across the region - emboldened by the Arab Spring revolts - have targeted Sufi sites in Egypt, Mali and other parts of Libya over the past year... A Facebook page titled &quot;Together for the Removal of the Abdel Salam al-Asmar Shrine&quot; congratulated supporters on the &quot;successful removal of the Asmar shrine, the largest sign of idolatry in Libya.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Other religious traditions==
{{Unreferenced section|date=September 2012}}
In [[Christianity and environmentalism|Green Christianity]] (or Creation-centered theology) animals, plants, and other parts of nature may be said to be ''venerated'' simply by taking good care of them, thereby showing honor and respect for God who made them. [[Creation myth|Creation]], being regarded as an icon of the Creator, is a valid object of veneration.

== See also ==
* [[Adoration]]
* [[Blessed Virgin Mary]]
* [[Genuflection]]
* [[Hagiography]]
* [[Iconography]]
* [[Idolatry]]
* [[Intercession of saints]]
* [[Muhammad in Islam]]
* [[Patron saint]]
* [[Pilgrimage]]
* [[Tzadik]]
* [[Veneration of the dead]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG0432/_P2H.HTM ON THE INVOCATION, VENERATION, AND RELICS, OF SAlNTS, AND ON SACRED IMAGES.] Roman Catholic teaching from the [[Council of Trent]] (1545–63)
*[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/05188b.htm &quot;Dulia&quot;] from the [[Catholic Encyclopedia]] (1911)
*[http://catholicintl.com/articles/Latria&amp;Dulia-the_Catholic_Response-William_Albrecht.pdf a Catholic defense of Latria and Dulia] a defense of the Catholic teachings of Latria and Dulia by Catholic apologist William Albrecht who covers the Biblical terms in their religious usage in the Bible

[[Category:Eastern Orthodoxy]]
[[Category:Sainthood]]
[[Category:Catholic spirituality]]
[[Category:Religious behaviour and experience]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]

[[cs:Kult svatých]]
[[de:Heiligenverehrung]]
[[es:Veneración de santos]]
[[fr:Dulie]]
[[ia:Veneration de sanctos]]
[[it:Venerazione]]
[[nl:Heiligenverering]]
[[pl:Kult świętych]]
[[pt:Veneração]]
[[sv:Vördnad]]
[[zh:敬奉]]</text>
      <sha1>d1hdkuguewaejr8eqrdevjuswngiz3s</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
