<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Vishnu</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19334491</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522413345</id>
      <parentid>522157450</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-11T01:28:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>198.179.108.31</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Theological attributes */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="64346">{{Other uses}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Hdeity infobox
| Image                    =Mahabharata06ramauoft 0678.jpg
| Caption                  = 
| Name                     = Vishnu
| Devanagari               = विष्णु
| Image_size               = 200px
| Sanskrit_Transliteration = {{IAST|viṣṇu}}
| Tamil Script             = விஷ்ணு
| Telugu_script            = విష్ణు
| Kannada_script           = ವಿಷ್ಣು
| Malayalam Script         = വിഷ്ണു
| Bengali Script           =  ৱিষ্ণু
| Affiliation              = [[Deva (Hinduism)|Deva]] ([[Trimurti]])
| God_of                   =
| Abode                    = [[Vaikunta]], [[Ksheera Sagara]]
| Weapon                   = [[Sudarshana Chakra]] and the Kaumodaki
| Consort                  = [[Lakshmi]], [[Bhudevi]]
| Mount                    = [[Garuda]]
| Mantra                   = Om Namo Narayanaya, Om Namo Bhagavate Vasudevaya,Om Vishnaveh Namaha
| Planet                   =
}}
'''Vishnu''' ([[Sanskrit]]: विष्णु) is a popular [[Hinduism|Hindu]] god, venerated as the Supreme Being in the Vaishnava sect. He is also commonly known as [[Narayana]] or [[Hari]]. [[Smarta]] followers of [[Adi Shankara]], among others, venerate Vishnu as one of [[Panchayatana puja]].&lt;ref&gt;The Sri Vaishnava Brahmans, K. Rangachari (1931)p. 2&lt;/ref&gt;
The [[Vishnu Sahasranama]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.swami-krishnananda.org/vishnu/vishnu_1.html |title=Sri Vishnu Sahasaranama – Transliteration and Translation of Chanting |publisher=Swami-krishnananda.org |date= |accessdate=2011-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; declares Vishnu as [[Paramatman]] (supreme soul) and [[Parameshwara (God)|Parameshwara]] (supreme [[God]]). It describes Vishnu as the All-Pervading essence of all beings, the master of—and beyond—the past, present and future, one who supports, sustains and governs the Universe and originates and develops all elements within. This illustrates the omnipresent characteristic of Vishnu. Vishnu governs the aspect of preservation and sustenance of the universe, so he is called &quot;Preserver of the universe&quot;.

In the [[Puranas]], Vishnu is described as having the divine colour of water filled clouds, four-armed, holding a lotus, [[Mace (club)|mace]], [[shankha]] ([[conch]]) and [[Sudarshana Chakra|chakra]] (wheel). Vishnu is also described in the [[Bhagavad Gita]] as having a 'Universal Form' (''Vishvarupa'') which is beyond the ordinary limits of human perception or imagination.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url        = http://vedabase.net/bg/11/3/en1
 |title      = Bhagavad-gita As It Is Chapter 11 Verse 3
 |publisher  = vedabase.net
 |accessdate = 2008-05-10
 |last       = [[Prabhupada]]
 |first      = AC Bhaktivedanta
}} &quot;see the cosmic manifestation&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

His eternal or permanent abode beyond the material universe is [[Vaikuntha]] which is a realm of eternal bliss and happiness. It is also known as Paramdhama, which means final or highest place for liberated souls, where they enjoy eternal bliss and happiness. [[Vaikuntha]] is situated beyond the material universe and hence, can not be perceived or measured by material science and logics.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tirumala.org/sapthagiri/062003/vaikuntha.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

His other abode within the material universe is [[Ksheera Sagara]], where he reclines and rests on [[Shesha]]. It is known to be the topmost realm in the material universe, even higher than [[Satyaloka]] where [[Brahma]] resides. Vishnu manages and sustains the universe from there. Hence, [[Ksheera Sagara]] is also sometimes known as local [[Vaikuntha]] of the material universe, which is approachable by demigods in order to meet the lord in case of any emergency or disturbance in universal balance.

In almost all Hindu denominations, Vishnu is either worshipped directly or in the form of his ten avatara, most famous of whom are [[Rama]] and [[Krishna]].&lt;ref name = Krishna4&gt;
{{cite book
|author=Matchett, Freda
|title=Krsna, Lord or Avatara? the relationship between Krsna and Visnu: in the context of the Avatara myth as presented by the Harivamsa, the Visnupurana and the Bhagavatapurana
|publisher=Routledge
|location=Surrey
|year=2000
|page=254
|isbn=0-7007-1281-X
|oclc=
|doi=
|accessdate=
}}
p. 4&lt;/ref&gt; The Puranabharti describes each of these [[Dasavatara of Vishnu|''Dasavatara'' of Vishnu]]. Among the ten principal [[Avatar]]a described, nine have occurred in the past and one will take place in the future, at the end of [[Kali Yuga]]. These incarnations take place in all Yugas in cosmic scales, the avatars and their stories show that god is indeed unimaginable, unthinkable and unbelievable. The [[Bhagavad Gita]] mentions their purpose as being to rejuvenate [[Dharma]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vedabase.net/bg/4/7/en1 Bhagavad Gita 4.7] &quot;...at that time I descend Myself&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; and vanquish negative forces, the forces of evil that threaten Dharma, as also to display His divine nature in front of the conditioned/fallen souls.

The [[Trimurti]] ({{lang-en|‘three forms’}}; [[Sanskrit]]: ''{{IAST|trimūrti}}'') is a concept in [[Hinduism]] &quot;in which the cosmic functions of creation, maintenance, and destruction are personified by the forms of [[Brahma]] the creator, Vishnu the maintainer or preserver, and [[Shiva]] the destroyer or transformer.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;For quotation defining the trimurti see Matchett, Freda. &quot;The {{IAST|Purāṇas}}&quot;, in: Flood (2003), p. 139.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;For the Trimurti system having Brahma as the creator, Vishnu as the maintainer or preserver, and Shiva as the transformer or destroyer see: Zimmer (1972) p. 124.&lt;/ref&gt; These three deities have been called &quot;the Hindu triad&quot;&lt;ref&gt;For definition of trimurti as &quot;the unified form&quot; of Brahmā, {{IAST|Viṣṇu}} and Śiva and use of the phrase &quot;the Hindu triad&quot; see: Apte, p. 485.&lt;/ref&gt; or the &quot;Great [[Trinity]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;For the term &quot;Great Trinity&quot; in relation to the Trimurti see: Jansen, p. 83.&lt;/ref&gt; Of the three members of the Trimurti, the Bhagavata Purana, which espouses the [[Vaishnavite]] viewpoint, explains that the greatest benefit can be had from Vishnu.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://vedabase.net/sb/1/2/23/en |title=Srimad Bhagavatam Canto 1 Chapter 2 Verse 23 |publisher=Vedabase.net |date= |accessdate=2011-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Puranas]] and [[Vedas]], [[Narayana]] or [[Hari]] or Vishnu is the name used for addressing [[Para Brahman]] [[Supreme Being]]. Vishnu is used to address the same Supreme Lord who accepts [[Sattva]] [[Guna]] for sustainance and maintenance of universe and restores dharma or religion by taking incarnations or [[avatar]] in every Yuga.

==Name==
[[File:Museum für Indische Kunst Dahlem Berlin Mai 2006 036 2.jpg|right|thumb|200px|A 13th-century [[Cambodia]]n statue of Vishnu]]
[[File:Belur Vishnu.jpg|right|thumb|200px|At [[Chennakesava Temple]] at [[Belur]], '''[[Karnataka]]''' [[India]]]]
[[File:VishnuGandhara.JPG|thumb|200px|A 4th–6th century CE Sardonyx seal representing Vishnu with a worshipper. The inscription in cursive [[Bactrian language|Bactrian]] reads: &quot;[[Mihira]], Vishnu (left) and [[Shiva]]&quot;.]]
[[File:God Vishnu with Lakshmi and Saraswati.jpg|thumb|200px|right|12th century stone sculpture of God Vishnu flanked by two apsaras one with a fan(left) and the other with Tambura(right).]]

The traditional explanation of the name ''{{IAST|Viṣṇu}}'' involves the root ''{{IAST|viś}}'', meaning &quot;to settle&quot; (cognate with Latin ''[[:wikt:vicus|vicus]]'', English ''[[:wikt:-wich|-wich]]'' &quot;village&quot;, Slavic: vas ''[[:wikt:-wiki/ves|-ves]]'', or also (in the [[Rigveda]]) &quot;to enter into, to pervade&quot;, glossing the name as &quot;the All-Pervading One&quot;.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}
An early commentator on the [[Vedas]], [[Yaska]], in his [[Nirukta]], defines Vishnu as ''vishnu vishateh'' &quot;one who enters everywhere&quot;, and ''yad vishito bhavati tad vishnurbhavati,'' &quot;that which is free from fetters and bondages is Vishnu&quot;.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

Vishnu itself is the second name in the [[Vishnu Sahasranama]], the thousand names of Vishnu.
[[Adi Sankara]] in his commentary on the ''Sahasranama'' states derivation from ''{{IAST|viś}}'', with a meaning &quot;presence everywhere&quot; (&quot;As he pervades everything, ''vevesti'', he is called ''Vishnu''&quot;,).  [[Adi Sankara]] states (regarding [[Vishnu Purana]], 3.1.45): &quot;The Power of the Supreme Being has entered within the universe. The root ''{{IAST|viś}}'' means 'enter into.'&quot; [[Swami Chinmayananda]], in his translation of Vishnu sahasranama further elaborates on that verse: &quot;The root Vis means to enter. The entire world of things and beings is pervaded by Him and the Upanishad emphatically insists in its mantra 'whatever that is there is the world of change.' Hence, it means that He is not limited by space, time or substance. Chinmayananda states that that which pervades everything is Vishnu.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Swami Chinmayananda's translation of Vishnu sahasranama pgs. 16–17, Central Chinmaya Mission Trust.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Characteristics==
The number of auspicious qualities of Vishnu as the supreme god are countless, with the following six qualities being the most important:
*''Jñāna'' (Omniscience), defined as the power to know about all beings simultaneously
*''Aishvarya'' (Sovereignty), derived from the word [[Ishvara]], which consists in unchallenged rule over all
*''Shakti'' (Energy), or power, which is the capacity to make the impossible possible
*''Bala'' (Strength), which is the capacity to support everything by will and without any fatigue
*''Vīrya'' (Vigor), which indicates the power to retain immateriality as the supreme being in spite of being the material cause of mutable creations
*''Tejas'' (Splendor), which expresses His self-sufficiency and the capacity to overpower everything by His spiritual effulgence&lt;ref name= Tapasyananda&gt;{{cite book
 | author = Tapasyananda
 | year =  1991
 | title =  Bhakti Schools of Vedānta
 | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=Q_VtAAAACAAJ
 | isbn = 81-7120-226-8
 | publisher = Sri Ramakrishna Math
 | location = Madras
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Smriti and Shruti==

===Vedas===
In the [[Yajur Veda]], Taittiryia Aranyaka (10-13-1), [[Narayana sukta]], Lord Narayana is mentioned as the supreme being. The first verse of [[Narayana sukta]] mentions the words &quot;paramam padam&quot; which literally means &quot;highest post&quot; and may be understood as the &quot;supreme abode for all souls&quot;. [[Rigveda]] (1.022.20a) for Vishnu also mentions the same &quot;paramam padam&quot;. This special status is not given to any deity in the Vedas apart from Lord Vishnu and Lord Narayana {{Citation needed|date=July 2012}}. This perhaps is an indication that Narayana is just the another name for Vishnu himself, thus establishing the his supremacy. Narayana is also one of the thousand names of Vishnu as mentioned in the [[Vishnu Sahasranama]].

In the [[Rigveda]], Vishnu is mentioned 93 times. He is frequently invoked alongside other deities, especially [[Indra]], who he helps in killing [[Vritra]], and with whom he drinks [[Soma]].
His distinguishing characteristic in the Vedas is his association with light.
Two Rigvedic hymns in [[Mandala 7]] are dedicated to Vishnu.
In 7.99, Vishnu is addressed as the god who separates heaven and earth. This characteristic he shares with [[Indra]].

Hymn 7.100 refers to the celebrated   'three steps' of Vishnu by which he strode over the universe and in three places planted his step. The 'Vishnu Sukta' ([[RV 1]].154) says that the first and second of Vishnu's strides (those encompassing the earth and air) are visible to men and the third is in the heights of heaven (sky). This last place is described as Vishnu's supreme abode in RV 1.22.20:
:''The princes evermore behold / that loftiest place where Visnu is / Laid as it were an eye in heaven.'' (trans. [[Ralph T.H. Griffith|Griffith]])
Griffith's &quot;princes&quot; are the ''sūri'', either &quot;inciters&quot; or lords of a sacrifice, or priests charged with pressing the Soma. The verse is quoted as expressing Vishnu's supremacy by Vaishnavites.

Though such solar aspects have been associated with Vishnu by tradition as well as modern-scholarship, he was not just the representation of the sun, as he traverses in his strides both vertically and horizontally.

In hymns 1.22.17, 1.154.3, 1.154.4 he strides across the earth with three steps, in 6.49.13, 7.100.3 strides across the earth three times and in 1.154.1, 1.155.5,7.29.7 he strides vertically, with the final step in the heavens. The same Veda also says he strode wide and created space in the cosmos for Indra to fight Vritra. By his stride he said to have made dwelling for men possible, the three being a symbolic representation of its all-encompassing nature. This all-enveloping nature and benevolence to men were to remain the enduring attributes of Vishnu. As the triple-strider he is known as Tri-vikrama and as Uru-krama for the strides were wide.

The general view is that Vedas place [[Indra]] in considerably superior position to Vishnu's Avatar of Vamana. Vamana helps Indra by restoring his Kingdom as mentioned in the [[Vamana Purana]].

An alternate translation is provided by Wilson (page 269 of document)&lt;ref name=&quot;wilbourhall.org&quot;&gt;http://www.wilbourhall.org/pdfs/Vedas/RgVedaWilson/RgVedaWilson_VOL_IV.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; according to Sayana.

When Thy (younger brother) Viṣṇu (Vamana) by (his) strength stepped his three paces, then verily thy beloved horses bore thee. (Rigveda 8:12:27)&lt;ref name=&quot;wilbourhall.org&quot;/&gt;

Wilson also mentions the possible translation as given by Griffith as a footnote. However the following verse from Rig Veda renders the above translation by Wilson more probable.

:''Him whose three places that are filled with sweetness, imperishable, joy as it may list them, '''Who verily alone upholds''' the threefold, the earth, the heaven, and all living creatures.''(Rigveda 1:154:4)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sacred-texts.com/hin/rigveda/rv01154.htm |title=Rig Veda: Rig-Veda Book 1: HYMN CLIV. Viṣṇu |publisher=Sacred-texts.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;'''

Wilson also offers alternate translation for Rigveda 10:113:2 (pages 318–319)&lt;ref&gt;http://www.wilbourhall.org/pdfs/Vedas/RgVedaWilson/RgVedaWilson_VOLVI.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

:''Viṣṇu offering the portion of Soma, glorifies by his own vigor that greatness of his. Indra, the lord of wealth, with the associated gods having slain Vr.tra, became deserving of honour.'' (Rigveda 10:113:2)

This verse glorifies Viṣṇu as one who is glorified by his own strength, while Indra became deserving of honor after having slain Vrtra only in association with other gods.

However Viṣṇu praising other gods need not be taken as worship. Wilson translates as follows.

:''Viṣṇu, the mighty giver of dwellings praises thee, and Mitra and Varuna; the company of Maruts imitates thee in exhilaration. (Rigveda 8:15:9) (page 280)&lt;ref name=&quot;wilbourhall.org&quot;/&gt;''

The following verses show categorically Viṣṇu as distinguished from other gods in Rig Veda.

:''He who presents (offering) to Viṣṇu, '''the ancient, the creator, the recent, the self-born'''; he who celebrates the great birth of that mighty one; he verily possessed of abundance, attains (the station) that is to be sought (by all).'' (Rigveda 1:156:2) (page 98)&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceC&quot;&gt;http://www.wilbourhall.org/pdfs/Vedas/RgVedaWilson/RgVedaWilson_VOL_II.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

No being that is or that has been born, divine Viṣṇu, has attained the utmost limit of thy magnitude, by which thou hast upheld the vast and beautiful heaven, and sustained the eastern horizon of Earth.(Rigveda 7:99:2) (page 196)&lt;ref name=&quot;wilbourhall.org&quot;/&gt;

'''Vishnu blesses Indra:'''

:''The divine Viṣṇu, the best of the doers of good deeds, who came to the pious instituter of rite (Indra), to assist (at its celebration), knowing (the desires of the worshiper), and present at the three connected period (of worship), shows favor to the Arya, and admits the author of the ceremony to a share of the sacrifice.'' (Rigveda 1:156:5) (page 99)&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceC&quot;/&gt;

However, [[Jan Gonda]], the late Indologist, states that Vishnu, although remaining in the background of Indra's exploits, contributes by his presence, or is key to Indra's success.&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;&gt;Aspects of early Visnuism, pg. 32, by Jon Gonda at http://books.google.com/books?id=b8urRsuUJ9oC&amp;pg=PA156&amp;dq=indra+superior+vishnu&amp;lr=&amp;cd=40#v=onepage&amp;q=indra%20superior%20vishnu&amp;f=false&lt;/ref&gt; Vishnu is more than a mere companion, equal in rank or power to Indra, or sometime the one who made Indra's success possible.&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt;

Moreover, even when Vishnu is described as subordinate to Indra, such a description is found in only the hymns to Indra, but in a [[kathenotheistic]] religion like that of the Rigveda, each god, for the time being, is supreme in the mind of the devotee. But in the Vaishnava canon the 'Vishnu' who is subordinate to Indra is identified as being none other than [[Vamana]], who is Vishnu's Avatar, and he is different from the Supreme God Sreeman Narayana or Narayana who is referred to as Vishnu by Vaishnavites.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nilakanta Sastri 1980&quot;&gt;Nilakanta Sastri, K.A. (1980). ''Advanced History of India'', Allied Publishers, New Delhi.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Upanishadic Vedic Literature pg. 86&quot;/&gt; Vishnu is not a mere sacrificial deity; he is a God who lives in the highest celestial region, compared with those who live in the atmospheric or terrestrial regions;&lt;ref name=&quot;Upanishadic Vedic Literature pg. 86&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=2X2q0e-dkwMC&amp;pg=PA84&amp;dq=indra+vishnu+vedas&amp;lr=&amp;cd=190#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false |title=Atman in Pre-Upanisadic Vedic Literature – H. G Narahari – Google Books |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, Vishnu is a god who is content with mere prayer, unlike almost all of the other gods who receive sacrificial offerings such as [[havis]] or [[soma]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Upanishadic Vedic Literature pg. 86&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Naradiyamahapuranam.jpg|thumb|left|200px|Vishnu with his consort [[Lakshmi]] resting on [[Shesha|Shesha Nag]] from The Atha Naradiyamahapuranam. The ''[[Naradeya Purana]]'' describes the mechanics of the cosmos. [[Narada]] and [[Brahma]] are also pictured.]]
However, in the Rig Vedic texts, the deity or god referred to as Vishnu is none other than the Sun God who also bore the name Suryanarayana, who in turn was also called Vishnu. So the 'Vishnu' referred to in the Rig Veda is none other than the Sun God Suryanarayana or Surya and he in turn, is entirely different from the Vishnu who is Sreeman Narayana (the Lord/Consort of Sree or Lakshmi, who is also the central deity in 'Vishnu Puranam', 'Vishnu Sahasranamam', 'Purusha Sooktham' (wherein he is identified very clearly not as the Sun or Suryanarayana (the purveyor of the skies), but as Narayana or Vishnu and further identified as the Supreme Lord who has Sreedevi (Lakshmi) and Bhoodevi (Goddess Earth or Bhoomi) as his wives/consorts (&quot;Hreeshcha-tey-Lakshmeeshcha-patnyauh&quot;). The Vaishnavites make a further distinction by extolling the qualities of Vishnu or [[Narayana]] by highlighting him as a personality or entity much different from other deities like [[Shiva|Siva]], [[Brahma]] or the minor deity [[Surya]] the Sun who also bears the name Vishnu.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nilakanta Sastri 1980&quot;/&gt;

In the [[Puranas]] Indra frequently becomes proud and haughty. This act of his incurs the displeasure of his creators namely [[Brahma]], who along with [[Shiva|Siva]] the Destroyer God start by giving boons to demons or [[Asuras]] like Hiranyaksha, Hiranyakashyapu, Ravana, who are able to defeat Indra in wars between the [[Deva (Hinduism)|Devas]] and Asuras. Indra in turn has no option but to take advice of the sages who say that no one can save him but the Protector God Sreeman Narayana or Vishnu the Supreme Lord. Indra goes and prays before Vishnu for protection and the Supreme Lord obliges him by taking [[avatar]]a or birth or generating himself on Earth in various forms i.e. first as amphibean, water-born being namely the Matsya or fish, then as a creature capable of living on land as well as water, i.e. the Koorma avatara (Tortoise), then half-man, half-animal namely Varaha (the Pig-faced/human-bodied Lord) and Narasimha (Lord with Lion face and claws and human body). Later the same [[Narayana]] or Vishnu appears as full-fledged human being in the form of Vamana (the short-heighted person), Parashuram, Ram, Krishna, Balarama or Buddha and finally as Kalki avataram for performing his task of protecting his devotees from the [[Asuras]] or anti-God, anti-religious entities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nilakanta Sastri 1980&quot;/&gt;

The Vaishnava canon claims absolute clarity in identification of the Supreme Lord Vishnu (Sreeman Narayana or Narayana) from the Vishnu of the Rig Veda who they claim is none other than the Sun God Suryanarayana, who incidentally is also bears a secondary name Vishnu. In the Vaishnava canon, it is none other than Lord Vishnu or Sreeman Narayana who is their Supreme God who takes manifest forms or avatarams across various 'yugas (ages or periods) to save humanity from the clutches of evil beings, who became powerful after receiving boons from the two other Gods of the Trinity viz. [[Brahma]] and [[Shiva]]. They believe the acts of Sreeman [[Narayana]] also called Vishnu were certainly not performed by the minor deity Suryanarayana, or the Sun, also known as Vishnu of the Rig Vedas to be the Sun God Surya or Suryanarayana, who was also called and worshipped as Vishnu during the Rig Vedic period. This is borne out by the fact that neither are there are in number, very few temples dedicated to the [[Sun]] or Suryanarayana, nor indeed of the Vedic God [[Indra]], nor is there any pronounced importance followed by worship of [[Indra]] in the Hindu religion, which practice was discontinued after [[Indra]]'s defeat at the hands of the demons and Asuras and his forced abdication of the throne.

Following the defeat of [[Indra]] and his displacement as the Lord of Heaven or Swarga, according to the [[Vaishnava]] canon, the Supreme Lord of the universe Sreeman Narayana or Vishnu takes his incarnations or avatarams on earth to save mankind, thus taking the place of the Supreme God with him not being worshipped and eulogized by Vaishnavites alone, but also getting recognized by [[Shaivites]] and the [[Smartha]]s. A direct consequence of this was the almost complete absence of [[Indra]] and to a lesser extent, of the [[Sun]] or Suryanarayana, a minor deity from [[Hindu]] temples from the deities being considered fit for worshipping as the chief or most important deity. A glaring example being quoted in support of non-worship of deities like [[Indra]] or non-prominence of other major Gods like [[Shiva]] and [[Brahma]], (who is in any case not having more than a temple or two on earth) by [[Vaishnavites]] is the fact of their Supreme Lord Vishnu or Narayana taking avatarams to defeat and kill either the demons or Asuras like Hiranyaksha, Hiranyakashyipu or Ravana who have vanquished [[Indra]] himself and/or demons who have empowered themselves by pleasing and getting boons from other powerful Gods like [[Brahma]] and [[Shiva]]. These demons received boons making them virtually indestructible by any person. But [[Narayana]] or Vishnu outwits them by appearing as half-human half-animal before demons like Hiranyakashyipu (who had taken a boon that he will not be killed at any specific time of the day or by any human or animal) or Ravana (who becomes invincible by taking a boon from God Shiva that he will not be killed by any Deva – a celestial being with godly powers) who is considered the greatest among devotees of [[Shiva]] gets slayed by Vishnu, who appears before him as a mere human being i.e. [[Lord Rama]], the son of [[Dasharatha]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Nilakanta Sastri 1980&quot;/&gt;

The Vaishnava canon thus claims supremacy of Vishnu even among the Gods by quoting his victories over or killing of those very powerful entities who are themselves devotees of other Gods like the creator [[Brahma]] or the destroyer [[Shiva]]. The Vaishnava canon finally distinguishes [[Narayana]] or the Supreme Lord Vishnu from other deities like [[Shiva]] the Destroyer or [[Brahma]] the creator, first by pointing out the accepted iconography or sculptures of Vishnu in reclining position as having the creator [[Brahma]] sprouting or emerging from Vishnu's navel i.e. showing [[Brahma]] himself as having been created by Vishnu out of his own person. This is interpreted as the creator being created by his own creator i.e. [[Brahma]] himself being created by Vishnu and going on to create the Universe on the instructions of Vishnu. Secondly, [[Rudra]] or [[Shiva]] is none other than the Son of Brihaspati. Thirdly, there is the act of the creator [[Brahma]] and the destroyer God [[Shiva]] go on to give boons to demons or Asuras and as a consequence of granting boons to evil beings, they divest themselves of their powers to eliminate them, which are now vested with the Supreme Lord among the Gods i.e. Vishnu or [[Narayana]] also called Sreeman Narayana, who takes various avatars or forms to come to earth to slay or defeat those demons. This is again interpreted as the triumph of Lord Vishnu or [[Narayana]] because it would mean that [[Shiva]] and [[Brahma]] can only grant boons to good beings and since they cannot distinguish between the two types of beings, they have to entrust this responsibility to the God who protects all good beings. Thus, they have no option but to leave all devotees under the care of the Protector Lord, i.e. the Supreme Lord of the Vaishnava canon, i.e. Lord [[Narayana]] or Vishnu. Third and lastly, the Vaishnava canon makes the final distinction in addition to the above two qualities of Lord Vishnu or [[Narayana]], so as to reinforce his pre-eminence and supremacy among all the Gods because Sreeman Narayana or Vishnu in his myriad forms never ever grants a wish to evil beings, as is done according to the [[Puranas]] by both the creator God [[Brahma]] or the destroyer God [[Shiva]]. So they regard Sreeman Narayana or Vishnu as a protector God who makes a clear distinction between bad and good beings and never favours or grants boons or wishes to evil entities as would be done by both [[Shiva]] and [[Brahma]] and is thus regarded by them as the only God worthy of worship as the preferred deity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nilakanta Sastri 1980&quot;/&gt;

The above actions of Vishnu automatically led to the lowering of status of Indra among Hindu deities and leads directly to the ascendancy of Vishnu or Narayana, as per the Vaishnava canon.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nilakanta Sastri 1980&quot;/&gt;

===Brahmanas===

[[File:FourArmedVishnuPandyaDynasty8-9thCentury.jpg|thumb|left|Four-armed Vishnu, [[Pandya Dynasty]], 8–9th century CE.]]
In the [[Rigveda]], Shakala shakha: [[Aitareya Brahmana]] Verse 1 : ''agnir vai devānām avamo viṣṇuḥ paramas, tadantareṇa sarvā anyā devatā'' declares that [[Agni]] is the lowest or youngest god and Vishnu is the greatest and the oldest God.
In the Brahmanas, the supremacy of Lord Vishnu is clearly announced. Here He is repeatedly addressed as &quot;Yajnapati&quot; or the one whom all the sacrifices are meant to please.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nilakanta Sastri 1980&quot;/&gt; Even if the sacrifices are offered to the demigods, Lord Vishnu is the one who accepts the sacrifice and allots the respective fruits to the performer.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nilakanta Sastri 1980&quot;/&gt;  There is mention of one such incident where a demonic person performs a sacrifice by abducting the rishis (Sanskrit name for sages who constantly meditate by chanting God's name) forcefully. The sacrifice was meant to bring about the destruction of Indra. But the rishis,who used to worship Indra as a demigod were intelligent enough to alter a single pronunciation of the ved-mantra. The purpose of the entire sacrifice was reversed. When the fruit of the sacrifice was given, when the demon was on the verge of dying, he clearly calls out to lord Vishnu,whom he addresses as Supreme Godhead and &quot;the father of all living entities including himself&quot;. Aitareya Brahmana: 1:1:1 mentions Vishnu as the Supreme God. But in the Vaishnava canon, in different ages, with Vishnu in different forms, his relationship with the 'asuras' or evil-beings including demons (Hiranyaksha and Hiranyakashyipu were considered demons) has always been adversarial, with the asuras always causing harm or killing good beings including sages and devotees of Vishnu, with the sages and 'devas' (celestial beings including Indra – not considered a God in Vaishnava canon) doing penance and calling out to Lord Vishnu for protection. In response to the call of devotees and being described as the one and only saviour of the world, Sreeman Narayana or Vishnu, being the Protector God, always obliges by taking avatarams (incarnations as Narasimha, Rama etc.) to finally vanquish and eliminate the asuras. In the Vaishnava canon, Narayana or Lord Vishnu is clearly defined as one who has never given or granted any boons to the asuras (to clearly distinguish him from other gods like [[Shiva]] and [[Brahma]], who granted boons to demons or evil beings), but he is the only God called upon to save good beings by defeating or killing the very evil beings who became powerful or even invincible after being granted boons by the destroyer [[Shiva]] and the creator [[Brahma]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Nilakanta Sastri 1980&quot;/&gt; In any case Lord Vishnu himself is not a Brahmana. He belongs to Satriyan group.

[[Sayana]] writes that [[Aitareya Brahmana]] 1-1-1 ''agnir vai devānām avamo viṣṇuḥ paramas,tadantareṇa sarvā anyā devatā'' does not indicate any hierarchy among gods. Even in Rigveda Samhita, where '''avama''' and '''parama''' are '''not''' applied to denote '''rank and dignity''', but only to mark place and locality. In Rigveda 1:108:9,: ''yadindrāghnī avamasyāṃ pṛthivyāṃ madhyamasyāṃ paramasyāmuta sthaḥ |'' i.e., in the lowest place, the middle (place), and the highest (place). Agni, the fire, has, among the gods, the lowest place; for he resides with man on the earth ; while the other gods are either in the air, or in the sky. Vishnu occupies the highest place ; for he represents (in the Rigveda) the sun in its daily and yearly course. The words ''avama'' and ''parama'' is to be understood as 'First' and 'Last' respectively. To prove this meaning to be the true one, Sayana adduces the mantra (1,4. As'val. Sr. S. 4, 2), ''agnir mukham prathamo devatanam samgathanam uttamo vishnur asit'', i.e., Agni was the first of the deities assembled, (and) Vishnu the last. In the Kausitaki-Brahmana (7.1) Agni is called '''avarardhya''' (instead of avama), and Visnu '''parardhya'''(instead of parama),i.e., belonging to the lower and higher halves (or forming the lower and higher halves).&lt;ref&gt;page 1 foot note 1, Aitareya Brahmana , By Martin Haug, SUDHINDRA NATH VASU, M. B., AT THE PANINI OFFICE, BAHADURGANJ, ALLAHABAD.,1922.&lt;/ref&gt; The Vishnu Purana gives tremendous importance to the worship of Vishnu, but mentions that sacrifices to Sreeman Narayana are to begin only with both the lighting of fire or 'Agni', pouring of sacrificial offerings to Narayana or Vishnu in 'Agni' so that those offerings reach the Supreme God Vishnu and are accepted by him. Worship of Lord Vishnu through Yagnyas (or Homams) and other rituals, will not bear fruit or the desired result in case 'Agni' is not given any role in the process.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nilakanta Sastri 1980&quot;/&gt;

Muller says &quot;Although the gods are sometimes distinctly invoked as the great and the small, the young and the old (RV. i. 27. 13), this is only an attempt to find the most comprehensive expression for the divine powers, and nowhere is any of the gods represented as the slave of others. It would be easy to find, in the numerous hymns of the Veda, passages in which almost every single god is represented as supreme and absolute.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;page 533, History of Ancient Sanskrit Literature by Prof Max muller. Printed by Spottiwoode and Co. New-Street Square London.&lt;/ref&gt;

However this notion is not completely correct as per the following verses, which shows Rig Veda does recognize one or more gods being subject to other god(s).

Him whose high law not Varuna nor Indra, not Mitra, Aryaman, nor Rudra breaketh, Nor evil-hearted fiends, here for my welfare him I invoke, God Savitar, with worship.(Rigveda 2.038.09)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://flaez.ch/cgi-bin/rv.pl?nr=229&amp;txt=shppgr |title=RV 2 38 |publisher=Flaez.ch |date= |accessdate=2011-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sacred-texts.com/hin/rigveda/rv02038.htm |title=Rig Veda: Rig-Veda, Book 2: HYMN XXXVIII. Savitar |publisher=Sacred-texts.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

I invite to this place, with reverential salutations, for my good, that divine Savita, whose functions neither Indra, nor Varun.a, nor Mitra nor Aryaman nor Rudra nor the enemies (of the gods), impede. (Rigveda 2.038.09)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.srivaishnava.org/scripts/veda/rv/rvbook2.htm |title=Rigveda Sam.hita_: Devana_gari script and English Translation, Man.d.ala 2 |publisher=Srivaishnava.org |date= |accessdate=2011-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wilbourhall.org/pdfs/Vedas/RgVedaWilson/RgVedaWilson_VOL_II.pdf |title=(page 308) |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2011-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The following verse suggests Rudra gaining his strength from worship of Viṣṇu.

With offerings I propitiate the branches of this swift-moving God, the bounteous Visnu. Hence Rudra gained his Rudra-strength: O Asvins, ye sought the house that hath celestial viands.(Rigveda 7.040.05)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://flaez.ch/cgi-bin/rv.pl?txt=shppgr&amp;trl=iso&amp;buch=7&amp;hymnus=40 |title=RV 7 40 |publisher=Flaez.ch |date= |accessdate=2011-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sacred-texts.com/hin/rigveda/rv07040.htm |title=Rig Veda: Rig-Veda, Book 7: HYMN XL. Viśvedevas |publisher=Sacred-texts.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Viṣṇu Smṛti===
[[File:Garuda Vishnu Laxmi.jpg|thumb|left|200px|Vishnu and [[Lakshmi]] riding on Vishnu's ''[[Vahana]]'' [[Garuda]] – Painting from Rajasthan, Bundi, c.1730 (in [[Los Angeles County Museum of Art]] )]]

The [[Viṣṇu Smṛti]] (700-1000AD) is one of the latest books of the [[Dharmaśāstra]] tradition of Hinduism and also the only one which does not deal directly with the means of knowing [[dharma]], focusing instead on the [[bhakti]] tradition and requiring daily [[puja (Hinduism)|puja]] to the god Viṣṇu.  It is also known for its handling of the controversial subject of the practice of [[sati (practice)|sati]] (the burning of a widow on her husband’s funeral pyre).&lt;ref&gt;Olivelle 2007: 149–150.&lt;/ref&gt;  The text was not actually composed by the sage Viṣṇu himself, but rather by an individual or group writing much after his death.  This group brought together a collection of all of the commonly known legal maxims which were attributed to the sage Viṣṇu into one book as the Indian oral culture began to be recorded more formally.&lt;ref&gt;Lariviere 1989: xxiii&lt;/ref&gt;

==Theological attributes==
{{Main|Vaishnavism}}
{{Hinduism}}


Vishnu is the only [[Bhagavan]] as declared in the [[Bhagavata Purana|Bhagavata]] 1.2.11 in the verse: &quot;vadanti tat tattva-vidas tattvam yaj jnanam advayam brahmeti paramatmeti bhagavan iti sabdyate&quot;. The meaning of the verse is as follows: &quot;Learned transcendentalists who know the Absolute Truth call this nondual substance [[Brahman]], Paramātma, and [[Bhagavan]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Bhagavata Purana]] [http://vedabase.net/sb/1/2/11/en 1.2.11]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Vishnu Purana]] (6.5.79) the personality named [[Parashara|Parashara Rishi]] defines six bhagas as follows:

:''{{IAST|aiśvaryasya samagrasya vīryasya yaśasaḥ śriyaḥ}}''
:''{{IAST|jñāna-vairāgyayoś caiva ṣannāḥ bhaga itīṇganā}}''

[[Jiva Gosvami]] explains the verse in his [[Jiva Goswami#19-Gopala-champu|Gopala Champu]] (Pūrva 15.73) and [[Jiva Goswami#b) Bhagavata-sandarbha|Bhagavata Sandarbha]] 46.10:

:''{{IAST|jñāna-śakti-balaiśvarya-vīrya-tejām.sy aśeṣataḥ}}''
:''{{IAST|bhagavac-chabda-vācyāni vinā heyair guṇādibhiḥ}}''

:&quot;The substantives of the word bhagavat ({{IAST|bhagavat-śabda-vācyāni}}) are unlimited ({{IAST|aśes.atah.}}) knowledge (jñāna), energies (śakti), strength (bala), opulence (aiśvarya), heroism (vīrya), splendor (tejas), without (vinā) objectionable (heyair) qualities ({{IAST|guṇādibhiḥ}}).&quot;

Vishnu possesses six such divine glories, namely,
* {{IAST|Jñāna}} [[jnana|Omniscient]]; defined as the power to know about all beings simultaneously;
* Aishvarya [[Opulence]], which persists in unchallenged rule over all;
* Shakti [[shakti|Energy]], or power, which is the capacity to make the impossible possible;
* Bala [[bala (strength)|Strength]], which is the capacity to support everything by his will and without any fatigue;
* Virya [[virya|Vigour]], or valour which indicates the power to retain immateriality as the Supreme Spirit or Being in spite of being the material cause of mutable creations;
* {{IAST|Tèjas}} [[Resplendent]], or Splendour, which expresses his self-sufficiency and the capacity to overpower everything by his spiritual effulgence; cited from ''Bhakti Schools of Vedanta'', by Swami Tapasyananda.

However, the actual number of auspicious qualities of Vishnu is countless, with the above-mentioned six qualities being the most important. Other important qualities attributed to Vishnu are Gambhirya (inestimatable grandeur), Audarya (generosity), and Karunya (compassion). [[Natya Shastra]] lists Vishnu as the presiding deity of the [[Sringara]] [[Rasa (aesthetics)|rasa]].

The [[Rigveda]] says: Vishnu can travel in three strides. The first stride is the Earth. The second stride is the visible sky. The third stride cannot be seen by men and is the heaven where the gods and the righteous dead live. (This feature of three strides also appears in the story of his avatar [[Vamana]] called [[Trivikrama]].) The Sanskrit for &quot;to stride&quot; is the [[root (linguistics)|root]] ''kram''; its [[reduplication|reduplicated]] [[perfect (grammar)|perfect]] is ''chakram'' ({{IAST|[[guna|guņa]]}} grade) or ''chakra'' ([[zero-grade]]), and in the [[Rigveda]] he is called by [[epithet]]s such as ''{{IAST|vi-chakra-māņas}}'' = &quot;he who has made 3 strides&quot;. The Sanskrit word ''chakra'' also means &quot;wheel&quot;. That may have suggested the idea of Vishnu carrying a [[chakram|chakra]].

[[File:Beikthano (Vishnu) Nat.jpg|thumb|Vishnu (Beikthano in Burmese) on his mount, the garuda, in the traditional Burmese depiction.]]

===Five forms===
In [[Sri Vaishnavism]], another school, Vishnu assumes five forms:
#In the Para Form, Para is the highest form of Vishnu found only in Sri [[Vaikunta]] also called [[Moksha]], along with his consort Lakshmi, (and  [[Bhuma Devi]] and Nila devi, avatars of Lakshmi) and surrounded by liberated souls like [[Ananta]], [[Garuda]], and a host of Muktas (liberated souls).
#In the Vyuha form which itself divides into four, Vishnu assumes four forms, which exercise different cosmic functions and controls activities of living beings.
#In the Vibhava form, Vishnu assume various manifestations, called Vibhavas, more popularly known as [[Avatar]]as from time to time, in order to protect the virtuous, punish the evil-doers and re-establish righteousness.
#In the Antaryami; &quot;Dwelling within&quot; or &quot;Suksma Vasudeva&quot; form, Vishnu exists within the souls of all living beings and in every atom of matter.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sriranganatha.tripod.com/id49.html |title=SrimAn nArAyaNa |publisher=Sriranganatha.tripod.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;
#In the Arcavatara or Image manifestation, the Lord is easily approachable to the devotees since they cannot worship Para, Vyuha, Vibhava and Antaryami forms directly, which can only be imagined or meditated upon because they are beyond our reach. Such images can be
##revealed by the Lord himself, for example, a self-manifested ([[Swayambhu]]) icon ([[murti]]), e.g. The Mahavishnu Temple at [[Tirunelli]], The [[Sri Ranganathaswamy Temple (Srirangam)|Sri Ranganathaswamy Temple]] at [[Srirangam]], The [[Tirumala Venkateswara Temple]] etc.; or
##installed by [[Deva (Hinduism)|devas]] or celestial beings such as such as [[Guruvayur Temple]] installed by [[Vayu]]; or
##installed by humans, and consecrated according to Vaishnava [[Āgama (Hinduism)|Agama]] [[shastras]] or scriptures such as Lord [[Jagannath]] of [[Jagannath Temple (Puri)]] at [[Puri]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= SRIVAISHNAVISM&amp;nbsp;— A CONSCISE STUDY&amp;nbsp;— PART III |url=http://www.srivaishnavan.com/tomcat/srivaish3.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

See also [[Pañcaratra]]

==Relation with Shiva==
[[File:Ravivarmapress Rama family.jpg|upright|thumb|Rama with Sita on the throne, their children Lava and Kusha on their laps. Behind the throne, Lakshamana, Bharata and Shatrughna stand. Hanuman bows to Rama before the throne. Valmiki to the left]]
The Trimurthis are inseparable and in complete harmony in view of their common vision and universal good. They complement each other. Lord Vishnu is widely seen as the brother of Shiva's consort Parvati. In fact Vishnu formalized the wedding of Shiva and Parvati and acted as Parvati's brother in all the ceremonies and performed 'Kanya Daan', while the creator-god Brahma acted as the priest of the wedding. The mother goddess Parvati is referred to as his sister in sacred hymns – 'Narayani' in Devi Stotram, 'Vaishnavi' in Ambashtakam and as 'Padmanabha Sahodari' in Lalita Sahasranama Stotram. In fact it should be remembered that Goddess Durga(Parvati) and Vishnu (as his avatar Krishna) were actually born as brother and sister in Krishnavatar in Dwapara Yuga – Durga takes Yasoda's womb as 'Yogamaya' and Krishna takes Devaki's womb, both are interchanged. When Kansa tries to kill the baby skips out of his hans and transforms into Yogamaya who laughts aloud and informs him, &quot;You fool! your nemesis is born elsewhere. Your end is near&quot; and vanishes.

It should be noted that there is no concept of disagreement among the gods and they are ideal in all respects. However, ordinary men and sectarian groups not knowing this equilibrium and the sacred relationship among them, have in later ages woven several stories in vernacular presenting their preferred deity as Supreme and as 'sthala puranas' for the multitude of temples. These have nothing to do with the recognised original Puranas and other ancient Scriptures.

However their equilibrium is best manifested in Gajasura Samharam followed by Battle against Vinayaka. Similarly [[Samudra manthan]] episode and [[Hanuman]]'s part in the entire [[Ramayana]] are also a superlative examples of synergy between the two gods.

The rakshasa called Gajasura was an ardent devotee of Lord Siva. He underwent penance for many years to receive special boons. Siva, who was moved by Gajasura's devotion, offered a boon. Gajasura asked Siva to reside in his belly and Siva instantly agreed.

Meanwhile on Mount Kailash, Parvati was anxious to know her husband's whereabouts and finally approached her brother Lord Vishnu for help. Vishnu and Brahma disguised themselves as street players and along with Shiva's Bull carrier Nandi, they set out in search of Shiva. Then Vishnu, the omniscient director of the cosmic game, staged a small play. He transformed Nandi into a dancing bull and conducted him in front of Gajasura, with himself and Brahma playing musical instruments. The enchanting performance of the bull sent the demon into ecstasies, and he asked the flutist to tell him what he desired. The flutist asks for Shiva to be liberated. Hearing this, the demon king realised that the entertainer is none but Lord Vishnu himself and that his end is near. He also realises that Shiva cannot be made to live in his stomach forever because the whole world would become pell mell. Gajasura then prayed to Lord Shiva that he should be allowed to be immortal in the memories of people which Shiva agreed. Nandi made a dent in Gajasura's stomach and amid pitched chanting and prayers, Shiva emerged ripping apart the skin. To fulfill his wish, Lord Siva severed Gajasura's head and freed him from the cycle of births and deaths. Gajasura's head was subsequently used for Vinayaka and thus he became immortal with the world adoring Ganesha.

Although their names were mentioned in the Vedas, during the pure Vedic period, both Vishnu and [[Shiva]] (as identified with Rudra) played relatively minor roles, but by the time of the Brahmanas (c. 1000–700 BCE), both were gaining ascendance.&lt;ref&gt;For relatively minor position in Vedic times, and rise in progress by 1000–700 BCE see: Zimmer (1946), p. 125, note 2.&lt;/ref&gt; By the Puranic period, both deities had major sects of devotees, creating a schism in the society.&lt;ref&gt;For the rise in popularity of Shiva and Vishnu, and the role of Puranas in promoting sectarian positions, see: Flood (1996), pp. 110–111.&lt;/ref&gt;

Of significance is both the creator [[Brahma]] and [[Shiva]] the destroyer also played supportive roles by keeping company of [[Lord Vishnu]] in his incarnated forms. [[Hanuman]] the 'Vanara' completely dedicated to [[Rama|Ram]], who gives him company and obeys his command while playing an important part in [[Rama|Ram]]'s life is regarded in Vaishnava canon as being none other than [[Shiva]] the destroyer only, because it is through the blessings of [[Shiva]] that [[Hanuman]] is born to his mother Anjani for he also bears the name Anjaniputra. Thus, [[Hanuman]] the constant consort of Vishnu, with his idol being present in not just temples of [[Rama]], but also in temples of [[Krishna]], [[Narasimha]] i.e. all the avatarams of Vishnu is considered by [[Vaishnavas]] as being none other than Lord [[Shiva]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Nilakanta Sastri 1977&quot;&gt;Nilakanta Sastri, K.A. (1977) Reprint 1980, ''Advanced History of India'', Allied Publishers, New Delhi.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Harihara.jpg|thumb|right|Vishnu (left half—blue) and Shiva (right half—white)]]
Syncretic forces produced stories in which the two deities were shown in cooperative relationships and combined forms. [[Harihara]] is the name of a combined deity form of both Vishnu ([[Hari]]) and Shiva (Hara).&lt;ref&gt;Chakravarti, pp. 54–55.&lt;/ref&gt; This dual form, which is also called Harirudra, is mentioned in the [[Mahabharata]].&lt;ref&gt;For Harirudra citation to Mbh. III.39.76f see: Hopkins (1969), p. 221.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Relations with other deities==
{{Unreferenced section|date=May 2009}}
[[File:Halebidu Lakshminarayana.jpg|right|thumb|x216px|text|Vishnu with Lakshmi (''[[Laxminarayan|Lakshmi-Narayana]]'') at [[Halebidu]].]]
Vishnu's consort is [[Lakshmi]], the goddess of wealth. [[Maya (Hinduism)|Maya]] is the samvit (the primary intelligence)dark matter of the universe is Vishnu, while the other five attributes emerge from this samvit and hence Maya or dark energy of the universe is Lakshmi is his ahamata, activity, or Vishnu's Power. This power of God, Maya or Shakti, is personified and is called Shree or Lakshmi, Maya, [[Vishnumaya]], or Mahamaya, and She is said to manifest Herself in, 1) kriyāshakti, (Creative Activity) and 2) bhütishakti (Creation) of Universe. Hence this world cannot part with his creativity i.e., dark energy of universe, which is a feminine form which in its feminine form is called Shree or Lakshmi or Maya. He therefore needs consort Goddess Lakshmi to be with Him always. Thus goddess Lakshmi has to accompany Vishnu in all His incarnations. Her various avatars as Lord Vishnu's consort are –

Varahavataram  – [[Bhudevi]]

Ramavataram    – [[Vedavati]] &amp; [[Sita]]

Krishnavataram – [[Radha]] &amp; [[Rukmini]]

Venkateswara   – [[Padmavathi]]

Vishnu's vehicle is [[Garuda]], the eagle, and he is commonly depicted as riding on his shoulders. Another name of him is &quot;Veda-Atma&quot; or The Soul of the Vedas and Vedic truth.

==Iconography==
{{Unreferenced section|date=May 2009}}
[[File:Airlangga.jpg|right|thumb|x216px|The 11th century [[Java]]n statue of Vishnu mounting [[Garuda]], mortuary deified depiction of King [[Airlangga]]]]
According to various [[Purana]], Vishnu is the ultimate omnipresent reality, is shapeless and [[omnipresence|omnipresent]]. However, a strict iconography governs his representation, whether in pictures, icons, or idols:

*He is to be depicted as a four-armed male-form: The four arms indicate his all-powerful and all-pervasive nature. The physical existence of Vishnu is represented by the two arms in the front while the two arms at the back represent his presence in the spiritual world. The [[Upanishad]] titled ''Gopal Uttartapani'' describes the four arms of Vishnu.

*Also on his chest is the ''srivatsa'' mark, symbolising his consort Lakshmi. It is on the chest of Vishnu, where Lakshmi resides.
*Around his neck, he wears the auspicious &quot;[[Kaustubha]]&quot; jewel, and a garland of flowers (vanamaalaa). It is in this jewel, on Vishnu's chest that Lakshmi dwells.
*A [[crown (headgear)|crown]] should adorn his head: The [[crown (headgear)|crown]] symbolizes his supreme authority. This crown is sometimes depicted having a peacock feather, borrowing the iconography from image of his Krishna avataar.
*He is to shown wearing two earrings: The [[earring]]s represent inherent opposites in creation&amp;nbsp;— knowledge and ignorance; happiness and unhappiness; pleasure and pain.
*He rests on [[Ananta]]: the immortal and infinite snake
[[File:Vishnu.jpg|frame|right|Vishnu holding Panchajanya in his upper left hand]]
[[File:Vishnu and Lakshmi on Shesha Naga, ca 1870.jpg|thumb|Vishnu reclining on the [[Shesha]] Naga with his consort Lakshmi pressing his feet.]]
Vishnu is always to be depicted holding the four attributes associated with him, being:
# A [[conch]] shell or ''Shankha'', named &quot;[[Panchajanya]]&quot;, held by the upper left hand, which represents Vishnu's power to create and maintain the universe. The ''[[Panchajanya]]'' represents the five elements or ''Panchabhoota'' – water, fire, air, earth and sky or space. It also represents the five airs or [[Pranas]] that are within the body and mind. The conch symbolizes that Vishnu is the primeval Divine sound of creation and universal maintenance. it also represented as [[Om]]. In the [[Bhagavad Gita]], Krishna avatara states that of sound vibrations, 'He is Om'.
# The chakra, a sharp-spinning discus-like weapon, named &quot;[[Sudarshana]]&quot;, held by the upper right hand, which symbolizes the purified spiritualized mind. The name ''Sudarshana'' is derived from two words – ''Su'', which means ''good'', ''superior'', and ''Darshan'', which means ''vision'' or ''Sight''; together, it is &quot;Superior Vision&quot;.  The [[chakram|chakra]] represents destruction of one's ego in the awakening and realization of the souls original nature and god, burning away of spiritual ignorance and illusion, and developing the higher spiritual vision and insight to realize god.
# A [[Mace (club)|mace]] or ''Gada'', named &quot;Kaumodaki&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Dallapiccola, Anna L. ''[[Dictionary of Hindu Lore and Legend]]'' Thames &amp; Hudson, London, ISBN 0-500-51088-1&lt;/ref&gt; held by the lower left hand,  symbolizes Vishnu's divine power is the source all spiritual, mental and physical strength. It also signifies Vishnu's power to destroy materialistic or demoniac tendencies called anarthas; within the person's consciousness that hinders them from reaching god. Vishnu's mace is the power of the Divine within us to spiritually purify and uplift us from our materialistic bonds.
# A lotus flower or [[Padma (attribute)|Padma]], held by the lower right hand, represents spiritual liberation, Divine perfection, purity and the unfolding of Spiritual consciousness within the individual. The lotus opening its petals in the light of the Sun is indicative of the expansion and awakening of our long dormant, original spiritual consciousness in the light of god. The lotus in Vishnu's hand symbolizes that god is the power and source from which the universe and the individual soul emerges. It also represents Divine Truth or [[Satya]], the originator of the rules of conduct or [[Dharma]], and Divine [[Vedic]] knowledge or [[jnana]]. The lotus also symbolizes that Vishnu is the embodiment of spiritual perfection and purity. Also that He is the wellspring of these qualities and that the individual soul must seek to awaken these intrinsic Divine qualities from Vishnu by surrendering to and linking with Him.
[[File:Garudabkkholidayinn0609.jpg|thumb|200px|A statue in [[Bangkok]], [[Thailand]] depicting Vishnu mounted on his ''vahana'' Garuda]]

To this may be added, conventionally, the vanamaala flower garland and Vishnu's bow, the Shaarnga, and his sword Nandaka. A verse of the Vishnu Sahasranama stotram states;''&quot;vanamālī gadhī shārngī shanki chakri cha nandaki / shrīmān nārāyaņo vişņo vāsudevo abhirakşatu//&quot;'';   translation: Protect us Oh Lord Narayana who wears the forest garland,who has the mace, conch, sword and the wheel. And who is called Vishnu and the Vasudeva.

In general, Vishnu is depicted in one of the following three ways:
#Standing upright on a lotus flower, often with Lakshmi, his consort, beside him on a similar pedestal;
#Reclining on the coiled-up thousand-hooded ''[[Shesha]] Naga'', with his consort Lakshmi, seated at his feet; the assemblage rests on the &quot;Kshira Sagar&quot; ([[ocean of Milk]]). In this representation, Brahma is depicted as sitting on a lotus that grows out of Vishnu's navel.
#Riding on the back of his [[eagle]] mount, known as [[Garuda]]. Another name for Garuda is &quot;Veda atma&quot;; Soul of the Vedas. The flapping of his wings symbolizes the power of the Divine Truth of Vedic wisdom. Also the eagle represents the soul. Garuda carrying Vishnu symbolizes the soul or jiva atma carrying the Super soul or Param atma within it.

==Avatars==
{{Main|Avatar#Avatars of Vishnu|l1=Avatars of Vishnu}}
{{See also|Dashavatara}}
[[File:Avatars.jpg|thumb|250px|Ten avatars of Vishnu ([[Matsya]], [[Kurma]], [[Varaha]], [[Vamana]], [[Krishna]], [[Kalki]], [[Gautama Buddha in Hinduism|Buddha]], [[Parshurama]], [[Rama]] &amp; [[Narasimha]]. Painting from [[Jaipur]], now at the [[Victoria and Albert Museum]]]]
There are ten avatars (''dashavatara'') of Vishnu commonly considered as the most prominent:&lt;ref&gt;[[Garuda Purana]] Texts 1.86.10–11&lt;/ref&gt;

# '''[[Matsya]]''', the fish that kills Damanaka to save the vedas and saves mankind.
# '''[[Kurma]]''', the turtle that helps the Devas and Asuras churn the ocean for the nectar of immortality.
# '''[[Varaha]]''', the boar that rescues the Earth and kills Hiranyaksha.
# '''[[Narasimha]]''', the one (half-Lion half- human) who defeats the demon Hiranyakashapu  (Nara = man, simha = lion).
# '''[[Vamana]]'''. the dwarf that grows into a giant to save the world from King Bali.
# '''[[Parashurama]]''', A Sage, Rama with the axe, who appeared in the [[Treta Yuga]].
# '''[[Rama]]''', Sri Ramachandra, the prince and king of [[Ayodhya]] and killed Demon King Raavana.
# '''[[Krishna]]''' (meaning 'dark coloured' or 'all attractive' or the Existence of Bliss, Vishnu sahasranama, Sankara's interpretation of the
# '''[[Kalki]]''' (&quot;Eternity&quot;, or &quot;timeless&quot;, destroyer of time or &quot;The Destroyer of foulness&quot;), who is expected to appear at the end of [[Kali Yuga]], the time period in which we currently exist.
# '''[[Gautam Buddha]] ''' (&quot;awakened one&quot; or &quot;the enlightened one.&quot;)

Some versions of the above list include [[Hayagriva]] amongst the Dasavataras. Apart from the above mentioned ten principal avatars, another 22 avatars are also given in Chapter 3, Canto 1 of the Bhagavata Purana. Following this list the Bhagavatam states that as well as these avatars &quot;the incarnations of the Lord are innumerable, like rivulets flowing from inexhaustible sources of water&quot;.

==Thousand names of Vishnu==
{{Unreferenced section|date=May 2009}}
{{Main|Vishnu sahasranama}}

[[File:Vishnu sahasranama manuscript, c1690.jpg|thumb|[[Vishnu sahasranama]] manuscript, ca. 1690.]]

Vishnu has a very large number of names and followers that are collected in the [[Vishnu sahasranama]] (&quot;Vishnu's thousand names&quot;) from within the larger work ''[[Mahabharata]]''. The character [[Bhishma]] recites the names before Krishna on the battlefield of [[Kurukshetra]], praising him (Vishnu) as the supreme god. These Sahasranama are regarded as the essence of all [[Vedas]] by followers of [[Vaishnavism]], who believe sincere chanting of Vishnu Sahasranama results in spiritual well-being and a greater awareness of God.

The names are generally derived from the ''anantakalyanaguna''s (meaning: infinite auspicious attributes). Some names are:

*[[Anish]] (Supreme)
*[[Achintya]] (Incomprehensible, beyond understanding, also interpreted as remover of all worries from devotees)
*Achyutha (infallible)
*Akshaj (synonym for Lord Vishnu)
*Amar (immortal, deathless, son of Aum)
*[[Ananta]] (endless, eternal, infinite)
* Anirudha (the one that cannot be stopped)
*[[Venkateswara|Balaji]] (another name of Vishnu)
*[[Damodar (name of Krishna)|Damodara]] (having a rope (dama) around his belly (udara): a name of Krishna)
*[[Govinda]] (protector of the cows &amp; Brahmins; master of the senses: a name of Krishna)
*[[Hari]] (one who takes away)
*[[Hayagriva]] (Horse-necked)
*[[Jagannatha]] (Owner/Ruler of the world/universe)
*[[Janardana]] (One who is worshiped by people for Wealth)
*[[Keshava]] (slayer of [[Keshi (demon)|Keshi]], having long or much or handsome hair, from [[Atharvaveda]] viii, 6, 23)
*[[Krishna]] (born during the third epoch or [[yuga]], his deeds range from cow protection (go rakshya) to absolving the earth of load of sins)
*[[Madhava (Vishnu)|Madhava]] (relating to the season of spring)
*[[Madhusudana]] (he who destroyed the demon called [[Madhu-Kaitabh]])
*[[Narayana]] (said to mean &quot;he who is the abode of ''nār'' (= ether)&quot;, i.e., the whole universe's shelter. Also means &quot;The supreme Man who is the foundation of all men&quot;. Another meaning is &quot;He who lays in the water&quot;.
*[[Padmanabha]] (lotus-naveled one, from whose [[navel]] sprang the [[nelumbo nucifera|lotus]] which contained Brahma, who created the universe)
*[[Parthasarathy]] (Charioteer of Arjuna/Partha)
*[[Perumal]] Name he is known in [[Tamil language|Tamil]]
*[[Thirumaal]]Name he is known in [[Tamil language|Tamil]]
*[[Maalavan]] Name he is known in [[Tamil language|Tamil]]
*[[Purushottama]] – The Supreme Eternal Being
*[[Rama|Ram]] (born during the second epoch or [[Yuga]], his deeds primarily established the ideal living principles for a man)
*[[Rishikesh|Hrishikesh]] (Lord of the senses or Lord within the heart; &quot;hri&quot; root meaning the heart)
*[[Narayana|Satyanarayana]] (a combination of [[satya]] and Narayana meaning 'protector of truth')
* Shikhandee: He who wears a peacock feather.
*[[Suryanarayan]] (the one who destroys the evil/sins and who comforts us) described in Vishnu kautuvam.
*[[Sridhar]]a (consort of Sri = [[Laxmi]] or Ultimate wealth)
*[[Sriman]] (the pride of [[Shri]] or Lakshmi); Often Sriman is combined with the name, Narayana, to form a compound word, [[Sriman Narayana]].
*[[Srinivasa]] (the abode of [[Shri]]) (also specifically referring to his form in the temple at [[Tirumala Venkateswara Temple|Tirupati]]). Also the form of Vishnu at Tirupati is well known as [[Venkateswara]].
*[[Trivikrama]] (Conqueror of the three worlds, as in Vamana avatara).
*Vishal (Immense, The Unstoppable One).
*[[Vamana]] (dwarfish, small or short in stature, a dwarf brahmana)
*[[Vāsudeva]] ( &quot;All-Pervading god&quot;, with the long vowel A; it also means &quot;the son of [[Vasudeva]]&quot;, i.e. Krishna)
*[[Shree-esh]] (One who has Shree or Lakshmi as his consort / Husband of Goddess Lakshmi).
* [[Guruvayurappan]] Lord of Guruvayur (Temple made by Guru (Brihaspati) &amp; Vayu deva)
*[[Jagannath]] is the south eastern name of Vishnu. The word juggernaut has its origin from this name of Vishnu (The Jagannatha temple is in Puri, Orissa where every year there is a festival in which huge chariots are drawn through the city. These chariots are the vahana (vehicle) for the 3 main gods of this temple – Jagannatha, Balabhadra (Jagannath's brother) and Subhadra (Jagannatha's sister). Hundreds of men are needed to pull each of these chariots. When they start moving, they keep moving and are difficult to stop. That is the idea behind the word juggernaut which means something huge that cannot be stopped.)
*Sohama means the most intelligent, it is strongest form of Vishnu with a thousand brains and hands

According to the Siddhartha-samhita there are twenty-four forms of Lord Vishnu. The twenty-four forms are
{|
|
#[[Vasudeva]]
#[[Sankarshana]]
#[[Pradyumna]]
#[[Anirudha]]
#[[Keshava]]
#[[Narayana]]
|&lt;ol start=&quot;7&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[[Krishna|Madhava]]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[[Govinda]]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vishnu&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[[Madhusudana]]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[[Trivikrama]]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[[Vamana]]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
|&lt;ol start=&quot;13&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[[Sridhara]]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[[Hrishikesha]]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[[Padmanabha]]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[[Damodara]]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[[Purushottama]]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[[Achyutha]]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
|&lt;ol start=&quot;19&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[[Nrisimha]]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[[Janardana]]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[[Hari]]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[[Krishna]]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[[Adhokshaja]]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upendra&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
 |}Sourish comes from the Indian word which means, &quot;Lord Vishnu

==See also==
*[[Bhagavan]]
*[[Garbhodaksayi Vishnu]]
*[[Garuda]]
*[[Great Architect of the Universe]]
*[[Ksirodakasayi Vishnu]]
*[[List of names of Vishnu]]
*[[Mahavishnu]]
*[[Narasimha]]
*[[Narayana]]

==Further reading==
* {{cite book | author = Translation by Richard W. Lariviere| title = The Nāradasmr̥ti| publisher = University of Philadelphia | year = 1989| isbn = }}
*Patrick Olivelle.  [http://www.indologica.it/volumi/doc_XXXIII/chapter%2007%20Olivelle.pdf &quot;The Date and Provenance of the Viṣṇu Smṛti.&quot;]  ''Indologica Taurinensia'', 33 (2007): 149–163.
* {{cite book | author = [[Devdutt Pattanaik]]| title = 7 Secrets of Vishnu| publisher = westland ltd| year = 2011| isbn = 978-93-80658-68-1}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.1stholistic.com/prayer/hindu/hol_hindu-vishnu.htm Vishnu, the god of Preservation, by Dr. C.P.Ramaswami Aiyar]
* [http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/hinduism/deities/vishnu.shtml BBC Religion &amp; Ethics – Who is Vishnu] (bbc.co.uk)

==Footnotes==
{{Cleanup-link rot|date=November 2011}}

{{Hindu Culture and Epics}}
{{VishnuAvatars}}
{{Famous Vishnu temples}}

[[Category:Characters in the Bhagavata Purana]]
[[Category:Forms of Vishnu| ]]
[[Category:Vaishnavism]]
[[Category:Hindu gods]]
[[Category:Rigvedic deities]]
[[Category:Savior gods]]
[[Category:Solar gods]]
[[Category:Triple deities]]
[[Category:Names of God in Hinduism]]
[[Category:Sanskrit words and phrases]]

[[af:Wisjnoe]]
[[als:Vishnu]]
[[ar:فيشنو]]
[[an:Viṣṇu]]
[[as:বিষ্ণু]]
[[ast:Visnú]]
[[bn:বিষ্ণু]]
[[bg:Вишну]]
[[bo:ཁྱབ་འཇུག]]
[[bs:Višnu]]
[[br:Vichnou]]
[[ca:Vixnu]]
[[cs:Višnu]]
[[cy:Vishnu]]
[[da:Vishnu]]
[[de:Vishnu]]
[[et:Višnu]]
[[el:Βισνού]]
[[es:Visnú]]
[[eo:Viŝnuo]]
[[eu:Vishnu]]
[[fa:ویشنو]]
[[fr:Vishnou]]
[[gl:Vishnu]]
[[gu:વિષ્ણુ]]
[[ko:비슈누]]
[[hi:विष्णु]]
[[hr:Višnu]]
[[id:Wisnu]]
[[is:Visnjú]]
[[it:Vishnu]]
[[he:וישנו]]
[[jv:Wisnu]]
[[kn:ವಿಷ್ಣು]]
[[ka:ვიშნუ]]
[[lv:Višnu]]
[[lt:Višnus]]
[[hu:Visnu]]
[[ml:വിഷ്ണു]]
[[mr:विष्णु]]
[[ms:Vishnu]]
[[my:ဗိဿနိုးနတ်]]
[[nl:Vishnoe]]
[[ne:विष्णु]]
[[new:विष्णु (सन् १९९५या संकिपा)]]
[[ja:ヴィシュヌ]]
[[no:Vishnu]]
[[nn:Visjnu]]
[[or:ବିଷ୍ଣୁ]]
[[pnb:وشنو]]
[[km:ព្រះវិស្ណុ]]
[[nds:Wischnu]]
[[pl:Wisznu]]
[[pt:Vixnu]]
[[ro:Vișnu]]
[[ru:Вишну]]
[[sa:विष्णुः]]
[[sco:Vishnu]]
[[simple:Vishnu]]
[[sk:Višnu]]
[[sl:Višnu]]
[[sr:Вишну]]
[[sh:Višnu]]
[[fi:Vishnu]]
[[sv:Vishnu]]
[[tl:Vishnu]]
[[ta:விஷ்ணு]]
[[te:విష్ణువు]]
[[th:พระวิษณุ]]
[[tr:Vişnu]]
[[uk:Вішну]]
[[ur:وشنو]]
[[vi:Vishnu]]
[[fiu-vro:Višnu]]
[[war:Vishnu]]
[[zh:毗湿奴]]</text>
      <sha1>4w8c0ksl6ii2ypubjapssqyz9cqz5kc</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
