<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Western Schism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>543939</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522098448</id>
      <parentid>522098082</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T01:16:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Truthkeeper88</username>
        <id>7411880</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Help:Reverting|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/107.205.197.4|107.205.197.4]] ([[User talk:107.205.197.4|talk]]) to last version by Plain jack</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10625">{{No footnotes|date=December 2010}}
{{refimprove|date=December 2010}}
The '''Western Schism''' or '''Papal Schism''' was a split within the [[Catholic Church]] from 1378 to 1417. Two men simultaneously claimed to be the true [[pope]]. Driven by politics rather than any [[History of Catholic dogmatic theology|theological disagreement]], the [[Schism (religion)|schism]] was ended by the [[Council of Constance]] (1414–1418). The simultaneous claims to the papal chair of two different men hurt the reputation of the office. The Western Schism is sometimes called the '''Great Schism''', although this term is also applied to the [[East–West Schism]] of 1054.

==Origin==
The [[schism (religion)|schism]] in the western Roman Church resulted from the return of the papacy to [[Rome]] under [[Pope Gregory XI|Gregory XI]] in 1378, ending the [[Avignon Papacy]], which had developed a reputation of corruption that estranged major parts of Western [[Christendom]]. This reputation can be attributed to perceptions of predominant French influence and to the papal [[Curia (Roman Catholic Church)|curia]]'s efforts to extend its powers of patronage and increase its revenues.

After Pope Gregory XI died, the Romans rioted to ensure the election of a Roman for pope. In 1378 the [[Cardinal (Catholicism)|cardinals]] elected a [[Naples|Neapolitan]] when no viable Roman candidates presented themselves. [[Pope Urban VI]], born Bartolomeo Prignano, the [[Archbishop of Bari]], was elected. Urban had been a respected administrator in the papal [[Apostolic Chancery|chancery]] at Avignon, but as pope he proved suspicious, reformist, and prone to violent outbursts of temper. Many of the cardinals who had elected him soon regretted their decision: the majority removed themselves from Rome to [[Anagni]], where, even though Urban was still reigning, they elected Robert of Geneva as a rival pope on September 20 of the same year. Robert took the name [[Avignon Pope Clement VII|Pope Clement VII]] and reestablished a papal court in Avignon. The second election threw the Church into turmoil. There had been [[antipope]]s—rival claimants to the papacy—before, but most of them had been appointed by various rival factions; in this case, a single group of leaders of the Church had created both the pope and the antipope.

The conflicts quickly escalated from a church problem to a diplomatic crisis that divided Europe. Secular leaders had to choose which claimant they would recognize:
{|
|-
!style=&quot;background: #FFC0C0&quot;|Avignon
!style=&quot;background: #E0E0FF&quot;|Rome
|-
||[[Kingdom of France|France]], [[Kingdom of Aragon|Aragon]], [[Crown of Castile|Castile and León]], [[Kingdom of Cyprus|Cyprus]], [[Duchy of Burgundy|Burgundy]], [[County of Savoy|Savoy]], [[Kingdom of Naples|Naples]], and [[Kingdom of Scotland|Scotland]] recognized the Avignon claimant;
||[[Denmark]], [[Kingdom of England|England]], [[County of Flanders|Flanders]], the [[Holy Roman Empire]], [[Hungary]], [[History of Ireland (1169–1536)|Ireland]] (English Dominion), [[Kingdom of Norway|Norway]], [[Kingdom of Poland (1025–1385)|Poland]], [[Kingdom of Sweden|Sweden]], [[Republic of Venice]], and other City States of [[northern Italy]], recognized the Roman claimant.
|}
In the Iberian Peninsula there were the [[Ferdinand Wars]] (''Guerras fernandinas'') and the [[1383–1385 Crisis]] in [[Portugal]], during which dynastic opponents supported rival claimants to the papal office.

==Consequences==
[[Image:Habemus Papam 1415.jpg|thumb|left|250px|''[[Habemus Papam]]'' at the Council of Constance]]
Sustained by such national and factional rivalries throughout Catholic Christianity, the schism continued after the deaths of both initial claimants; Pope [[Boniface IX]], crowned at Rome in 1389, and antipope [[Avignon Pope Benedict XIII|Benedict XIII]], who reigned in Avignon from 1394, maintained their rival courts. When Boniface died in 1404, the eight cardinals of the [[Roman numerals|Roman]] conclave offered to refrain from electing a new pope if Benedict would resign; but when his legates refused on his behalf, the Roman party then proceeded to elect [[Pope Innocent VII]].

In the intense partisanship characteristic of the Middle Ages, the schism engendered a fanatical hatred noted by [[Johan Huizinga]]:&lt;ref&gt;Huizinga, ''[[The Autumn of the Middle Ages|The Waning of the Middle Ages]]'', 1924:14&lt;/ref&gt; when the town of [[Bruges]] went over to the &quot;obedience&quot; of Avignon, a great number of people left to follow their trade in a city of Urbanist allegiance; &quot;in 1382, the [[oriflamme]], which might only be unfurled in a holy cause, was taken up against the Flemings, because they were Urbanists, that is, infidels&quot;.

Efforts were made to end the Schism through force or diplomacy. The French crown even tried to coerce Benedict XIII, whom it nominally supported, into resigning. None of these remedies worked. The suggestion that a church council should resolve the Schism, first made in 1378, was not adopted at first because [[canon law]] required that a pope call a council. Eventually theologians like [[Pierre d'Ailly]] and Jean Gerson, as well as canon lawyers like [[Francesco Zabarella]], adopted arguments that equity permitted the Church to act for its own welfare in defiance of the [[letter of the law]].

Eventually the cardinals of both factions secured an agreement that Benedict and Pope Gregory XII would meet at [[Savona]]. They balked at the last moment, and both colleges of cardinals abandoned their popes. A [[Ecumenical Council|church council]] was held at [[Council of Pisa|Pisa]] in 1409 under the auspices of the cardinals to try solving the dispute, but it added to the problem by electing another antipope, [[Pope Alexander V|Alexander V]]. He reigned briefly from June 26, 1409, to his death in 1410, when he was succeeded by antipope [[Schismatic Pope John XXIII|John XXIII]], who won some but not universal support.

==Resolution==
Finally, the [[Council of Constance]] in 1414, advised by the theologian [[Jean Gerson]], secured the resignations of antipope [[Antipope John XXIII|John XXIII]] and the successor in Rome of Innocent VII, [[Pope Gregory XII]] (who resigned in 1415, but not before formally empowering the Council of Constance to elect the new pope, thus ensuring the legitimacy of the election), and [[excommunication|excommunicated]] the claimant who refused to step down, [[Avignon Pope Benedict XIII]]. The Council then elected [[Pope Martin V]], essentially ending the schism. Nonetheless, the Kingdom of Aragon did not recognize Martin V and continued to recognize Benedict XIII. Archbishops loyal to Benedict XIII subsequently elected [[Antipope Benedict XIV]] (Bernard Garnier) and three followers simultaneously elected [[Antipope Clement VIII]], but the Western Schism was by then practically over. (Clement VIII resigned in 1429 and apparently recognized Martin V.)

The line of Roman popes is now recognized as the legitimate line, but confusion on this point continued until the 19th century. Pope [[Pius II]] decreed that no appeal could be made from pope to council; this left no way to undo a papal election by anyone but the elected pope. No such crisis has arisen since the 15th century, and so there has been no need to revisit this decision. The alternate papal claimants have become known in history as [[antipope]]s. Those of Avignon were dismissed by Rome early on, but the Pisan popes were included in the ''Annuario Pontificio'' as popes well into the 20th century. Thus the Borgia pope [[Alexander VI]] took his regnal name in sequence after the Pisan Alexander V.

==Historiography==
According to Broderick:
:&quot;Doubt still shrouds the validity of the three rival lines of pontiffs during the four decades subsequent to the still disputed papal election of 1378. This makes suspect the credentials of the cardinals created by the Roman, Avignon, and Pisan claimants to the Apostolic See. Unity was finally restored without a definitive solution to the question; for the Council of Constance succeeded in terminating the Western Schism, not by declaring which of the three claimants was the rightful one, but by eliminating all of them by forcing their abdication or deposition, and then setting up a novel arrangement for choosing a new pope acceptable to all sides. To this day the Church has never made any official, authoritative pronouncement about the papal lines of succession for this confusing period; nor has Martin V or any of his successors. Modern scholars are not agreed in their solutions; although they tend to favor the Roman line.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Broderick, J.F. 1987. &quot;The Sacred College of Cardinals: Size and Geographical Composition (1099–1986).&quot; ''Archivum historiae Pontificiae'', '''25''': p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{WesternSchism}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
*''The Three Popes: An Account of the Great Schism'', by Marzieh Gail.
*''The Great Schism: 1378'', by John Holland Smith (New York 1970).
*''The Origins of the Great Schism: A study in fourteenth century ecclesiastical history'', by Walter Ullmann (Hamden, Conn: Archon Books, 1967 (rev. of 1948 original publication)).

==External links==
{{Portal|Catholicism}}
*[http://archive.org/details/ageofgreatwester08lock The Age of the Great Western Schism]
*[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/13539a.htm Catholic Encyclopedia article]

{{Periods of papal history}}
{{Christian History|collapsed}}
{{Catholicism}}

[[Category:Western Schism| Western Schism]]
[[Category:Avignon Papacy]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]

{{Link GA|fr}}

[[af:Westerse Skisma]]
[[ar:الانشقاق الغربي]]
[[an:Gran Scisma d'Occident]]
[[ast:Cisma d'Occidente]]
[[bg:Папска схизма]]
[[bs:Zapadni raskol]]
[[ca:Cisma d'Occident]]
[[da:Skisma#Det store skisma / Øst-vest-skismaet]]
[[de:Abendländisches Schisma]]
[[es:Cisma de Occidente]]
[[eo:Granda okcidenta skismo]]
[[eu:Mendebaldeko Zisma]]
[[fa:دو دستگی غرب]]
[[fr:Grand Schisme d'Occident]]
[[ko:서방 교회의 분열]]
[[hr:Zapadni raskol]]
[[id:Skisma Barat]]
[[it:Scisma d'Occidente]]
[[he:הקרע המערבי]]
[[la:Magnum schisma occidentale]]
[[mk:Западна шизма]]
[[nl:Westers Schisma]]
[[ja:教会大分裂]]
[[no:Det vestlige skisma]]
[[nds:Grote Schisma]]
[[pl:Wielka schizma zachodnia]]
[[pt:Grande Cisma do Ocidente]]
[[ru:Великий западный раскол]]
[[simple:Western Schism]]
[[sr:Западна шизма]]
[[sh:Zapadna šizma]]
[[fi:Suuri skisma (katolisuus)]]
[[sv:Den stora schismen]]
[[tr:Büyük Schisma]]
[[uk:Західна схизма]]
[[zh:天主教會大分裂]]</text>
      <sha1>a5oc8qcqd6jr3zn4ox68ojq16g6xhxl</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
