<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Wicca</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>33295</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522309993</id>
      <parentid>522286193</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T10:07:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kim Dent-Brown</username>
        <id>1916097</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted [[WP:AGF|good faith]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/69.156.87.120|69.156.87.120]] ([[User talk:69.156.87.120|talk]]): Rv unexplained removal of material. using [[WP:TWINKLE|TW]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="89973">{{Use British English|date=October 2012}}
{{About|the duotheistic religion|other uses}}
[[File:The Spiral Pentacle by SingingGandalf.jpg|thumb|240px|This [[pentacle]], worn as a [[pendant]], depicts a [[pentagram]], or five-pointed star, used as a symbol of Wicca by many adherents.]]
{{Paganism (contemporary)}}
'''Wicca''' ({{IPAc-en|lang|pron|ˈ|w|ɪ|k|ə}}) is a [[Paganism (contemporary)|modern pagan]] [[religion]] that draws upon a diverse set of [[paganism|ancient pagan]] religious motifs for its theological structure and ritual practice. The religion usually incorporates the practice of [[Witchcraft (contemporary)|witchcraft]]. Developed in England in the first half of the 20th century,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Triumph of the Moon: A History of Modern Pagan Witchcraft |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford, NY |first=Ronald |last=Hutton |year=1999 |page=vii |isbn=0-19-820744-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wicca was later popularised in the 1950s and early 1960s by [[Gerald Gardner (Wiccan)|Gerald Gardner]].{{cn|date=July 2012}} Gardner was a retired British civil servant, and an amateur anthropologist and historian who had a broad familiarity with pagan religions, esoteric societies and occultism in general. At the time Gardner called it the &quot;witch cult&quot; and &quot;witchcraft&quot;, and referred to its adherents as &quot;the Wica&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;WitchcraftToday&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Gardner |first=Gerald B |authorlink=Gerald Gardner (Wiccan) |title=Witchcraft Today |publisher=Mercury Publishing |location=Lake Toxaway, NC |year=1999 |origyear=1954 |oclc=44936549 |isbn=0-8065-2593-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; From the 1960s onward, the name of the religion was normalised to &quot;Wicca&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://www.thewica.co.uk/wica_or_wicca.htm |title=Wica or Wicca? - Politics and the Power of Words |journal=The Cauldron |first=Melissa |last=Seims |issue=129 |year=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Wicca is traditionally and primarily a [[dualism|duotheistic]] religion centred upon the idea of [[Gender binary|gender]] [[Binary opposition|polarity]] and the worship of a [[Triple Goddess (Neopaganism)|Moon Goddess]] and a [[Horned God]]. (This core theology was originally described by Gerald Gardner, the founder of the religion; and Doreen Valiente, who wrote much of the original liturgical materials.) The Goddess and the God may be regarded as the Divine Feminine and the Divine Masculine. They are complementary opposites or dualities, bearing similarities to the concept of [[yin and yang]] in Taoism. The God and Goddess are generally seen as lovers and equals, the Divine Couple who together co-create the cosmos. (See [[Wiccan views of divinity]].)

In addition to the core duotheism of Wicca, however, there are several other [[theology|theological]] positions possible, including [[pantheism]], [[polytheism]], and [[henotheism]]; and even, for Dianic feminist witches, a form of [[monotheism|monothestic]] [[Goddess movement#Wicca|goddess worship]]. These various theological perspectives are not necessarily regarded as mutually exclusive, and any individual Wiccan may shift from one perspective to another, or combine two or more perspectives together in one ritual. The metaphysical flexibility that allows for embracing more than one theological perspective at a time may seem paradoxical, but it is a common feature of Wicca as a [[mystery religion]].

Wicca also involves the ritual practice of [[Magic (paranormal)|magic]], ranging from the &quot;low magic&quot; or &quot;folk magic&quot; of shamanism and witchcraft to more elaborate and complex rites influenced by the [[ceremonial magic]] of the [[Hermeticism|Western Hermetic Tradition]]. Wiccans frequently subscribe to a broad code of morality known as the [[Wiccan Rede]], although this is not taken literally or even adhered to by all Wiccans. Another characteristic of Wiccan religion is the ritual celebration of the lunar and solar cycles. Lunar rites, known as [[esbat]]s are usually held around the time of the full moon; but they may also be held at the new moon, or the waxing or waning moon. The solar or seasonal festivals, known as [[sabbat]]s take place eight times a year, in regular intervals known as the [[Wheel of the Year]]. While both the God and the Goddess are usually honoured at both kinds of rituals, the [[Triple Goddess (Neopaganism)|Goddess]] is mainly associated with the [[Moon]], and the [[Horned God|God]] is mainly associated with the [[Sun]].

There are various denominations within Wicca, which are referred to as ''traditions''. Some, such as [[Gardnerian Wicca|Gardnerian]] and [[Alexandrian Wicca]], follow in the initiatory lineage of Gardner. Others,  such as the [[Dianic Wicca|Dianic tradition]], take primary influence from other figures and may not insist on any initiatory lineage.

The [[Wicca (etymology)|application of the word ''Wicca'']] has given rise to &quot;a great deal of disagreement and infighting&quot;.&lt;ref name=whitepomegranate&gt;{{cite journal |title=The meaning of &quot;Wicca&quot;: A study in etymology, history and pagan politics|journal=The Pomegranate |first=Ethan Doyle |last=White |year=2010 |issue=2 |ISSN=1528-0268}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gardnerian and Alexandrian Wicca are often collectively termed [[British Traditional Wicca]], and many of their practitioners consider the term ''Wicca'' to apply only to these lineaged traditions. Others do not use the word &quot;Wicca&quot; at all, instead preferring to be referred to only as &quot;Witchcraft,&quot; while others believe that all modern witchcraft traditions can be considered &quot;Wiccan.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;DrawingDownMoon&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Adler |first=Margot |authorlink=Margot Adler |title=Drawing Down the Moon: Witches, Druids, Goddess-worshippers and Other Pagans in America Today |publisher=Beacon Press |location=Boston |year=1979 |isbn=0-8070-3237-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gallagher2005&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Wicca Bible: the Definitive Guide to Magic and the Craft |first=Ann-Marie |last=Gallagher |publisher=Sterling Publishing |location=[[New York City|New York]] |year=2005 |isbn=1-4027-3008-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; Popular culture, as seen in TV programmes like [[Buffy the Vampire Slayer (TV series)|''Buffy the Vampire Slayer'']] tends to use the terms “Wiccan” and &quot;Wicca&quot; as completely synonymous with the terms “Witch” and “Witchcraft” respectively.

{{TOC limit|3}}

==Beliefs==
Beliefs vary markedly between different traditions and individual practitioners. However, various commonalities exist between these disparate groups, which usually include views on theology, the afterlife, magic and morality.

Some common Wiccan paths and spiritual groups include Gardnerian, Alexandrian, Celtic, and Dianic Wicca along with many others.

===Theology===
{{Main|Wiccan views of divinity}}
[[File:Horned God and Mother Goddess (Doreen Valiente's Altar).jpg|thumb|right|Altar statues of the Horned God and Mother Goddess as crafted by Bel Bucca, and owned by the 'Mother of Wicca', [[Doreen Valiente]].]]

Wiccan views on [[theology]] are numerous and varied and there is no universally agreed-upon [[canon law|religious canon]], but Wicca is traditionally a duotheistic religion that venerates both a &quot;[[Triple Goddess (Neopaganism)|Triple Goddess]]&quot; associated with the Moon and stars and fate, and a [[Horned God]] associated with forests and animals and the realm beyond death. These two deities are variously understood through the frameworks of [[pantheism]] (as being dual aspects of a single [[Deity|godhead]]), [[dualistic cosmology|duotheism]] (as being two polar opposites), [[hard polytheism]] (being two distinct deities in a larger pantheon which includes other pagan gods) or [[soft polytheism]] (being composed of many lesser deities). In some pantheistic and duotheistic conceptions, deities from diverse cultures may be seen as aspects of the Goddess or God.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gallagher2005&quot; /&gt; However, there are also other theological viewpoints to be found within the Craft, including [[monotheism]], the concept that there is just one deity, which is seen by some, such as [[Dianic Wicca]]ns, as being the Goddess, whilst by others, like the [[Church and School of Wicca]], as instead being genderless. There are other Wiccans who are [[atheism|atheists]] or [[agnosticism|agnostics]], not believing in any actual deity, but instead viewing the gods as psychological archetypes of the human mind which can be evoked and interacted with.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}

According to the Witches [[Janet Farrar|Janet]] and [[Stewart Farrar]], who held a pantheistic, duotheistic and [[animism|animistic]] view of theology, Wiccans &quot;regard the whole cosmos as alive, both as a whole and in all of its parts&quot;, but that &quot;such an organic view of the cosmos cannot be fully expressed, and lived, without the concept of the God and Goddess. There is no manifestation without polarisation; so at the highest creative level, that of Divinity, the polarisation must be the clearest and most powerful of all, reflecting and spreading itself through all the microcosmic levels as well&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Janet Farrar|Farrar, Janet]] and [[Stewart Farrar|Farrar, Stewart]]. (1987). ''The Witches' Goddess: The Feminine Principle of Divinity''. London: Robert Hale. Page 2-3.&lt;/ref&gt;

==== The God and the Goddess ====
For most Wiccans, the God and Goddess are seen as complementary polarities in the universe that balance one another out, and in this manner they have been compared to the concept of [[yin and yang]] found in [[Taoism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Witches' Goddess: The Feminine Principle of Divinity |publisher=Robert Hale |location=London |first=Janet |last=Farrar |coauthors=Farrar, Stewart |year=1987 |page=59 |isbn=0-7090-2800-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; As such they are often interpreted as being &quot;embodiments of a life-force manifest in nature&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;NatureRelToday&quot;&gt;{{cite book |url=http://books.google.com/?id=rLYCOOUlsBcC&amp;pg=PA6 |title=Nature Religion Today: Paganism in the Modern World |first=Joanne |last=Pearson |coauthors=Roberts, Richard H; Samuel, Geoffrey |publisher=Edinburgh University Press |location=Edinburgh |pages=6 |month=December |year=1998 |isbn=0-7486-1057-X |oclc=39533917}}&lt;/ref&gt; with some Wiccans believing that they are simply symbolic of these polarities, whilst others believing that the God and the Goddess are genuine beings that exist independently. The two divinities are often given symbolic associations, with the Goddess commonly being symbolised as the [[Earth]] (i.e. [[Mother Nature|Mother Earth]]), but also sometimes as the [[Moon]], which complements the God being viewed as the [[Sun]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Teen Witch: Wicca for a New Generation |publisher=Llewellyn|location=St Paul, Minnesota |first=Silver |last=Ravenwolf |year=1998 |page=25 |isbn=1-56718-725-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box|width=246px|align=left|quote=&quot;The Gods are real, not as persons, but as vehicles of power. Briefly, it may be explained that the personification of a particular type of cosmic power in the form of a God or Goddess, carried out by believers and worshippers over many centuries, builds that God-form or Magical Image into a potent reality on the Inner Planes, and makes it a means by which that type of cosmic power may be contacted.&quot;|source=[[Gerald Gardner (Wiccan)|Gerald Gardner]] (1959)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Meaning of Witchcraft |publisher=Aquarian |first=Gerald |last=Gardner |year=1959 |page=260 |isbn=0-939708-02-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; }}

Traditionally the God is viewed as a [[Horned God]], associated with nature, wilderness, sexuality, hunting and the life cycle.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Witches' God: Lord of the Dance |publisher=Robert Hale |location=London |first=Janet |last=Farrar |coauthors=Farrar, Stewart |year=1989 |pages=32–34 |isbn=0-7090-3319-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Horned God is given various names according to the tradition, and these include [[Cernunnos]], [[Pan (mythology)|Pan]], Atho and Karnayna.

At other times the God is viewed as the [[Green Man]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Farrar 1989 35–38&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Witches' God: Lord of the Dance |publisher=Robert Hale |location=London |first=Janet |last=Farrar |coauthors=Farrar, Stewart |year=1989 |pages=35–38 |isbn=0-7090-3319-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt; a traditional figure in European art and architecture, and they often interpret him as being associated with the natural world. The God is also often depicted as a [[solar deity|Sun God]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Witches' God: Lord of the Dance |publisher=Robert Hale |location=London |first=Janet |last=Farrar |coauthors=Farrar, Stewart |year=1989 |pages=15–17 |isbn=0-7090-3319-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt; particularly at the festival of [[Litha]], or the summer solstice. Another expression of the God is that of the Oak King and the Holly King, one who rules over winter and spring, the other who rules over summer and autumn.&lt;ref name=&quot;Farrar 1989 35–38&quot;/&gt;

The Goddess is usually portrayed as a [[Triple Goddess (Neopaganism)|Triple Goddess]], thereby being a triadic deity comprising a Maiden goddess, a [[Mother goddess]], and a Crone goddess, each of whom has different associations, namely virginity, fertility and wisdom.&lt;ref&gt;[[Janet Farrar|Farrar, Janet]] and [[Stewart Farrar|Farrar, Stewart]]. (1987). ''The Witches' Goddess: The Feminine Principle of Divinity''. London: Robert Hale. Page 29-37.&lt;/ref&gt; She is also commonly depicted as a [[lunar deity|Moon Goddess]],&lt;ref&gt;[[Janet Farrar|Farrar, Janet]] and [[Stewart Farrar|Farrar, Stewart]]. (1987). ''The Witches' Goddess: The Feminine Principle of Divinity''. London: Robert Hale. Page 38-44.&lt;/ref&gt; and is often given the name of [[Diana (mythology)|Diana]] after the ancient Roman deity. Some Wiccans, particularly from the 1970s onwards, have viewed the Goddess as the more important of the two deities, who is pre-eminent in that she contains and conceives all. In this respect, the God is viewed as the spark of life and inspiration within her, simultaneously her lover and her child.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Witches' God: Lord of the Dance |publisher=Robert Hale |location=London |first=Janet |last=Farrar |coauthors=Farrar, Stewart |year=1989 |pages=7–10 |isbn=0-7090-3319-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This is reflected in the traditional structure of the [[coven]].&lt;ref name=&quot;WitchesBible&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=A Witches' Bible: The Complete Witches Handbook |first=Janet |last=Farrar |authorlink=Janet Farrar |coauthors=and [[Stewart Farrar]] |publisher=Phoenix Publishing |location=London |pages=181–182 |year=1981 |isbn=0-919345-92-1 |oclc=62866821}}&lt;/ref&gt; In one [[monotheism|monotheistic]] form of the Craft, [[Dianic Wicca]], the Goddess is the sole deity, a concept that has been criticised by members of other more egalitarian traditions.

According to Gerald Gardner, &quot;the Goddess&quot; is a deity of prime importance, along with her consort the [[Horned God]]. In the earliest Wiccan publications, she is described as a tribal goddess of the witch community, neither omnipotent nor universal, and it was recognised that there was a greater &quot;[[unmoved mover|Prime Mover]]&quot;, although the witches did not concern themselves much with this being.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Gerald |last=Gardner |authorlink=Gerald Gardner (Wiccan) |title=The Meaning of Witchcraft |pages=26–27 |year=1988 |origyear=1959 |publisher=Copple House Books |location=Lakemont, GA US|isbn=0-939708-02-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The concept of having a religion venerating a Horned God accompanying a goddess had been devised by the Egyptologist [[Margaret Murray]] during the 1920s. She believed, based upon her own theories about the [[Witch trials in Early Modern Europe|Early Modern witch trials in Europe]], that those two deities, though primarily the Horned God, had been worshipped by a [[Witch-cult hypothesis|Witch-Cult]] ever since western Europe had succumbed to Christianity. Whilst now widely discredited, Gerald Gardner was a supporter of her theory, and believed that Wicca was a continuation of that historical Witch-Cult, and that the Horned God and Goddess were therefore ancient deities of the British Isles.&lt;ref name=&quot;MeaningWitchcraft1&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Meaning of Witchcraft |last=Gardner |first=Gerald B |authorlink=Gerald Gardner (Wiccan) |publisher=Copple House Books |location=Lakemont, GA |pages=260–261 |year=1988 |origyear=1959 |isbn=0-939708-02-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; Modern scholarship has disproved his claims, however various horned gods and mother goddesses were indeed worshipped in the British Isles during the ancient and early medieval periods.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Pagan Religions of the Ancient British Isles |publisher=Blackwell |location= |first=Ronald |last=Hutton |year=1991 |pages=260–261 |isbn=0-631-17288-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Pantheism, Polytheism and Animism====
[[File:Horned God.JPG|upright|thumb|right|A sculpture of the Horned God of Wicca found in the [[Museum of Witchcraft]] in [[Boscastle]], [[Cornwall]].]]

Many Wiccans believe that the God and Goddess are merely two aspects of the same [[Deity|godhead]], often viewed as a [[pantheism|pantheistic]] deity, thereby encompassing everything in the universe within its divinity. In his public writings, Gardner referred to this being as the [[Cosmological argument|Prime Mover]], and claimed that it remained unknowable,&lt;ref name=&quot;MeaningWitchcraft2&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Meaning of Witchcraft |last=Gardner |first=Gerald B |authorlink=Gerald Gardner (Wiccan) |publisher=Copple House Books |location=Lakemont, GA |pages=26–27 |year=1988 |origyear=1959 |isbn=0-939708-02-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; although in the rituals of his tradition, [[Gardnerian Wicca|Gardnerianism]], it is referred to as ''Dryghten'',&lt;ref name=&quot;WitchBlood&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Witch Blood! The Diary of a Witch High Priestess! |first=Patricia |last=Crowther |authorlink=Patricia Crowther (Wiccan) |publisher=House of Collectibles |location=New York City |year=1974 |isbn=0-87637-161-6 |oclc=1009193}}&lt;/ref&gt; which had originally been an [[Old English]] term meaning ''[[The Lord]]''. Since then it has been given other names by different Wiccans, for instance [[Scott Cunningham]] called it by its name in [[Neo-Platonism]], ''[[Henosis|The One]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Cunningham |first=Scott |authorlink=Scott Cunningham |title=Wicca: A Guide for the Solitary Practitioner |isbn=0-87542-184-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other Wiccans such as [[Starhawk]] use the term ''Star Goddess'' to describe the universal pantheistic deity that created the [[cosmos]], and regard her as a knowable deity that can and should be worshipped.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wicca-spirituality.com/charge-of-the-star-goddess.html Charge of the Star Goddess--Starhawk]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://barsoomfishrap.org/chrgstar.html Charge of the Star Goddess--&quot;Book of the Goddess&quot; (Co-edited by Julie Ann Rhoads and Ann Forfreedom in 1979-80):]&lt;/ref&gt;

As well as pantheism and duotheism, many Wiccans accept the concept of [[polytheism]], thereby believing that there are many different deities. Some accept the view espoused by the occultist [[Dion Fortune]] that &quot;all gods are one god, and all goddesses are one goddess&quot; —that is that the gods and goddesses of all cultures are, respectively, aspects of one supernal God and Goddess. With this mindset, a Wiccan may regard the Germanic [[Eostre]], Hindu [[Kali]], and Christian [[Virgin Mary]] each as manifestations of one supreme Goddess and likewise, the Celtic [[Cernunnos]], the ancient Greek [[Dionysus]] and the Judeo-Christian [[Yahweh]] as aspects of a single, archetypal god. A more strictly [[polytheism|polytheistic]] approach holds the various goddesses and gods to be separate and distinct entities in their own right. The Wiccan writers [[Janet Farrar]] and [[Gavin Bone]] have postulated that Wicca is becoming more polytheistic as it matures, tending to embrace a more traditionally pagan worldview.&lt;ref name=&quot;ProgressiveWitchcraft&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Progressive Witchcraft: Spirituality, Mysteries, and Training in Modern Wicca |first=Janet |last=Farrar |authorlink=Janet Farrar |coauthors=and [[Gavin Bone]] |publisher=New Age Books |location=Franklin Lakes, NJ |month=January |year=2004 |isbn=1-56414-719-3 |oclc=53223741}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some Wiccans conceive of deities not as literal personalities but as metaphorical [[archetype]]s or [[thoughtform]]s, thereby technically allowing them to be [[atheism|atheists]].&lt;ref name=&quot;DrawingDownMoon2&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Adler |first=Margot |authorlink=Margot Adler |title=Drawing Down the Moon: Witches, Druids, Goddess-worshippers and Other Pagans in America Today |pages=25, 34–35 |publisher=Beacon Press |location=Boston |year=1979 |isbn=0-8070-3237-9 |oclc=6918454}}&lt;/ref&gt; Such a view was purported by the High Priestess [[Vivianne Crowley]], herself a [[psychology|psychologist]], who considered the Wiccan deities to be [[Jungian archetypes]] that existed within the subconscious that could be evoked in ritual. It was for this reason that she said that &quot;The Goddess and God manifest to us in dream and vision.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Crowleyarchetype&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Crowley |first=Vivianne |authorlink=Vivianne Crowley |title=Wicca: The Old Religion in the New Millennium|pages=129 |isbn=0-7225-3271-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Wicca is essentially an [[Immanence|immanent]] religion, and for some Wiccans, this idea also involves elements of [[animism]]. A belief central to Wicca is that the Goddess and the God (or the goddesses and gods) are able to manifest in personal form, most importantly through the bodies of Priestesses and Priests via the rituals of [[Drawing down the Moon (ritual)|Drawing down the Moon]] or Drawing down the Sun.

===Afterlife===
Belief in the afterlife varies among Wiccans,&lt;ref&gt;''The Wicca Bible'' by Anne-Marie Gallagher, Godsfield, page 34-39&lt;/ref&gt; although [[reincarnation]] is a traditional Wiccan teaching dating back to the [[New Forest coven]] in the 1930s. The influential High Priest [[Raymond Buckland]] said that a human's soul reincarnates into the same species over many lives in order to learn lessons and advance spiritually,&lt;ref name=&quot;CompleteBookByRayBucks&quot;&gt;{{cite book |url=http://books.google.com/?id=fr0pse0LBK0C&amp;printsec=frontcover |title=Buckland's Complete Book of Witchcraft |publisher=Llewellyn |location=[[Saint Paul, Minnesota|Saint Paul]] |first=Raymond |last=Buckland |pages=17, 18, 53 |year=1986 |isbn=0-87542-050-8 |oclc=14167961}}&lt;/ref&gt; but this belief is not universal, as many Wiccans believe in the reincarnation of the soul through different species. However, a popular saying amongst Wiccans is that &quot;once a witch, always a witch&quot;, indicating a belief that Wiccans are the reincarnations of previous witches.&lt;ref name=&quot;Valiente reincarnation&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=An ABC of Witchcraft Past and Present |publisher=Hale |location= |first=Doreen |last=Valiente |pages=Introduction |year=1973 |isbn=0-919345-77-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Typically, Wiccans who believe in reincarnation believe that the soul rests between lives in the [[Otherworld]] or [[The Summerland|Summerland]], known in Gardner's writings as the &quot;ecstasy of the Goddess&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hutton&quot;&gt;{{cite book | first=Ronald | last=Hutton | authorlink=Ronald Hutton | title=Triumph of the Moon: A History of Modern Pagan Withcraft| publisher = Oxford University Press| year=1999 }} Page 392&lt;/ref&gt; Many Wiccans believe in the ability to contact the spirits of the dead who reside in the Otherworld through [[Mediumship|spirit mediums]] and [[ouija boards]], particularly on the Sabbat of [[Samhain]], though some disagree with this practice, such as the High Priest [[Alex Sanders (Wiccan)|Alex Sanders]], who stated that &quot;they are dead; leave them in peace.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Farrar on Sanders&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=What Witches Do |publisher= |location= |first=Stewart |last=Farrar |pages=88  |year= |isbn=0-919345-17-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; This belief was likely influenced by [[Spiritualism]], which was very popular at the time of Wicca's emergence, and with which Gardner and other early Wiccans such as Buckland and Sanders had some experience.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Hutton |first=Ronald |authorlink=Ronald Hutton |year=1999 |title=Triumph of the Moon |pages=392 |isbn=0-9555237-5-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite some belief therein, Wicca does not place an emphasis on the afterlife, focusing instead on the current one; as the historian [[Ronald Hutton]] remarked, &quot;the instinctual position of most [Wiccans], therefore, seems to be that if one makes the most of the present life, in all respects, then the next life is more or less certainly going to benefit from the process, and so one may as well concentrate on the present&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hutton&quot;&gt;{{cite book | first=Ronald | last=Hutton | authorlink=Ronald Hutton | title=Triumph of the Moon: A History of Modern Pagan Withcraft| publisher = Oxford University Press| year=1999 }} Page 393&lt;/ref&gt;

===Magic===
Many Wiccans believe in [[Magic (paranormal)|magic]], a force they see as being capable of manipulation through the practice of [[witchcraft]] or [[Magic (paranormal)|sorcery]]. Some spell it &quot;magick&quot;, a variation coined by the influential occultist [[Aleister Crowley]], though this spelling is more commonly associated with Crowley's religion of [[Thelema]] than with Wicca. Indeed, many Wiccans agree with the definition of magic offered by [[ceremonial magic]]ians,&lt;ref name=&quot;Valiente on Magic&quot;&gt;{{cite book |url= |title=An ABC of Witchcraft Past and Present |publisher=Hale |location= |first=Doreen |last=Valiente |pages=231  |year=1973 |isbn= 0-919345-77-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; such as Aleister Crowley, who declared that magic was &quot;the science and art of causing change to occur in conformity with will&quot;, whilst another prominent ceremonial magician, [[MacGregor Mathers]] stated that it was &quot;the science of the control of the secret forces of nature&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Valiente on Magic&quot; /&gt; Many Wiccans believe magic to be a law of nature, as yet misunderstood or disregarded by contemporary science,&lt;ref name=&quot;Valiente on Magic&quot; /&gt; and as such they do not view it as being [[supernatural]], but being a part of the &quot;super powers that reside in the natural&quot; according to [[Leo Martello]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Adler158-159&quot;&gt;{{cite book | first=Margot | last=Adler | authorlink=Margot Adler | title=Drawing Down the Moon: Witches, Druids, Goddess-worshippers and Other Pagans in America Today | publisher = Penguin| year=2006 | isbn=0-14-019536-X }} Page 158-159&lt;/ref&gt; Some Wiccans believe that magic is simply making full use of the five senses that achieve surprising results,&lt;ref name=&quot;Adler158-159&quot;/&gt; whilst other Wiccans do not claim to know how magic works, merely believing that it does because they have observed it to be so.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hutton&quot;&gt;{{cite book | first=Ronald | last=Hutton | authorlink=Ronald Hutton | title=The Triumph of the Moon: A History of Modern Pagan Witchcraft| publisher = Oxford University Press| year=1999 | isbn=0-19-820744-1 }} Page 394-395&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box|width=246px|align=left|quote=&quot;The point [of magic in Witchcraft] is to make the &quot;bendable&quot; world bend to your will... Unless you possess a rock-firm faith in your own powers and in the operability of your spell, you will not achieve the burning intensity of will and imagination which is requisite to make the magic work.&quot;|source=[[Paul Huson]] (1970)&lt;ref&gt;Huson, Paul (1970). ''Mastering Witchcraft''. Page 27. Putnam.&lt;/ref&gt;
 }}
Wiccans cast [[spellcasting|spells]] or ''workings'' during ritual practices, often held inside a [[sacred circle]], in an attempt to bring about real changes in the physical world (these rituals are further explained in the &quot;Ritual practices&quot; section below). Common Wiccan spells include those used for [[spiritual healing|healing]], for protection, fertility, or to banish negative influences.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wiccan spells&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Wicca Bible |publisher=Godsfield |location= |first=Ann-Marie |last=Gallagher |pages=250 to 265 |year=2005 |isbn=1-4027-3008-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many early Wiccans, such as [[Alex Sanders (Wiccan)|Alex Sanders]], [[Sybil Leek]] and [[Doreen Valiente]], referred to their own magic as &quot;[[magic (paranormal)|white magic]]&quot;, which contrasted with &quot;[[black magic]]&quot;, which they associated with [[evil]] and [[Satanism]]. Sanders also used the similar terminology of &quot;[[left hand path]]&quot; to describe malevolent magic, and &quot;[[right hand path]]&quot; to describe magic performed with good intentions;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hutton&quot;&gt;{{cite book | first=Alex | last=Sanders | authorlink=Alex Sanders (Wiccan) | title=The Alex Sanders Lectures| publisher = Magickal Childe| year=1984 | isbn=0-939708-05-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; terminology that had originated with the occultist [[Madame Blavatsky]] in the 19th century. Some modern Wiccans however have stopped using the white-black magic and left-right hand path dichotomies, arguing for instance that the colour [[black]] should not necessarily have any associations with evil.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Wicca Bible |publisher=Godsfield |location= |first=Ann-Marie |last=Gallagher |pages=321  |year=2005 |isbn=1-4027-3008-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The scholars of religion, [[Rodney Stark]] and [[William Sims Bainbridge|William Bainbridge]], claimed, in 1985, that Wicca had &quot;reacted to [[secularisation]] by a headlong plunge back into magic&quot; and that it was a reactionary religion which would soon die out. This view was heavily criticised in 1999 by the historian [[Ronald Hutton]], who claimed that the evidence displayed the very opposite, that &quot;a large number [of Wiccans] were in jobs at the cutting edge [of scientific culture], such as computer technology.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hutton&quot; /&gt;

===Morality===
{{Main|Wiccan morality}}
{{Quote box|width=246px|align=right|quote=&quot;Bide the Wiccan laws ye must, in perfect love and perfect trust...
Mind the Threefold Law ye should - three times bad and three times good...
Eight words the Wiccan Rede fulfill - an it harm none, do what ye will.&quot;|source=[[Lady Gwen Thompson]]&lt;ref&gt;Mathiesin, Robert; Theitic (2005). ''The Rede of the Wiccae''. Providence, Rhode Island: Olympian Press. Page 60-61,&lt;/ref&gt;
 }}

There exists no [[dogma]]tic [[moral]] or [[ethics|ethical code]] followed universally by Wiccans of all traditions, however a majority follow a code known as the [[Wiccan Rede]], which states &quot;an it harm none, do what ye will&quot; (a variation of the Thelemic abjuration put forward by [[Aleister Crowley]]:&quot;Do what thou wilt shall be the whole of the Law; Love is the Law, Love under Will&quot;). This is usually interpreted as a declaration of the freedom to act, along with the necessity of taking responsibility for what follows from one's actions and minimising harm to oneself and others.&lt;ref name=&quot;ExegesisRede&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://www.draknet.com/proteus/rede.htm |title=Exegesis on the ''Rede'' |journal=[[Harvest (Neopagan magazine)|Harvest]] |first=Judy |last=Harrow |volume=5 |issue=3 |month=[[Oimelc]] |year=1985 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5QgCzLc0I |archivedate=2007-07-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another common element of Wiccan morality is the [[Rule of Three (Wicca)|Law of Threefold Return]] which holds that whatever benevolent or malevolent actions a person performs will return to that person with triple force, or with equal force on each of the three levels of body, mind and spirit,&lt;ref name=&quot;Lembke3fold&quot;&gt;Lembke, Karl (2002) [http://web.archive.org/web/20050508032805/http://www.witchvox.com/va/dt_va.html?a=usca&amp;c=words&amp;id=3801 ''The Threefold Law''].&lt;/ref&gt; similar to the eastern idea of [[karma]]. The Wiccan Rede was introduced into Wicca by Gerald Gardner and formalised publicly by [[Doreen Valiente]], one of his High Priestesses.  The Threefold Law was an interpretation of Wiccan ideas and ritual, made by [[Monique Wilson]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Adams|first=Luthaneal|title=The Book of Mirrors|year=2011|publisher=Capall Bann|location=UK|isbn=1-86163-325-4|pages=218|url=http://www.amazon.co.uk/Book-Mirrors-Luthaneal-Adams/dp/186163336X/ref=pd_rhf_gw_p_t_1}}&lt;/ref&gt;  and further popularised by [[Raymond Buckland]], in his books on Wicca.

Many Wiccans also seek to cultivate a set of eight virtues mentioned in [[Doreen Valiente]]'s ''[[Charge of the Goddess]]'',&lt;ref name=&quot;EightSabbats&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Eight Sabbats for Witches |first=Janet |last=Farrar |authorlink=Janet Farrar |coauthors=and [[Stewart Farrar]] |publisher=Robert Hale Publishing |location=London |month=May |year=1992 |origyear=1981 |isbn=0-7090-4778-9 |oclc=26673966}}&lt;/ref&gt; these being mirth, reverence, honour, humility, strength, beauty, power and compassion. In Valiente's poem, they are ordered in pairs of complementary opposites, reflecting a [[dualism]] that is common throughout Wiccan philosophy. Some lineaged Wiccans also observe a set of  [[Wiccan Laws]], commonly called the ''Craft Laws'' or ''Ardanes'', 30 of which exist in the Gardnerian tradition and 161 of which are in the Alexandrian tradition. Valiente, one of Gardner's original High Priestesses, argued that the first thirty of these rules were most likely invented by Gerald Gardner himself in mock-archaic language as the by-product of inner conflict within his Bricket Wood coven - &lt;ref name=&quot;RebirthofWitchcraft&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Rebirth of Witchcraft |first=Doreen |last=Valiente |authorlink=Doreen Valiente |publisher=Robert Hale Publishing |location=London |year=1989 |pages=70–71 |isbn=0-7090-3715-5 |oclc=59694320}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TriumphoftheMoon&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Triumph of the Moon: A History of Modern Pagan Witchcraft |first=Ronald |last=Hutton |authorlink=Ronald Hutton |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=New York City |date=2005-05-24 |origyear=1999 |isbn=0-19-820744-1 |oclc=41452625}}&lt;/ref&gt; the others were later additions made by [[Alex Sanders (Wiccan)|Alex Sanders]] during the 1960s.

Although Gerald Gardner initially demonstrated an aversion to [[Homosexuality and Wicca|homosexuality]], claiming that it brought down &quot;the curse of the goddess&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;WitchcraftToday2&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Gardner |first=Gerald B |authorlink=Gerald Gardner (Wiccan) |title=Witchcraft Today |publisher=Rider and Company |location=London |year=1954 |pages=69, 75 |oclc=1059746 |isbn=0-8065-2593-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; it is now generally accepted in all traditions of Wicca, with certain groups like the Minoan Brotherhood openly crafting their philosophy around it,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Drawing Down the Moon: Witches, Druids, Goddess-worshippers and Other Pagans in America Today|publisher=Penguin |first=Margot |last=Adler |year=2006 [1986] |pages=130–131 |isbn=0-14-019536-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; and various important figures in the Craft, such as Alex Sanders and Eddie Buczynski, being openly homosexual or [[bisexual]].

===Five elements===
[[File:Five elements and pentagram.svg|upright|thumb|right|Five Elements with Pentagram]]
Many traditions hold a belief in the five [[classical elements]], although they are seen as symbolic as representations of the [[phase (matter)|phases of matter]]. These five elements are invoked during many magical rituals, notably when consecrating a [[magic circle]]. The five elements are [[Air (classical element)|air]], [[Fire (classical element)|fire]], [[Water (classical element)|water]] and [[Earth (classical element)|earth]], plus [[Aether (classical element)|aether]] (or spirit), which unites the other four.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zell2006-42&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Creating Circles &amp; Ceremonies |url=http://books.google.com/?id=i3Iqu0h1VH0C&amp;lpg=PA84&amp;pg=PA42 |publisher=New Page Books |location=[[Franklin Lakes, New Jersey|Franklin Lakes]] |first=Oberon |last=Zell-Ravenheart |coauthors=Zell-Ravenheart, Morning Glory |year=2006 |page=42 |isbn=1-56414-864-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; Various analogies have been devised to explain the concept of the five elements; for instance, the Wiccan [[Ann-Marie Gallagher]] used that of a tree, which is composed of earth (with the soil and plant matter), water (sap and moisture), fire (through [[photosynthesis]]) and air (the creation of [[oxygen]] from [[carbon dioxide]]), all of which are believed to be united through spirit.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gallagher2005&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Wicca Bible: The Definitive Guide to Magic and the Craft |publisher=Sterling |location=New York |first=Ann-Marie |last=Gallagher |year=2005 |pages=77–78 |isbn=1-4027-3008-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box|width=246px|align=left|quote=&quot;Darksome Night and Shining Moon,&lt;br/&gt;
East and South and West and North,&lt;br/&gt;
Hearken to the Witches' Rune;&lt;br/&gt;
Hear me now, I call thee forth.&quot;|source=[[Doreen Valiente]]
 }}

Traditionally in the Gardnerian Craft, each element has been associated with a cardinal point of the compass; air with east, fire with south, water with west, earth with north and the spirit with centre.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gallagher2005&quot; /&gt; However, some Wiccans, such as [[Frederic Lamond (Wiccan)|Frederic Lamond]], have claimed that the set cardinal points are only those applicable to the geography of southern England, where Wicca evolved, and that Wiccans should determine which directions best suit each element in their region, for instance, those living on the east coast of [[North America]] should invoke water in the east and not the west because the colossal body of water, the [[Atlantic ocean]], is to their east.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lamond2004&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Fifty Years of Wicca |publisher=Green Magic |location=United Kingdom |first=Frederic R |last=Lamond |year=2004 |pages=88–89 |isbn=0-9547230-1-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other Craft groups have associated the elements with different cardinal points, for instance [[Robert Cochrane (witch)|Robert Cochrane]]'s Clan of Tubal Cain associated earth with south, fire with east, water with west and air with north,&lt;ref&gt;Valiente, Doreen (1989). The Rebirth of Witchcraft. London: Hale. Page 124.&lt;/ref&gt; and each of which were controlled over by a different deity who were seen as children of the primary Horned God and Goddess. The five elements are symbolised by the five points of the [[pentagram]], the most prominently used symbol of Wicca.&lt;ref name=&quot;ABCwitchcraft&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=An ABC of Witchcraft Past and Present |first=Doreen |last=Valiente |authorlink=Doreen Valiente |publisher=Phoenix Publishing |location=[[Custer, Washington|Custer]] |year=1988 |origyear=1973 |pages=264 |isbn=0-919345-77-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Practices==
The Neopagan researcher and High Priestess [[Margot Adler]], who defined ritual as being &quot;one method of reintegrating individuals and groups into the cosmos, and to tie in the activities of daily life with their ever present, often forgotten, significance&quot; noted that rituals, celebrations and rites of passage in Wicca are not &quot;dry, formalised, repetitive experiences&quot;, but are performed with the purpose of inducing a [[religious experience]] in the participants, thereby altering their consciousness.&lt;ref name=&quot;AdleronRitual&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Drawing Down the Moon: Witches, Druids, Goddess-worshippers and Other Pagans in America |first=Margot |last=Adler |authorlink=Margot Adler  |publisher=Penguin |pages=164 |year=2005 [1979] |isbn=0-14-019536-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; She noted that many Wiccans remain sceptical about the existence of the gods, afterlife etc but remain involved in the Craft because of its ritual experiences, with one, Glenna Turner, saying that &quot;I love myth, dream, visionary art. The Craft is a place where all of these things fit together - beauty, pageantry, music, dance, song, dream.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;AdleronRitual2&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Drawing Down the Moon: Witches, Druids, Goddess-worshippers and Other Pagans in America |first=Margot |last=Adler |authorlink=Margot Adler  |publisher=Penguin |pages=172 |year=2005 [1979] |isbn=0-14-019536-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The High Priest and Craft historian [[Aidan Kelly]] claimed that the practices and experiences within Wicca were actually far more important than the beliefs, stating that &quot;it's a religion of ritual rather than theology. The ritual is first; the myth is second. And taking an attitude that the myths of the Craft are 'true history' in the way a [[Christian fundamentalism|fundamentalist]] looks at the legends of [[Book of Genesis|Genesis]] really seems crazy. It's an alien head-space.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;AdleronRitual3&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Drawing Down the Moon: Witches, Druids, Goddess-worshippers and Other Pagans in America |first=Margot |last=Adler |authorlink=Margot Adler  |publisher=Penguin |pages=173 |year=2005 [1979] |isbn=0-14-019536-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, Adler stated that &quot;ironically, considering the many pronouncements against Witchcraft as a threat to reason, the Craft is one of the few religious viewpoints totally compatible with modern science, allowing total scepticism about even its own methods, myths and rituals&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;AdleronRitual4&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Drawing Down the Moon: Witches, Druids, Goddess-worshippers and Other Pagans in America |first=Margot |last=Adler |authorlink=Margot Adler  |publisher=Penguin |pages=174 |year=2005 [1979] |isbn=0-14-019536-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ritual practices===
[[File:Athame.JPG|thumb|An [[athame]], ritual knife or dagger used in Wiccan practices.]]
{{Main|Magical tools in Wicca}}

There are many [[rituals]] within Wicca that are used when celebrating the Sabbats, worshipping the deities and working magic. Often these take place on a [[full moon]], or in some cases a new moon, which is known as an [[Esbat]]. In typical rites, the coven or solitary assembles inside a ritually cast and purified [[magic circle]]. Casting the circle may involve the [[invocation]] of the &quot;Guardians&quot; of the cardinal points, alongside their respective classical elements; air, fire, water and earth. Once the circle is cast, a seasonal ritual may be performed, prayers to the God and Goddess are said, and spells are sometimes worked; these may include various forms of 'raising energy', including raising a [[cone of power]] for the purposes of sending healing or other magic to persons outside of the sacred space. These rites often include a special set of [[Magical tools in Wicca|magical tools]]. These usually include a knife called an [[athame]], a [[wand]], a [[pentacle]] and a [[chalice (cup)|chalice]], but other tools include a broomstick known as a [[Besom broom#In Wicca|besom]], a [[cauldron]], [[candle]]s, [[incense]] and a curved blade known as a [[boline]]. An altar is usually present in the circle, on which ritual tools are placed and representations of the [[God]] and the [[Goddess]] may be displayed.&lt;ref&gt;Crowley, Vivianne. ''Wicca: The Old Religion in the New Age'' (1989) London: The Aquarian Press. ISBN 0-85030-737-6&lt;/ref&gt; Before entering the circle, some traditions fast for the day, and/or ritually bathe. After a ritual has finished, the God, Goddess and Guardians are thanked, the directions are dismissed and the circle is closed.

A central aspect of Wicca (particularly in Gardnerian and Alexandrian Wicca), often sensationlised by the media  is the traditional practice of working in the nude, also known as ''[[Skyclad (Neopaganism)|skyclad]]''. This practice seemingly derives from a line in ''[[Aradia, or the Gospel of the Witches#Influence on Wicca and Stregheria|Aradia]]'', [[Charles Leland]]'s supposed record of Italian witchcraft.&lt;ref&gt;[[Charles Leland|Leland, Charles]] (1899). ''[[Aradia, or the Gospel of the Witches]]''. David Nutt. Page 7.&lt;/ref&gt; Other traditions wear robes with cords tied around the waist or even normal street clothes. In certain traditions, ritualised [[sex magic]] is performed in the form of the [[Great Rite]], whereby a High Priest and High Priestess invoke the God and Goddess to possess them before performing [[sexual intercourse]] to raise magical energy for use in spellwork. In nearly all cases it is instead performed &quot;in token&quot;, thereby merely symbolically, using the athame to symbolise the penis and the chalice to symbolise the womb.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Witches' Way: Principles, Rituals and Beliefs of Modern Witchcraft |publisher=Phoenix Publishing|location= |first=Janet |last=Farrar |coauthors=Farrar, Stewart |year=1984 |pages=156–174 |isbn=0-919345-71-9  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A common liturgical rite or poem used in Wicca is &quot;The Charge of the Goddess&quot;. In its modern from it is generally used by Wiccans in the rescension of [[Doreen Valiente]], who developed it from Gardner's version. Gardner's wording of the original &quot;Charge&quot; used in paraphrase many passages from Aleister Crowley's [[Liber AL]][[The Book of the Law]], (especially from Ch 1, spoken by Nuit, the Star Goddess) thus linking modern Wicca irrevocably to the revelations of [[Thelema]].

===Wheel of the Year===
[[File:Wheel of the Year.JPG|upright|thumb|right|A painted Wheel of the Year at the [[Museum of Witchcraft]], [[Boscastle]], [[Cornwall]], [[England]], displaying all eight of the Sabbats.]]

{{Main|Wheel of the Year}}

Wiccans celebrate several seasonal festivals of the year, commonly known as [[Sabbats]]. Collectively, these occasions are termed the Wheel of the Year.&lt;ref&gt;[[Janet Farrar|Farrar, Janet]] and [[Stewart Farrar|Farrar, Stewart]]. ''Eight Sabbats for Witches'' (1981) (published as Part 1 of ''A Witches' Bible'', 1996) Custer, Washington, USA: Phoenix Publishing Inc. ISBN 0-919345-92-1&lt;/ref&gt; Most Wiccans celebrate a set of eight of these Sabbats; however, other groups such as those associated with the [[Clan of Tubal Cain]] only follow four. In the rare case of the Ros an Bucca group from [[Cornwall]], only six are adhered to.&lt;ref&gt;Gary, Gemma (2008). ''Traditional Witchcraft: A Cornish Book of Ways''. Troy Books. Page 147.&lt;/ref&gt; The four Sabbats that are common to all British derived groups are the [[cross-quarter day]]s, sometimes referred to as ''Greater Sabbats''. They originated as festivals celebrated by the ancient [[Celts|Celtic]] peoples of [[Ireland]], and possibly other Celts of mainland Europe.&lt;ref&gt;Evans, Emrys (1992). ''Mythology''. Little Brown &amp; Company. ISBN 0-316-84763-1. Page 170.&lt;/ref&gt; In the Egyptologist [[Margaret Murray]]'s ''The Witch-Cult in Western Europe'' (1921) and ''The God of the Witches'' (1933), in which she dealt with what she believed to be a historical [[Witch-cult hypothesis|Witch-Cult]], she stated that these four festivals had survived Christianisation and had been celebrated in the pagan Witchcraft religion. Subsequently, when Wicca was first developing in the 1930s through to the 1960s, many of the early groups, such as [[Robert Cochrane (witch)|Robert Cochrane]]'s Clan of Tubal Cain and [[Gerald Gardner (Wiccan)|Gerald Gardner]]'s [[Bricket Wood coven]] adopted the commemoration of these four Sabbats as described by Murray. Gardner himself made use of the English names of these holidays, stating that &quot;the four great Sabbats are Candlemass{{sic}}, May Eve, Lammas, and Halloween; the equinoxes and solstices are celebrated also.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Meaning of Witchcraft |last=Gardner |first=Gerald B |authorlink=Gerald Gardner (Wiccan) |publisher=Red Wheel |page=10 |year=2004 |origyear=1959 |isbn=0-939708-02-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The other four festivals commemorated by many Wiccans are known as ''Lesser Sabbats'', and comprise of the [[solstice]]s and the [[equinox]]es, and were only adopted in 1958 by members of the Bricket Wood coven,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Lamond |first=Frederic |authorlink=Frederic Lamond (Wiccan) |title=Fifty Years of Wicca |year=2004 |location=Sutton Mallet, England |publisher=Green Magic |isbn=0-9547230-1-5 |pages=16–17}}&lt;/ref&gt; before subsequently being adopted by other followers of the Gardnerian tradition, and eventually other traditions like [[Alexandrian Wicca]] and the [[Dianic Wicca|Dianic]] tradition. The names of these holidays that are commonly used today are often taken from [[Germanic paganism|Germanic pagan]] and [[Celtic polytheism|Celtic polytheistic]] holidays. However, the festivals are not reconstructive in nature nor do they often resemble their historical counterparts, instead exhibiting a form of [[universalism]]. Ritual observations may display cultural influence from the holidays from which they take their name as well as influence from other unrelated cultures.&lt;ref&gt;Crowley, Vivianne. ''Wicca: The Old Religion in the New Age'' (1989) London: The Aquarian Press. ISBN 0-85030-737-6 p.23&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 90%; width: 100%&quot;
!Sabbat
!Northern Hemisphere
!Southern Hemisphere
!Historical Origins
!Associations
|-
|[[Samhain]], aka [[Halloween]]
|31 October
|30 April, or 1 May
|[[Celtic polytheism|Celtic paganism]] (''see also'' [[Celts]])
|Death and the ancestors.
|-
|[[Yuletide]]
|21 or 22 December
|21 June
|[[Germanic paganism]]
|[[Winter Solstice]] and the rebirth of the [[sun]].
|-
|[[Imbolc]], aka [[Candlemas]]
|1 or 2 February
|1 August
|[[Celtic polytheism|Celtic paganism]] (''see also'' [[Celts]])
|First signs of [[spring (season)|spring]].
|-
|[[Ostara]]
|21 or 22 March
|21 or 22 September
|[[Germanic paganism]]
|[[Spring Equinox]] and the beginning of [[spring (season)|spring]].
|-
|[[Beltaine]], aka [[May Eve]] or [[May Day]]
|30 April or 1 May
|1 November
|[[Celtic polytheism|Celtic paganism]] (''see also'' [[Celts]])
|The full flowering of [[spring (season)|spring]]. [[Fairy|Fairy folk]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Wicca Bible: The Definitive Guide to Magic and the Craft |publisher=Godsfield |location=London |first=Anne-Marie |last=Gallagher |year=2005 |page=67 |isbn=9781841812502}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|[[Litha]]
|21 or 22 June
|21 December
|Possibly Neolithic
|[[Summer Solstice]].
|-
|[[Lughnasadh]], aka [[Lammas]]
|1 or 2 August
|1 February
|[[Celtic polytheism|Celtic paganism]] (''see also'' [[Celts]])
|The harvest of grain.
|-
|[[Mabon ap Modron|Mabon]], aka [[Modron]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Wicca Bible: The Definitive Guide to Magic and the Craft |publisher=Godsfield |location=London |first=Anne-Marie |last=Gallagher |year=2005 |page=72 |isbn=9781841812502}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|21 or 22 September
|21 March
|No historical pagan equivalent.
|[[Autumn Equinox]]. The harvest of fruit.
|}

=== Rites of passage ===
[[File:Falguiere Diana p1070131.jpg|thumb|left|100px|Bust of Diana wearing a moon crown]]
Various [[rites of passage]] can be found within Wicca. Perhaps the most significant of these is an [[initiation]] ritual, through which somebody joins the Craft and becomes a Wiccan. In [[British Traditional Wicca]]n (BTW) traditions, there is a line of initiatory descent that goes back to [[Gerald Gardner (Wiccan)|Gerald Gardner]], and from him is said to go back to the [[New Forest coven]]; however, the existence of this coven remains unproven.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Simpson |first1=Jacqueline |year=2005 |title=Witching Culture: Folklore and Neo-Paganism in America |journal=Folklore |volume=116}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gardner himself claimed that there was a traditional length of &quot;a year and a day&quot; between when a person began studying the Craft and when they were initiated, although he frequently broke this rule with initiates. In BTW, initiation only accepts someone into the first degree. To proceed to the second degree, an initiate has to go through another ceremony, in which they name and describe the uses of [[Magical tools in Wicca|the ritual tools and implements]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Farrars initiation&quot;&gt;{{cite book | first=Farrar| last=Stewart | authorlink=Stewart Farrar | title=The Witches' Way| publisher = | year= | isbn=0-919345-71-9}}Chapter II - Second Degree Initiation&lt;/ref&gt; It is also at this ceremony that they are given their [[craft name]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Farrars initiation&quot; /&gt; By holding the rank of second degree, a BTW is considered capable of initiating others into the Craft, or founding their own semi-autonomous covens.&lt;ref name=&quot;Farrars initiation&quot; /&gt; The third degree is the highest in BTW, and it involves the participation of the [[Great Rite]], either actual or symbolically, and in some cases ritual [[flagellation]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Farrars initiation2&quot;&gt;{{cite book | first=Farrar| last=Stewart | authorlink=Stewart Farrar | title=The Witches' Way| publisher = | year= | isbn=0-919345-71-9}}Chapter III - Third Degree Initiation&lt;/ref&gt; which is a rite often dispensed with due to its sado-masochistic overtones. By holding this rank, an initiate is considered capable of forming covens that are entirely autonomous of their parent coven.&lt;ref name=&quot;Farrars initiation2&quot; /&gt;

According to new-age religious scholar [[James R. Lewis (scholar)|James R. Lewis]], in his book ''Witchcraft today: an encyclopaedia of Wiccan and neopagan traditions'', a high priestess becomes a queen when she has successfully hived off her first new coven under a new third-degree high priestess (in the orthodox Gardnerian system). She then becomes elgible to wear the &quot;moon crown&quot;. The sequence of high priestess and queens traced back to Gerald Gardner is known as a lineage, and every orthodox Gardnerian High Priestess has a set of &quot;lineage papers&quot; proving the authenticity of her status.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=FSnxlwQV0ccC&amp;pg=PA238&amp;dq=Third-Degree+High+Priestess.+She+then+becomes+eligible+to+wear+the+Moon+Crown&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=TzD1TdvfBJK-sAOlkZTQCw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Third-Degree%20High%20Priestess.%20She%20then%20becomes%20eligible%20to%20wear%20the%20Moon%20Crown&amp;f=false] Witchcraft today: an encyclopedia of Wiccan and neopagan traditions - Page 238, by James R. Lewis&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Paganavebury.jpg|thumb|A handfasting ceremony at [[Avebury]] in [[England]], which occurred during [[Beltane]] in 2005]]

This three-tier degree system following initiation is largely unique to BTW, and traditions heavily based upon it. The [[Cochrane's Craft|Cochranian tradition]], which is not BTW, but based upon the teachings of [[Roy Bowers|Robert Cochrane]], does not have the three degrees of initiation, merely having the stages of novice and initiate.

Some solitary Wiccans also perform self-initiation rituals, to dedicate themselves to becoming a Wiccan. The first of these to be published was in [[Paul Huson]]'s ''[[Mastering Witchcraft]]'' (1970), and unusually involved recitation of the [[Lord's Prayer]] backwards as a symbol of defiance against the historical [[Witch Hunt]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Mastering Witchcraft: A Practical Guide for Witches, Warlocks and Covens |publisher=Putnum |location=New York |first=Paul |last=Huson |year=1970 |pages=22–23 |oclc=79263 |isbn=0-595-42006-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; Subsequent, more overtly pagan self-initiation rituals have since been published in books designed for solitary Wiccans by authors like [[Doreen Valiente]], [[Scott Cunningham]] and [[Silver RavenWolf]].

[[Handfasting]] is another celebration held by Wiccans, and is the commonly used term for their weddings. Some Wiccans observe the practice of a trial marriage for a year and a day, which some traditions hold should be contracted on the Sabbat of Lughnasadh, as this was the traditional time for trial, &quot;[[Telltown]] marriages&quot; among the Irish. A common marriage vow in Wicca is &quot;for as long as love lasts&quot; instead of the traditional Christian &quot;till death do us part&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Gallagher, Anne-Marie. (2005). ''The Wicca Bible: The Definitive Guide to Magic and the Craft''. London: Godsfield Press. Page 370.&lt;/ref&gt; The first ever known Wiccan wedding ceremony took part in 1960 amongst the [[Bricket Wood coven]], between [[Frederic Lamond (Wiccan)|Frederic Lamond]] and his first wife, Gillian.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Triumph of the Moon: A History of Modern Pagan Witchcraft |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford, NY |first=Ronald |last=Hutton |year=1999 |page=325 |isbn=0-19-820744-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Infants in Wiccan families may be involved in a ritual called a [[Wiccaning]], which is analogous to a [[Infant baptism|Christening]]. The purpose of this is to present the infant to the God and Goddess for protection. Despite this, in accordance with the importance put on free will in Wicca, the child is not necessarily expected or required to adhere to Wicca or other forms of paganism should they not wish to do so when they get older.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}}

=== Book of Shadows ===
{{Main|Book of Shadows}}
In Wicca, there is no set sacred text such as the Christian [[Bible]], Jewish [[Tanakh]] or Islamic [[Qur'an]], although there are certain scriptures and texts that various traditions hold to be important and influence their beliefs and practices. Gerald Gardner used a book containing many different texts in his covens, known as the [[Book of Shadows]], which he would frequently add to and adapt. In his Book of Shadows, there are texts taken from various sources, including [[Charles Godfrey Leland]]'s ''[[Aradia, or the Gospel of the Witches]]'' (1899) and the works of 19th–20th century [[occultism|occultist]] [[Aleister Crowley]], whom Gardner knew personally. Also in the Book are examples of poetry largely composed by Gardner and his High Priestess [[Doreen Valiente]], the most notable of which is the ''[[Charge of the Goddess]]''.

{{Quote box|width=246px|align=left|quote=&quot;The Book of Shadows is not a Bible or Quran. It is a personal cookbook of spells that have worked for the owner. I am giving you mine to copy to get you started: as you gain experience discard those spells that don’t work for you and substitute those that you have thought of yourselves.&quot;|source=[[Gerald Gardner (Wiccan)|Gerald Gardner]] to his followers.&lt;ref&gt;Lamond, Frederic (2004). ''Fifty Years of Wicca''. Page 14. Green Magic.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Similar in use to the [[grimoires]] of [[Magician (paranormal)|ceremonial magicians]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Crowley1989&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Wicca: The Old Religion in the New Age |publisher=Aquarian Press |location=London |first=Vivianne |last=Crowley |year=1989 |pages=14–15 |isbn=0-85030-737-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Book contained instructions for how to perform rituals and spells, as well as religious poetry and chants like ''[[Eko Eko Azarak]]'' to use in those rituals. Gardner's original intention was that every copy of the Book would be different, because a student would copy from their initiators, but changing things which they felt to be personally ineffective, however amongst many Gardnerian Witches today, particularly in the [[United States]], all copies of the Book are kept identical to the version that the High Priestess [[Monique Wilson]] copied from Gardner, with nothing being altered. The Book of Shadows was originally meant to be kept a secret from non-initiates into BTW, but parts of the Book have been published by authors including [[Charles Cardell]], Lady Sheba, [[Janet Farrar]] and [[Stewart Farrar]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Farrar1996&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=A Witches' Bible |publisher=Phoenix Publishing |location=Custer, Washington |author=Farrar, Janet |coauthors=[[Stewart Farrar|Farrar, Stewart]] |year=1996 |isbn=0-919345-92-1 |authorlink=Janet Farrar}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;witch-bos-2004&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Witchcraft and the Book of Shadows |publisher=I-H-O Books |location=Thame |first=Gerald |last=Gardner |authorlink=Gerald Gardner (Wiccan) |editor=Naylor, A R (ed.) |year=2004 |isbn=1-872189-52-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Today, adherents of many non-BTW traditions have also adopted the concept of the Book of Shadows, with many solitaries also keeping their own versions, sometimes including material taken from the published Gardnerian Book of Shadows. In other traditions however, practices are never written down, meaning that there is no need for a Book of Shadows.

In certain ''Traditional Witchcraft'' traditions, different forms of literature are used, for instance in the [[1734 tradition]], the published articles of [[Robert Cochrane (witch)|Robert Cochrane]] along with letters he wrote to [[Joseph Bearwalker Wilson|Joseph Wilson]], [[Robert Graves]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.the-cauldron.org.uk/robertcochraneletters.html |title=Robert Cochrane’s Letters to Robert Graves |publisher=The Cauldron |editor=Grevel Lindop |date=24 May 2010 |accessdate=8 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and others are held in high esteem&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Robert Cochrane Letters: An Insight into Modern Traditional Witchcraft |author=Cochrane, Robert  |coauthors=Michael Howard and Evan John Jones |publisher=Capall Bann Publishing |location=UK |year=2003 |isbn=1-86163-221-5 |authorlink=Robert Cochrane (witch)}}&lt;/ref&gt; whilst in the Sabbatic tradition, various grimoires are followed, such as the ''Azoetia'' of [[Andrew Chumbley]].

===Symbols===
{{No sources|section|date=November 2012}}
[[File:Triple-Goddess-Waxing-Full-Waning-Symbol.svg|thumb|Tripple Moon symbol of the [[Triple Goddess (Neopaganism)|Triple Moon Goddess]].]]
A range of [[Religious symbols|symbol]]s are used by Wiccans. The most common is the [[pentagram]], the five pointed star, as a representation of ([[Macrocosm and microcosm|microcosmic]]) [[wikt:quinary|quinaries]]. Each of its points are associated with one of the five [[classical elements]], the five human appendages, etc. Other common symbols include the [[triskelion]], [[triquetra]], [[Three hares]], and [[:File:Wiccan Triple Moon.png|Triple moon]].

==Traditions==
{{See also|List_of_Neopagan_movements#Wicca|l1=List of Wiccan organisations|Category:Wiccan traditions}}
In the 1950s through to the 1970s, when the Wiccan movement was largely confined to lineaged groups such as [[Gardnerian Wicca]], a &quot;tradition&quot; usually implied the transfer of a lineage by initiation. However, with the rise of more and more such groups, often being founded by those with no previous initiatory lineage, the term came to be a synonym for a [[religious denomination]] within Wicca. There are many such traditions&lt;ref name=&quot;BeaufortIndex&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://beaufort.bravepages.com/ |title=Beaufort House Index of English Traditional Witchcraft |work=Beaufort House Association |date=1999-01-15 |accessdate=2007-04-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DiffTypesCraft&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hexarchive.com/wicca/witchcraft.htm |title=Different types of Witchcraft |work=Hex Archive |accessdate=2007-04-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; and there are also many [[solitary practitioner]]s who do not align themselves with any particular lineage, working alone. There are also covens that have formed but who do not follow any particular tradition, instead choosing their influences and practices eclectically.

Those traditions which trace a line of initiatory descent back to Gerald Gardner include [[Gardnerian Wicca]], [[Alexandrian Wicca]] and the [[Algard]] tradition; because of their joint history, they are often referred to as [[British Traditional Wicca]], particularly in [[North America]]. Other traditions trace their origins to different figures, even if their beliefs and practices have been influenced to a greater or lesser extent by Gardner. These include [[Cochrane's Craft]] and the [[1734 tradition]], both of which trace their origins to [[Robert Cochrane (witch)|Robert Cochrane]]; [[Feri]], which traces itself back to [[Victor Anderson (poet)|Victor Anderson]] and [[Gwydion Pendderwen]]; and [[Dianic Wicca]], whose followers often trace their influences back to [[Zsuzsanna Budapest]]. Some of these groups prefer to refer to themselves as ''Witches'', thereby distinguishing themselves from the BTW traditions, who more typically use the term ''Wiccan'' (see [[Wicca#Etymology|Etymology]]).

Many traditions, including those of British Traditional Wicca, require formal [[initiation]] within an established [[coven]] for membership of their respective traditions. In this manner, all BTW's can trace a direct line of descent all the way back to Gardner. Other traditions, however, do not hold this to be necessary.

===Covens===
Lineaged Wicca is organised into [[coven]]s of initiated priests and priestesses. Covens are autonomous, and are generally headed by a High Priest and a High Priestess working in partnership, being a couple who have each been through their first, second and third degrees of initiation. Occasionally the leaders of a coven are only second-degree initiates, in which case they come under the rule of the parent coven. Initiation and training of new priesthood is most often performed within a coven environment, but this is not a necessity, and a few initiated Wiccans are unaffiliated with any coven.&lt;ref name=&quot;CompleteBookByRayBucks&quot; /&gt;

A commonly quoted Wiccan tradition holds that the ideal number of members for a coven is [[13 (number)|thirteen]], though this is not held as a hard-and-fast rule.&lt;ref name=&quot;CompleteBookByRayBucks&quot; /&gt; Indeed, many U.S. covens are far smaller, though the membership may be augmented by unaffiliated Wiccans at &quot;open&quot; rituals. When covens grow beyond their ideal number of members, they often split (or &quot;hive&quot;) into multiple covens, yet remain connected as a group. A grouping of multiple covens is known as a grove in many traditions.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}}

Initiation into a coven is traditionally preceded by a waiting period of at least a year and a day. A course of study may be set during this period. In some covens a &quot;dedication&quot; ceremony may be performed during this period, some time before the initiation proper, allowing the person to attend certain rituals on a probationary basis. Some solitary Wiccans also choose to study for a year and a day before their self-dedication to the religion.

=== Eclectic Wicca ===
While the origins of modern Wiccan practice lie in coven activity and the careful handing on of practices to a small number of initiates, since the 1970s a widening public appetite made this unsustainable. From about that time larger, more informal, often publicly advertised camps and workshops began to take place and it has been argued &lt;ref&gt;Howard, Michael (2009). Modern Wicca. Woodbury, Minnesota: Llewellyn. Page 299-301&lt;/ref&gt; that this more informal but more accessible method of passing on the tradition is responsible for the rise of eclectic Wicca. Eclectic Wiccans are more often than not solitary practitioners. Some of these solitaries do, however, attend gatherings and other community events, but reserve their spiritual practices (Sabbats, Esbats, spell-casting, [[worship]], magical work, etc.) for when they are alone. Eclectic Wicca is the most popular variety of Wicca in America&lt;ref&gt;Smith, Diane (2005). ''Wicca and Witchcraft for Dummies''. Wiley Publishing. Pg. 125.&lt;/ref&gt; and eclectic Wiccans now significantly outnumber lineaged Wiccans; their beliefs and practices tend to be much more varied.&lt;ref name=&quot;NWCFAQ&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.newwiccanchurch.org/articles/btwfaq.htm |title=British Traditional Wicca F.A.Q. |publisher=New Wiccan Church International |location=Sacramento, CA |accessdate=2009-07-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Eclecticism|Eclectic]] Wiccans do not follow a single tradition exclusively, and each create their own [[syncretic]] spiritual path by adopting, reclaiming, and reinventing the beliefs and rituals of a variety of religious traditions connected to Wicca, paganism or neo-Paganism. An eclectic can be described as free of tradition, even while eclecticism is described as a tradition of Wicca.  An eclectic might also be a follower of a particular religious or philosophical path, and yet develop individual ideas and ritual practices based on diverse sources. An eclectic approach to Wicca may draw from a diverse range of ancient and modern beliefs or practices, for example: [[ancient Egypt]]ian, [[ancient Greece|Greek]], [[Asian people|Asian]], [[Hebrew]], [[Saxon]], [[Anglo-Saxon]], [[Polynesian mythology|Polynesian]] or [[Celtic polytheism|Celtic]].&lt;ref&gt;Hutton, Ronald (1993) ''The Pagan Religions of the Ancient British Isles: Their Nature and Legacy''. ISBN 0-631-18946-7&lt;/ref&gt;  Eclectic Wicca is a positive, peaceful, [[earth-centred religion]], with a core ideology informed by those values and beliefs which are common to many Wiccan, pagan, [[polytheistic]],&lt;ref&gt;Weinstein, Marion (2003) ''Earth Magic: a book of shadows for positive witches'' New Page Books ISBN 1-56414-638-3&lt;/ref&gt; [[Shamanism|shamanic]], [[Hawaiian Religion|Hawaiian]],&lt;ref&gt;Cunningham, Scott (1995) - ''Hawaiian Magic and Spirituality'' (ISBN 1-56718-199-6)&lt;/ref&gt; or Polynesian religious traditions.  Eclecticism may also reflect theories derived from psychology and philosophy, for example, [[self-actualization]], [[Jungian archetypes]]&lt;ref&gt;Cunningham, Scott (1988) - ''Wicca: A Guide for the Solitary Practitioner'' (ISBN 0-87542-118-0)&lt;/ref&gt; and [[karma]].

==History==
{{Main|History of Wicca}}

===Origins and early development, 1921–1959===
In the 1920s and 30s, the Egyptologist [[Margaret Murray|Dr Margaret Murray]] published several books detailing her theories that [[Witch trials in Early Modern Europe|those persecuted as witches during the Early Modern period in Europe]] were not, as the persecutors had claimed, followers of [[Satanism]], but adherents of a surviving pre-Christian [[paganism|pagan]] religion - the [[Witch-cult hypothesis|Witch-Cult]]. Despite now being discredited by further historical research, her theories were widely accepted and supported at the time.

It was during the 1930s that the first evidence appears for the practice of a pagan Witchcraft religion&lt;ref name=&quot;WiccanRoots&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Wiccan Roots: Gerald Gardner and the Modern Witchcraft Revival |first=Philip |last=Heselton |authorlink=Philip Heselton |publisher=Capall Bann Pub. |location=Freshfields, Chieveley, [[Berkshire]] |month=November |year=2001 |isbn=1-86163-110-3 |oclc=46955899}} See also [[Nevill Drury]]. &quot;Why Does Aleister Crowley Still Matter?&quot; Richard Metzger, ed. ''Book of Lies: The Disinformation Guide to Magick and the Occult.'' Disinformation Books, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; (what would be recognisable now as Wicca) in England. It seems that several groups around the country, in such places as [[Norfolk]],&lt;ref&gt;Bourne, Lois (1998). ''Dancing With Witches''. Hale. Page 51.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cheshire]]&lt;ref&gt;Heselton, Philip (2003). ''Gerald Gardner and the Cauldron of Inspiration''. Capall Bann. Page 254.&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[New Forest]] had set themselves up as continuing in the tradition of Murray's Witch-Cult, albeit with influences coming from disparate sources such as [[ceremonial magic]], [[folk magic]], [[Freemasonry]], [[Theosophy]], [[Romanticism]], [[Neo-druidry|Druidry]], [[classical mythology]] and Asian religions.

The Witchcraft religion became more prominent beginning in 1951, with the repeal of the [[Witchcraft_Act#Witchcraft_Act_1735|Witchcraft Act of 1735]], after which several figures, such as [[Charles Cardell]], [[Cecil Williamson]] and most notably [[Gerald Gardner (Wiccan)|Gerald Gardner]], began propagating their own versions of the Craft. Gardner claimed to have been initiated into the [[New Forest coven]] in 1939, before forming his own tradition, later termed [[Gardnerian Wicca|Gardnerianism]], which he spread through the formation of groups like the [[Bricket Wood coven]]. His tradition, aided by the help of his High Priestess [[Doreen Valiente]] and the publication of his books ''[[Witchcraft Today]]'' (1954) and ''[[The Meaning of Witchcraft]]'' (1959), soon became the dominant form in the country, and spread to other parts of the [[British Isles]].

===Adaptation and spread, 1960–present===
Following Gardner's death in 1964, the Craft continued to grow unabated despite sensationalism and negative portrayals in British tabloids, with new traditions being propagated by figures like [[Robert Cochrane (witch)|Robert Cochrane]], [[Sybil Leek]] and most importantly [[Alex Sanders (Wiccan)|Alex Sanders]], whose [[Alexandrian Wicca]], which was predominantly based upon Gardnerian Wicca, albeit with an emphasis placed on [[ceremonial magic]], spread quickly and gained much media attention. Around this time, the term &quot;Wicca&quot; began to be commonly adopted over &quot;Witchcraft&quot; and the faith was exported to countries like [[Australia]] and the [[United States]].

It was in the United States and in Australia that new, home-grown traditions, sometimes based upon earlier, regional folk-magical traditions and often mixed with the basic structure of Gardnerian Wicca, began to develop, including [[Victor Anderson (poet)|Victor Anderson]]'s [[Feri]], [[Joseph Bearwalker Wilson|Joseph Wilson's]] [[1734 tradition]], [[Aidan Kelly]]'s [[New Reformed Orthodox Order of the Golden Dawn]] and eventually [[Zsuzsanna Budapest]]'s [[Dianic Wicca]], each of which emphasised different aspects of the faith.&lt;ref name=&quot;NewPagans&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The New Pagans |first=Hans |last=Holzer |authorlink=Hans Holzer |publisher=Doubleday |location=Garden City, NY |year=1972 |oclc=281240}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was also around this time that books teaching people how to become Witches themselves without formal initiation or training began to emerge, among them [[Paul Huson]]'s ''[[Mastering Witchcraft]]'' (1970) and ''Lady Sheba's Book of Shadows'' (1971). Similar books continued to be published throughout the 1980s and 1990s, fuelled by the writing of such authors as [[Doreen Valiente]], [[Janet Farrar]], [[Stewart Farrar]] and [[Scott Cunningham]], who popularised the idea of self-initiation into the Craft.

In the 1990s, amid ever-rising numbers of self-initiates, the popular media began to explore &quot;witchcraft&quot; in fictional films like ''[[The Craft (film)|The Craft]]'' and television series like ''[[Charmed]]'', introducing numbers of young people to the idea of religious witchcraft. This growing demographic was soon catered to through the [[Internet]] and by authors like [[Silver Ravenwolf]], much to the criticism of traditional Wiccan groups and individuals. In response to the way that Wicca was increasingly portrayed as trendy, eclectic, and influenced by the [[New Age movement]], many Witches turned to the pre-Gardnerian origins of the Craft, and to the traditions of his rivals like Cardell and Cochrane, describing themselves as following &quot;Traditional Witchcraft&quot;. Prominent groups within this Traditional Witchcraft revival included [[Andrew Chumbley]]'s Cultus Sabbati and the Cornish Ros an Bucca coven.

===Etymology===
{{Main|Wicca (etymology)}}

The term &quot;Wicca&quot; first achieved widespread acceptance when referring to the religion in the 1960s and 70s. Prior to that, the term &quot;Witchcraft&quot; had been more widely used. Whilst being based upon the [[Old English]] word ''wicca'', which referred solely to male sorcerers, the actual individual who coined the capitalised term &quot;Wicca&quot; is unknown, though it has been speculated that it was [[Charles Cardell]], who certainly used the term &quot;Wiccen&quot; during the 1950s.

===Demographics===
The actual number of Wiccans worldwide is unknown, and it has been noted that it is more difficult to establish the numbers of members of Neopagan faiths than many other religions due to their disorganised structure.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.neopagan.net/HowManyPagans.html |title=How Many “Pagans” Are There? |work=Neopagan.net |first=Isaac |last=Bonewits |year=2005 |accessdate=7 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, [[Adherents.com]], an independent website which specialises in collecting estimates of world religions, cites over thirty sources with estimates of numbers of Wiccans (principally from the USA and UK). From this, they developed a median estimate of 800,000 members.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.adherents.com/Na/i_w.html |title=Statistical summary pages: W |work=Adherents.com |accessdate=7 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States population alone, there have been many attempts at finding a figure, with the 2001 American Religious Identification Survey estimating that at least 134,000 adults identified themselves as Wiccans, compared to 8,000 in 1990.&lt;ref name=&quot;ARIS&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/16/us/16wiccan.html |title=Wiccans Keep the Faith With a Religion Under Wraps |work=The New York Times |first=Neela |last=Banerjee |date=16 May 2007 |accessdate=7 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wiccans have also made up significant proportions of various groups within that country; for instance, Wicca is the largest non-Christian faith practised in the [[United States Air Force]], with 1,434 airmen identifying themselves as such.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.airforcetimes.com/news/2010/01/airforce_religion_011610w/ |title=Respect healthy for different faiths |work=Air Force Times |first=Erik |last=Holmes |date=17 January 2010 |accessdate=20 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box|width=300px|align=left|quote=&quot;[The average Wiccan is] a man in his forties, or a woman in her thirties, [[Caucasian race|Caucasian]], reasonably well educated, not earning much but probably not too concerned about material things, someone that demographers would call [[lower middle class]].&quot;|source=[[Leo Ruickbie]] (2004)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Witchcraft Out of the Shadows |publisher=Hale |first=Leo |last=Ruickbie |year=2004 |page=177 |isbn=0-7090-7567-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In the United Kingdom, census figures do not allow an accurate breakdown of traditions within the Pagan heading, as a campaign by the [[Pagan Federation]] before the [[United Kingdom Census 2001|2001 Census]] encouraged Wiccans, Heathens, Druids and others all to use the same write-in term 'Pagan' in order to maximise the numbers reported. {{clear}}

==Acceptance of Wiccans==
{{Main|Religious discrimination against Neopagans}}
[[File:Baphosimb.gif|thumb|The use of the inverted pentagram by the [[Church of Satan]] has contributed to the misidentification of Wiccans as [[satanism|Satanists]].]]
Wicca emerged in a predominantly [[Christianity|Christian]] country, and from its inception suffered opposition from certain Christian groups and from the popular tabloids like the ''[[News of the World]]''. Some Christians still believe that Wicca is a form of [[Satanism]], despite important differences between these religions,&lt;ref name=&quot;Davis2003&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=New Religious Movements and Religious Liberty in America |url=http://books.google.com/?id=up5fnY7Wp1wC&amp;pg=PA75 |publisher=[[Baylor University Press]] |location=[[Waco, Texas|Waco]] |author=Davis, Derek; Hankins, Barry |edition=2nd |year=2003 |pages=75 |isbn=0-918954-92-4 |oclc=52895492 |quote=Much to the chagrin of practitioners of Wicca, there has been confusion in the minds of many about their religion, which is often linked with Satanism, although there are important differences.}}&lt;/ref&gt; such as the lack of a [[Satan]]-like figure in Wiccan theology. Due to negative connotations associated with witchcraft, many Wiccans continue the traditional practice of secrecy, concealing their faith for fear of persecution. Revealing oneself as Wiccan to family, friends or colleagues is often termed &quot;coming out of the broom-closet&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;slate031204&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.slate.com/id/2090966/ |title=Witch Way |work=Slate.com |author='Bewitched' |date=2003-12-04 |accessdate=2008-05-16 |quote=Believe me, coming out of the &quot;broom closet&quot; is a one-way trip.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a similar way, some people have accused Wicca of being anti-Christian, a claim disputed by Wiccans such as [[Doreen Valiente]], who stated that whilst she knew many Wiccans who admired [[Jesus]], &quot;witches have little respect for the doctrines of the churches, which they regard as a lot of man-made dogma&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Valienteand Christ&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=An ABC of Witchcraft Past and Present |url= |publisher=Hale |location= |author=Valiente, Doreen |edition= |year=1973 |pages=Introduction |isbn=0-919345-77-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United States, a number of legal decisions have improved and validated the status of Wiccans, especially ''[[Dettmer v. Landon]]'' in 1985. However, Wiccans have encountered hostility from some politicians and Christian organisations,&lt;ref name=&quot;SatanicArmy&quot;&gt;{{cite press release |url=http://web.archive.org/web/20020617210538/http://www.freecongress.org/press/releases/990609.htm |title='Satanic' Army Unworthy of Representing United States |publisher=Free Congress Foundation |date=1999-06-09 |accessdate=2007-07-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RISwiccan&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://www.trincoll.edu/depts/csrpl/RINVol2No2/wicca.htm  |title=Something Wiccan This Way Comes |journal=Religion in the News |first=Mark |last=Silk |month=Summer |year=1999 |volume=2 |issue=2 |issn=1525-7207 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070524174633/http://www.trincoll.edu/depts/csrpl/RINVol2No2/wicca.htm |archivedate = 2007-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BarrProject&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.lawstreet.com/journal/art991101wiccan.html  |title=Barr's Witch Project: Lawmaker Wants to Ban Witches from the Military |work=LawStreet Journal |date=1999-11-01 |accessdate=2007-07-11 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20000229034145/http://www.lawstreet.com/journal/art991101wiccan.html |archivedate = 2000-02-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; including former president of the United States [[George W. Bush]], who stated that he did not believe Wicca to be a religion.&lt;ref name=&quot;George W. Bush Justifies Off-The-Cuff Bigotry&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.positiveatheism.org/writ/bushwicca.htm |title=George W. Bush Justifies Off-The-Cuff Bigotry |work=Positive Atheism Magazine |date=1999-06-01 |accessdate=2008-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Debates over the origin of Wicca==

According to the history of Wicca given by Gerald Gardner, Wicca is [[Witch-cult hypothesis|the survival of a theoretical European witch-cult]] that was persecuted during the [[witch trial]]s. Theories of an organised pan-European witch-cult, as well as mass trials thereof, have been largely discredited, but it is still common for Wiccans to claim solidarity with witch trial victims.&lt;ref name=&quot;WitchcraftInside&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Witchcraft From The Inside: Origins of the Fastest Growing Religious Movement in America |first=Raymond |last=Buckland |authorlink=Raymond Buckland |publisher=[[Llewellyn Publications]] |location=St. Paul, MN |date=1 September 2002 |origyear=1971 |edition=3rd |isbn=1-56718-101-5 |oclc=31781774}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The notion of the survival of Wiccan traditions and rituals from ancient sources is contested by most recent researchers, who suggest that Wicca is a 20th century creation which combines elements of freemasonry and 19th century occultism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/print/2001/01/the-scholars-and-the-goddess/5910/ |title=The Scholars and the Goddess |journal=The Atlantic Monthly |first=Charlotte |last=Allen |month=January |year=2001 |issue=287 |oclc=202832236}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, historians such as [[Ronald Hutton]] have noted that Wicca not only predates the modern New Age movement but also differs markedly in its general philosophy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hutton1999&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Triumph of the Moon: A History of Modern Pagan Witchcraft |publisher=Oxford University Press |first=Ronald |last=Hutton |year=1999 |isbn=0-19-820744-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In his 1999 book ''The Triumph of the Moon'', Ronald Hutton researched the Wiccan claim that ancient pagan customs have survived into modern times after being Christianised in medieval times as folk practices. Hutton found that most of the folk customs which are claimed to have pagan roots (such as the Maypole dance) actually date from the Middle Ages. He concluded that the idea that medieval revels were pagan in origin is a legacy of the Protestant Reformation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hutton1999&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Goddess Unmasked |publisher=Spence |location=Dallas |first=Philip G |last=Davis |year=1998 |isbn=0-9653208-9-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Modern scholarly investigations have concluded that Witch trials were substantially fewer than claimed by Gardner, and seldom at the behest of religious authorities. For example, in the book ''Witches and Neighbors'', Robin Briggs (1996) examines the history of witchcraft in medieval Europe and refutes the widely-told story that large numbers of independent women were burned at the stake by vindictive Christian ecclesiastics for the crime of practising naturalistic healing or neopagan religion. Most scholars estimate that a total of 40,000 people were executed as witches during the entire medieval period, and that church authorities participated reluctantly in this process, which was largely fuelled by the political turmoil of the [[Reformation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://draeconin.com/database/witchhunt.htm |title=Recent Developments in the Study of The Great European Witch Hunt |journal=The Pomegranate |first=Jenny |last=Gibbons |month=August |year=1998 |issue=5 |ISSN=1528-0268}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Witchesandneighbors&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Witches and Neighbors |publisher=Penguin |first=Robin |last=Briggs |year=1998 |isbn=0-14-014438-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{clear}}

==References and footnotes==
{{Reflist|colwidth=35em}}

==Further reading==
;Significant historical works
:* {{cite book |title=[[Witchcraft Today]] |publisher=Ryder |first=Gerald |last=Gardner |authorlink=Gerald Gardner (Wiccan) |year=1954}}
:* {{cite book |title=[[The Meaning of Witchcraft]] |publisher=Aquarian |first=Gerald |last=Gardner |year=1959}}

;Practices and beliefs
:* {{cite book |title=Eight Sabbats for Witches |publisher=R. Hale |first1=Stewart |last1=Farrar |author1-link=Stewart Farrar |first2=Janet |last2=Farrar |author2-link=Janet Farrar |year=1981}}
:* {{cite book |title=Coming to the Edge of the Circle: A Wiccan Initiation Ritual |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |first=Nikki |last=Bado-Fralick |year=2005}}

;History of Wicca
:* {{cite book |title=Crafting the Art of Magic: A History of Modern Witchcraft, 1939-1964 |first=Aidan A |last=Kelly |authorlink=Aidan A. Kelly |publisher=Llewellyn |year=1991 |isbn=0-87542-370-1}}
:* {{cite book |title=The Triumph of the Moon: A History of Modern Pagan Witchcraft |publisher=Oxford University Press |first=Ronald |last=Hutton |authorlink=Ronald Hutton |year=1999}}
:* {{cite book |title=Wiccan Roots: Gerald Gardner and the Modern Witchcraft Revival |first=Philip |last=Heselton |authorlink=Philip Heselton |publisher=Capall Bann |year=2000 |isbn=1-86163-110-3}}
:* {{cite book |title=Gerald Gardner and the Witchcraft Revival: The Significance of His Life and Works to the Story of Modern Witchcraft|first=Philip |last=Heselton |publisher=[[I-H-O Books]] |year=2001 |isbn=1-872189-16-4}}
:* {{cite book |title=Gerald Gardner and the Cauldron of Inspiration: An Investigation into the Sources of Gardnerian Witchcraft|first=Philip |last=Heselton |publisher=Capall Bann |year=2003 |isbn=1-86163-164-2}}

;Wicca in different countries
:* {{cite book |title=A Community of Witches: Contemporary Neo-Paganism and Witchcraft in the United States |publisher=[[University of South Carolina Press]] |first=Helen A |last=Berger |year=1999}}
:* {{cite book |title=Her Hidden Children: The Rise of Wicca and Paganism in America |publisher=AltaMira Press |first=Chas S |last=Clifton |year=2006}}
:* {{cite book |title=Witching Culture: Folklore and Neo-Paganism in America |publisher=[[University of Pennsylvania Press]] |first=Sabina |last=Magliocco |authorlink=Sabina Magliocco |year=2004}}
:* {{cite book |title=Witchcraft and Paganism in Australia |publisher=Melbourne University Press |first=Lynne |last=Hume |year=1997}}

;General
:* {{cite book |title=The Witch Book: The Encyclopedia of Witchcraft, Wicca, and Neo-paganism |publisher=Visible Ink Press |first=Raymond |last=Buckland |authorlink=Raymond Buckland |year=2002}}
:* {{cite book |title=Witchcraft Today: An Encyclopedia of Wiccan and Neopagan Traditions |publisher=ABC-CLIO |first=James R |last=Lewis |year=1999}}
:* {{cite book |title=The Encyclopedia of Modern Witchcraft and Neo-Paganism |publisher=[[Kensington Publishing|Kensington]] |editor1-first=Shelly |editor1-last=Rabinovitch |editor2-first=James R |editor2-last=Lewis |year=2002}}
:* {{cite book |title=Magical Religion and Modern Witchcraft |editor1-first=James R |editor1-last=Lewis |publisher=[[State University of New York Press]] |year=1996}}
:* {{cite book |title=Persuasions of the Witch's Craft: Ritual Magic in Contemporary England |publisher=Picador |first=T M |last=Luhrmann |year=1994}}

==External links==
&lt;!--======================== {{No more links}} ============================
    | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. Wikipedia  |
    | is not a collection of links nor should it be used for advertising. |
    |                                                                     |
    |           Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.         |
    | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.  |
    |                                                                     |
    | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or   |
    | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
    | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)   |
    | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.         |
    ======================= {{No more links}} =============================--&gt;
{{Portal|Wicca}}
* {{Wiktionary-inline|wicca|Wicca}}
* {{Commons category-inline|Wicca}}
* [http://www.witchvox.org/ Witchvox.org] - Neopagan news and networking
* [http://www.cog.org/ Covenant of the Goddess (U.S.)]
* [http://www.paganfed.org/ Pagan Federation (UK)], [http://www.ca.paganfederation.org/ (Canada)]
* [http://www.equinoxjournals.com/POM/index ''The Pomegranate''] - The International Journal of Pagan Studies

{{WiccaandWitchcraft}}
{{Paganism topics (contemporary)}}

{{Good article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2011}}

[[Category:Wicca| ]]
[[Category:Neopagan traditions]]
[[Category:Witchcraft]]
[[Category:Paganism]]

{{Link FA|pt}}

[[af:Wicca]]
[[als:Wicca]]
[[ar:ويكا]]
[[an:Wicca]]
[[bg:Уика]]
[[br:Wicca]]
[[ca:Wicca]]
[[cs:Wicca]]
[[cy:Wica]]
[[da:Wicca]]
[[de:Wicca]]
[[et:Wicca]]
[[es:Wicca]]
[[eo:Viko]]
[[fa:ویکا]]
[[fr:Wicca]]
[[gd:Wicca]]
[[gl:Wicca]]
[[ko:위카]]
[[hr:Wicca]]
[[ia:Wicca]]
[[is:Wicca]]
[[it:Wicca]]
[[he:ויקה]]
[[la:Wicca]]
[[lt:Wicca]]
[[hu:Wicca]]
[[mk:Вика]]
[[ml:വിക്ക]]
[[nl:Wicca]]
[[ja:ウィッカ]]
[[no:Wicca]]
[[nn:Wicca]]
[[pl:Wicca]]
[[pt:Wicca]]
[[ro:Wicca]]
[[ru:Викка]]
[[si:විකා]]
[[simple:Wicca]]
[[sk:Wicca]]
[[sr:Vika]]
[[sh:Wicca]]
[[fi:Wicca]]
[[sv:Wicca]]
[[tr:Vika]]
[[uk:Вікка]]
[[zh:威卡教]]</text>
      <sha1>a8dun0vxzf1z2b9sa2sbf9lldiv3vlk</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
