<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Witches' Sabbath</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>248497</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520624932</id>
      <parentid>520621997</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-30T18:25:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Garamond Lethe</username>
        <id>16446711</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 520621997 by [[Special:Contributions/74.128.193.152|74.128.193.152]] ([[User talk:74.128.193.152|talk]]) See [[Circumcision of Jesus]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17999">{{About|the historical and legendary Witches' Sabbath|the modern Wiccan Sabbat|Wheel of the Year||esbat|new moon|And (disambiguation){{!}}And|Saturday}}

[[File:Hexensabbat.jpg|thumb|288px|Representation of Sabbat gatherings from the chronicles of [[Johann Jakob Wick]].&lt;!--This description came from caption in German article--&gt;]]
The '''Witches' Sabbath''' or '''Sabbat''' is a meeting of those who practice [[witchcraft]] and other rites.

European records indicate cases of persons being accused or tried for taking part in Sabbat gatherings, from the [[Middle Ages]] to the 17th century or later.

== Etymology ==

The English word “sabbat” came indirectly from [[Hebrew]] (שַׁבָּת). In Hebrew it means “to cease” or “to rest”. In [[Judaism]] [[Shabbat]] is the rest day celebrated on Friday evening into Saturday. In connection with the [[Middle Ages|Medieval]] popularity of the belief that Jews [[Theistic Satanism|worship the Devil]], satanic gatherings of witches were called “sabbats” or “[[synagogues]]”.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} The latter is a Jewish places of worship, much like a church. Alternately, some Christians were accused of [[Judaizers|Judaizing]]. Christian Sabbathkeepers, who never accepted Emperor [[Constantine the Great|Constantine]]'s [[Lord's Day#Edict of Constantine|edict]] in 321 A.D., the first enforcing Christian [[Lord's Day|worship on Sunday]] rather than on Sabbath, were demonized and accused of witchcraft; hence, the accusatory nomenclature, &quot;witches' sabbath.&quot;{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

== The Sabbat in history ==
Although allusions to Sabbats were made by the Catholic [[Canon law (Catholic Church)|Canon law]] since about 905, the first book that mentions the Sabbat is, theoretically, ''[[Canon Episcopi]]'', included in [[Burchard of Worms]]'s collection in the 11th century. The ''Canon Episcopi'' alleged that &quot;[[Diana (mythology)|Diana]]'s rides,&quot; (by the name of the Roman goddess of the hunt) were false, and that these [[spirit travel]]s did not occur in reality. ''[[Errores Gazariorum]]'' later evoked the Sabbat, in 1452.

In the 13th century the accusation of participation in a Sabbat was considered very serious. Helping to publicize belief in and the threat of the Witches' Sabbath was the extensive preaching of the popular Franciscan reformer, Saint [[Bernardino of Siena]] (1380–1444), whose widely circulating sermons contain various references to the sabbath as it was then conceived and hence represent valuable early sources into the history of this phenomenon.&lt;ref&gt;See Franco Mormando, ''The Preacher's Demons: Bernardino of Siena and the Social Underworld of Early Renaissance Italy'', Chicago, University of Chicago Press, 1999, esp. pp.66-68, 75, 76, 77; see all of Chapter Two of Mormando's book for an extensive account of Bernardino's vehement preaching against witches and witchcraft, which helped pave the way for the explosion of the later &quot;Witch Hunts.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;   Some allusions to meetings of witches with demons are also made in the Inquistors' manual of witch-hunting, the ''[[Malleus Maleficarum]]'' (1486). Nevertheless, it was during the Renaissance when Sabbat folklore was most popular, more books on them were published, and more people lost their lives when accused of participating. ''Commentarius de Maleficius'' (1622), by [[Peter Binsfeld]], cites accusation of participation in Sabbats as a proof of guiltiness in an accusation for the practice of witchcraft.

A Sabbat is also shown in Nathaniel Hawthorne's short story &quot;Young Goodman Brown&quot; where Brown finds a meeting of Devil worshipers from Salem village.

It is important to note, however, that in spite of the number of times that authorities retold stories of the sabbat, modern researchers have been unable to find any corroboration that any such event ever occurred.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Hendrix|first=Scott E.|title=The Pursuit of Witches and the Sexual Discourse of the Sabbat|journal=Anthropology|year=2011|month=December|volume=11|issue=2|pages=41–58}}&lt;/ref&gt; The historian Scott E. Hendrix presents a two-fold explanation for why these stories were so commonly told in spite of the fact that sabbats likely never actually occurred in his study &quot;The Pursuit of Witches and the Sexual Discourse of the Sabbat.&quot; First, belief in the existence of witches was widespread in late medieval and early-modern Europe. Many religious authorities believed there was a vast underground conspiracy of witches who were responsible for the horrific famines, plague, warfare, and problems in the Catholic Church that became endemic in the fourteenth century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Hendrix|first=Scott E.|title=The Pursuit of Witches and the Sexual Discourse of the Sabbat|journal=Anthropology|year=2011|month=December|volume=11|issue=2|pages=42–43}}&lt;/ref&gt; By blaming witches, religious authorities provided a handy scapegoat for those who might otherwise question God's goodness. Second, stories of the sabbat, with its prurient orgiastic elements, caused these stories to be told and retold. In effect, the sabbat acted as an effective 'advertising' gimmick, causing knowledge of what these authorities believed to be the very real threat of witchcraft to be spread more rapidly across the continent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Hendrix|first=Scott E.|title=The Pursuit of Witches and the Sexual Discourse of the Sabbat|journal=Anthropology|year=2011|month=December|volume=11|issue=2|pages=44–58}}&lt;/ref&gt; Unfortunately that also meant that stories of the sabbat promoted the hunting, prosecution, and execution of supposed witches.

== What has been said about the Sabbat by the Catholic Church ==
=== Ritual elements ===
The ''[[Compendium Maleficarum]]'' (1608), by [[Francesco Maria Guazzo]], aka Guaccio, Guaccius is a book published by an Italian priest with some illustrations of what he imagined could be a Sabbat, and gives a description of it; a brief summary can be cited as an example: &quot;the attendants go riding flying goats, trample the cross, are made to be re-baptised in the name of the Devil, give their clothes to him, kiss the Devil's behind, and dance back to back forming a round&quot;.

According to [[Hans Baldung Grien]] (ca 1484-1545) and [[De Lancre|Pierre de Rostegny]], aka De Lancre (1553–1631) human flesh was eaten during Sabbats, preferably children, and also human bones stewed in a special way. It was also said by some authors{{By whom|date=July 2007}} that salt, bread and oil were prohibited because the Devil hated them; while other testimonies told about delicious dishes. Other descriptions add that human fat, especially of non-baptised children, was used to make an unguent that enabled the witches to fly; such an ointment is referred to in &quot;[[Young Goodman Brown]]&quot; by [[Nathaniel Hawthorne]] in a conversation between Goody Cloyse and the dark stranger.  It was also believed{{Who|date=July 2007}} that witches could fly by themselves, ride a broom, or be carried by demons to the place of the meeting.

The most common belief on which authors{{Who|date=July 2007}} agreed is that Satan was present at the Sabbat, often as a [[goat]] or [[satyr]], and many agreed that more demons were present. Another belief said that sometimes a person could offer his/her own body to be possessed by some [[demon]] serving as a [[Mediumship|medium]] (see [[demon possession]]). It was believed{{By whom|date=July 2007}} that the Sabbat commenced at [[midnight]] and ended at [[dawn]], beginning with a [[procession]], continuing with a [[banquet]], then a [[Black Mass]], and culminating with an [[orgy]] in which uninhibited sexual intercourse with demons in male or female form was practiced. Consumption of [[hallucinogen]]s and sometimes [[alcohol]] was often reported.

=== Location ===
According to folklore, the Sabbat was most often celebrated in isolated places, preferably forests or mountains. Some famous places where these events were said to have been celebrated are [[Briany]], [[Carignano]], [[Benevento]], [[Puy-de-Dôme]] (France), [[Blocksberg]], [[Melibäus]], the [[Black Forest]], (Germany), the [[Łysa Góra|Bald Mount]] ([[Poland]]), [[Vaspaku]], [[Zabern]], [[Kopastatö]] ([[Hungary]]), [[San Colombano al Lambro]] (Italy) and more, but it was also said that [[Stonehenge]] (England) was a place for Sabbats. In the [[Basque Country (historical territory)|Basque country]] the Sabbat (there called [[Akelarre (witchcraft)|Akelarre]], or 'field of the goat') was said to be celebrated in isolated fields.

=== Dates ===
There is no agreement among authors concerning the dates on which the Sabbats were to be celebrated. Some hypothosized they would take place during the night of the Sunday before the time the Christian mass was celebrated, some authors disagreed telling that Satan was less powerful on holy days.

Some commonly mentioned dates were February 1 (to some February 2), May 1 (Great Sabbat, [[Walpurgis Night]]), August 1 (lammas), November 1 ([[Halloween]], commencing on October 30's eve), [[Easter]], and [[Christmas]]. Other less frequently mentioned dates were [[Good Friday]], January 1 (day of Jesus' circumcision), June 23 ([[John the Apostle|St. John]]'s Day), December 21 ([[Thomas (Apostle)|St. Thomas]]), and [[Corpus Christi (feast)|Corpus Christi]]. and others.

The modern Sabbats that many Wiccans and Neo-Pagans now follow are: Imbolc (February 2), Ostara (Spring Equinox), Beltane (May 1), Litha (Summer Solstice), Lammas (August 1), Mabon (Autumn Equinox), Samhain (October 31) and Yule (Winter Solstice). (See also [[Wheel of the Year]])

According to the testimonies of ''benandanti'' and similar European groups (see below), common dates for gatherings are during the weeks of the [[Ember days]], during the [[twelve days of Christmas]] or at [[Pentecost]].

=== Depictions of witches' sabbaths in various art forms ===
[[Image:Faust's_Dream,_by_Luis_Ricardo_Falero.jpg|thumb|250px|Faust's Vision by Luis Ricardo Falero]]
As referenced earlier, Hawthorne seems to have been describing a witches' sabbath and the surrounding activity in his short story, &quot;Young Goodman Brown.&quot;  Musically, the supposed ritual has been used as inspiration for such works as [[Night on Bald Mountain]] by [[Modest Mussorgsky]] and the fifth movement of [[Hector Berlioz|Hector Berlioz's]] [[Symphonie Fantastique]].

Depictions in painting include the following:
* ''[[Witches' Sabbath (Goya, 1798)|Witches' Sabbath]]'' by [[Francisco Goya]] (1798) [[Museum of Lázaro Galdiano]]
* [[Witches' Sabbath (The Great He-Goat)|''Witches' Sabbath'' or ''The Great He-Goat'']] by [[Francisco Goya]] (1823) [[Museo del Prado]]
* ''[[:File:Witches Flight Goya.jpg|Witches' Flight]]'' by Francisco Goya (1798) Museo del Prado
* ''[[:File:LuisRicardsFalero-AFairyUnderStarry1Skies-Large.jpg|Muse of the Night (Witches' Sabbath)]]'' by [[Luis Ricardo Falero]] (1880)
* ''Witches' Sabbath in Roman Ruins'' by [[Jacob van Swanenburgh]] (1608)
* ''The Vision of [[Faust]]'' by [[Luis Ricardo Falero]] (1878)
* ''Witches' Sabbath'' by [[Francken|Frans Francken]] (1606)

==Disputed accuracy of the accounts==
The descriptions of Sabbats were made or published by priests, jurists and judges who never took part in these gatherings, or were transcribed during the process of the [[witchcraft trials]].  That these testimonies reflect actual events is for most of the accounts considered doubtful. Norman Cohn argued that they were determined largely by the expectations of the interrogators and free association on the part of the accused, and reflect only popular imagination of the times, influenced by [[ignorance]], [[fear]], and religious intolerance towards minority groups.&lt;ref&gt;[[Norman Cohn|Cohn, Norman]] (1977) ''Europe's Inner Demons''&lt;/ref&gt;
Some of the existing accounts of the Sabbat were given when the person recounting them was being [[torture]]d.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Marnef |first=Guido |authorlink= |editor-last=Schäfer |editor-first=Peter |editor-link=Peter Schäfer |editor2-last=Kippenberg |editor2-first=Hans Gerhard |contribution=Between Religion and Magic: An Analysis of Witchcraft Trials in the Spanish Netherlands, Seventeenth Century |title=Envisioning Magic: A Princeton Seminar and Symposium |publisher=Brill |year=1997 |location= |pages=235-54 |url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=sgRcr0ScIO0C&amp;pg=PA251&amp;lpg=PA251&amp;dq=%22from+the+confessions%22+torture+sabbath&amp;source=web&amp;ots=4qrR1lhZcn&amp;sig=hQmnVG4y_DRyBtrqTPdhRBlDtUo&amp;hl=en#PPA252,M1 |isbn =90-04-10777-0}} p. 252&lt;/ref&gt; and so motivated to agree with suggestions put to them.

Many of the diabolical elements of the Witches' Sabbath stereotype, such as the eating of babies, poisoning of wells, [[host desecration|desecration of hosts]] or [[osculum infame|kissing of the devil's anus]], were also made about heretical Christian sects, [[leper]]s, [[Muslim]]s, and [[Judaism|Jew]]s&lt;ref name=GinzburgEcstasies/&gt; (see [[blood libel]]). The term is the same as the normal English word &quot;[[Biblical Sabbath|Sabbath]]&quot; (itself a transliteration of Hebrew &quot;[[Shabbat]]&quot;, the seventh day, on which the [[God|Creator]] rested after creation of the world), referring to the witches' equivalent to the [[Christian Sabbath|Christian day of rest]]; a more common term was &quot;synagogue&quot; or &quot;synagogue of Satan&quot;,&lt;ref name=Kieckhefer&gt;{{cite book|author=Kieckhefer, Richard|title=European Witch Trials: Their Foundations in Popular and Learned Culture, 1300&amp;#150;1500|publisher=Routledge &amp; K. Paul|year=1976}}&lt;/ref&gt; possibly reflecting anti-Jewish sentiment, although the acts attributed to witches bear little resemblance to the [[Sabbath in Christianity]] or Jewish [[Shabbat]] customs. The ''[[Errores Gazariorum]]'' (''Errors of the Cathars''), which mentions the Sabbat, while not discussing the actual behavior of the [[Cathars]], is named after them, in an attempt to link these stories to a heretical Christian group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last=Peters |first=Edward| contribution=Sorceror and Witch| editor-last=Jolly |editor-first=Karen Louise 
|editor2-last=Raudvere |editor2-first=Catharina et al. |url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=GzitzV4fSWgC&amp;pg=PA233&amp;lpg=PA233&amp;dq=errores+gazariorum+cathars&amp;source=web&amp;ots=MkcqEoAwxs&amp;sig=kpZ2TSZjUXELGn2sEI_TJxughwM&amp;hl=en|title=Witchcraft and Magic in Europe: The Middle Ages | isbn=978-0-485-89003-7 | year=2001 |pages=233-37 | publisher=Continuum International Publishing Group}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Christian missionaries' attitude to African cults was not much different in principle to their attitude to the Witches' Sabbath in Europe; some accounts viewed them as a kind of Witches' Sabbath, but they are not.&lt;ref&gt;[[Robert E. Park|Park, Robert E.]], &quot;[http://www.jstor.org/pss/2769036 Review of ''Life in a Haitian Valley''],&quot; ''American Journal of Sociology'' Vol. 43, No. 2 (Sep., 1937), pp. 346-348.&lt;/ref&gt; Some African communities believe in witchcraft, but as in the European witch trials, people they believe to be &quot;witches&quot; are condemned rather than embraced.

===Possible connections to real groups===
{{main|Witch-cult hypothesis}}
Other historians, including [[Carlo Ginzburg]], [[Éva Pócs]], Bengt Ankarloo and Gustav Henningsen hold that these testimonies can give insights into the belief systems of the accused. Ginzburg famously discovered records of a group of individuals in northern Italy, calling themselves ''[[benandanti]]'', who believed that they went out of their bodies in spirit and fought amongst the clouds against evil spirits to secure prosperity for their villages, or congregated at large feasts presided over by a goddess, where she taught them magic and performed divinations.&lt;ref name=&quot;GinzburgEcstasies&quot;&gt;Ginzburg, Carlo. ''Ecstasies: Deciphering the Witches' Sabbath''.&lt;/ref&gt; Ginzburg links these beliefs with similar testimonies recorded across Europe, from the ''[[armier]]s'' of the [[Pyrenees]], from the followers of [[Signora Oriente]] in fourteenth century [[Milan]] and the followers of [[Richella]] and 'the wise Sibillia' in fifteenth century northern Italy, and much further afield, from [[Livonia]]n [[werewolf|werewolves]], [[Dalmatia]]n ''[[krsnik|kresniki]]'', [[Hungary|Hungarian]] ''[[táltos]]'', [[Romania]]n ''[[căluşari]]'' and [[Ossetians|Ossetian]] ''[[burkudzauta]]''. In many testimonies these meetings were described as out-of-body, rather than physical, occurrences.&lt;ref name=&quot;GinzburgEcstasies&quot;/&gt;

== See also ==
{{commons category|Witches' Sabbath}}
*[[Akelarre (witchcraft)|Akelarre]]
*[[Sorginak]]
*[[Witchcraft]]
*[[Witch-hunt]]

== Sources ==
*{{cite book | author=[[Michael Harner|Harner, Michael]] | title=Hallucinogens and Shamanism| year=1973}} - See the chapter &quot;The Role of Hallucinogenic Plants in European Witchcraft&quot;
*{{cite book | author=[[Jules Michelet|Michelet, Jules]] | title=[[Satanism and Witchcraft]]: The Classic Study of Medieval Superstition | year=1862 | isbn=978-0-8065-0059-1}} The first modern attempt to outline the details of the medieval Witches' Sabbath.
*{{cite book |author=[[Montague Summers|Summers, Montague]] | title=The History of Witchcraft |year=1926}} Chapter IV, ''The Sabbat'' has detailed description of Witches' Sabbath, with complete citations of sources.
*{{cite encyclopedia | title=Sabbat | encyclopedia=The Encyclopedia of Witchcraft and Demonology | editor-last=Robbins | editor-first=Rossell Hope | year=1959 | publisher=Crown | pages=414-424}}  See also the extensive topic bibliography to the primary literature on pg. 560.

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Witchcraft]]

[[br:Sabad (sorserezh)]]
[[ca:Aquelarre]]
[[cs:Čarodějnický sabat]]
[[da:Heksesabbat]]
[[de:Hexensabbat]]
[[es:Aquelarre]]
[[eo:Sabatorgio]]
[[eu:Akelarre]]
[[fa:بزم جادوان]]
[[fr:Sabbat (sorcellerie)]]
[[hr:Crni sabat]]
[[it:Sabba]]
[[lt:Šabašai]]
[[nl:Heksensabbat]]
[[ja:サバト (魔女)]]
[[no:Heksesabbat]]
[[pl:Sabat (zlot)]]
[[pt:Sabbat]]
[[ru:Шабаш]]
[[fi:Noitasapatti]]
[[sv:Häxsabbat]]
[[uk:Шабаш]]</text>
      <sha1>h9g88ry5oyqr2mple5pu45v0rhl6hyh</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
