<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Yeshua (name)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>167083</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516881238</id>
      <parentid>514721138</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-09T20:27:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ROO BOOKAROO</username>
        <id>12696536</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Etymology */ Yehoshua, and not &quot;Yeshoshua&quot;</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27611">:''For other persons named Yeshua, or other claimed transcriptions of Jesus, see [[Yeshua (disambiguation)]]. For the person, teaching, and acts of Jesus Christ, see [[Jesus]] and [[Historical Jesus]]. For the [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] proper name, see [[Yeshu]]. See also [[Jesus in the Talmud]]''

'''Yeshua''' ({{lang|he|ישוע}}, with vowel pointing {{lang|he|יֵשׁוּעַ}} - ''yēšūă‘'' in [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]])&lt;ref&gt;[[Strong's Concordance|Strong's]] '''Yeshuwa'''&lt;/ref&gt; was a common alternative form of the name {{lang|he|יְהוֹשֻׁעַ}} (&quot;Yehoshuah&quot; - Joshua) in later books of the [[Hebrew Bible]] and among Jews of the [[Second Temple period]]. The name corresponds to the Greek spelling ''Iesous'', from which comes the English spelling [[Jesus]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | last  =Ilan
 | first =Tal
 | title =Lexicon of Jewish Names in Late Antiquity Part I: Palestine 330 BCE-200 CE (Texte und Studien zum Antiken Judentum 91)
 | publisher =J.C.B. Mohr
 | year  =2002
 | location =Tübingen, Germany
 | pages =129}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | last  =Stern
 | first =David
 | title =Jewish New Testament Commentary
 | publisher =Jewish New Testament Publications
 | year  =1992
 | location =Clarksville, Maryland
 | pages =4–5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Hebrew spelling ''Yeshua'' (ישוע) appears in some later books of the Hebrew Bible. Once for [[Joshua]] the son of Nun, and 28 times for [[Joshua the High Priest]] and ([[KJV]] &quot;Jeshua&quot;) and other priests called Jeshua - although these same priests are also given the spelling Joshua in 11 further instances in the books of [[Book of Haggai|Haggai]] and [[Book of Zechariah|Zechariah]]. It differs from the usual Hebrew Bible spelling of [[Joshua]] (יְהוֹשֻׁעַ ''y'hoshuaʿ''), found 218 times in the Hebrew Bible, in the absence of the consonant [[he (letter)|he ה]] and placement of the semivowel [[vav (letter)|vav]] ו after, not before, the consonant [[Shin (letter)|shin ש]]. It also differs from the Hebrew spelling ''[[Yeshu]]'' (ישו) which is found in [[Ben Yehuda]]'s dictionary and used in most secular contexts in modern Hebrew to refer to [[Jesus of Nazareth]], though the Hebrew spelling ''Yeshua'' (ישוע) is generally used in [[Bible translations into Hebrew|translations of the New Testament into Hebrew]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Franz Delitzsch]] ''Hebrew New Testament,'' Matthew 1:1, BFBS 1877, [[Isaac Salkinsohn]] ''Hebrew New Testament'' Matthew 1:1, TBS 1891&lt;/ref&gt; and used by Hebrew speaking Christians in Israel. The name ''Yeshua'' is also used in Israeli Hebrew historical texts to refer to other Joshuas recorded in Greek texts such as [[Jesus ben Ananias]] and [[Jesus ben Sira]].&lt;ref&gt;Robert E. Van Voorst Jesus outside the New Testament 2000 ISBN 978-0-8028-4368-5 p124 &quot;This is likely an inference from the Talmud and other Jewish usage, where Jesus is called Yeshu, and other Jews with the same name are called by the fuller name Yehoshua, &quot;Joshua&quot;&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

In English the name ''Yeshua'' is extensively used by followers of [[Messianic Judaism]] as well as other [[Christian denominations]] who wish to use what they consider to be Jesus' Hebrew or Aramaic name.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

==Etymology==
[[Image:Yeshua hebreo.jpg|left|thumb|The Greek transliteration {{lang|el|Ἰησοῦς}} (''{{lang|el-Latn|Iēsous}}'') *jesu-os &amp;rarr; {{IPA-el|jeˈsus|}} can stand for both Classical Biblical Hebrew ''Yehoshua'' {{IPA-he|jəhoˈʃuaʕ|}} (top two) and Late Biblical Hebrew ''Yeshua'' {{IPA-he|jeˈʃuaʕ|}} (bottom). This later form developed within Hebrew (not Aramaic).&lt;ref&gt;David Talshir, 'Rabbinic Hebrew as Reflected in Personal Names', ''Scripta Hierosylamitana'' vol. 37, Magnes Press, Hebrew University in Jerusalem, 1998:374ff.&lt;/ref&gt; All three spelling variants occur in the Hebrew Bible, including when referring to the same person. During the Second Temple Period, Jews of Galilee tended to preserve the traditional spelling, keeping the &lt;ו&gt; letter for the {{IPA|[o]}} in the first syllable, even adding an additional letter for the {{IPA|[u]}} in the second syllable. However, Jews of Jerusalem tended to spell the name as they pronounced it, {{IPA|[jeˈʃuaʕ]}}, contracting the spelling to ישוע without the {{IPA|[o]}} letter. Later, Aramaic references to the Hebrew Bible adopted the contracted phonetic form of this Hebrew name as an Aramaic name.]]

{{main|Names and titles of Jesus in the New Testament}}

Yeshua in Hebrew is verbal derivative from &quot;to rescue&quot;, &quot;to deliver&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Brown Driver Briggs]] Brown-Driver-Briggs Hebrew and English Lexicon; Hendrickson Publishers 1996 ISBN 1-56563-206-0&lt;/ref&gt; Its usage among the Jews of the [[Second Temple Period]], the Biblical Aramaic/Hebrew name {{lang|he|יֵשׁוּעַ}} ''Yeshua‘'' was common: the [[Hebrew Bible]] mentions several individuals with this name - while also using their full name Joshua. This name is a feature of biblical books written in the post-Exilic period ([[Book of Ezra|Ezra]], [[Book of Nehemiah|Nehemiah]], and [[Books of Chronicles|Chronicles]]) and was found in the [[Dead Sea Scrolls]], though Haggai and Zechariah prefer the spelling Joshua. [[Strong's Concordance]] connects the name {{lang|he|יֵשׁוּעַ}} Yeshua`, in the English form Jeshua (as used in multiple instances in Ezra, Nehemiah, and 1 and 2 Chronicles), with the verb &quot;to deliver&quot; (or, &quot;to rescue&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;[[Brown Driver Briggs]] Brown-Driver-Briggs Hebrew and English Lexicon; Hendrickson Publishers 1996 ISBN 1-56563-206-0&lt;/ref&gt; It is often translated as &quot;He saves,&quot; to conform with Matthew 1:21: &quot;She will bear a Son; and you shall call His name Jesus, for He will save His people from their sins&quot; (NASB).&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The New Strong's Exhaustive Concordance of the Bible (Nashville: Thomas Nelson Publishers 1990)&lt;/ref&gt;

The name {{lang|he|יֵשׁוּעַ}} &quot;Yeshua&quot; (transliterated in the English Old Testament as Jeshua) is a late form of the Biblical Hebrew name {{lang|he|יְהוֹשֻׁעַ}} Yehoshua ([[Joshua]]), and spelled with a [[waw (letter)|waw]] in the second syllable. The Late Biblical Hebrew spellings for earlier names often contracted the theophoric element ''Yeho-'' to ''Yo-''.
Thus {{lang|he|יהוחנן}} Yehochanan contracted to {{lang|he|יוחנן}} Yochanan.&lt;ref&gt;David Talmshir, &quot;Rabbinic Hebrew as Reflected in Personal Names&quot; in ''Scripta Hierosolymitana: Publications of the Hebrew University of Jerusalem'', vol. 37 (Jerusalem: Magnes Press: Hebrew University of Jerusalem 1998)&lt;/ref&gt; However, there is no name (aside from Yehoshua`) in which Yeho- became Ye-.

The name ישוע occurs in the Hebrew of the Old Testament at verses Ezra 2:2, 2:6, 2:36, 2:40, 3:2, 3:8, 3:9, 3:10, 3:18, 4:3, 8:33; Nehemiah 3:19, 7:7, 7:11, 7:39, 7:43, 8:7, 8:17, 9:4, 9:5, 11:26, 12:1, 12:7, 12:8, 12:10, 12:24, 12:26; 1 Chronicles 24:11; and 2 Chronicles 31:15, and also in Aramaic at Ezra 5:2. In Nehemiah 8:17 this name refers to Joshua son of Nun, the successor of Moses, as leader of the Israelites.  Note that in earlier English (where adaptations of names of Biblical figures were generally based on the Latin [[Vulgate]] forms), Yeshua was generally transcribed identically to &quot;Jesus&quot; in English.  It was only when the Protestant Bible translators of ca. 1600 went back to the original languages that a distinction between Jesus and Jeshua appeared in English.

The name Yehoshua has the form of a compound of &quot;Yeho-&quot; and &quot;shua&quot;: Yeho- {{lang|he|יְהוֹ}} is another form of {{lang|he|יָהו}} ''Yahu'', a theophoric element standing for the name of God יהוח (the Tetragrammaton YHWH, sometimes transcribed into English as Yahweh or Jehovah), and {{lang|he|שׁוּעַ}} ''shua‘'' is a noun meaning &quot;a cry for help&quot;, &quot;a saving cry&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;{{lang|he|וֹשֻׁשׁוּעַ}}&quot;, Ernest Klein, ''A Comprehensive Etymological Dictionary of the Hebrew Language'' (New York: MacMillan Publishing Company 1987), where it means &quot;a cry for help&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;{{lang|he|וֹשֻׁשׁוּעַ}}&quot;, William L. Holladay, ''A Concise Hebrew and Aramaic Lexicon of the Old Testament'' (Michigan: William B. Eerdmans Publishing 1971), where it means &quot;a cry for help&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;{{lang|he|שָׁוַע}}&quot;, M. Jastrow, ''Dictionary of the Talmud'' reprinted (Jerusalem: Khorev 1990), where {{lang|he|שׁוֹשֻׁוּעַ}} is explained by the verb &quot;to cry for help&quot;,&lt;/ref&gt; that is to say, a shout given when in need of rescue. Together, the name would then literally mean, &quot;God is a saving-cry,&quot; that is to say, shout to God when in need of help.

Another explanation for the name Yehoshua is that it comes from the root {{lang|he|ישע}} yod-shin-‘ayin, meaning &quot;to deliver, save, or rescue&quot;. According to the [[Book of Numbers]] verse 13:16, the name of [[Joshua son of Nun]] was originally ''Hoshea`'' {{lang|he|הוֹשֵעַ}}, and the name &quot;Yehoshua`&quot; {{lang|he|יְהוֹשֻׁעַ}} is usually spelled the same but with a [[yodh|yod]] added at the beginning. &quot;Hoshea`&quot; certainly comes from the root {{lang|he|ישע}}, &quot;yasha&quot;, yod-shin-`ayin (in the [[Hif'il]] form the yod becomes a waw), and not from the word {{lang|he|שוע}} shua` ([[Jewish Encyclopedia]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title =Jewish Encyclopedia | publisher =[[Funk and Wagnalls]] | date =1901-19-06 | location =entry JOSHUA (JEHOSHUA) | url =http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=544&amp;letter=J&amp;search=Joshua%20bin%20Nun}}&lt;/ref&gt;) although ultimately both roots appear to be related.

In the 1st century, [[Philo of Alexandria]], in a Greek exposition, offered this understanding of Moses’s reason for the name change of the biblical hero Jehoshua/[[Joshua son of Nun]] from Hoshea [similar to hoshia` meaning &quot;He rescued&quot;] to Yehoshua in commemoration of his salvation: &quot;And Ιησους refers to salvation of the Lord&quot; [Ιησους or Iesous being the Greek form of the name] ({{lang|grc|Ἰησοῦ δὲ σωτηρία κυρίου}}) (''On the Change of Names'' 21.121).

Similarly, the [[Septuagint]] renders [[Ben Sira]] as saying (in the Greek form of the name): &quot;Ιησους the son of Naue [Yehoshua Ben Nun] who ''according to his name'' became great unto [the] salvation/deliverance of his chosen ones&quot; ({{lang|grc|Ἰησοῦς Ναυῆ .. ὃς ἐγένετο κατὰ τὸ ὄνομα αὐτοῦ μέγας ἐπὶ σωτηρίᾳ ἐκλεκτῶν αὐτοῦ}}) (Ben Sira 46:1-2). However, Ben Sira originally wrote in Hebrew in the 2nd century BC, and the only extant Hebrew manuscript for this passage has &quot;in his days&quot; ({{lang|he|בימיו}}), not &quot;according to his name&quot; (which would be {{lang|he|כשמו}} in Hebrew),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Segel
 | first = Moshe Tsvi
 | title =Sefer Ben-Sira Hash-Shalem
 | publisher =Mosad Byalik
 | year =1953
 | location =Chapter 46 verse 2
 | pages =317}}&lt;/ref&gt;
and thus does not comment on the name Yehoshua as connoting {{lang|he|יְּשׁוּעָה}} &quot;deliverance&quot;: &quot;Yehoshua Ben Nun, who was formed to be ''in his days'' a great deliverer for his chosen ones&quot; ({{lang|he|יהושע בן נון... אשר נוצר להיות בימיו תשועה גדלה לבחיריו}}). Possibly, the translators understood the phrase &quot;was formed in his days&quot; to refer to being transformed by his name change, and thus has &quot;according to his name&quot; as a paraphrastic translation, or else they were working from a different text.

The distinction between the longer ''Yehoshua'' and shorter ''Yeshua'' forms does not exist in Greek.
===Archaeological evidence===
[[Tal Ilan]]'s lexicon of [[Second Temple]] period names on inscriptions in Palestine (2002) includes  for &quot;Joshua&quot; 85 examples of Hebrew ''Yeshua,'' 15 of ''Yehoshua,'' and 48 examples of ''Iesous'' in Greek inscriptions,&quot; with only one Greek variant as ''Iesoua.''&lt;ref&gt;Buried Hope Or Risen Savior: The Search for the Jesus Tomb 2008 p81 Charles Quarles - 2008 &quot;The distinction between the longer and shorter forms does not exist in Greek. The Greek Iesous (Ineous) was used to represent both Yehoshua' and Yeshua'. There are 48 instances of Iesous (Iesous and several eccentric spellings),  &quot;&lt;/ref&gt; One ossuary of the around twenty known with the name Yeshua, Rahmani No.9, discovered by [[Ezra Sukenik]] in 1931, has &quot;Yeshu... Yeshua ben Yosef.&quot; The &quot;Yeshu...&quot; may have been scratched out.&lt;ref&gt;Photo in Witherington &amp; Schanks p59-60&lt;/ref&gt; Two [[Jewish magical papyri|Jewish magical incantation bowls]] have been discovered both bearing variant spellings of Yeshua.&lt;ref&gt;Incantation bowls in Montgomery and Moussaief/Levene 2002. See transcription in Bauckham essay in Quarles.&lt;/ref&gt;

Apart from the &quot;Yesh.. Yeshua ben Yosef&quot; ossuary, the only other known evidence for the existence of a Yeshu form prior to the material related to [[Jesus in the Talmud]], is a graffito which [[Joachim Jeremias]] identified in Bethesda in 1966, but which is now filled in.&lt;ref&gt;New Testament theology Joachim Jeremias - 1977 &quot;... 1965, 284-93: 285; a graffito which I found in the south wall of the southern pool at Bethesda, now covered in, also read [y\fw ', see my: The Rediscovery of Bethesda, New Testament Archaeology Monograph No I, Louisville, Ky., 1966, ...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Pronunciation==
Yeshua יֵשוּעַ {{IPA-he|jeˈʃuăʕ|}}. The Hebrew letter Yod י {{IPA|/j/}} is vocalized with the Hebrew vowel ''[[tsere]]'' {{IPA|/e/}} (a 'long' ''e'' like the first syllable of &quot;neighbor&quot; but not [[diphthong]]ized) rather than with a ''[[shva na|shva]]'' {{IPA|/ə/}} (as Y'shua) or ''segol'' {{IPA|/ɛ/}} (Yesh-shua). The final letter Ayin ע is {{IPAslink|ʕ}} (a rough, guttural sound not found in Greek or English), sometimes transcribed &quot; ` &quot; (''Yeshua`''). The final {{IPA|[ăʕ]}} represents the &quot;patach genuvah&quot; (&quot;furtive&quot; ''[[patach]]''), indicating that the consonant `''ayin'' is pronounced after the ''a'' vowel, and the word's stress is moved to the middle syllable (the characteristics of the furtive patach can be seen in other words, such as רוח {{IPA|[ˈruăħ]}} 'spirit').&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hebrew4christians.com/Grammar/Unit_Three/Furtive_Patach/furtive_patach.html&lt;/ref&gt;
Thus it is pronounced {{IPA-he|jeˈʃu.aʕ|}} in Modern Hebrew, approximately {{respell|ye|SHEW|ə}}.

The Hebrew name of the historical Jesus is probably pronounced 'Yeshua', although this is uncertain and depends on the reconstruction of several ancient Hebrew dialects. Talshir suggests, even though Galileans tended to keep the traditional spelling for 'Yehoshua' יהושוע with the letter Vav for {{IPA|/o/}}, they still pronounced the name similarly to the Judeans, as 'Yeshua' {{IPA|[jeˈʃuaʕ]}}, who tended to spell the name phonetically as ישוע, perhaps reducing the name thus: {{IPA|[jəhoˈʃuaʕ]}} &gt; {{IPA|[joˈʃuaʕ]}} &gt; {{IPA|[jeˈʃuaʕ]}}, with the {{IPA|/o/}} palatizing (via 'dissimilation') before the {{IPA|/ʃ/}}.&lt;ref&gt;Talshir 1998:374,376.&lt;/ref&gt;

Qimron describes the general linguistic environment of Hebrew dialects by the time of the Dead Sea Scrolls. The articulation of the {{IPA|/h/}} (along with other guttural phonemes {{IPA|/ʔ/}}, {{IPA|/ħ/}}, and {{IPA|/ʕ/}}, as well as approximants {{IPA|/j/}} and {{IPA|/w/}}) [[lenition|weakened]] significantly.&lt;ref&gt;Elisha Qimron, ''The Hebrew Of The Dead Sea Scrolls'', Scholars Press, Harvard Semitic Studies vol. 29, 1986:25.&lt;/ref&gt; Thus Hebrew pronunciations became less stable when two successive vowels were no longer separated by a consonant {{IPA|/h/}}. The speakers optionally either reduced the two vowels to a single vowel or oppositely expanded them to emphasize each vowel separately, sometimes forming a furtive glide in between, {{IPA|[w]}} or {{IPA|[j]}}.&lt;ref&gt;Qimron:26, 31-35.&lt;/ref&gt; For example, the Dead Sea Scrolls spell the Hebrew word ראוי {{IPA|/rɔˈʔui̯/}} ('seen') variously, recording both pronunciations: reduced ראו {{IPA|[ro]}} and expanded ראואי {{IPA|[rɔˈuwi]}}.&lt;ref&gt;Qimron:35.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Hebrew name 'Yehoshua' generally reduced to 'Yeshua', but an expanded 'Yehoshua' is possible, especially in Galilee whose traditional orthography possibly reflects this.

==Original name for Jesus==
The English name ''Jesus'' derives from the [[Late Latin]] name ''{{lang|la|Iesus}}'', which transliterates the [[Koine]] Greek name {{lang|grc|Ἰησοῦς}} ''{{lang|grc-Latn|Iēsoûs}}''.

In the [[Septuagint]] and other Greek-language [[Jewish]] texts, such as the writings of [[Josephus]] and [[Philo of Alexandria]], {{lang|grc|Ἰησοῦς}} ''{{lang|grc-Latn|Iēsoûs}}'' is the standard Koine Greek form used to translate both of the Hebrew names: ''Yehoshua'' and ''Yeshua''.  Greek {{lang|grc|Ἰησοῦς}} or Iēsoûs is also used to represent the name of Joshua son of Nun in the New Testament passages Acts 7:45 and Hebrews 4:8. (It was even used in the Septuagint to translate the name ''Hoshea'' in one of the three verses where this referred to Joshua the son of Nun—Deut. 32:44.)

During the second Temple period (beginning 538 BC – 70 AD), ''Yeshua'' first became a known form of the name ''Yehoshua''. All occurrences of ''Yeshua'' in the Hebrew Bible are in I [[Book of Chronicles|Chron.]] 24:11, II Chron. 31:15, [[Book of Ezra|Ezra]], and [[Book of Nehemiah|Nehemiah]] where it is transliterated into English as [[Jeshua (disambiguation)|Jeshua]]. Two of these men (Joshua the son of Nun and [[Joshua the High Priest]]) are mentioned in other books of the Hebrew Bible where they are instead called ''Yehoshua'' &lt;ref&gt;Price, James D. [http://www.direct.ca/trinity/yehoshua.html Yehoshua, Yeshua or Yeshu; Which one is the name of Jesus in Hebrew?], accessed March 6, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; (transliterated into English as Joshua).

The earlier form ''Yehoshua'' did not disappear, however, and remained in use as well. In the post-exilic books, Joshua the son of Nun is called both Yeshua bin-Nun (Nehemiah 8:17) and Yehoshua (I Chronicles 7:27). The short form ''Yeshua'' was used for [[Jesus ben Sirach]] in Hebrew fragments of the [[Wisdom of Sirach]]. (Some concern remains over whether these fragments faithfully represent the original Hebrew text or are instead a later translation back into Hebrew.&lt;ref&gt;William Chomsky, ''Hebrew: The Eternal Language'', Jewish Publication Society of America, 1957 p.140&lt;/ref&gt;) The earlier form ''Yehoshua'' saw revived usage from the [[Hasmonean]] period onwards, although the name ''Yeshua'' is still found in letters from the time of the [[Bar Kokhba Revolt]] (132-135 AD).

In the documentary ''[[The Lost Tomb of Jesus]]'', archeologist [[Amos Kloner]] stated that the name Yeshua was then a popular form of the name Yehoshua and was &quot;one of the common names in the time of the [[Second Temple]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
 | last =Mendel
 | first =Roi
 | title =Ha-&quot;chasifa&quot; shel qever Yeshu: qiddum mkhirot
 | journal =[[Yedioth Ahronoth]]
 | date =25 February 2007
 | url =http://www.ynet.co.il/articles/0,7340,L-3368783,00.html
 | accessdate = 2007-02-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
In discussing whether it was remarkable to find a tomb with the name of Jesus (the particular ossuary in question bears the inscription &quot;Yehuda bar Yeshua&quot;), he pointed out that the name had been found 71 times in burial caves from that time period.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
 | last =Pilkington
 | first =Ed
 | coauthors = Rory McCarthy
 | title =Is this really the last resting place of Jesus, Mary Magdalene - and their son?
 | journal =[[The Guardian]]
 | date =27 February 2007
 | url =http://www.guardian.co.uk/religion/Story/0,,2022252,00.html
 | accessdate = 2007-02-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Thus, both the full form ''Yehoshua'' and the abbreviated form ''Yeshua'', were in use during the Gospel period - and in relation to the same person, as in the Hebrew Bible references to Yehoshua/Yeshua son of Nun, and Yehoshua/Yeshua the high priest in the days of Ezra.

[[Clement of Alexandria]] and [[St. Cyril of Jerusalem]] considered the Greek form ''Iesous'' to be the original,{{Or|date=July 2011}} even going so far as to interpret it as a true Greek name and not simply a transliteration of Hebrew.{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}} (A similar situation is seen in the use of the true Greek name Simon as a translation of the Hebrew name Shim'on in texts such as Sirach.) Eusebius related it to the Greek root meaning &quot;to heal&quot; thus making it a variant of ''Jason'' meaning ''healer''.

However, the New Testament describes Jesus as  being a part of a Jewish milieu, reading the Hebrew Bible and debating with [[Pharisees]] over interpretations of the [[Halakha|Jewish legal tradition]]. The [[Gospel]]s record several [[Hebrew]] and [[Aramaic]] words or expressions spoken by him. Moreover, [[Eusebius]] reports that Jesus's student [[Matthew the Evangelist|Matthew]] wrote a [[gospel]] &quot;in the Hebrew language&quot;. (Note, scholars typically argue the word &quot;Hebrew&quot; in the New Testament refers to Aramaic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | title =Wycliffe Bible Dictionary
 | publisher =Hendrickson Publishers
 | year =1975
 | location =entry HEBREW LANGUAGE}}&lt;/ref&gt;)

An argument in favor of the Hebrew reduced form {{lang|he|ישוע}} ''Yeshua'', as opposed to ''Yehoshua'', is the Old [[Syriac]] Bible (c. 200 AD) and the [[Peshitta]] preserve this same spelling but using the equivalent Aramaic letters {{lang|ar|}}. ''Yeshu'' {{IPA|/jeʃuʕ/}} (Syriac does not use a 'furtive' pathach so extra {{IPA|/a/}} is not used) is still the pronunciation used in the West Syriac dialect, whereas East Syriac has rendered the pronunciation of these same letters as ''Išô‘'' {{IPA|/iʃoʔ/}}. These texts were translated from the Greek, but the name is not a simple transliteration of the Greek form because Greek did not have an &quot;sh&quot; {{IPA|[ʃ]}} sound, and substituted {{IPA|[s]}}; and likewise lacked and therefore omitted the final ''‘ayin'' sound {{IPA|[ʕ]}}. It can be argued that the [[Aramaic]] speakers who used this name had a continual connection to the Aramaic-speakers in communities founded by the [[Twelve apostles|apostles]] and other students of Jesus, thus independently preserved his historical name. Alternatively, Talshir (1998) suggests that Aramaic references to the Hebrew Bible had long used ''Yeshua'' for Hebrew names such as Yehoshua Ben Nun.&lt;ref&gt;Talshir:374-375. --- article states Yeshua p374-375? &lt;/ref&gt; So the possibility of Jesus having been ''Yehoshua'' remains.

==Syriac==
The Aramaic of the [[Peshitta]] does not distinguish between ''[[Joshua]]'' and ''[[Jesus]]'', and the Lexicon of [[William Jennings (Syriacist)|William Jennings]] gives the same form '''{{lang|syc|ܝܫܘܥ}}''' ''{{transl|syc|yēšū‘}}'' for both names.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dukhrana.com/lexicon/word.php?adr=2:9575&amp;font=Estrangelo+Edessa Jennings]&lt;/ref&gt; The Hebrew final letter [[ayin]] '''{{lang|he|ע}}''' is equivalent to final '''{{lang|syc|ܥ}}''' in [[Syriac]].

==Yeshua, Yehoshua and Yeshu in the Talmud==
In the [[Talmud]], only one reference is made to the spelling ''Yeshua'', in verbatim quotation from the Hebrew Bible regarding Jeshua son of Jozadak (elsewhere called Joshua son of Josedech). The Talmud does refer to several people named Yehoshua from before (e.g. [[Joshua ben Perachyah]]) and after Jesus (e.g. [[Joshua ben Hananiah]]). However in references to [[Jesus in the Talmud]], where the name occurs, it is rendered [[Yeshu]], which is a name reserved in Aramaic and Hebrew literature from the early medieval period until today, solely for Jesus of Nazareth, not for other Joshuas. However some scholars, such as [[Johann Maier (talmudic scholar)|Maier]] (1978) regard the two named &quot;Yeshu&quot; texts in the Talmud (Sanhedrin 43a and 107b) to be later amendments, and not original.&lt;ref&gt;J. Maier ''Jesus von Nazareth'' 1978. G. Theissen, ''Historical Jesus''. 1998. R. Voorst ''Jesus outside the New Testament'' 2000&lt;/ref&gt;
===Rabbinical commentary on the difference Yeshu/Yeshua===
''Yeshua'' was used as the name for Jesus in late additions to the [[Josippon|Yosippon]]; however, its usage here is a translation back into the Hebrew ''Yeshua'' from the Greek.

In general rabbinical sources use Yeshu, and this is the form to which some named references to [[Jesus in the Talmud]] as ''[[Yeshu]]'' occur in some manuscripts of the Babylonian Talmud, though some scholars, such as [[Johann Maier (talmudic scholar)|Maier]] (1978) have argued that the presence of the [[Yeshu (name)|name Yeshu]] in these texts is a late interpolation. Other Hebrew sources referencing [[Yeshu]] include the ''[[Toledot Yeshu]]'', [[Sefer Nestor ha-Komer]], Jacob ben Reuben's [[Milhamoth ha-Shem]], [[Sefer Nizzahon Yashan]], [[Sefer Joseph Hamekane]], the works of [[Ibn Shaprut]], [[Moses ha-Kohen de Tordesillas]], and [[Hasdai Crescas]], etc.

The [[Yeshu (name)|name Yeshu]] is unknown in archeological sources and inscriptions, except for one ossuary found in Palestine which has an inscription where someone has started to write first ''Yeshu..'' (incorrectly?) and then written ''Yeshua bar Yehosef'' beneath it.&lt;ref&gt;''Brother of Jesus'' [[Hershel Shanks]], [[Ben Witherington]] [http://books.google.com/books?id=HWjhff705FkC&amp;pg=PA60&amp;dq#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false photo of the &quot;Yeshu... Yeshua bar Yehosef&quot; ossuary and dual inscription]&lt;/ref&gt; There are 24 other ossuaries to various Yeshuas and Yehoshuas. None of the others have ''Yeshu''. All other &quot;Joshuas&quot; in the Talmud, rabbinical writings, modern Hebrew, are always ''Yeshua'' or ''Yehoshua''. There are no undisputed examples of any Aramaic or Hebrew text where Yeshu refers to anyone else than Jesus.&lt;ref&gt;Jesus outside the New Testament p124 Robert E. Van Voorst - 2000 &quot;This is likely an inference from the Talmud and other Jewish usage, where Jesus is called Yeshu, and other Jews with the same name are called by the fuller name Yehoshua, &quot;Joshua&quot; (eg, b Sanh. 107b on p. &quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of rabbinical sources comment on the reasons for the missing [[ayin]] from Yeshu, as opposed to the Hebrew Bible Yeshua and Yehoshuah. [[Leon Modena]] argues that it was Jesus himself who made his disciples remove the ayin, and that therefore they cannot now restore it. A tradition states that the shortening to Yeshu relates to the Y-SH-U of the [[yimach shemo]] &quot;may his name be obliterated.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Michael H. Cohen A Friend of All Faiths - Page 42  - 2004 &quot;In Hebrew school, one of my teachers had explained that Yeshu (Hebrew for Jesus), rather than meaning &quot;Saviour,&quot; in fact was an acronym that stood for yimach shemo ve-zichrono: &quot;may his name and memory be erased &quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Proceedings: Volume 4 Aḳademyah ha-leʼumit ha-Yiśreʼelit le-madaʻim - 1969 &quot;Perhaps the most significant of these is the passage where instead of the printed 'that certain man' we find 'Jesus the Nazarene — may his name be obliterated' (thus also in a Genizah MS, British Museum, Or. 91842). &quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Against this [[David Flusser]] suggested that the name ''Yeshu'' itself was &quot;in no way abusive,&quot; but &quot;almost certainly&quot; a Galilean dialect form of [[Yeshua]].&lt;ref&gt;New Testament theology [[Joachim Jeremias]] - 1977 &quot;... deliberate truncation made for anti-Christian motives; rather, it is 'almost certainly' (Flusser, Jesus, 13) the Galilean pronunciation of the name; the swallowing of the 'ayin was typical of the Galilean dialect (Billerbeck I 156f. &lt;/ref&gt;
==See also==
{{portal|Christianity}}
* [[Aramaic of Jesus]]
* [[Hoshea]]
* [[Josiah]]
* [[Yahshua]]
* [[Yahshuah]]
* [[Joseph (name)|Yoseph]]
* [[Joshua|Yoshua]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Yeshua}}
[[Category:Jesus]]
[[Category:Hebrew-language names]]

[[de:Jeschua]]
[[es:Yeshúa]]
[[he:ישוע]]
[[nl:Jesjoea]]
[[pt:Yeshua]]
[[zh:耶书亚 (名字)]]</text>
      <sha1>kkgaegt7996seh764e0wi87flmp77j9</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
