<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Yeshiva University</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>67240</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522419269</id>
      <parentid>522419228</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-11T02:23:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Wavelength</username>
        <id>271168</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>revising [[letter case]]—[[MOS:HEAD]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="31839">{{Use mdy dates|date=May 2012}}
{{Infobox university
|name            = Yeshiva University
|image_name      =
|motto           = תורה ומדע ([[Hebrew language|Hebrew]])&lt;br&gt; '''[[Torah Umadda]]''' (&quot;Torah and secular knowledge&quot;)
|free_label = Slogan
|free = &quot;Torah U'Madda&quot;
|established     = 1886
|type            = Private, Jewish
|calendar=  Semester
|endowment       = US$1.1258 [[1000000000 (number)|billion]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2011_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values_Final_January_17_2012.pdf |title=U.S. and Canadian Institutions Listed by Fiscal Year 2011 Endowment Market Value and Percentage Change in Endowment Market Value from FY 2010 to FY 2011|publisher=Copyright 2012 National Association of College and University Business Officers and Commonfund Institute |accessdate=March 10, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |faculty        = 4,714
|president       = [[Richard M. Joel]]
|chancellor      = [[Norman Lamm]]
|undergrad       = 3,017
|postgrad        = 3,496
|alumni          = 44,243
|city            = New York
|state           = New York
|campus          = Urban
|athletics       = [[NCAA Division III]], [[Skyline Conference (New York)|Skyline Conference]]
|nickname        = Maccabees
|website         = [http://www.yu.edu/ www.yu.edu]
}}
'''Yeshiva University''' is a [[private university]] in New York City, with six campuses in New York and one in Israel. Founded in 1886, it is a research university ranked as 45th in the US among national universities by [[U.S. News &amp; World Report]] in 2012. It also ranked as 68th in the world by The Times Higher Education in 2011&lt;ref name=&quot;timeshighereducation.co.uk&quot;&gt;[http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/world-university-rankings/2010-2011/top-200.html The Times higher Education world university ranking 2011.] Accessed December 4, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; and among 400 in world by THES—QS World University Rankings.&lt;ref name=&quot;QS-undergrad&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.topuniversities.com/institution/yeshiva-university/wur|title=Yeshiva University Profile|publisher=2010 QS Intelligence Unit|accessdate=June 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Yeshiva University’s undergraduate schools—[[Yeshiva College (Yeshiva University)|Yeshiva College]], [[Stern College for Women]], and [[Syms School of Business]] &quot;offer a unique dual curriculum inspired by [[Modern Orthodox Judaism|Modern]]-[[Centrist Orthodoxy|Centrist]]-[[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox]] [[Judaism]]'s ''[[hashkafa]]'' (philosophy) of [[Torah Umadda]]'' (&quot;Torah and secular knowledge&quot;)'' combining the finest, contemporary academic education with the timeless teachings of Torah.”&lt;ref name=missionstatement&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.yu.edu/MissionStatement/index.aspx |title=Mission Statement |publisher=Yeshiva University |accessdate=August 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Yeshiva University’s [[Albert Einstein College of Medicine]], [[Benjamin N. Cardozo School of Law]], and other graduate and professional schools promote a “dual emphasis on professional excellence and personal ethics.”&lt;ref name=missionstatement/&gt;

Yeshiva University is an independent institution chartered by New York State.{{Citation needed|date=December 2010}} It is accredited by the Commission on Higher Education of the [[Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]]&lt;ref name=&quot;MSCHE&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msche.org/institutions_view.asp?idinstitution=553|title=Yeshiva University Accredited|accessdate=July 20, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and by several professional agencies.&lt;ref name=selfpublish&gt;''This is Yeshiva University: 2007–2008''&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{Main|History of Yeshiva University}}

[[File:Zysman Hall jeh.jpg|thumb|right|David H. Zysman Hall, a [[Moorish Revival]] building on Yeshiva University's Wilf Campus, is home to the former main [[beit midrash]] ([[Torah study]] hall)]]

Yeshiva University is the oldest institution of higher learning in the United States that combines Jewish scholarship with studies in the liberal arts, sciences, medicine, law, business, social work, Jewish studies and education, and psychology.{{Citation needed|date=December 2010}}

Yeshiva University has its roots in the [[Etz Chaim Yeshiva (Manhattan)|Etz Chaim Yeshiva]] founded in 1886 on the [[Lower East Side]] of Manhattan, a [[cheder]]-style elementary school founded by Eastern European immigrants that offered study of [[Talmud]] along with some secular education, including instruction in English.{{Citation needed|date=May 2012}}

As of August 2012,&lt;ref name=&quot;AboutYU&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=About Yeshiva University |url=http://www.yu.edu/about/ |date=August 2012 |work=YU.edu |accessdate=October 16, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Yeshiva University enrolls approximately 6,400 undergraduate students, 3,500 graduate students, and 1,000 students at its affiliated high schools and [[Rabbi Isaac Elchanan Theological Seminary]]. It conferred 1,822 degrees in 2007 and offers community service projects serving New York, Jewish communities, the United States and Canada.&lt;ref name=selfpublish/&gt;

[[Richard M. Joel]] is Yeshiva University's president, while Rabbi Dr. [[Norman Lamm]] serves as chancellor.  President Joel's nomination as president was unprecedented and considered by some to be controversial, because he is the first president of YU who is not a rabbi. The university's past leaders include Dr. [[Bernard Revel]], Dr. [[Samuel Belkin]], and &quot;The Rav,&quot; Rabbi [[Joseph B. Soloveitchik]].

==Campus==

The University's main campus, Wilf Campus, is located in [[Washington Heights, Manhattan|Washington Heights]].  A 1928 plan to build a spacious [[Moorish Revival]] campus around several gardens and courtyards was cancelled by the Great Depression of 1929 after only one building had been erected.  Building continued after the Depression in modern style and by the acquisition of existing neighborhood buildings.&lt;ref name=Appelbaum&gt;{{Cite journal
  | authorlink = Diana Muir Appelbaum
  | title = Building Bust, The unbuilt synagogues of the Great Depression
  | journal = Tablet Magazine
  | date = August 20, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In the past 122 years, Yeshiva University has expanded to comprise some twenty colleges, schools, affiliates, centers, and institutions, with several affiliated hospitals and health care institutions. It has campuses and facilities in [[Manhattan]] ([[Washington Heights, Manhattan|Washington Heights]], [[Murray Hill, Manhattan|Murray Hill]], [[Greenwich Village]]), the [[Bronx]], [[Queens]], and [[Israel]].

==Student life==

Yeshiva University maintains four campuses in New York City:

#The Resnick Campus in the [[Morris Park, Bronx|Morris Park]] neighborhood of the eastern [[Bronx]] contains the Albert Einstein College of Medicine and the Ferkauf Graduate School of Psychology, along with dormitories, a library, a hospital and other medical facilities.
#The Brookdale Center in the [[Greenwich Village]] neighborhood of downtown [[Manhattan]] contains the Benjamin Cardozo School of Law, law clinics and office, and a dormitory. The Center for Jewish History, which includes the Yeshiva University Museum along with other institutions, is nearby in the Chelsea neighborhood.
#The Beren Campus in the [[Murray Hill, Manhattan|Murray Hill]] neighborhood of [[Midtown Manhattan]] is home to the undergraduate schools for women, including Stern College for Women and the Midtown branch of the [[Syms School of Business]], along with dormitories and other facilities. The Azrieli School has classes on this campus as well.
#The Wilf Campus is centered around the area of [[Tenth Avenue (Manhattan)|Amsterdam Ave]] and West 185th Street in the [[Washington Heights, Manhattan|Washington Heights]] neighborhood of upper Manhattan. Yeshiva University's main office is located within the Wilf Campus, at 500 185th St.,&lt;ref name=campusmap&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.yu.edu/images/campusmap.pdf |title=Yeshiva University Campus Map}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Wilf is considered the main campus. It is home to the undergraduate schools for men, the rabbinical seminary, the Belz School of Jewish Music, the high school for boys, the Azrieli Graduate School for Jewish Education and Administration, the Wurzweiler School for Social Work, and the Bernard Revel Graduate school, along with other divisions, offices, libraries, dormitories, and other facilities.

The high school for girls is located in New York City as well, in the Holliswood neighborhood of eastern [[Queens]].

=== S. Daniel Abraham Israel Program ===
The campus in [[Jerusalem]], in the [[Bayit VeGan]] neighborhood, contains a branch of the rabbinical seminary and an office coordinating the '''S. Daniel Abraham Israel Program''',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.yu.edu/jip/index.aspx S. Daniel Abraham Israel Program Home Page]&lt;/ref&gt; a formal arrangement between Yeshiva University and 42 men's and women's yeshivot in Israel that enables students to incorporate study in Israel into their college years. While studying in Israel, students are exposed to intense, concentrated study of Jewish subjects with top teachers while learning firsthand about Israel's land, people, history, and culture.

Yeshiva University Israel advisers visit each school regularly to offer academic guidance, career planning, and personal counseling. In addition, the program sponsors lectures and activities where students can gather under the auspices of Yeshiva University, and a guidance center to provide support to help ease the occasionally challenging adjustment to a year's study in Israel. Yeshiva University also cosponsors major events for American students in Israel, such as the Battle of the Bands and Inter-Seminary Choir Competition, and an annual career fair.

The program is headquartered at the Student Center at Yeshiva University's Israel Campus in the [[Bayit Vegan]] neighborhood of [[Jerusalem]]. Rabbi Ari Solomont serves as director of the program.&lt;ref&gt;[http://media.www.yucommentator.com/media/storage/paper652/news/2008/11/03/News/Rabbi.Ari.Solomont.Named.New.Director.Of.Israel.Program-3522144.shtml Rabbi Ari Solomont Named New Director of Israel Program]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Student government===
Numerous clubs and activities are maintained by the students in each school, generally under the auspices of a student government. Activities are funded by a student activities fee collected by the school but freely distributed by the elected council. (Athletics are usually an academic department.) Each graduate school maintains a student council, such as the Student Bar Association at Cardozo, which, in turn, supports the many clubs and publications in each school.

At the undergraduate level, there are separate student governments on the two campuses. Although the two student governments are separate, they work closely in coordinating joint events. The men's schools are represented overall by the Yeshiva Student Union, and specifically by the Yeshiva College Student Association, the Syms Student Council, the Student Organization of Yeshiva (SOY, which represents both undergraduate MYP students as well as RIETS students), and student councils for SBMP, IBC, and JSS. The latter four run most Jewish-related activities on campus, including holiday celebrations and the famed SOY Seforim (Jewish book) sale annually around February, which is open to the general public and attracts large crowds from near and far. There are also individual councils for each class, council committees, a Student Court, and clubs.

The women's schools are represented by the Stern College and Syms Student Councils; there are also a Torah Activities Council, which coordinates Jewish-related events, and individual class councils, along with various clubs.

The various positions on all councils are chosen by elections open to all students (both as voters and candidates) generally held in the Spring (for the following year's councils), although Freshman and Sophomore class councils are elected in the Fall, the latter owing to the large number of students spending the freshman year abroad in Israel.

The undergraduate men's newspaper is The Commentator, and the undergraduate women's The Observer, as well as a co-ed satirical news site The Quipster; there is also a student newspaper (in addition to a number of law journals) at Cardozo. There are numerous other publications on a wide range of topics, both secular and religious, produced by the various councils and academic clubs, along with many official university publications and the university press. The call letters of the student radio station are WYUR, currently an Internet-only station, available at &lt;code&gt;wyur.net&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wyur.net WYUR.net]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Dormitories and student housing===
{{Unreferenced section|date=December 2010}}
There are dormitory and dining facilities on each campus. Cardozo has a single dormitory building a block south of the classroom building, while Einstein has a number of student housing buildings on campus for single and married students.

Approximately 80% of the undergraduate student populations live on campus.

The Wilf Campus includes three main dormitory buildings: Morgenstern (nicknamed &quot;Morg&quot;) Rubin, and Muss Halls. Many upperclassmen and some graduate students live in the surrounding independent housing that is run by the university or in other nearby buildings; there is also a small high school dormitory on campus, Strenger Hall, which houses some older students as well who serve as counselors.

The Beren campus includes four dormitory buildings: Brookdale, Schottenstein, the 36th Street and 35th Street Residence Halls.  Many students live in university-administered independent housing nearby.

===Athletics===
Yeshiva University is home to a variety of NCAA-level sports teams.  The teams, nicknamed &quot;The Maccabees&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.yu.edu/athletics/ |title=Yeshiva Maccabees homepage |publisher=Yeshiva Maccabees |accessdate=August 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; include: men's baseball, basketball, golf, volleyball, wrestling, women's basketball, Cross Country, Fencing, soccer, tennis, and volleyball.

One of the most successful teams in Yeshiva University sports history is the fencing team, known as the &quot;Taubermen&quot;, named after the coach of the team, Professor Arthur Tauber, who served as the head coach of the team from 1949 through 1985.

Because of Yeshiva's dual curriculum, most of the sports teams practice at night, sometimes even as late as 11:00&amp;nbsp;pm. A few of the sports teams have been known to get in an early morning practice or workout before classes begin at 9:00&amp;nbsp;am.

One of the unique{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}} aspects of Yeshiva athletics is the way it connects with communities around the country. It is not rare for a team to participate in a weekend tournament outside of New York City and for the athletes to stay with local families in the area. Most recently this has taken place in Boston with the basketball and fencing teams, and in Hollywood, Florida with the baseball team in 2008. Yeshiva even maintains an international connection through the many international students who participate in NCAA sports. While some teams may only have one or two nationalities, others have as many as nine different nationalities representing the school on the sports field.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://spider.mc.yu.edu/news/articles/article.cfm?id=101718 |title=Players From Nine Countries Find Common Goal in Men's Soccer Team |date=November 11, 2008 |work=Yeshiva University News |publisher=Yeshiva University |accessdate=August 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Yeshiva has seen a few of its student-athletes go on to professional-level competition. Two members of the Yeshiva Maccabees Baseball team were drafted out of college by professional teams of the [[Israeli Baseball League]]. One of them, pitcher Aryeh Rosenbaum, even celebrated a championship with his team in the IBL's first year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.skylineconference.org/News/bball/2007/6/12/israel_baseball_league.asp?path=bball |title=Two former Yeshiva University Baseball players to compete in new Israeli Baseball League |author=Mike Spinner |date=December 6, 2007 |work=Yeshiva Sports Information |publisher=Skyline Conference  |accessdate=August 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Olympic gold medalist [[Henry Wittenberg]] was at one time the coach of the wrestling team.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTimesObit&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2010/03/10/sports/10wittenberg.html?ref=obituaries|title=Henry Wittenberg, Champion Wrestler, Dies at 91|work=The New York Times|date=March 10, 2010|accessdate=March 10, 2010 | first=Richard | last=Goldstein}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Yeshiva's Men's Basketball team is an annual playoff contender. The best era for Yeshiva basketball in recent history has been the first few years and last few years of the 1990s.  Banners hang in the Max Stern Athletic Center commemorating seasons from both eras. The 2007–2008 season had particular note as Yeshiva was home to the NCAA Skyline Conference's Rookie of the Year.

The 2008–2009 season saw the men's NCAA volleyball team have its best season ever. Other teams that are quickly becoming contenders are the men's soccer, baseball, and tennis teams.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}} In the 2009–2010 season, the men's NCAA volleyball team won the HVMAC (Hudson Valley Men's Athletic Conference) Championship.

In 2010, the Men's Cross Country team won the HVMAC Championship by a huge landslide.  The team repeated as champions in 2011.  YU Maccabee Sam Cohen won the individual championship.

====Student groups and organizations====
A wide variety of student clubs, groups, and organizations are available to the student body to join. These groups range from groups like the Commentator (a student newspaper) to the University Drama society that puts on the occasional performance. 
 
In 2010 students gathered together to create a &quot;Tolerance Club&quot;, the purpose of which was to promote the idea of  there being a diversity of people within the  Yeshiva University community. During the first meeting a panel was assembled that included a few openly Gay Jewish Orthodox men who discussed their experience growing up in the Orthodox community. Soon after the club had begun it was promptly shut down by the university Faculty for allegedly promoting values that were not in agreement with orthodox Judiasm.&lt;ref name=&quot;Didn’t Think Tolerance Could Be Controversial? Welcome To Yeshiva University&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://newvoices.org/2009/05/05/0073-2/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Rankings==

The [[U.S. News and World Report]]'s 2011 &quot;America's Best Colleges&quot; ranked Yeshiva University as the 45th best national University. In 2009 &quot;America's Best Colleges&quot; ranked Yeshiva University as the 50th best national university rising from the 2008 rank of 52nd. YU was also ranked 41st &quot;Best Value&quot; Colleges, and 5th in percentage of students studying abroad (90% of the class of 2007).  Yeshiva University's Albert Einstein School of Medicine was ranked 41st in the nation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-medical-schools Top Medical Schools 2011], ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]. Retrieved July 30, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Washington Monthly]] 2007 College Rankings placed Yeshiva University 94th nationally.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonmonthly.com/features/2007/0709.rankings.html The Washington Monthly College Rankings], ''[[Washington Monthly]]. Retrieved April 14, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; In a similar list, The [[Center for Measuring University Performance]] found Yeshiva University 45th nationally among the Top American Research Universities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://mup.asu.edu/research2006.pdfl The Top American Research Universities: 2006 Annual Report], ''The Center for Measuring University Performance. Retrieved July 29, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

YU has also received worldwide recognition. ''[[The Times Higher Education Supplement]]'' of the UK ranked it as 68th in the world in 2011,&lt;ref name=&quot;timeshighereducation.co.uk&quot;/&gt; a substantial jump from the 172nd top world university ranking it received in 2006 and the 254th ranking the school received in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.topuniversities.com/worlduniversityrankings/results/2006/ THES – QS World University Rankings 2006 – Top 200 Universities], ''[[The Times Higher Education Supplement]]''. Retrieved July 28, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Shanghai Jiao Tong University]], the university is ranked in the 151–200 category among world universities and 76–98 among universities in the Americas.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ed.sjtu.edu.cn/ranking.htm Academic Ranking of World Universities 2006] ''[[Shanghai Jiao Tong University]]. Retrieved July 29, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

The university's national research impact has also been evaluated. The university's rank of research impact in Biology &amp; Biochemistry placed 5th in the US by [[Thomson Reuters]], surpassing Washington University, Stanford, Duke, and UCSF.&lt;ref&gt;[http://scientific.thomsonreuters.com/products/rsg/rankings/ US University Top Tens] ''[[Thomson Reuters]]. Retrieved July 28, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable faculty and alumni==

===Notable faculty===
* Dr. [[Jekuthiel Ginsburg]]
* Rabbi [[Benjamin Blech]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://spider.mc.yu.edu/news/articles/article.cfm?id=100064 |title=YU Professor Publishes Ninth Book: Taking Stock: A Spiritual Guide to Rising Above Life's Financial Ups and Downs |author=Rabbi Benjamin Blech |date=October 13, 2003 |work=Taking Stock |accessdate=August 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Rabbi Dr. [[J. David Bleich]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cardozo.yu.edu/MemberContentDisplay.aspx?ccmd=ContentDisplay&amp;ucmd=UserDisplay&amp;userid=10490&amp;contentid=1250 |title=J. David Bleich |author=Herbert and Florence Tenzer Professor of Jewish Law and Ethics |work=Profile |publisher=Cardozo |accessdate=August 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Elisheva Carlebach]]
* Rabbi [[Shalom Carmy]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.yu.edu/faculty/carmy/page.aspx?id=9490&amp;ekmensel=510_submenu_0_link_1 |title=Rabbi Shalom Carmy |publisher=Yeshiva University |accessdate=August 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Dr. [[David Alan Johnson]]
* Rabbi Dr. [[David Berger (professor)|David Berger]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rabbis.org/news/article.cfm?id=100627 |title=Rabbi David Berger: Professor of History, Brooklyn College and the Graduate Center, City University of New York, New York, NY  |author=Rabbi David Berger |date=November 23, 2005 |publisher=Rabbinical Council of America |accessdate=August 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Joshua Fishman]]
* Rabbi [[Elazar Hurvitz]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.yu.edu/revel/index.aspx?id=1003 |title=Core Faculty |publisher=Bernard Revel, Gradual School of Jewish Studies |accessdate=August 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Dr. [[Adam Zachary Newton]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.yu.edu/faculty/newton/page.aspx?id=36868&amp;ekmensel=15074e5e_2762_0_36868_1 |title=? |author=Dr. Adam Zachary Newton |publisher=Yeshiva University Faculty |accessdate=August 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Rabbi Dr. [[Moshe David Tendler]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://pewforum.org/events/0503/tendlerbio.htm |title=? |publisher=The Pew Forum on Religion and Public Life |accessdate=August 27, 2010 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080306064329/http://pewforum.org/events/0503/tendlerbio.htm |archivedate = March 6, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Rabbi [[Hershel Schachter]]
* Rabbi [[Eli Baruch Shulman]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://spider.mc.yu.edu/news/articles/article.cfm?id=101033 |title=Rabbi Eliahu Baruch Shulman of Brooklyn Joins Faculty of Yeshiva University’s Yeshiva Program/Mazer School of Talmudic Studies |date=October 6, 2005 |publisher=Yeshiva University News |accessdate=August 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Rabbi Dr. [[Jacob J. Schachter]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rabbis.org/news/article.cfm?id=100792 |title=Rabbi Dr. Jacob J. Schacter University Professor of Jewish History and Jewish Thought and Senior Scholar at the Center for the Jewish Future at Yeshiva University, New York, NY |date=June 6, 2006 |publisher=Rabbinical Council of America |accessdate=August 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Rabbi Dr. [[Haym Soloveitchik]]
* Rabbi Dr. [[Michael Rosensweig]]
* [[Rachel Wischnitzer]]
* Rabbi [[Benjamin Yudin]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.shomrei-torah.org/ravyudin.htm Rabbi Benjamin Yudin], Congregation Shomrei Torah. Retrieved March 27, 2008. &quot;He pursued a dual graduate study program, earning smicha (rabbinic ordination) from Y. U.'s Rabbi Isaac Elchanan Theological Seminary, as well as a master's degree in Jewish History.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable alumni==
* James Babendir, Business
*[[Jeff Ballabon]], American lawyer
* Dr. [[Howard Dean]] ([[Doctor of Medicine|M.D.]], [[Albert Einstein College of Medicine]])&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Candidates / Howard Dean |publisher=CNN |date=February 18, 2004 |url=http://www.cnn.com/ELECTION/2004/special/president/candidates/dean.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Professor [[Laurence Dreyfus]], Bach Scholar and Fellow of [[Magdalen College, Oxford]]
* Rabbi Dr. [[Seth Farber]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://eng.itim.org.il/?CategoryID=243 |title=ITIM Staff |publisher=ITIM Life, the Jewish-Life Information Center |accessdate=August 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Adam Ferziger]]
* Rabbi Dr. [[Barry Freundel]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.kesher.org/community/freundel_bio.shtml |title=Kesher Israel's rabbi for the past eighteen years is Rabbi Barry Freundel |author=Rabbi Dr. Barry Freundel |publisher=Kesher Israel |accessdate=August 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Professor [[Hillel Furstenberg]], American-Israeli mathematician
* Professor [[Ari L. Goldman]]
* [[Baruch Goldstein]], perpetrator of the [[Cave of the Patriarchs Massacre]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/1994/07/03/weekinreview/june-26-july-2-hebron-massacre-israel-says-gunman-acted-by-himself.html?src=pm |title=June 26 – July 2: Hebron Massacre; Israel Says Gunman Acted by Himself
|author=Clyde Haberman |work=New York Times |date=July 3, 1994}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Gary Gruber]], Author, physicist, testing expert, educator
* [[Lucy Kaplansky]], American singer-songwriter
* [[Aaron Klein]], New York Times bestselling author, WABC radio host, journalist
* [[Daniel Kurtzer]], former United States Ambassador to Israel and Egypt
* [[Matthew Levitt]]
* [[Nat Lewin]], American lawyer
* Rabbi Dr. [[Moses Mescheloff]]
* Rabbi [[David Nesenoff]], filmmaker and journalist
* [[Chaim Potok]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/biography/Potok.html |title=Chaim Potok dead at age of 73, was literary pioneer and scholar |author=Ephross, Peter |date=June 23, 2002 |publisher=[[Jewish Virtual Library]] |accessdate=August 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Rabbi [[Shlomo Riskin]]
* Rabbi [[Jonathan Rosenblatt]]
* [[Sheldon Silver]], NY State Speaker
* [[Leonard Susskind]], the Felix Bloch professor of physics at Stanford University

==See also==
{{Portal|New York City|University}}
*[[American Jewish University]] – a Los Angeles based university, whose intimate undergraduate programs involve ethical Jewish principles.
*[[Bar-Ilan University]] – a [[Ramat Gan]] based university which aims &quot;to blend tradition with modern technologies and scholarship, and teach the compelling ethics of Jewish heritage to all.”
*[[College and university rankings]]
*[[Criticism of college and university rankings (North America)#2007 movement|Criticism of college and university rankings (North America)]]
*[[Education in New York City]]
*[[List of Yeshiva University people|Famous people affiliated with Yeshiva University]]
*[[Hebrew Theological College]] – a Chicago based institution, &quot;preparing its graduates for roles as educators and Rabbis&quot;, while providing &quot;broad cultural perspectives and a strong foundation in the Liberal Arts and Sciences.&quot;
*[[Jerusalem College of Technology]] – a [[Jerusalem]] based college, founded to &quot;educate students who see the synthesis of Jewish values and a profession as their way of life.&quot;
*[[Lander College]] – a New York City based college, a division of [[Touro College]], which offers &quot;a superior college education for students committed to serious Beis Medrash learning in an atmosphere of Torah.&quot; It has a program structure similar to MYP at Yeshiva College.
*[[Madoff Investment Scandal]]; YU Endowment Shaken By Madoff Storm, YU Loses $110 Million, Scrambles To Assess Immediate Damage.

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
*[http://www.yu.edu Yeshiva University]
*[http://www.yumacs.com Yeshiva University Athletics]

===Undergraduate schools===
*[http://www.yu.edu/yeshivacollege Yeshiva College]
*[http://www.yu.edu/stern Stern College for Women]
*[http://www.yu.edu/sysyms Syms School of Business]

===Graduate schools===
*[http://www.aecom.yu.edu Albert Einstein College of Medicine]
*[http://www.yu.edu/azrieli/ Azrieli Graduate School of Jewish Education and Administration]
*[http://www.cardozo.yu.edu/ Benjamin N. Cardozo School of Law]
*[http://www.yu.edu/Revel/ Bernard Revel Graduate School of Jewish Studies]
*[http://www.yu.edu/Ferkauf/ Ferkauf Graduate School of Psychology]
*[http://www.yu.edu/gpats/ GPATS – Graduate Program for Women in Advanced Talmudic Studies]
*[http://www.yu.edu/Wurzweiler/ Wurzweiler Graduate School of Social Work]

===Affiliates and centers===
*[http://www.riets.edu Rabbi Isaac Elchanan Theological Seminary]
*[http://www.yu.edu/prospective/belz.asp Philip and Sarah Belz School of Jewish Music]
*[http://www.yuhsg.org Yeshiva University High School for Girls]
*[http://www.yuhsb.org Yeshiva University High School for Boys]
*[http://www.yu.edu/cis Center for Israel Studies at Yeshiva University]
*[http://yu.edu/cjf Center for the Jewish Future]
*[http://www.yu.edu/ethics The Center for Ethics at Yeshiva University]
*[http://www.cardozo.yu.edu/cjl Center for Jewish Law and Contemporary Civilization]

===Scholarly and cultural resources===
*[http://www.yu.edu/cjf/ Yeshiva University Center for the Jewish Future]

===Student organizations===
*[http://www.Youtube.com/YUBaseball &quot;Yeshiva University Baseball&quot;] (NCAA Division III Baseball Program)
*''[[The Maccabeats]]'' (Yeshiva University's a cappella group) noted for their hit song [[Candlelight (song)|Candlelight]]
*[http://www.wyur.net ''WYUR:Yeshiva University Radio'']
*[http://www.yucommentator.org ''The Commentator''] (Yeshiva College and Sy Syms School of Business' student newspaper)
*[http://www.yuobserver.org ''The Observer''] (Stern College For Women's student newspaper)
*[http://www.MacsLive.com ''MacsLive, Online Home of Macs Basketball and the Red Sarachek Tournament'']
*[http://www.facebook.com/home.php?ref=home#/pages/New-York-NY/Yeshiva-University-Maccabees-Soccer/42896994224?ref=nf ''Yeshiva University Soccer'']
*[http://www.theseforimsale.com/ SOY Seforim Sale]

===Other YU resources===
*[http://www.yu.edu/torah YUTorah, home of online shiurim and materials]
*[http://www.yasharbooks.com/Yeshiva.html ''My Yeshiva College: 75 Years of Memories'']

{{YU}}
{{NYC Colleges}}
{{Skyline Conference navbox}}
{{OrthodoxJudaism}}
{{YU Roshei Yeshiva}}

{{Coord|40.85028|N|73.92972|W|source:placeopedia|display=title}}

[[Category:Yeshiva University| ]]
[[Category:Orthodox Jewish universities and colleges]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in New York City]]
[[Category:Washington Heights, Manhattan]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1886]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]]

[[ca:Yeshiva University]]
[[de:Yeshiva University]]
[[es:Universidad Yeshiva]]
[[eo:Universitato Yeshiva]]
[[fa:دانشگاه یشیوا]]
[[fr:Yeshiva University]]
[[ko:예시바 대학교]]
[[id:Universitas Yeshiva]]
[[he:ישיבה יוניברסיטי]]
[[ja:イェシーバー大学]]
[[no:Yeshiva University]]
[[ru:Иешива-университет]]
[[sh:Универзитет Јешива]]
[[sv:Yeshiva University]]
[[yi:ישיבה אוניווערסיטעט]]
[[zh:叶史瓦大学]]</text>
      <sha1>sqlrzqfk522xzpkknx36mtk1311uuwt</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
