<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Zionism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>34484</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519713924</id>
      <parentid>519675035</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-25T07:01:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dlv999</username>
        <id>16051679</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 519675035 by [[Special:Contributions/Z554|Z554]] ([[User talk:Z554|talk]])No evidence of dispute or discussion on talk. Do not re-add tag without explaining on talk what (if any) are the current NPOV concerns with this section.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="94954">{{about|Zionism as a movement, not the [[History of Israel]]||Zion (disambiguation)}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=February 2012}}
{{pp-semi-protected|small=yes}}
[[File:Flag of Israel.svg|thumb|right|Flag of Israel, the flag was adopted as the symbol of the Zionist Movement in the 1890s.]]

{{Nationalism sidebar}}
{{Aliyah}}
{{Jews and Judaism sidebar}}
{{Israelis}}

'''Zionism''' ({{lang-he|ציונות}}, ''Tsiyonut'') is a form of [[nationalism]] of [[Jews]] and [[Jewish culture]] that supports a Jewish [[nation state]] in territory defined as the [[Land of Israel]].{{sfn|Motyl|2001|pp=604.}} Zionism supports Jews upholding their Jewish identity and opposes the assimilation of Jews into other societies and has advocated the return of Jews to [[Israel]] as a means for Jews to be liberated from [[Antisemitism|anti-Semitic]] discrimination, exclusion, and persecution that has occurred in other societies.{{sfn|Motyl|2001|pp=604.}} Since the establishment of the [[State of Israel]], the Zionist movement continues primarily to advocate on behalf of the [[Jewish state]] and address threats to its continued existence and security. In a less common usage, the term may also refer to non-political, [[cultural Zionism]], founded and represented most prominently by [[Ahad Ha'am]]; and political support for the [[State of Israel]] by non-Jews, as in [[Christian Zionism]].

Critics of Zionism consider it a [[Colonialism|colonialist]]&lt;ref name=CHARCOL /&gt; or [[racism|racist]]&lt;ref name=CHARRAS /&gt; movement. Some scholars consider certain forms&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2003/nov/29/comment |title=Anti-Zionism is anti-semitism |work=The Guardian |date=2003-11-29 |accessdate=2003-11-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://jcpa.org/phas/phas-wistrich-f04.htm |title=Anti-Zionism and Anti-Semitism |work=Jerusalem Center for Public Affairs |date=Fall 2004 |accessdate=Fall 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; of opposition to Zionism to constitute [[Antisemitism]].&lt;ref name=Stauber /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;

−
{{citation

−
| first=Kenneth L. | last=Marcus

−
| title=Anti-Zionism as Racism: Campus Anti-Semitism and the Civil Rights Act of 1964

−
| journal=William &amp; Mary Bill of Rights Journal

−
| volume=15 | issue=3

−
| pages=837–891

−
| year=2007

−
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Overview==
The common denominator among all Zionists is the claim to [[Eretz Israel]] as the national homeland of the Jews and as the legitimate focus for the Jewish national self-determination (as shown, among others, by Gideon Shimoni).&lt;ref&gt;Gideon Shimoni, ''The Zionist Ideology'' (1995)&lt;/ref&gt; It is based on historical ties and [[Judaism|religious traditions]] linking the Jewish people to the [[Land of Israel]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Aviel Roshwald]], &quot;Jewish Identity and the Paradox of Nationalism&quot;, in Michael Berkowitz, (ed.). ''Nationalism, Zionism and Ethnic Mobilization of the Jews in 1900 and Beyond'', p. 15).&lt;/ref&gt; Zionism does not have a uniform ideology, but has evolved in a dialogue among a plethora of ideologies: General Zionism, [[Religious Zionism]], [[Labor Zionism]], [[Revisionist Zionism]], [[Green Zionism]], etc. 

After almost two millennia of existence of the [[Jewish diaspora]] without a national state, the Zionist movement was founded in the late 19th century by [[Secular Jewish culture|secular Jews]], largely as a response by [[Ashkenazi Jews]] to rising [[antisemitism]] in [[Europe]], exemplified by the [[Dreyfus affair]] in France and the [[Anti-Jewish pogroms in the Russian Empire]].&lt;ref&gt;Wylen, Stephen M. ''Settings of Silver: An Introduction to Judaism'', Second Edition, Paulist Press, 2000, p. 392).&lt;/ref&gt; The political movement was formally established by the [[Austria–Hungary|Austro-Hungarian]] journalist [[Theodor Herzl]] in 1897 following the publication of his book ''[[Der Judenstaat]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Walter Laqueur, ''The History of Zionism'' (2003) p 40&lt;/ref&gt; At that time, the movement sought to encourage [[Aliyah|Jewish migration]] to the Ottoman [[Palestine]].

Although initially one of several Jewish political movements offering alternative responses to [[Jewish assimilation|assimilation]] and antisemitism, Zionism grew rapidly and became the dominant force in Jewish politics with the destruction of Jewish life in Central and Eastern Europe where these alternative movements were rooted.

The movement was eventually successful in establishing Israel on May 14, 1948 (5 Iyyar 5708 in the [[Hebrew calendar]]), as the [[homeland for the Jewish people]]. The proportion of the world's Jews living in Israel has also steadily grown since the movement came into existence and over 40% of the [[Jewish population|world's Jews]] now live in Israel, more than in any other country. These two outcomes represent the historical success of Zionism, unmatched by any other Jewish political movement in the past 2,000 years.

In some academic studies, Zionism has been analyzed both within the larger context of [[diaspora politics]] and as an example of modern [[Wars of national liberation|national liberation movements]].&lt;ref&gt;A.R. Taylor, 'Vision and intent in Zionist Thought', in 'The transformation of Palestine', ed. by I. Abu-Lughod, 1971, ISBN 0-8101-0345-1, p. 10&lt;/ref&gt;

Zionism was also directed at assimilation into the modern world. As a result of the Diaspora, many of the Jewish people were outcasts and had no knowledge of the modern era.{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}} There were Jews who desired complete assimilation and were willing to neglect their faith in an attempt at modernization. The assimilationists, who are depicted{{By whom|date=January 2012}} as truly messianic, were a radical group in Jewish history. They desired a pure revolution: a complete integration of Jews into European society. This would dispel any dissimilarity between Jews and non-Jews.  They are described as messianic in their anticipation and desire of a new era.{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}  Assimilationists were not concerned with keeping their own identity but wanted homogeneity.{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}  They would disband their traditional views and opinions as long as it insured complete assimilation into the modern world. Another less radical form of assimilation was called cultural synthesis.{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}} Those in favor of cultural synthesis emphasized an obligation to maintain traditional Jewish values but also a need to conform to a modernist society. They are described{{By whom|date=January 2012}} as defensive and sought to reject the pure revolution that the assimilationists promoted. They aimed to eradicate any disparity between Jewish and modern life. However (in contrast with assimilationists), they also wanted to preserve their own faith and many of their traditional values.  They were concerned that if Jews lost their identification, the result would be detrimental. Those in favor of cultural synthesis desired a balance between change and continuity as opposed to the assimilationists who only wanted change.&lt;ref&gt;Tesler, Mark. Jewish History and the Emergence of Modern Political Zionism. Bloomington, IN: Indiana University Printing Press, 1994.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1975, the [[United Nations General Assembly]] passed a resolution that designated Zionism as &quot;[[Resolution 3379|a form of racism and racial discrimination]]&quot;. The resolution was repealed in 1991. Within the context of the [[Arab–Israeli conflict]], Zionism is viewed by critics as a system that [[Israel and the apartheid analogy|fosters apartheid]] and racism.&lt;ref&gt;Stefan Goranov, &quot;Racism: A Basic Principle of Zionism&quot; in Zionism and Racism.] Proceedings of an International Symposium. The International Organization for the elimination of all forms of racial discrimination. New Brunswick. North American, 1979. 262p.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Terminology==
The term &quot;Zionism&quot; itself is derived from the word [[Zion]] ({{lang-he|ציון, ''Tzi-yon''}}), referring to [[Jerusalem]]. Throughout eastern Europe at the time, there were numerous grassroots groups promoting the national resettlement of the Jews in what was termed their &quot;ancestral homeland&quot;, as well as the revitalization and cultivation of [[Hebrew]].  These groups were collectively called the &quot;[[Lovers of Zion]].&quot; The first use of the term is attributed to the Austrian [[Nathan Birnbaum]], founder of a nationalist Jewish students' movement ''Kadimah'', who used the term in his journal ''Selbstemanzipation'' (''Self Emancipation'') .&lt;ref&gt;De Lange, Nicholas, ''An Introduction to Judaism'', Cambridge University Press (2000), p. 30. ISBN 0-521-46624-5.&lt;/ref&gt;  Readings of the founders of Zionism shows that they lived in the same Europe which spawned fascism and Naziism, and they adopted the anti-Jewish view that Jews did not belong in Europe as the core of their ideology.&lt;ref&gt;Hertzberg, Arthur, &quot;The Zionist Idea: A Historical Analysis and Reader,&quot; Atheneum (1959)&quot; and Herzl, Thedor, &quot;The Diaries of Theodor Herzl,&quot; The Universal Library (1962).&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Organization==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;float:right; margin-left:16px;&quot;
|+ Members and delegates at the 1939 Zionist congress, by country/region (Zionism was banned in the Soviet Union). 70,000 Polish Jews supported the [[Revisionist Zionism]] movement, which was not represented.&lt;ref&gt;Source: ''A survey of Palestine'', prepared in 1946 for the [[Anglo-American Committee of Inquiry]], Volume II page 907 HMSO 1946.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! Country/Region
! Members
! Delegates
|-
| Poland
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|299,165
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|109
|-
| USA
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|263,741
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|114
|-
| Palestine
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|167,562
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|134
|-
| Romania
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|60,013
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|28
|-
| United Kingdom
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|23,513
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|15
|-
| South Africa
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|22,343
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|14
|-
| Canada
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|15,220
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|8
|}

The multi-national, worldwide Zionist [[Philosophical movement|movement]] is structured on [[representative democracy|representative democratic]] principles. Congresses are held every four years (they were held every two years before the Second World War) and delegates to the congress are elected by the membership. Members are required to pay dues known as a ''shekel''. At the congress, delegates elect a 30-man executive council, which in turn elects the movement's leader. The movement was democratic from its inception and women had the right to vote.

Until 1917, the [[World Zionist Organization]] pursued a strategy of building a [[Jewish National Home]] through persistent small-scale immigration and the founding of such bodies as the [[Jewish National Fund]] (1901&amp;nbsp;— a charity that bought land for Jewish settlement) and the [[Anglo-Palestine Bank]] (1903&amp;nbsp;— provided loans for Jewish businesses and farmers). In 1942, at the [[Biltmore Conference]], the movement included for the first time an express objective of the establishment of a Jewish state in the Land of Israel.

The 28th [[Zionist Congress]], meeting in Jerusalem in 1968, adopted the five points of the &quot;Jerusalem Program&quot; as the aims of Zionism today. They are:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hagshama.org.il/en/resources/view.asp?id=497&amp;subject=43 Hagshama.org]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Unity of the Jewish People and the centrality of Israel in Jewish life
* Ingathering of the Jewish People in its historic homeland, Eretz Israel, through [[Aliyah]] from all countries
* Strengthening of the State of Israel, based on the prophetic vision of justice and peace
* Preservation of the identity of the Jewish People through fostering of Jewish and Hebrew education, and of Jewish spiritual and cultural values
* Protection of Jewish rights everywhere

Since the creation of modern Israel, the role of the movement has declined and it is now a peripheral factor in [[Israeli politics]], though different perceptions of Zionism continue to play a role in Israeli and Jewish political discussion.

===Labor Zionism===
{{Main|Labor Zionists}}

Labor Zionism originated in Eastern Europe. Socialist Zionists believed that centuries of oppression in antisemitic societies had reduced Jews to a meek, vulnerable, despairing existence that invited further antisemitism, a view originally stipulated by [[Theodor Herzl]]. They argued that a revolution of the Jewish soul and society was necessary and achievable in part by Jews moving to Israel and becoming farmers, workers, and soldiers in a country of their own. Most socialist Zionists rejected the observance of traditional religious Judaism as perpetuating a &quot;Diaspora mentality&quot; among the Jewish people, and established rural communes in Israel called &quot;[[kibbutz]]im&quot;. The kibbutz began as a variation on a &quot;national farm&quot; scheme, a form of cooperative agriculture where the Jewish National Fund hired Jewish workers under trained supervision. The kibbutzim were a symbol of the Second [[Aliyah|Aliya]] in that they put great emphasis on communalism and egalitarianism, representing to a certain extent Utopian socialism. Furthermore, they stressed self-sufficiency, which became an important aspect of Labor Zionism. Though socialist Zionism draws its inspiration and is philosophically founded on the fundamental values and spirituality of Judaism, its progressive expression of that Judaism has often fostered an antagonistic relationship with [[Orthodox Judaism]].

Labor Zionism became the dominant force in the political and economic life of the [[Yishuv]] during the [[British Mandate of Palestine]] and was the dominant ideology of the political establishment in Israel until the [[Israeli legislative election, 1977|1977 election]] when the [[Israeli Labor Party]] was defeated. The [[Israeli Labor Party]] continues the tradition, although the most popular party in the kibbutzim is [[Meretz]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}} Labor Zionism's main institution is the Histadrut, which began by providing strikebreakers against a Palestinian worker's strike in 1920 and is now the largest employer in Israel after the Israeli government.

===Liberal Zionism===
{{Main|General Zionists}}
General Zionism (or Liberal Zionism) was initially the dominant trend within the Zionist movement from the [[First Zionist Congress]] in 1897 until after the First World War. General Zionists identified with the liberal European middle class to which many Zionist leaders such as Herzl and [[Chaim Weizmann]] aspired.
Liberal Zionism, although not associated with any single party in modern Israel, remains a strong trend in Israeli politics advocating free market principles, democracy and adherence to human rights. [[Kadima]], however, does identify with many of the fundamental policies of Liberal Zionist ideology, advocating among other things the need for Palestinian statehood in order to form a more democratic society in Israel, affirming the free market, and calling for equal rights for Arab citizens of Israel.

===Nationalist Zionism===
{{Main|Revisionist Zionism}}
Nationalist Zionism originated from the Revisionist Zionists led by [[Jabotinsky]]. The Revisionists left the World Zionist Organization in 1935 because it refused to state that the creation of a Jewish state was an objective of Zionism. The revisionists advocated the formation of a Jewish Army in Palestine to force the Arab population to accept mass Jewish migration. Revisionist Zionism evolved into the [[Likud]] Party in Israel, which has dominated most governments since 1977. It advocates that Israel maintain control of the West Bank and East Jerusalem, and takes a hard-line approach in the Israeli-Arab conflict. In 2005 the Likud split over the issue of creation of a Palestinian state on the occupied territories, and party members advocating peace talks helped form the [[Kadima]] party.

===Religious Zionism===
{{Main|Religious Zionism}}
In the 1920s and 1930s Rabbi [[Abraham Isaac Kook]] (the first [[Chief Rabbinate of Israel|Chief Rabbi of Palestine]]) and his son Rabbi Zevi Judah Kook saw great religious and traditional value in many of Zionism's ideals, while rejecting its anti-religious&lt;!-- secular?, please define --&gt; undertones. They taught that Orthodox (Torah) Judaism embraces and mandates Zionism's positive ideals, such as the ingathering of exiles, and political activity to create and maintain a Jewish political entity in the Land of Israel. In this way, Zionism serves as a bridge between Orthodox and secular Jews.

While other Zionist groups tended to moderate their nationalism over time, the [[Israeli-occupied territories|gains]] from the [[Six-Day War]] have led religious Zionism to play a significant role in Israeli political life. Now associated with the [[National Religious Party]] and [[Gush Emunim]], religious Zionists have been at the forefront of Jewish settlement in the West Bank and efforts to assert Jewish control over the [[Old City (Jerusalem)|Old City]] of Jerusalem.

===Green Zionism===
{{Main|Green Zionism}}

[[Green Zionism]] is a branch of Zionism primarily concerned with the environment of Israel. The only environmental Zionist party is the [[Green Zionist Alliance]].

===Neo-Zionism and Post-Zionism===
During the last quarter of the 20th century, classic nationalism in Israel declined. This led to the rise of two antagonistic movements: [[neo-Zionism]] and [[post-Zionism]]. Both movements mark the Israeli version of a worldwide phenomenon:

* Emergence of globalization, a market society and liberal culture
* Local backlash&lt;ref&gt;[[Uri Ram]], ''The Future of the Past in Israel&amp;nbsp;— A Sociology of Knowledge Approach'', in [[Benny Morris]], ''Making Israel'', p.224.&lt;/ref&gt;

Neo-Zionism and post-Zionism share traits with &quot;classical&quot; Zionism but differ by accentuating antagonist and diametrically opposed poles already present in Zionism. &quot;Neo Zionism accentuates the messianic and particularistic dimensions of Zionist nationalism, while post-Zionism accentuates its normalising and universalistic dimensions&quot;.&lt;ref name = &quot;Chan58&quot;&gt;[[Steve Chan]], [[Anita Shapira]], [[Derek Jonathan]], ''Israeli Historical Revisionism: from left to right'', Routledge, 2002, p.58.&lt;/ref&gt; Post-Zionism asserts that Israel should abandon the concept of a &quot;state of the Jewish people&quot; and strive to be a state of all its citizens,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.meforum.org/article/469 Can Israel Survive Post-Zionism?] by Meyrav Wurmser. Middle East Quarterly, March 1999&lt;/ref&gt; or a [[One-state solution|binational state]] where Arabs and Jews live together while enjoying some type of autonomy.

===Zionism and Haredi Judaism===
{{See also|Haredim and Zionism}}
Most Haredi Orthodox organizations do not belong to the Zionist movement; they view Zionism as secular, reject nationalism as a doctrine and consider Judaism to be first and foremost a religion. However, some Haredi movements such as [[Shas]] do openly affiliate with the Zionist movement.

Haredi rabbis do not consider Israel to be a [[halacha|halachic]] Jewish state because it is secular. However, they generally consider themselves responsible for ensuring that Jews maintain religious ideals and since most Israeli citizens are Jews they pursue this agenda within Israel. Others reject any possibility of a Jewish state, since according to them a Jewish state is completely forbidden by Jewish law, and a Jewish state is considered an oxymoron.

Two Haredi parties run in Israeli elections. They are sometimes associated with views that could be regarded as nationalist or Zionist, and have shown a preference for coalitions with more nationalist Zionist parties, probably because these are more interested in enhancing the Jewish nature of the Israeli state.

The Sephardi-Orthodox party [[Shas]] rejected association with the Zionist movement, however in 2010 it joined the [[World Zionist Organization]], its voters also generally regard themselves as Zionist and Knesset members frequently pursue what others might consider a Zionist agenda. Shas has supported territorial compromise with the Arabs and Palestinians but generally opposes compromise over Jewish holy sites.

The non-Hasidic or 'Lithuanian' Haredi Ashkenazi world is represented by the Ashkenazi [[Agudat Israel]]/[[United Torah Judaism|UTJ]] party has always avoided association with the Zionist movement and usually avoids voting on or discussing issues related to peace because its members do not serve in the army. The party does work towards ensuring that Israel and Israeli law are in tune with the [[halacha]], on issues such as [[Shabbat]] rest. The rabbinical leaders of the so-called Litvishe world in current and past generations, such as Rabbi [[Elazar Menachem Shach]] and Rabbi [[Avigdor Miller]], are strongly opposed to all forms of Zionism, religious and secular, but allow for slight cooperation in the form of participating in Israeli political life, including both passive and active participation in elections.

Many other [[Hasidic Judaism|Hasidic]] groups, most famously the [[Satmar (Hasidic dynasty)|Satmar]] Hasidim as well as the larger movement they are part of in Jerusalem, the [[Edah HaChareidis]], are strongly anti-Zionist. One of the best known Hasidic opponent of all forms of modern political Zionism was [[Hungary|Hungarian]] [[rebbe]] and [[Talmud]]ic scholar [[Joel Teitelbaum]]. In his view, the current [[State of Israel]], which was [[Declaration of the Establishment of the State of Israel|founded]] by people that included some anti-religious personalities in seeming violation of the traditional notion that Jews should wait for the Jewish Messiah, is seen as contrary to Judaism. The core citations from classical Judaic sources cited by Teitelbaum in his arguments against modern Zionism are based on a passage in the Talmud, Rabbi Yosi b'Rebbi Hanina explains (Kesubos 111a) that the Lord imposed &quot;[[Three Oaths]]&quot; on the nation of Israel: a) Israel should not return to the Land together, by force; b) Israel should not rebel against the other nations; and c) The nations should not subjugate Israel too harshly. According to Teitelbaum, the second oath is relevant concerning the subsequent wars fought between Israel and Arab nations.

Other opponent groups included in the Edah HaChareidis include [[Dushinsky]], [[Toldos Aharon]], [[Toldos Avrohom Yitzchok]], [[Spinka]], and others, numbering tens of thousands in Jerusalem, and hundreds of thousands worldwide.

The [[Neturei Karta]], an orthodox Haredi religious movement, strongly oppose Zionism and Israel; it considers the latter a racist regime.&lt;ref&gt;[http://globalfire.tv/nj/03en/jews/ttjews.htm &quot;We oppose the Zionists and their 'state'] vigorously and we continue our prayers for the dismantlement of the Zionist 'state' and peace to the world.&quot; Rabbi E Weissfish, NETUREI KARTA, Representatives of Orthodox Jewry, US, London, Palestine and worldwide.&lt;/ref&gt; The movement equates Zionism to [[Nazism]], stating &quot;Apart from the Zionists, the only ones who consistently considered the Jews a race were the Nazis.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nkusa.org/AboutUs/Zionism/greatgulf.cfm &quot;THE GREAT GULF BETWEEN ZIONISM AND JUDAISM&quot;] Paper delivered by G. J. Neuberger a member of Neturei Karta at the Tripoli Conference on Zionism and Racism.]&lt;/ref&gt; Naturei Carta believes that Zionist ideology is totally contrary to traditional [[Jewish law]] and beliefs and the teachings of the [[Torah|Holy Torah]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewsagainstzionism.com/zionism/whatis.cfm &quot;What is Zionism?&quot;] Jews against Zionism.&lt;/ref&gt; and that Zionism promotes [[antisemitism]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewsagainstzionism.com/antisemitism/zionismpromotes.cfm &quot;Zionism promotes [[antisemitism]].&quot;] Jews against Zionism.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Chabad-Lubavitch]] Hasidic movement has traditionally not identified itself as Zionist, although in recent years it has adopted a nationalist agenda and opposed any territorial compromise.

==Particularities of Zionist beliefs==
{{Main|Return to Zion|Aliyah|Racial antisemitism|New antisemitism|Religious antisemitism|Revival of the Hebrew language}}
{{See also|Yiddish|Ladino language|Hebraization of surnames}}

Zionism was established with the goal of creating a Jewish state. Though later Zionist leaders hoped to create a Jewish state in Eretz Yisrael, Theodor Herzl &quot;approached Great Britain about possible Jewish settlement in that country's East African colonies.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Tessler, Mark. A History of the Israeli-Palestinian Conflict. Indiana University Press, 1994. 47. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Aliyah]] (migration, literally &quot;ascent&quot;) to the Land of Israel is a recurring theme in Jewish prayers. Some Zionists consider Jews outside of Israel as living in exile.&lt;ref&gt;[http://esraten.com/all%20EN/okaia/OK--20.html Esraten.com]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Negation of the Diaspora|Rejection of life in the Diaspora]] is a central assumption in Zionism.&lt;ref&gt;E. Schweid, 'Rejection of the Diaspora in Zionist Thought', in ''Essential Papers on Zionism'', ed. By Reinharz &amp; Shapira, 1996, ISBN 0-8147-7449-0, p.133&lt;/ref&gt; Underlying this attitude is the feeling that the Diaspora restricts the full growth of Jewish individual and national life.

Zionists generally preferred to speak [[Hebrew]], a [[Semitic language]] that developed under conditions of freedom in ancient [[Kingdom of Judah|Judah]], modernizing and adapting it for everyday use. Zionists sometimes refused to speak [[Yiddish]], a language they considered affected by [[Christianity and antisemitism|Christian persecution]]. Once they moved to Israel, many Zionists refused to speak their (diasporic) mother tongues and gave themselves new, Hebrew names. Hebrew was preferred not only for ideological reasons, but also because it allowed members of the new Yishuv who came from different parts of the world to have a common language, thus furthering the political and cultural bonds between Zionists.

Major aspects of the Zionist idea are represented in the [[Israeli Declaration of Independence]]:

{{Quote|The Land of Israel was the birthplace of the Jewish people. Here their spiritual, religious and political identity was shaped. Here they first attained to statehood, created cultural values of national and universal significance and gave to the world the eternal Book of Books.

After being forcibly exiled from their land, the people kept faith with it throughout their Dispersion and never ceased to pray and hope for their return to it and for the restoration in it of their political freedom.

Impelled by this historic and traditional attachment, Jews strove in every successive generation to re-establish themselves in their ancient homeland. In recent decades they returned in their masses.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harris&quot;&gt;Harris, J. (1998) [http://etext.virginia.edu/journals/tr/archive/volume7/harris.html The Israeli Declaration of Independence] The Journal of the Society for Textual Reasoning, Vol. 7&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Zionism is dedicated to fighting antisemitism. Some Zionists believe antisemitism will never disappear (and that Jews must conduct themselves with this in mind),&lt;ref&gt;For an example of this view see ''The New Anti-Zionism and the Old Antisemitism: Transformations'' By: Raphael Jospe at [http://www.hagshama.org.il/en/resources/view.asp?id=2095 Hashama.org] accessed November 16, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; while others perceive Zionism as a vehicle with which to end antisemitism.

==History==
{{Main|History of Zionism|History of Israel}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;float:right; margin-left:16px;&quot;
|+ Population of Palestine by ethno-religious groups&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=unispal|title=UNSCOP Report to the General Assembly, Volume 1, CHAPTER II, Par. A.,12 (doc.nr. A/364)|publisher=United Nations Special Committee on Palestine|date=September 3, 1947|url=http://domino.un.org/UNISPAL.NSF/0/07175de9fa2de563852568d3006e10f3|accessdate=2012-05-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! style=&quot;width:50px;&quot;|year
! style=&quot;width:60px;&quot;|[[Islam in Palestine|Muslims]]
! style=&quot;width:60px;&quot;|[[Yishuv|Jews]]
! style=&quot;width:60px;&quot;|[[Palestinian Christians|Christians]]
! style=&quot;width:60px;&quot;|Others
! style=&quot;width:50px;&quot;|Total
|- style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;
||1922
||486,177 ''(74.91%)''
||83,790 ''(12.91%)''
||71,464 ''(11.01%)''
||7,617 ''(1.17%)''
||649,048
|- style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;
||1931
||493,147 ''(64.32%)''
||174,606 ''(22.77%)''
||88,907 ''(11.60%)''
||10,101 ''(1.32%)''
||766,761
|- style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;
||1941
||906,551 ''(59.68%)''
||474,102 ''(31.21%)''
||125,413 ''(8.26%)''
||12,881 ''(0.85%)''
||1,518,947
|- style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;
||1946
||1,076,783 ''(58.34%)''
||608,225 ''(32.96%)''
||145,063 ''(7.86%)''
||15,488 ''(0.84%)''
||1,845,559
|- style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;
||1950
||116,100
||1,203,000
||
||
||
|}
[[File:Theodore Herzl.jpg|thumb|right|[[Theodor Herzl]]]]
[[File:Delegates at First Zionist Congress.jpg|300px|right|thumb|The delegates at the [[First Zionist Congress]], held in [[Basel]], Switzerland (1897).]]

Since the first centuries CE most Jews have lived outside [[Land of Israel]] (Eretz Israel, better known as [[Palestine]] by non-Jews), although there has been a constant presence of Jews. According to Judaism, [[Eretz Israel]] is a land promised to the Jews by God according to the Bible. The Diaspora began in 586 BCE during the Babylonian occupation of Israel. The Babylonians destroyed the First Temple, which was central to Jewish culture at the time. After the 1st century [[Great Revolt]] and the 2nd century [[Bar Kokhba revolt]], the [[Roman Empire|Romans]] expelled the Jews from [[Judea]], changing the name to ''Syria Palaestina.'' The Bar Kokhba revolt caused a spike in anti-Semitism and Jewish persecution. The ensuing exile from Judea greatly increased the percent of Jews who were dispersed throughout the Diaspora instead of living in their original home.

[[Mount Zion|Zion]] is a hill near Jerusalem (now in the city), widely symbolizing the Land of Israel.

In the middle of the sixteenth century [[Joseph Nasi]], with the support of the [[Ottoman Empire]], tried to gather the Portuguese Jews, first to [[Cyprus]], then owned by the Republic of Venice and later to Tiberias. This was the only practical attempt to establish some sort of Jewish political center in Palestine between the fourth and 19th centuries.&lt;ref&gt;Joshep Nasi, Jewish Virtual Library, http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/biography/JosephNasi.html&lt;/ref&gt; In the seventeenth century [[Sabbatai Zebi]] (1626–1676) announced himself as the Messias and gained over many Jews to his side, forming a base in Salonica. He first tried to establish a settlement in Gaza, but moved later to Smyrna. After deposing the old rabbi [[Aaron Lapapa]] even the Jewish community of [[Avignon]]  prepared to emigrate to the new kingdom in the spring of 1666. The readiness of the Jews of the time to believe the messianic claims of Sabbatai Zevi may be largely explained by the desperate state of European Jewry in the mid-17th century. The bloody pogroms of [[Bohdan Khmelnytsky]] had wiped out one third of the Jewish population and destroyed many centers of Jewish learning and communal life. Finally, he was forced by the Ottoman Sultan [[Mehmed IV]] to visit him and, to the surprise of his followers, in the presence of the Sultan he converted to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;Cohen, 1948&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jewish Encyclopedia, Shabbethai Zebi, http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=531&amp;letter=S&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 19th century, a current in Judaism supporting a [[return to Zion]] grew in popularity,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lds.org/churchhistory/0,15478,3900-1,00.html#FlashPluginDetected Lds.org]&lt;/ref&gt; particularly in Europe, where antisemitism and hostility towards Jews were also growing, although this idea was rejected by the conferences of rabbis held in that epoch. Nonetheless, individual efforts supported the emigration of groups of Jews to Palestine, [[Aliyah#Pre-Zionist aliyah|pre-Zionist Aliyah]], even before 1897, the year considered as the start of practical Zionism.&lt;ref&gt;C.D. Smith, 2001, 'Palestine and the Arab-Israeli conflict', 4th ed., ISBN 0-312-20828-6, p. 1-12, 33–38&lt;/ref&gt;

The Reformed Jews rejected this idea of a return to Zion. The conference of rabbis, at [[Frankfurt am Main]], July 15–28, 1845, deleted from the ritual all prayers for a return to Zion and a restoration of a Jewish state. The Philadelphia conference, 1869, followed the lead of the German rabbis and decreed that the Messianic hope of Israel is &quot;the union of all the children of God in the confession of the unity of God&quot;. The Pittsburg conference, 1885, reiterated this Messianic idea of reformed Judaism, expressing in a resolution that &quot;we consider ourselves no longer a nation, but a religious community; and we therefore expect neither a return to Palestine, nor a sacrificial worship under the sons of Aaron, nor the restoration of any of the laws concerning a Jewish state&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Jewish Encyclopedia, Zionism, http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=132&amp;letter=Z&lt;/ref&gt;

Jewish settlements were established in the upper Mississippi region by W.D. Robinson in 1819 and near Jerusalem, by the American Consul [[Warder Cresson]], a convert to Judaism, in 1850. Before he succeeded, he was tried and condemned for lunacy in a suit brought forward by his own wife and son; after winning a second trial he established a colony in the [[Valley of Rephaim]], where he hoped to &quot;prevent any attempts being made to take advantage of the necessities of our poor brethren&amp;nbsp;... (that would)&amp;nbsp;... FORCE them into a pretended conversion.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Jewish Virtual Library, Warder Cresson, http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/biography/Cresson.html&lt;/ref&gt; Similar efforts were made in Prague, by [[Abraham Benisch]] and [[Moritz Steinschneider]] in 1835.

Sir [[Moses Montefiore]], famous for his intervention in favor of Jews around the world, including the attempt to rescue [[Edgardo Mortara]], established a colony for Jews in Palestine. In 1854, his friend [[Judah Touro]] bequeathed money to fund Jewish residential settlement in Palestine. Montefiore was appointed executor of his will, and used the funds for a variety of projects, including building in 1860 the first Jewish residential settlement and almshouse outside of the old walled city of Jerusalem&amp;nbsp;— today known as [[Mishkenot Sha'ananim]]. [[Laurence Oliphant (author)|Laurence Oliphant]] failed in a like attempt to bring to Palestine the Jewish proletariat of Poland, Lithuania, Romania, and the Turkish Empire (1879 and 1882). The official beginning of the construction of the [[New Yishuv]] in Palestine is usually dated back to the arrival of the [[Bilu]] group in 1882, which commenced the [[First Aliyah]].  In the following years, Jewish immigration to Palestine started in earnest. Most [[Jewish refugees|immigrants]] came from Russia, escaping the frequent [[pogrom]]s and state-led persecution. They founded a number of agricultural settlements with financial support from Jewish philanthropists in Western Europe. Further Aliyahs followed the [[Russian Revolution (1917)|Russian Revolution]] and [[Nazi]] persecution. However, at the end of the XIX century, Jews still were a minority in Palestina.

In the 1890s, [[Theodor Herzl]] infused Zionism with a new [[Der Judenstaat|ideology]] and practical urgency, leading to the [[First Zionist Congress]] at [[Basel]] in 1897, which created the [[World Zionist Organization]] (WZO).&lt;ref&gt;[http://fusion.dalmatech.com/%7Eadmin24/files/zionism_in-britishpalestine.pdf Zionism &amp; The British In Palestine], by [[Arjun Charan Sethi|Sethi, Arjun]] (University of Maryland) January 2007, accessed May 20, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Herzl's [[First Zionist Congress#Basel program|aim]] was to initiate necessary preparatory steps for the attainment of a Jewish state. Herzl's attempts to reach a political agreement with the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] rulers of Palestine were unsuccessful and other governmental support was sought. The WZO supported small-scale settlement in Palestine and focused on strengthening Jewish feeling and consciousness and on building a worldwide federation.

The Russian Empire, with its long record of state organized genocide and ethnic cleansing (&quot;pogroms&quot;) was widely regarded as the historic enemy of the Jewish people. As much of its leadership were German speakers, the Zionist movement's headquarters were located in Berlin. At the start of World War I, most Jews (and Zionists) supported Germany in its war with Russia.

Lobbying by a Russian Jewish immigrant, [[Chaim Weizmann]] and fear that [[American Jews]] would encourage the USA to support Germany culminated in the [[Balfour Declaration]] of 1917 by the British government (the Zionist congress had decided already by 1903 to decline an offer by the British to establish a homeland in Uganda). This endorsed the creation of a Jewish Homeland in Palestine. In addition, a Zionist military corps led by [[Jabotinsky]] were recruited to fight on behalf of Britain in Palestine.

In 1922, the [[League of Nations]] adopted the declaration in the [[British Mandate of Palestine|Mandate it gave to Britain]]:

{{quote|The Mandatory (…) will secure the establishment of the Jewish national home, as laid down in the preamble, and the development of self-governing institutions, and also for safeguarding the civil and religious rights of all the inhabitants of Palestine, irrespective of race and religion.|&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stateofisrael.com/mandate League of Nations Palestine Mandate, July 24, 1922]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Weizmann's role in obtaining the Balfour Declaration led to his election as the movement's leader. He remained in that role until 1948 and then became the first [[President of Israel]].

Jewish migration to Palestine and widespread Jewish land purchases from feudal landlords led to landlessness and fueled unrest&amp;nbsp;— often led by the same landlords who sold the land. There were riots in 1920, 1921 and 1929, sometimes accompanied by massacres of Jews&lt;ref&gt;[[Peel Commission]] report 1937, chapter 3.&lt;/ref&gt; The victims were usually from the non-Zionist Haredi Jewish communities in the [[Four Holy Cities]]. Britain supported Jewish immigration in principle, but in reaction to Arab violence imposed restrictions.

In 1933, [[Hitler]] came to power in Germany, and in 1935 the [[Nuremberg Laws]] made German Jews (and later [[Anschluss|Austrian]] and [[Czech Jews]]) stateless refugees. Similar rules were applied by the many [[Axis powers|Nazi allies]] in Europe. The subsequent growth in Jewish migration and impact of [[Nazi propaganda]] aimed at the Arab world led to the [[1936–1939 Arab revolt in Palestine]]. Britain established the [[Peel Commission]] to investigate the situation. The commission did not consider the situation of Jews in Europe, but called for a two-state solution and compulsory [[Population transfer|transfer of populations]].  Britain rejected this solution and instead implemented [[White Paper of 1939]]. This planned to end Jewish immigration by 1944 and to allow no more than 75,000 further Jewish migrants. This was disastrous to European Jews already being gravely discriminated against and in need of a place to seek refuge. The British maintained this policy until the end of the Mandate.

Growth of the Jewish community in Palestine and devastation of European Jewish life sidelined the World Zionist Organization. The Jewish Agency for Palestine under the leadership of [[David Ben-Gurion]] increasingly dictated policy with support from American Zionists who provided funding and influence in Washington, D.C., including via the highly effective [[American Palestine Committee]].

[[File:Declaration of State of Israel 1948.jpg|thumb|right|[[David Ben-Gurion]] proclaiming Israel's independence beneath a large portrait of [[Theodor Herzl]].]]
After World War II and [[the Holocaust]], a massive wave of [[Sh'erit ha-Pletah|stateless Jews]], mainly [[Holocaust survivors]], began [[Aliyah Bet|migrating to Palestine]] in small boats in defiance of British rules. The Holocaust united much of the rest of world Jewry behind the Zionist project.&lt;ref name=miracle&gt;{{cite journal|last=Johnson|first=Paul|title=The Miracle|journal=Commentary|year=1998|month=May|volume=105|pages=pp 21–28|accessdate=August 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The British either [[Cyprus internment camps|imprisoned these Jews in Cyprus]] (including many orphaned children) or [[sS Exodus|sent them]] to the British-controlled [[Allied Occupation Zones in Germany]]. This resulted in universal Jewish support for Zionism and the refusal of the U.S. Congress to grant economic aid to Britain. In addition, Zionist groups [[British–Zionist conflict|attacked the British in Palestine]] and, with its empire facing bankruptcy, Britain was forced to refer the issue to the newly created United Nations.

In 1947, the [[United Nations Special Committee on Palestine]] (UNSCOP) recommended that western Palestine should be partitioned into a Jewish state, an Arab state and a [[Corpus separatum (Jerusalem)|UN-controlled territory, ''Corpus separatum'', around Jerusalem]].&lt;ref&gt;United Nations Special Committee on Palestine; report to the General Assembly, A/364, September 3, 1947&lt;/ref&gt; This [[United Nations Partition Plan for Palestine|partition plan]] was adopted on November 29, 1947 with [[United Nations Partition Plan for Palestine|UN GA Resolution 181]], 33 votes in favor, 13 against, and 10 abstentions. The vote led to celebrations in the streets of Jewish cities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://youtube.com/watch?v=rEGUPlhtMWQ Three minutes, 2000 years], Video from the Jewish Agency for Israel, via YouTube&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Palestinian Arabs and the Arab states rejected the UN decision, demanding a single state and removal of Jewish migrants, leading to the [[1948 Arab–Israeli War]].

On May 14, 1948, at the end of the [[British Mandate of Palestine|British mandate]], the Jewish Agency, led by [[David Ben-Gurion]], declared the creation of the State of Israel, and the same day the armies of seven [[1948 Arab–Israeli War|Arab countries invaded Israel]]. The conflict led to an exodus of about [[1948 Palestinian exodus|711,000 Arab Palestinians]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://unispal.un.org/UNISPAL.NSF/0/93037E3B939746DE8525610200567883 General Progress Report and Supplementary Report of the United Nations Conciliation Commission for Palestine, Covering the period from December 11, 1949 to October 23, 1950],(doc.nr. 	A/1367/Rev.1); October 23, 1950&lt;/ref&gt;    known to Palestinians as [[Al Nakba]] (the &quot;catastrophe&quot;),  and the [[Jewish exodus from Arab lands|exodus of 850,000 Jews]] from the Arab world, mostly to Israel. Later, [[Land and Property laws in Israel#The 'Absentees Property Law'|a series of laws]] passed by the first Israeli government prevented Palestinians from returning to their homes, or claiming their property. They and many of their descendants remain [[Palestinian refugees|refugees]].&lt;ref&gt;Kodmani-Darwish, p. 126; Féron, Féron, p. 94.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;UNRWA&quot;&gt;http://www.unrwa.org/etemplate.php?id=87&lt;/ref&gt; The expulsion of the Palestinians has since been widely, and controversially, described as having involved &quot;[[ethnic cleansing]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=IANBLACK&gt;{{cite news |title=Memories and maps keep alive Palestinian hopes of return |author=Ian Black |newspaper=The Guardian |date=November 26, 2010 |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2010/nov/26/palestinian-refugees-middle-east-conflict }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=morris_shavit&gt;Shavit, Ari. [http://www.logosjournal.com/morris.htm Survival of the Fittest? An Interview with Benny Morris]. Logos. Winter 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

Since the creation of the State of Israel, the [[World Zionist Organization]] has functioned mainly as an organization dedicated to assisting and encouraging Jews to migrate to Israel. It has provided political support for Israel in other countries but plays little role in internal Israeli politics. The movement's major success since 1948 was in providing logistical support for migrating Jews and, most importantly, in assisting [[Soviet Jews]] in their struggle with the authorities over the right to leave the [[USSR]] and to practice their religion in freedom.

==Non-Jewish support for Zionism==
Political support for the Jewish return to the Land of Israel predates the formal organization of Jewish Zionism as a political movement. In the 19th century, advocates of the [[Restoration of the Jews to the Holy Land]] were called Restorationists. The return of the Jews to the Holy Land was widely supported by such eminent figures as [[Queen Victoria]], [[Napoleon Bonaparte]],&lt;ref&gt;http://www.haaretz.com/print-edition/news/herzl-hinted-at-napoleon-s-zionist-past-1.120723 Herzl hinted at Napoleon's 'Zionist past'&lt;/ref&gt; [[King Edward VII]], President [[John Adams]] of the United States, [[Jan Smuts|General Smuts]] of South Africa, [[Tomáš Garrigue Masaryk|President Masaryk]] of [[Czechoslovakia]], philosopher and historian [[Benedetto Croce]] from Italy, [[Henry Dunant]] (founder of the [[Red Cross]] and author of the [[Geneva Conventions]]), and scientist and humanitarian [[Fridtjof Nansen]] from [[Norway]].

The French government through Minister M. Cambon formally committed itself to &quot;...&amp;nbsp;the renaissance of the Jewish nationality in that Land from which the people of Israel were exiled so many centuries ago.&quot;

In China, top figures of the [[Kuomintang|Nationalist government]], including [[Sun Yat-sen]], expressed their sympathy with the aspirations of the Jewish people for a National Home.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |last=Goldstein |first=Jonathan |year=1999 |contribution=The Republic of China and Israel |editor-last=Goldstein |editor-first=Jonathan |title=China and Israel, 1948–1998: A Fifty Year Retrospective |pages=1–39 |place=Westport, Conn. and London |publisher=Praeger}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Christians supporting Zionism===
{{Main|Christian Zionism}}
Some Christians have actively supported the return of Jews to Palestine even prior to Zionism, as well as subsequently. One of the principal Protestant teachers who promoted the biblical doctrine that the Jews would return to their national homeland was [[John Nelson Darby]]. He is credited with being the major promoter of the idea following his 11 lectures on the hopes of the church, the Jew and the gentile given in Geneva in 1840. His views were embraced by many evangelicals and also affected international foreign policy. Notable early supporters of Zionism include British Prime Ministers [[David Lloyd George]] and [[Arthur Balfour]], American President [[Woodrow Wilson]] and British [[Major-general (United Kingdom)|Major-General]] [[Orde Wingate]], whose activities in support of Zionism led the British Army to ban him from ever serving in Palestine. According to Charles Merkley of Carleton University, Christian Zionism strengthened significantly after the [[Six-Day War]] of 1967, and many [[Dispensationalism|dispensationalist]] Christians, especially in the United States, now strongly support Zionism.

The founder of [[Latter Day Saint movement]], [[Joseph Smith, Jr.]], in his last years alive, declared &quot;the time for Jews to return to the land of Israel is now.&quot; In 1842, Smith sent [[Orson Hyde]], an Apostle of the [[Church of Christ (Latter Day Saints)|Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints]], to Jerusalem to dedicate the land for the return of the Jews.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.signaturebookslibrary.org/Jews/jewsch6.htm |title=Orson Hyde and Israel's Restoration |publisher=Signaturebookslibrary.org |accessdate=June 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some [[Arab Christians]] publicly supporting Israel include US author [[Nonie Darwish]], and former Muslim [[Magdi Allam]], author of ''Viva Israele'',&lt;ref&gt;ISBN 978-88-04-56777-6&lt;/ref&gt; both born in Egypt. [[Brigitte Gabriel]], a Lebanese-born Christian US journalist and founder of the [[American Congress for Truth]], urges Americans to &quot;fearlessly speak out in defense of America, Israel and Western civilization&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=anonymous|title=Mission/Vision|publisher=American Congress for Truth|date=unknown|url=http://americancongressfortruth.com/mission-vision.asp|accessdate=April 17, 2008 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080324132304/http://www.americancongressfortruth.com/mission-vision.asp &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = March 24, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Muslims supporting Zionism===
{{Main|Muslim Zionism}}
In 1873, [[Qajar dynasty|Shah of Persia]] [[Naser al-Din Shah Qajar]] met with British Jewish leaders, including Sir [[Moses Montefiore]], during his journey to Europe. At that time, the Persian king suggested that the Jews buy land and establish a state for the Jewish people.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worldjewishcongress.org/communities/mideast/comm_iran.html World Jewish Congress&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Muslims who publicly defended Zionism include Dr. [[Tawfik Hamid]], former member of a terror organization and current Islamic thinker and reformer,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.tawfikhamid.com |title=Dr. Tawfik Hamid's Official Website- Part of the Potomac Institute of Policy Studies |publisher=Tawfikhamid.com |accessdate=June 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sheikh Prof. [[Abdul Hadi Palazzi]], Director of the Cultural Institute of the Italian Islamic Community,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.frontpagemag.com/Articles/Printable.aspx?GUID={4E73EA93-5E8C-492D-9EC7-716F1342DDC6} |title=FPM Article |publisher=Frontpagemag.com |accessdate=June 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Tashbih Sayyed]], a Pakistani-American scholar, journalist, and author.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Neuwirth |first=Rachel |url=http://www.islam-watch.org/Others/Tashbih-Sayyed-A%20Fearless-Muslim-Zionist.htm |title=Tashbih Sayyed ― A Fearless Muslim Zionist |publisher=Islam Watch |date=June 24, 2007 |accessdate=June 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On occasion, some non-Arab Muslims such as some [[Kurds]] and [[Berber people|Berbers]] have also voiced support for Zionism.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Islam, Islam, Laïcité, and Amazigh Activism in France and North Africa&quot; (2004 paper), Paul A. Silverstein, Department of Anthropology, Reed College&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Why not a Kurdish-Israeli alliance?&quot;&gt;[http://www.iran-press-service.com/ips/articles-2004/august/israel_kurds_11804.shtml Why not a Kurdish-Israeli Alliance? (Iran Press Service)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| last = anonymous| title = Berbers, Where Do You Stand on Palestine?| publisher = MEMRI| date = February 26, 2009| url = http://www.memri.org/bin/latestnews.cgi?ID=SD226209| accessdate =March 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the Palestine Mandate era, [[As'ad Shukeiri]], a Muslim scholar ('alim) of the Acre area, and the father of [[PLO]] founder [[Ahmad Shukeiri]], rejected the values of the Palestinian Arab national movement and was opposed to the [[anti-Zionist]] movement.&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopedia of the modern Middle East, Volume 4, Reeva S. Simon, Philip Mattar, Richard W. Bulliet. Macmillan Reference USA, 1996. p. 1661&lt;/ref&gt; He met routinely with [[Zionist]] officials and had a part in every pro-Zionist Arab organization from the beginning of the [[British Mandate for Palestine|British Mandate]], publicly rejecting [[Mohammad Amin al-Husayni]]'s use of Islam to attack Zionism.&lt;ref name=&quot;shadows1&quot;&gt;Army of Shadows: Palestinian Collaboration with Zionism, 1917–1948. By Hillel Cohen. University of California Press, 2009. p. 84&lt;/ref&gt;

Some Indian Muslims have also expressed opposition to [[Anti-Zionism#Muslim|Islamic anti-Zionism]]. In August 2007, a delegation of the All India Organization of [[Imam (Sunni Islam)|Imams]] and mosques led by [[Maulana Jamil Ilyas]] visited Israel. The meet led to a joint statement expressing &quot;peace and goodwill from Indian Muslims&quot;, developing dialogue between Indian Muslims and Israeli Jews, and rejecting the perception that the [[Israeli-Palestinian conflict]] is of a religious nature.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indianmuslims.info/news/2007/aug/15/american_jewish_group_takes_indian_muslims_israel.html American Jewish group takes Indian Muslims to Israel | Indian Muslims&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The visit was organized by the [[American Jewish Committee]]. The purpose of the visit was to create meaningful debate about the status of Israel in the Muslim eyes worldwide, and strengthen the relationship between India and Israel. It is suggested that the visit could
&quot;open Muslim minds across the world to understand the democratic nature of the state of Israel, especially in the Middle East&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://yaleglobal.yale.edu/content/dialogue-democracy-indian-muslims-visit-israel Dialogue of Democracy: Indian Muslims Visit Israel | YaleGlobal Online Magazine&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hindu support for Zionism===
{{Main|India–Israel relations}}
After Israel's creation in 1948, the [[Indian National Congress]] government opposed Zionism. Some writers have claimed that this was in order to get more Muslim votes in India (where Muslims numbered over 30 million at the time).&lt;ref name=&quot;kap&quot;&gt;[http://www.southasiaanalysis.org/papers2/paper131.html INDIA&amp;nbsp;— ISRAEL RELATIONS: THE IMPERATIVES FOR ENHANCED STRATEGIC COOPERATION&amp;nbsp;— Subhash Kapila]&amp;nbsp;— [[South Asia Analysis Group]]&lt;/ref&gt; However, conservative Hindu nationalists, led by the [[Sangh Parivar]], openly supported Zionism, as did Hindu Nationalist intellectuals like [[Vinayak Damodar Savarkar]] and [[Sita Ram Goel]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Hindu pro-Zionism&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.scribd.com/doc/9680428/Hindu-ProZionism-and-PhiloSemitism |title=Hindu Pro-Zionism and Philo-Semitism |publisher=Scribd |date=December 30, 2008 |accessdate=June 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Zionism as a national liberation movement to repatriate the Jewish people to their ancestral homeland appealed to many [[Hindu Nationalist]]s, who viewed their struggle for [[Indian Independence Movement|independence from British rule]] and the [[Partition of India]] as national liberation for [[Persecution of Hindus|long-oppressed]] Hindus.

An international opinion survey has shown that India is the most pro-Israel country in the world.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ynet.co.il/english/articles/0,7340,L-3696887,00.html ynet article]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://netwmd.com/blog/2009/04/22/3955 netwmd article].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.danielpipes.org/blog/2009/04/india-the-most-pro-israel-country daniel pipes article]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://digg.com/world_news/India_the_Most_Pro_Israel_Country digg article].&lt;/ref&gt; In more current times, conservative Indian parties and organizations tend to support Zionism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hindu pro-Zionism&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://us.rediff.com/news/2003/sep/10sharon11.htm |title=RSS slams Left for opposing Sharon's visit: Rediff.com India News |publisher=Us.rediff.com |date=September 10, 2003 |accessdate=June 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; This has invited attacks on the [[Hindutva]] movement by parts of the Indian left opposed to Zionism, and allegations that Hindus are conspiring with the &quot;[[Jewish Lobby]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://ghadar.insaf.net/June2004/MainPages/zionism.htm |title=G h a d a r . 2 0 0 4 |publisher=Ghadar.insaf.net |accessdate=June 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Marcus Garvey and Black Zionism==
{{See also|Alliance of Black Jews|Jews and Judaism in the African diaspora}}
Zionist success in winning British support for formation of a Jewish National Home in Palestine helped to inspire the Jamaican nationalist [[Marcus Garvey]] to form a movement dedicated to returning Americans of African origin to Africa. During a speech in [[Harlem]] in 1920, Garvey stated: &quot;other races were engaged in seeing their cause through&amp;nbsp;— the Jews through their Zionist movement and the Irish through their Irish movement&amp;nbsp;— and I decided that, cost what it might, I would make this a favorable time to see the Negro's interest through.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''[[Negro World]]'' March 6, 1920, cited in [http://www.international.ucla.edu/africa/mgpp/lifeintr.asp University of California, Los Angeles] (accessed November 29, 2007)&lt;/ref&gt;
Garvey established a shipping company, the [[Black Star Line]], to allow Black Americans to emigrate to Africa, but for various reasons failed in his endeavour.

Garvey helped inspire the [[Rastafari movement]] in Jamaica, the [[Black Jews]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.blackjews.org/RabbiBios/RabbiFord.html BlackJews.org&amp;nbsp;— A Project of the International Board of Rabbis&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[African Hebrew Israelites of Jerusalem]] who initially moved to Liberia before settling in Israel.

==Opposition to Zionism==
 
{{Main|Anti-Zionism|Timeline of Anti-Zionism}}
{{See also|Non-Zionism|Post-Zionism|Neo-Zionism|New Antisemitism|Criticism of Israel}}

Zionism is opposed by a wide variety of organizations and individuals. Among those opposing Zionism are some secular Jews,&lt;ref&gt;
*{{Cite web|title=The First National Jewish Anti-Zionist Gathering|url=http://www.jewsconfrontapartheid.org/|accessdate=September 17, 2010}}
*{{Cite web|title=Not In Our Name . . Jewish voices opposing Zionism|url=http://www.nion.ca/|accessdate=September 17, 2010}}
*{{Cite web|title=Jews Against Zionism|url=http://www.jewsagainstzionism.org|accessdate=September 17, 2010}}
*{{Cite web|title=International Jewish Anti-Zionist Network|url=http://www.ijsn.net/home/|accessdate=September 17, 2010}}
*{{cite web|title=Charter of the International Jewish anti-Zionist Network |url=http://www.ijsn.net/about_us/charter/|publisher=International Jewish anti-Zionist Network |accessdate=October 29, 2010}}
&lt;/ref&gt; some branches of Judaism ([[Satmar (Hasidic dynasty)|Satmar]] Hasidim and  [[Neturei Karta]]), the former Soviet Union,&lt;ref&gt;{{ru icon}} [http://encycl.yandex.ru/art.xml?art=bse/00071/37300.htm&amp;encpage=bse&amp;mrkp=http%3A//hghltd.yandex.com/yandbtm%3Furl%3Dhttp%253A//encycl.yandex.ru/texts/bse/00071/37300.htm%26text%3D%25F1%25E8%25EE%25ED%25E8%25E7%25EC%26reqtext%3D%25F1%25E8%25EE%25ED%25E8%25E7%25EC%253A%253A781659%26%26isu%3D2 Сионизм], Большая советская энциклопедия (Zionism. [[Great Soviet Encyclopedia]], 3rd Edition. 1969–1978)&lt;/ref&gt;  some African-Americans,&lt;ref&gt;
*West, Cornell, ''Race Matters'', 1993. pp 73–74
*Dollinger, Mark, &quot;African American-Jewish Relations&quot; in ''Antisemitism: a historical encyclopedia of prejudice and persecution, Vol 1, 2005.'', p 4-5&quot;
*Hacker, Andrew (1999) &quot;Jewish Racism, Black anti-Semitism&quot;, in ''Strangers &amp; neighbors: relations between Blacks &amp; Jews in the United States'', Maurianne Adams (Ed.). Univ of Massachusetts Press, 1999. p. 20
&lt;/ref&gt; many in the Muslim world, and Palestinians. Reasons for opposing Zionism are varied, and include the perceptions of unfair land confiscation, expulsions of Palestinians, violence against Palestinians, and alleged racism. Arab states in particular strongly oppose Zionism, which they believe is responsible for the [[1948 Palestinian exodus]].

Zionism had also been opposed by some Jews for other reasons even before the establishment of the state of Israel because &quot;Zionism constitutes a danger, spiritual and physical, to the existence of our people.'.&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Holocaust Victims Accuse&quot; by Reb. Moshe Shonfeld; Bnei Yeshivos NY, NY; (1977)&lt;/ref&gt; The book also states &quot;The booklet which we are publishing here, 'Serufay. Ha Kivshbnim Maashimim' ('The Holocaust Victims Accuse'), serves as an attempt to show, by means of testimonies., documents and reports, how Zionism and its high-level organizations brought a catastrophe upon our people during the era of the Nazi holocaust.&quot;

===Catholic Church and Zionism===

The initial response of the Catholic Church seemed to be one of strong opposition to Zionism. Shortly after the 1897 Basle Conference, the semi-official Vatican periodical (edited by the Jesuits) [[Civilta Cattolica]] gave its biblical-theological judgement on political Zionism: &quot;1827 years have passed since the prediction of Jesus of Nazareth was fulfilled&amp;nbsp;... that [after the destruction of Jerusalem] the Jews would be led away to be slaves among all the nations and that they would remain in the dispersion [diaspora, galut] until the end of the world.&quot; The Jews should not be permitted to return to Palestine with sovereignty: &quot;According to the Sacred Scriptures, the Jewish people must always live dispersed and vagabondo [vagrant, wandering] among the other nations, so that they may render witness to Christ not only by the Scriptures&amp;nbsp;... but by their very existence&quot;.

Nonetheless, Theodore Herzl travelled to Rome in late January 1904, after the sixth Zionist Congress (August, 1903) and six months before his death, looking for some kind of support. In January 22, Herzl first met the Secretary of State, Cardinal [[Rafael Merry del Val]]. According to Herzl's private diary notes, the Cardinal agreed on the history of Israel being the same as the one of the Catholic Church, but asked beforehand for a conversion of Jews to Catholicism. Three days later, Herzl met Pope [[Pius X]], who replied to his request of support for a Jewish return to Israel in the same terms, saying that &quot;we are unable to favor this movement. We cannot prevent the Jews going to Jerusalem, but we could never sanction it&amp;nbsp;... The Jews have not recognized our Lord, therefore we cannot recognize the Jewish people.&quot; In 1922 the same recourse of preordained divine judgment in the Bible was utilized by the same periodical to oppose Zionism, alleging that the rejection and [[Death of Jesus|killing of Jesus by the Jews]] condemned them in the eyes of Catholics.{{Citation needed|date=May 2012}} This initial attitude changed over the next 50 years, until 1997, when at the [[Holy See|Vatican]] symposium of that year, Pope [[John Paul II]] rejected the Christian roots of anti-Semitism, expressing that &quot;...&amp;nbsp;the wrong and unjust interpretations of the New Testament relating to the Jewish people and their supposed guilt [in Christ's death] circulated for too long, engendering sentiments of hostility toward this people.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;A Catholic Views&amp;nbsp;— Zionism and the State of Israel, http://198.62.75.1/www1/ofm/mag/MAen9901.html&lt;/ref&gt;

===Characterization as colonialism===
Zionism has been characterized as [[colonialism]], and Zionism has been [[Anti-Zionism|criticized]] for promoting unfair confiscation of land, involving expulsion of indigenous peoples, and causing violence towards Palestinians. The characterization of Zionism as colonialism has been described by, among others, [[Nur Masalha]], Gershon Shafir, [[Michael Prior (theologian)|Michael Prior]], [[Ilan Pappe]], and  [[Baruch Kimmerling]].&lt;ref name=CHARCOL&gt;
*Shafir, Gershon, ''Being Israeli: the dynamics of multiple citizenship'', 	Cambridge University Press, 2002, pp 37–38
*Bareli, Avi, &quot;Forgetting Europe: Perspectives on the Debate about Zionism and Colonialism&quot;, in ''Israeli historical revisionism: from left to right'',  Psychology Press, 2003, pp 99–116
*[[Ilan Pappe|Pappé Ilan]], ''A history of modern Palestine: one land, two peoples'', Cambridge University Press, 2006, pp 72–121
*Prior, Michael, ''The Bible and colonialism: a moral critique'',  Continuum International Publishing Group, 1997, pp 106–215
*Shafir, Gershon, &quot;Zionism and Colonialism&quot;, in ''The Israel / Palestinian Question'', by Ilan Pappe,  Psychology Press, 1999, pp 72–85
*Lustick, Ian, ''For the Land and the Lord'' …
*Zuriek, Elia, ''The Palestinians in Israel:  A Study in Internal Colonialism'',  Routledge &amp; K. Paul, 1979
*Penslar, Derek J., &quot;Zionism, Colonialism and Postcolonialism&quot;, in ''Israeli historical revisionism: from left to right'',  Psychology Press, 2003, pp 85–98
*[[Ilan Pappé|Pappe, Ilan]], ''The ethnic cleansing of Palestine'',	Oneworld, 2007
*{{citation|title=The Bible and Zionism: invented traditions, archaeology and post-colonialism in Palestine-Israel|volume=1|last=Masalha|first=Nur|year=2007|publisher=Zed Books|page=16}}
*{{citation|title=The Dark Side of Zionism: Israel's Quest for Security Through Dominance|last=Thomas|first=Baylis|publisher=Lexington Books|year=2011|page=4}}
*{{citation|title=Zionism and the state of Israel: a moral inquiry|last=Prior|first=Michael|publisher=Psychology Press|year=1999|page=240}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

Others, such as [[Shlomo Avineri]] and [[Mitchell Bard]], view Zionism not as colonialist movement, but as a national movement that is contending with the Palestinian one.&lt;ref&gt;
* [http://www.haaretz.com/print-edition/opinion/post-zionism-doesn-t-exist-1.224973 Post-Zionism doesn't exist]. Shlomo Avineri.
* [http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/Zionism/colonial.html Zionism Is Not Colonialism]. By Mitchell Bard.&lt;/ref&gt; [[David Hoffman]] rejected the claim that Zionism is a 'settler-colonial undertaking' and instead characterized Zionism as a national program of [[affirmative action]], adding that there is unbroken Jewish presence in Israel back to antiquity.&lt;ref&gt;Hoffman, David. Zionism is not a 'settler-colonial undertaking'. The Mail &amp; Guardian, South Africa. June 28, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Noam Chomsky]], John P. Quigly, [[Nur Masalha]], and [[Cheryl Rubenberg]] have criticised Zionism, saying it unfairly confiscates land and expels Palestinians.&lt;ref&gt;
*{{cite book
|title=The Holy Land in transit: colonialism and the quest for Canaan
|first=Steven George
|last=Salaita
|publisher=Syracuse University Press
|year=2006
|isbn=0-8156-3109-X
|page= 54
}}
*{{cite book
|title=The gun and the olive branch: the roots of violence in the Middle East
|first=David
|last=Hirst
|publisher=Nation Books
|authorlink=David Hirst (journalist)
|year= 2003
|isbn=1-56025-483-1
|pages= 418–419
}}
*{{cite book
|title=World orders, old and new
|first=Noam
|last=Chomsky
|authorlink=Noam Chomsky
|publisher=Columbia University Press
|year= 1996
|isbn=0-231-10157-0
|page=264:
}}
*{{cite web
|url= http://97.74.65.51/readArticle.aspx?ARTID=15043
|title=FrontPage magazine interview with Christopher Hitchens
|date=December 11, 2003
|deadurl=yes}} {{dead link|date=September 2010}}
*{{cite book
|title=Imperial Israel and the Palestinians: the politics of expansion
|first=Nur
|last=Masalha
|authorlink=Nur Masalha
|publisher=Pluto Press
|year=2000
|isbn=0-7453-1615-8
|page=93
}}
*{{cite web
|url=http://www.atheistnexus.org/forum/topics/hitchens-dawkins-and-harris
|title=Essay by James M. Martin from &quot;Atheist Nexus&quot;
}}
*{{cite book
|title=Palestine and Israel: a challenge to justice
|first=John B.
|last=Quigley
|publisher=Duke University Press
|year=1990
|isbn=0-8223-1023-6
|pages=176–177
}}
*{{cite book
|title=Fateful triangle: the United States, Israel, and the Palestinians (2nd Ed, revised)
|first=Noam
|last=Chomsky
|publisher=South End Press
|year= 1999
|isbn=0-89608-601-1
|pages=153–154
}}
*Saleh Abdel Jawad (2007) &quot;Zionist Massacres: the Creation of the Palestinian Refugee Problem in the 1948 War&quot; in  ''Israel and the Palestinian refugees'', Eyal Benvenistî, Chaim Gans, Sari Hanafi (Eds.), Springer, p. 78.
*{{cite book
|title=Land or peace: whither Israel?
|first=Yael
|last=Yishai
|publisher=Hoover Press
|year= 1987
|isbn=0-8179-8521-2
|pages= 112–125
}}
*{{cite book
|title=The Palestinians: in search of a just peace
|first=Cheryl
|last=Rubenberg
|publisher=Lynne Rienner Publishers
|authorlink=Cheryl Rubenberg
|year= 2003
|isbn=1-58826-225-1
|page=  162
}}
*{{cite book
|title=Islam and the West post 9/11
|first=Ron
|last=Geaves
|publisher=Ashgate Publishing, Ltd.
|year= 2004
|isbn=0-7546-5005-7
|page= 31
}}
*{{cite book
|title=The Palestine Yearbook of International Law, 1998–1999, Volume 10
|first=Anis F.
|last=Kassim
|publisher=Martinus Nijhoff Publishers
|year= 2000
|isbn=90-411-1304-5
|page=9
}}
*Raphael Israeli, ''Palestinians Between Israel and Jordan''', Prager, 1991, pages 158–159, 171, 182.
&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Edward Said]] and [[Michael Prior (theologian)|Michael Prior]] claim that the notion of expelling the indigenous population was an early component of Zionism, citing Herzl's diary from 1895 which states &quot;we shall endeavour to expel the poor population across the border unnoticed&amp;nbsp;— the process of expropriation and the removal of the poor must be carried out discreetly and circumspectly.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;
*[[Edward W. Said|Said, Edward]], ''The Edward Said reader'',  Random House, Inc., 2000, pp  128–129
*Prior, Michael P. ''Zionism and the state of Israel: a moral inquiry'', Psychology Press, 1999, pp 191–192
*[[Derek Penslar|Penslar, Derek]], ''Israel in history: the Jewish state in comparative perspective'', Taylor &amp; Francis, 2007, p 56.
&lt;/ref&gt; [[Derek Penslar]] says that Herzl may have been considering either South America or Palestine when he wrote the diary entry about expropriation.&lt;ref&gt;
*[[Derek Penslar|Penslar, Derek]], ''Israel in history: the Jewish state in comparative perspective'', Taylor &amp; Francis, 2007, p 56.
&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ilan Pappe]] argued that Zionism results in [[ethnic cleansing]].&lt;ref&gt;
*[[Ilan Pappé|Pappe, Ilan]], ''The ethnic cleansing of Palestine'',	Oneworld, 2007
&lt;/ref&gt; This view diverges from other [[New Historians]], such as [[Benny Morris]], who accept the [[1948 Palestinian exodus|Palestinian exodus]] narrative but place it in the context of war, not ethnic cleansing.&lt;ref&gt;Rane, Halim. Islam and Contemporary Civilisation. Academic Monographs, 2010. ISBN 978-0-522-85728-3. p. 198&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Saleh Abdel Jawad]], [[Nur Masalha]], [[Michael Prior (theologian)|Michael Prior]], [[Ian Lustick]], and [[John Rose (UK politician)|John Rose]] have criticised Zionism for having been responsible for violence against Palestinians, such as the [[Deir Yassin massacre]], [[Sabra and Shatila massacre]], and [[Cave of the Patriarchs massacre]].&lt;ref&gt;
*Khallidi, Walid, &quot;Plan Dalet: The Zionist Master Plan for the Conquest of Palestine&quot;, in ''Middle East Forum'', no. 22, Nov 1961, p 27.
*Weisburd,  David, ''Jewish Settler Violence'', Penn State Press, 1985, pp 20–52
*Lustick, Ian, &quot;Israel's Dangerous Fundamentalists&quot;, ''Foreign Policy'', 68 (Fall 1987), pp 118–139
*Tessler, Mark, &quot;Religion and Politics in the Jewish State of Israel&quot;, in ''‪Religious resurgence and politics in the contemporary world‬'', (Emile Sahliyeh, Ed)., SUNY Press, 1990, pp 263–296.
*{{Cite book
|title=Reckless rites: Purim and the legacy of Jewish violence
|first=Elliott S.
|last=Horowitz
|publisher=Princeton University Press
|year= 2006
|isbn=0-691-12491-4
|pages= 6–11
}}
*{{Cite book
|title=An understanding of Judaism
|first=John D.
|last= Rayner
|isbn=1-57181-971-1
|year= 1997
|page=57}}
*Saleh Abdel Jawad (2007) &quot;Zionist Massacres: the Creation of the Palestinian Refugee Problem in the 1948 War&quot; in  ''Israel and the Palestinian refugees'', Eyal Benvenistî, Chaim Gans, Sari Hanafi (Eds.), Springer, p. 78:
:&quot;.. the Zionist movement, which claims to be secular, found it necessary to embrace the idea of 'the promised land' of Old Testament prophecy, to justify the confiscation of land and the expulsion of the Palestinians.  For example, the speeches and letter of Chaim Weizman, the secular Zionist leader, are filled with references to the biblical origins of the Jewish claim to Palestine, which he often mixes liberally with more pragmatic and nationalistic claims.  By the use of this premise, embraced in 1937, Zionists alleged that the Palestinians were usurpers in the Promised Land, and therefore their expulsion and death was justified.  The Jewish-American writer Dan Kurzman, in his book ''Genesis 1948'' … describes the view of one of the Deir Yassin's killers: 'The Sternists followed the instructions of the Bible more rigidly than others.  They honored the passage (Exodus 22:2): 'If a thief be found …' This meant, of course, that killing  a thief was not really muder.  And were not the enemies of Zionism thieves, who wanted to steal from the Jews what God had granted them?' ''
*Ehrlich, Carl. S., (1999) &quot;Joshua, Judaism, and Genocide&quot;, in ''Jewish Studies at the Turn of the Twentieth Century'', Judit Targarona Borrás, Ángel Sáenz-Badillos (Eds). 1999, Brill. p 117-124.
*Hirst, David, ''The Gun and the Olive Branch: The Roots of Violence in the Middle East''.  1984, p 139.
*Lorch, Netanel, ''The Edge of the Sword:  Israel's War of Independence, 1947–1949'', Putnam, 1961, p 87
*[[Ilan Pappé|Pappe, Ilan]], ''The ethnic cleansing of Palestine'',	Oneworld, 2007, p 88
&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1938, [[Mahatma Gandhi]] rejected Zionism, saying that the establishment of a Jewish national home in Palestine is a religious act and therefore must not be performed by force. He wrote, &quot;Palestine belongs to the Arabs in the same sense that England belongs to the English or France to the French. It is wrong and inhuman to impose the Jews on the Arabs&amp;nbsp;... Surely it would be a crime against humanity to reduce the proud Arabs so that Palestine can be restored to the Jews partly or wholly as their national home&amp;nbsp;... They can settle in Palestine only by the goodwill of the Arabs. They should seek to convert the Arab heart.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;William R. Slomanson. Fundamental Perspectives on International Law. p. 50&lt;/ref&gt;

===Characterization as racist===
{{See also|Racism in Israel#Zionism|Israel, Palestinians, and the United Nations|Israel and the apartheid analogy}}
Critics of Zionism consider it a [[Colonialism|colonialist]]&lt;ref name=CHARCOL /&gt; or [[racism|racist]]&lt;ref name=CHARRAS /&gt; movement. Some scholars consider certain forms of opposition to Zionism to constitute Antisemitism.&lt;ref name=Stauber /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{citation
| first=Kenneth L. | last=Marcus
| title=Anti-Zionism as Racism: Campus Anti-Semitism and the Civil Rights Act of 1964
| journal=William &amp; Mary Bill of Rights Journal
| volume=15 | issue=3
| pages=837–891
| year=2007
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  According to [[new historian]] [[Avi Shlaim]], throughout its history up to present day, Zionism &quot;is replete with manifestations of deep hostility and contempt towards the indigenous population.&quot; Shlaim balances this by pointing out that there have always been individuals within the Zionist movement that have criticized such attitudes. He cites the example of [[Ahad Ha'am]], who after visiting Palestine in 1891, published a series of articles criticizing the aggressive behaviour and political ethnocentrism of Zionist settlers. Ha'am wrote that the Zionists &quot;behave towards the Arabs with hostility and cruelty, trespass unjustly upon their boundaries, beat them shamefully without reason and even brag about it, and nobody stands to check this contemptible and dangerous tendency&quot; and that they believed that &quot;the only language that the Arabs understand is that of force.&quot;&lt;ref name=LRB&gt;{{cite journal|last=shlaim|first=Avi|title=It can be done|journal=[[London Review of Books]]|date=9|year=1994|month=June|volume=16|issue=11|pages=26-27|url=http://www.lrb.co.uk/v16/n11/avi-shlaim/it-can-be-done|accessdate=16/10/2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Some critics of Zionism describe it as racist or discriminatory.&lt;ref name=CHARRAS&gt;
*''Zionism, imperialism, and race'', Abdul Wahhab Kayyali, ʻAbd al-Wahhāb Kayyālī (Eds),	Croom Helm, 1979
*Gerson, Allan, &quot;The United Nations and Racism:  the Case of Zionism and Racism&quot;, in ''Israel Yearbook on Human Rights 1987, Volume 17; Volume 1987, Yoram Dinstein, Mala Tabory  (Eds), Martinus Nijhoff Publishers, 1988, p 68
*Hadawi, Sami, ''Bitter harvest: a modern history of Palestine'', Interlink Books, 1991, p 183
*Beker, Avi, ''Chosen: the history of an idea, the anatomy of an obsession'', Macmillan, 2008, p 131, 139, 151
*Dinstein, Yoram, ''Israel Yearbook on Human Rights 1987, Volume 17; Volume 1987'', p 31, 136ge
*Harkabi,  Yehoshafat, ''Arab attitudes to Israel'', pp 247–8&lt;/ref&gt;  Some criticisms of Zionism specifically identify Judaism's notion of the &quot;[[Jews as a chosen people|chosen people]]&quot; as the source of racism in Zionism,&lt;ref&gt;
*Korey, William, ''Russian antisemitism, Pamyat, and the demonology of Zionism'', Psychology Press, 1995, pp 33–34
*Beker, Avi, ''Chosen: the history of an idea, the anatomy of an obsession'', Macmillan, 2008, pp 139
*Shimoni, Gideon, ''Community and conscience: the Jews in apartheid South Africa'', UPNE, 2003, p 167
&lt;/ref&gt; despite that being a religious concept unrelated to Zionism.{{citation needed|date=July 2012}}

In December 1973, the UN passed a series of resolutions condemning South Africa and included a reference to an &quot;unholy alliance between [[Portuguese Colonial War|Portuguese colonialism]], [[Apartheid]] and Zionism.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Resolution 3151 G (XXVIII) of December 14, 1973 by the UN General Assembly&lt;/ref&gt;  At the time there was little cooperation between [[Israel – South Africa relations|Israel and South Africa]],&lt;ref&gt;Israel and Black Africa: A Rapprochement? Ethan A. Nadelmann. Journal of Modern African Studies, Vol. 19, No. 2 (Jun., 1981), pp. 183–219&lt;/ref&gt; although the two countries would develop a close relationship during the 1970s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2006/feb/07/southafrica.israel Brothers in arms&amp;nbsp;— Israel's secret pact with Pretoria (The Guardian, February 7, 2006)]&lt;/ref&gt; Parallels have also been drawn between aspects of South Africa's apartheid regime and certain Israeli policies toward the Palestinians, which are seen as manifestations of racism in Zionist thinking.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6390755.stm UN envoy hits Israel 'apartheid' (BBC, Feb. 23, 2007)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2009/feb/16/israelandthepalestinians-israeli-elections-2009 It's time to rethink Zionism (The Guardian, Feb. 17, 2009)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.counterpunch.org/christison11082003.html Zionism as a Racist Ideology, by Kathleen and Bill Christinson (Counterpunch, November 8 / 9, 2003)]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1975 the [[UN General Assembly]] passed [[Resolution 3379]], which said &quot;Zionism is a form of racism and racial discrimination&quot;. According to the resolution, &quot;any doctrine of racial differentiation of superiority is scientifically false, morally condemnable, socially unjust, and dangerous.&quot; The resolution named the occupied territory of Palestine, Zimbabwe, and South Africa as examples of racist regimes. Resolution 3379 was pioneered by the Soviet Union and passed with numerical support from Arab and African states amidst accusations that Israel was supportive of the apartheid regime in South Africa.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cfr.org/un/un-general-assembly-resolution-3379-racial-discrimination/p11284 UN General Assembly Resolution 3379, Racial Discrimination (Council on Foreign Relations, November 10, 1975)]&lt;/ref&gt; In 1991 the resolution was repealed with [[UN General Assembly Resolution 46/86]],&lt;ref name=&quot;mfa.gov.il&quot;&gt;[http://www.mfa.gov.il/MFA/Foreign%20Relations/Israels%20Foreign%20Relations%20since%201947/1988-1992/260%20General%20Assembly%20Resolution%2046-86-%20Revocation 260 General Assembly Resolution 46-86- Revocation of Resolution 3379- December 16, 1991&amp;nbsp;— and statement by President Herzog Dec 16, 1991, VOLUME 11–12: 1988–1992]&lt;/ref&gt; after Israel declared that it would only participate in the [[Madrid Conference of 1991]] if the resolution were revoked.&lt;ref&gt;Frum, David (2000). How We Got Here: The '70s. New York, New York: Basic Books. p. 320. ISBN 0-465-04195-7.&lt;/ref&gt;

Arab countries sought to associate Zionism with racism in connection with a [[World Conference against Racism 2001|2001 UN conference on racism]], which took place in [[Durban]], South Africa,&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/1484002.stm Anger over Zionism debate (BBC, Sept. 4, 2001)]&lt;/ref&gt; which caused the United States and Israel to walk away from the conference as a response. The final text of the conference did not connect Zionism with racism. A human rights forum arranged in connection with the conference, on the other hand, did equate Zionism with racism and censured Israel for what it called &quot;racist crimes, including acts of genocide and ethnic cleansing&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/1523600.stm US abandons racism summit(BBC, Sept. 3, 2001)]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[African Charter on Human and Peoples' Rights]] was adopted in 1981 by the [[Organisation of African Unity]], which has since evolved into the [[African Union]]. The preamble of the charter includes a call to &quot;eliminate colonialism, neo-colonialism, apartheid, zionism and to dismantle aggressive foreign military bases and all forms of discrimination, particularly those based on race, ethnic group, color, sex. language, religion or political opinions&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www1.umn.edu/humanrts/instree/z1afchar.htm African [Banjul&lt;nowiki&gt;]&lt;/nowiki&gt; Charter on Human and Peoples' Rights, adopted June 27, 1981 (Library of the University of Minnesota)]&lt;/ref&gt; The charter has been ratified by 53 African countries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www1.umn.edu/humanrts/instree/ratz1afchr.htm List of Countries Who Have Signed, Ratified/Adhered to the African Charter On Human And Peoples' Rights (as of January 7, 2005)]&lt;/ref&gt;

Some supporters of Zionism, such as [[Chaim Herzog]], argue that the movement is non-discriminatory and contains no racist aspects.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/UN/herzogsp.html Israeli Ambassador Chaim Herzog's Response To Zionism Is Racism Resolution. November 10, 1975.] &quot;You dare talk of racism when I can point with pride to the Arab ministers who have served in my government; to the Arab deputy speaker of my Parliament; to Arab officers and men serving of their own volition in our border and police defense forces, frequently commanding Jewish troops; to the hundreds of thousands of Arabs from all over the Middle East crowding the cities of Israel every year; to the thousands of Arabs from all over the Middle East coming for medical treatment to Israel; to the peaceful coexistence which has developed; to the fact that Arabic is an official language in Israel on a par with Hebrew; to the fact that it is as natural for an Arab to serve in public office in Israel as it is incongruous to think of a Jew serving in any public office in an Arab country, indeed being admitted to many of them. Is that racism? It is not! That, Mr. President, is Zionism.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

===Anti-Zionism as anti-Semitism===
{{Main|Anti-Zionism#Anti-Zionism and antisemitism|New Antisemitism}}

It is argued by some scholars that the opposition to Zionism at the more extreme fringes may be hard to separate from [[antisemitism]].&lt;ref name=Stauber&gt;Anti-semitism in Germany: the post-Nazi epoch since 1945 By Werner Bergmann, Rainer Erb, page 182, &quot;Continuity and Change: Extreme Right Perceptions of Zionism&quot; by Roni Stauber in Anti-semitism worldwide 1999/2000 Tel Aviv University&lt;/ref&gt;

Anti-semites have alleged that Zionism was, or is, part of a Jewish plot to take control of the world.&lt;ref&gt;[[Norman Cohn]], [[Warrant for Genocide]], Serif 2001 chapter 3&lt;/ref&gt; One particular version of these allegations, &quot;[[The Protocols of the Elders of Zion]]&quot; (subtitle &quot;Protocols extracted from the secret archives of the central chancery of Zion&quot;) achieved global notability. The protocols are fictional minutes of an imaginary meeting by Jewish leaders of this plot. Analysis and proof of their fraudulent origin goes as far back as 1921.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/anti-semitism/hoax.html A Hoax of Hate]&lt;/ref&gt;  A 1920 German version renamed them &quot;[[The Zionist Protocols]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Norman Cohn]], [[Warrant for Genocide]], Serif 2001 page 75-76&lt;/ref&gt; The protocols were [[The Protocols of the Elders of Zion#toc|extensively used as propaganda]] by the [[Nazis]] and remain widely [[Protocols of the Elders of Zion#Modern_era|distributed in the Arab world]]. They are referred to in the 1988 [[Hamas#Hamas Charter (1988)|Hamas charter]].&lt;ref&gt;Hamas charter, article 32: &quot;The Zionist plan is limitless. After Palestine, the Zionists aspire to expand from the Nile to the Euphrates. When they will have digested the region they overtook, they will aspire to further expansion, and so on. Their plan is embodied in the &quot;Protocols of the Elders of Zion&quot;&amp;nbsp;...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

There are examples of anti-Zionists using accusations, slanders, imagery and tactics previously associated with anti-semites. On October 21, 1973, then-Soviet ambassador to the United Nations [[Yakov Malik]] declared: &quot;The Zionists have come forth with the theory of the [[Chosen People]], an absurd ideology.&quot;  Similarly, an exhibit about Zionism and Israel in the Museum of Religion and Atheism in [[Saint Petersburg]] designates the following as Soviet Zionist material: Jewish [[tallit|prayer shawls]], ''[[tefillin]]'' and [[Passover]]'' [[Hagaddah]]s'',&lt;ref&gt;[[William Korey|Korey, W.]], &quot;Updating the Protocols,&quot; ''Midstream'', May 1970, p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; even though these are all ''religious'' items used by Jews for thousands of years.&lt;ref name=&quot;Why?&quot;&gt;[[Dennis Prager|Prager, D]]; [[Joseph Telushkin|Telushkin, J]]. ''Why the Jews?: The Reason for Antisemitism''. New York: [[Simon &amp; Schuster]], 1983. page 169-175.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Noam Chomsky]], [[Norman Finkelstein]],  Irfan Khawaja, and [[Tariq Ali]] have suggested that the characterization of [[anti-Zionism]] as [[anti-Semitic]] is inaccurate, sometimes obscures legitimate [[criticism of Israel]]'s policies and actions, and is sometimes a political ploy to stifle [[criticism of Israel]].&lt;ref&gt;
*Professor [[Noam Chomsky]] argues: &quot;There have long been efforts to identify anti-Semitism and anti-Zionism in an effort to exploit anti-racist sentiment for political ends; &quot;one of the chief tasks of any dialogue with the Gentile world is to prove that the distinction between anti-Semitism and anti-Zionism is not a distinction at all,&quot; Israeli diplomat Abba Eban argued, in a typical expression of this intellectually and morally disreputable position (Eban, Congress Bi-Weekly, March 30, 1973). But that no longer suffices. It is now necessary to identify [[criticism of Israel]]i policies as anti-Semitism&amp;nbsp;— or in the case of Jews, as &quot;self-hatred,&quot; so that all possible cases are covered.&quot;&amp;nbsp;— Chomsky, 1989 &quot;Necessary Illusions&quot;.
* American political scientist [[Norman Finkelstein]] argues that anti-Zionism and often just [[criticism of Israel]]i policies have been conflated with antisemitism, sometimes called [[new antisemitism]] for political gain: &quot;Whenever Israel faces a public relations débâcle such as the Intifada or international pressure to resolve the Israel-Palestine conflict, American Jewish organizations orchestrate this extravaganza called the 'new anti-Semitism.' The purpose is several-fold. First, it is to discredit any charges by claiming the person is an anti-Semite. It's to turn Jews into the victims, so that the victims are not the Palestinians any longer. As people like Abraham Foxman of the ADL put it, the Jews are being threatened by a new holocaust. It's a role reversal&amp;nbsp;— the Jews are now the victims, not the Palestinians. So it serves the function of discrediting the people leveling the charge. It's no longer Israel that needs to leave the Occupied Territories; it's the Arabs who need to free themselves of the anti-Semitism.&amp;nbsp;— http://www.zmag.org/znet/viewArticle/5104
* [[Tariq Ali]], a British-Pakistani historian and political activist, argues that the concept of new antisemitism amounts to an attempt to subvert the language in the interests of the State of Israel. He writes that the campaign against &quot;the supposed new 'anti-semitism'&quot; in modern Europe is a &quot;cynical ploy on the part of the Israeli Government to seal off the Zionist state from any criticism of its regular and consistent brutality against the Palestinians&amp;nbsp;... [[Criticism of Israel]] can not and should not be equated with anti-semitism.&quot; He argues that most pro-Palestinian, anti-Zionist groups that emerged after the [[Six-Day War]] were careful to observe the distinction between anti-Zionism and antisemitism. —&amp;nbsp;[[Tariq Ali|Ali, Tariq]]. [http://www.counterpunch.org/ali03042004.html &quot;Notes on Anti-Semitism, Zionism and Palestine&quot;], ''Counterpunch'', March 4, 2004, first published in ''il manifesto'', February 26, 2004.
*Khawaja, Irfan, &quot;Poisoning the Well: The False Equation of Anti-Zionism and Anti-Semitism&quot;,  ''History News Network'', [http://hnn.us/articles/10866.html]'
&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|History|Israel|Judaism|Palestine|Politics}}

===Types of Zionism===
* [[Cultural Zionism]]
* [[Green Zionism]]
* [[Reform Zionism]]
* [[Streams of Zionism]] (Political, Practical &amp; Synthetic Zionism)

===Zionist institutions and organizations===
* [[Histadrut]]
* The [[Jewish Agency for Israel]]
* [[World Zionist Organization]]
* [[Jewish National Fund]]
* [[Vaad Leumi]]
* [[Hanoar Hatzioni]]

===History of Zionism and Israel===
* [[Return to Zion]]
* [[Yehud Medinata]]
* [[Jewish diaspora]]
* [[Jewish people]]
* [[The Holocaust]]
* [[Gathering of Israel]]
* [[Aliyah]]
* [[History of Zionism]]
* [[History of Israel]]
* [[Israeli-Arab conflict]]
* [[Israeli–Palestinian conflict]]
* [[Israeli settlement]]
* [[List of Zionist figures]]
* [[Timeline of Zionism]]

===Miscellanea===
* [[American Council for Judaism]]
* [[Christian Zionism in the United Kingdom]]
* [[Jewish Autonomism]]
* [[Jewish emancipation]]
* [[Restoration of the Jews to the Holy Land]]
* [[Berne Trial]]

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Further reading==
* Armborst-Weihs, Kerstin: [http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:0159-2010092115 ''The Formation of the Jewish National Movement Through Transnational Exchange: Zionism in Europe up to the First World War''], [[European History Online]], Mainz: [[Institute of European History]], 2011, retrieved: August 17, 2011.
* Beller, Steven. ''Herzl'' (2004)
* Brenner, Michael, and Shelley Frisch. ''Zionism: A Brief History'' (2003) [http://www.amazon.com/dp/1558763015 excerpt and text search]
* Cohen, Naomi. ''The Americanization of Zionism, 1897–1948'' (2003). 304 pp. essays on specialized topics
* Friedman, Isaiah. &quot;Theodor Herzl: Political Activity and Achievements,&quot; ''Israel Studies'' 2004 9(3): 46–79, online in [[EBSCO]]
* [[David Hazony]], Yoram Hazony, and Michael B. Oren, eds., &quot;New Essays on Zionism,&quot; Shalem Press, 2007.
* Kloke, Martin: [http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:0159-2011081801 ''The Development of Zionism Until the Founding of the State of Israel''], [[European History Online]], Mainz: [[Institute of European History]], 2010, retrieved: June 13, 2012.
* Laqueuer, Walter. ''A History of Zionism: From the French Revolution to the Establishment of the State of Israel'' (2003) survey by a leading scholar [http://www.amazon.com/dp/0805211497 excerpt and text search]
* Medoff, Rafael. &quot;Recent Trends in the Historiography of American Zionism,&quot; ''American Jewish History'' 86 (March 1998), 117–134.
*{{cite book|last=Motyl|first=Alexander J.|authorlink=Alexander J. Motyl|title=Encyclopedia of Nationalism, Volume II|year=2001|publisher=Academic Press|location=|isbn=0-12-227230-7|ref=harv}}
* Pawel, Ernst. ''The Labyrinth of Exile: A Life of Theodor Herzl'' (1992) [http://www.amazon.com/dp/0374523517 excerpt and text search]
* Sachar, Howard M. ''A History of Israel: From the Rise of Zionism to Our Time'' (2007) [http://www.amazon.com/dp/0375711325 excerpt and text search]
* Shimoni, Gideon. ''The Zionist Ideology'' (1995)
* [[Gadi Taub|Taub, Gadi]]. ''The Settlers and the Struggle over the Meaning of Zionism'' (2010, Hebrew, English)
* Taylor, A.R., 1971, 'Vision and intent in Zionist Thought', in 'The transformation of Palestine', ed. by I. Abu-Lughod, ISBN 0-8101-0345-1, [[Northwestern University Press]], Evanston, USA
* Urofsky, Melvin I. ''American Zionism from Herzl to the Holocaust'' (1995), a standard history
* Wigoder, Geoffrey, ed. ''New Encyclopedia of Zionism and Israel'' (2nd ed. 2 vol. 1994); 1521pp

===Primary sources===
* Herzl, Theodor. ''A Jewish state: an attempt at a modern solution of the Jewish question'' (1896) [http://books.google.com/books?id=eXkLAAAAIAAJ&amp;dq=inauthor:herzl&amp;lr=&amp;as_drrb_is=q&amp;as_minm_is=0&amp;as_miny_is=&amp;as_maxm_is=0&amp;as_maxy_is=&amp;num=30&amp;as_brr=0 full text online]
* Herzl, Theodor. ''Theodor Herzl: Excerpts from His Diaries'' (2006) [http://books.google.com/books?id=2RhB8hgyK4UC&amp;dq=inauthor:herzl&amp;lr=&amp;as_drrb_is=q&amp;as_minm_is=0&amp;as_miny_is=&amp;as_maxm_is=0&amp;as_maxy_is=&amp;num=30&amp;as_brr=3 excerpt and text search]

==External links==
{{Commons category|Zionism}}
{{Wikisource|Zionism an Affirmation of Judaism}}
* [http://www.zionistarchives.org.il Central Zionist Archives site in Jerusalem]
* [http://www.hagshama.org.il/en/ WZO website]
{{wikisource-inline|Category:Zionism|Zionism}}
* [http://www.JewishState.com/ Jewish State.com] Zionism, News, Links
* [http://www.exodus1947.com Exodus1947.com] PBS Documentary Film focusing on the secret American involvement in Aliyah Bet, narrated by Morley Safer
* [http://www.sazionism.co.za/ SAZ&amp;nbsp;— Support Association for Zionism]
* [http://www.hanoar.co.uk Hanoar Hatzioni UK] A Jewish-Zionist Youth Movement
* [http://jewishmag.com/145mag/herzl_hechler/herzl_hechler.htm Theodore Herzl and Rev. William Hechler and the Zionist Beginnings]

{{Zionism}}
{{Jews and Judaism}}
{{Relpolnav}}
{{Ethnic nationalism}}

ref&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/print-edition/news/netanyahu-israel-s-arabs-are-the-real-demographic-threat-1.109045 Netanyahu: Israel's Arabs are the real demographic threat (Haaretz, Dec. 18, 2003)]

[[Category:History of Israel]]
[[Category:Jewish history]]
[[Category:Judaism-related controversies]]
[[Category:National liberation movements]]
[[Category:Palestine]]
[[Category:Religion and politics]]
[[Category:Zionism| ]]
[[Category:Nationalism]]
[[Category:Political theories]]

{{Link GA|pl}}
{{Link FA|eo}}
{{Link FA|als}}

[[als:Zionismus]]
[[ar:صهيونية]]
[[an:Sionismo]]
[[az:Sionizm]]
[[zh-min-nan:Sek-an-chú-gī]]
[[be:Сіянізм]]
[[bg:Ционизъм]]
[[bs:Cionizam]]
[[ca:Sionisme]]
[[ceb:Siyonismo]]
[[cs:Sionismus]]
[[cy:Seioniaeth]]
[[da:Zionisme]]
[[de:Zionismus]]
[[et:Sionism]]
[[el:Σιωνισμός]]
[[es:Sionismo]]
[[eo:Cionismo]]
[[eu:Sionismo]]
[[fa:صهیونیسم]]
[[fr:Sionisme]]
[[gl:Sionismo]]
[[ko:시오니즘]]
[[hy:Սիոնիզմ]]
[[hr:Cionizam]]
[[id:Zionisme]]
[[is:Zíonismi]]
[[it:Sionismo]]
[[he:ציונות]]
[[jv:Zionisme]]
[[ka:სიონიზმი]]
[[kk:Сионизм]]
[[ku:Siyonîzm]]
[[lad:Zionizmo]]
[[lv:Cionisms]]
[[lt:Sionizmas]]
[[hu:Cionizmus]]
[[mk:Ционизам]]
[[ml:സിയോണിസ്റ്റ് പ്രസ്ഥാനം]]
[[arz:صهيونيه]]
[[mzn:صهیونیسم]]
[[ms:Zionisme]]
[[mwl:Sionismo]]
[[nl:Zionisme]]
[[ja:シオニズム]]
[[no:Sionisme]]
[[nn:Sionisme]]
[[oc:Sionisme]]
[[ps:سهيونېزم]]
[[pl:Syjonizm]]
[[pt:Sionismo]]
[[ro:Sionism]]
[[ru:Сионизм]]
[[sq:Cionizmi]]
[[simple:Zionism]]
[[sk:Sionizmus]]
[[sl:Sionizem]]
[[sr:Ционизам]]
[[fi:Sionismi]]
[[sv:Sionism]]
[[th:ขบวนการไซออนิสต์]]
[[tr:Siyonizm]]
[[uk:Сіонізм]]
[[ur:صیہونیت]]
[[vi:Chủ nghĩa phục quốc Do Thái]]
[[wa:Siyonisse]]
[[war:Sionismo]]
[[yi:ציוניזם]]
[[zh:錫安主義]]</text>
      <sha1>5dj334zagao3hmtjcjic8bma29b2iee</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
