<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Zoroastrianism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>34533</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522113900</id>
      <parentid>521897309</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T03:14:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Gerakibot</username>
        <id>4112738</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>r2.7.1) (Robot: Modifying [[bo:ཛོ་​ར་​སིའི་​ཆོས་​ལུགས།]], [[fa:دین زردشتی]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="78711">{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Zoroastrianism}}
{{Multiple issues|synthesis=March 2012
|weasel=March 2012
|POV=March 2012}}

&lt;!-- PLEASE REVIEW COMMENTS ON THE TALK PAGE BEFORE EDITING THE LEDE (LEAD SENTENCES) --&gt;
'''Zoroastrianism''' {{IPAc-en|ˌ|z|ɒr|oʊ|ˈ|æ|s|t|r|i|ə|n|ɪ|z|əm}}, also called '''Mazdaism''' and '''Magianism''', is a [[religion]] and philosophy based on the teachings of the prophet [[Zoroaster]] (also known as Zarathustra in [[Avestan language|Avestan]]) and was formerly among the world's largest religions. It was probably founded some time before the 6th century BCE in the eastern part of ancient [[Greater Iran]] ([[Persia]]). 

In Zoroastrianism, the [[Creator deity|creator]] [[Ahura Mazda]] is all good, and no [[evil]] originates from him. Thus, in Zoroastrianism good and evil have distinct sources, with evil (''druj'') trying to destroy the creation of Mazda (''[[asha]]''), and good trying to sustain it. While Ahura Mazda is not [[Immanence|immanent]] in the world, his creation is represented by the [[Amesha Spenta]]s and the host of other [[Yazata]]s, through whom the works of God are evident to humanity, and through whom worship of Mazda is ultimately directed. The most important texts of the religion are those of the [[Avesta]], of which a significant portion has been lost, and mostly only the [[liturgies]] of which have survived. The lost portions are known of only through references and brief quotations in the later works, primarily from the 9th to 11th centuries.

In some form, it served as the national &lt;!--pre-3rd century--&gt; or [[state religion]]&lt;!--3rd-7th centuries --&gt; of a significant portion of the [[Iranian people]] for many centuries. The religion first dwindled when the [[Achaemenid Empire]] [[Wars of Alexander the Great|was invaded]] by [[Alexander III of Macedon]], after which it collapsed and disintegrated&lt;ref&gt;Hoschander, Jacob. &quot;The Book of Esther in the Light of History: Chapter IV&quot;, The Jewish Quarterly Review, New Series, Vol. 10, No. 1 (Jul., 1919), pp. 87–88&lt;/ref&gt; and it was further [[Muslim conquest of Persia|gradually marginalized]] by [[Islam]] from the 7th century onwards with the decline of the [[Sassanid Empire]].&lt;ref&gt;Hourani, p. 87.&lt;/ref&gt; The political power of the pre-Islamic Iranian dynasties lent Zoroastrianism immense prestige in ancient times, and some of its leading doctrines were adopted by other religious systems. It has no major theological divisions (the only significant schism is based on calendar differences), but it is not uniform. Modern-era influences have a significant impact on individual and local beliefs, practices, values and vocabulary, sometimes merging with tradition and in other cases displacing it. By one estimate, there are between 124,000 and 190,000 Zoroastrians worldwide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/06/us/06faith.html?pagewanted=1&amp;_r=2 |title=Zoroastrians Keep the Faith, and Keep Dwindling - NYTimes.com |first=Laurie |last=Goodstein |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=September 6, 2006 |publisher=[[New York Times Company|NYTC]] |location=[[New York, NY|New York]] |issn=0362-4331 |accessdate=September 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Terminology==
The ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'' attests use of the term ''Zoroastrianism'' in 1874 in [[Archibald Sayce|Archibald Sayce's]] ''Principles of Comparative Philology''.&lt;ref&gt;
Oxford English Dictionary&lt;/ref&gt;  The first surviving reference to Zoroaster in Western scholarship is attributed to [[Thomas Browne]] (1605–1682), who briefly refers to the prophet in his 1643 ''[[Religio Medici]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Browne, T. (1643) &quot;Religio Medici&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The [[OED]] records 1743 (Warburton, ''Pope's Essay'') as the earliest reference to Zoroaster.

The term ''Mazdaism'' {{IPAc-en|ˈ|m|æ|z|d|ə|.|ɪ|z|əm}} is a typical 19th century construct, taking ''Mazda-'' from the name [[Ahura Mazda]] and adding the suffix ''-ism'' to suggest a belief system. The March 2001 draft edition of the ''[[OED]]'' also records an alternate form, ''Mazdeism'', perhaps derived from the French ''Mazdéisme'', which first appeared in 1871. The Zoroastrian name of the religion is ''Mazdayasna'', which combines ''Mazda-'' with the [[Avestan language]] word ''[[yasna]]'', meaning &quot;worship, devotion&quot;.

In [[English language|English]], an adherent of the faith commonly refers to himself or herself as a Zoroastrian or as a Zarathustrian. An older, but still widespread expression is ''Behdin'', meaning &quot;follower of ''Daena''&quot;, for which &quot;Good Religion&quot; is one translation. In the Zoroastrian [[liturgy]], the term ''Behdin'' is also used as a title for an individual who has been formally inducted into the religion in a ''[[Navjote]]'' ceremony.

==Distinguishing characteristics==

===Basic beliefs===
{{refimprove section|date=February 2010}}
Zoroastrians believe that there is one universal and [[Transcendence (religion)|transcendent]] God, [[Ahura Mazda]]. He is said to be the one uncreated Creator to whom all worship is ultimately directed.&lt;ref name=&quot;iranica.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Zoroastrianism: Holy text, beliefs and practices|date=2010-03-01|accessdate=2010-03-01|url=http://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/zoroastrianism-i-historical-review}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ahura Mazda's creation—evident as ''[[asha]]'', truth and order—is the [[antithesis]] of chaos, which is evident as ''druj'', falsehood and disorder. The resulting conflict involves the entire universe, including humanity, which has an active role to play in the conflict.&lt;ref name=&quot;iranica.com&quot;/&gt;

The religion states that active participation in life through good deeds is necessary to ensure happiness and to keep chaos at bay. This active participation is a central element in Zoroaster's concept of [[free will]], and Zoroastrianism rejects all forms of [[monasticism]]. Ahura Mazda will ultimately prevail over the evil [[Angra Mainyu]] or Ahriman, at which point the universe will undergo a cosmic renovation and time will end. In the final renovation, all of creation—even the souls of the dead that were initially banished to &quot;darkness&quot;—will be reunited in Ahura Mazda, returning to life in the undead form. At the end of time, a savior-figure (a [[Saoshyant]]) will bring about a final renovation of the world (''[[frashokereti|frasho.kereti]]''), in which the dead will be revived.&lt;ref name=&quot;iranica.com&quot;/&gt;

In Zoroastrian tradition, the &quot;chaotic&quot; is represented by Angra Mainyu (also referred to as &quot;Ahriman&quot;), the &quot;Destructive Principle&quot;, while the benevolent is represented through Ahura Mazda's [[Amesha Spenta|Spenta Mainyu]], the instrument or &quot;Bounteous Principle&quot; of the act of creation. It is through Spenta Mainyu that transcendental Ahura Mazda is [[immanence|immanent&lt;!-- immanent is the correct English language word. --&gt;]] in humankind, and through which the Creator interacts with the world. According to Zoroastrian [[cosmology]], in articulating the [[Ahuna Vairya]] formula, Ahura Mazda made His ultimate triumph evident to Angra Mainyu. As expressions and aspects of Creation, Ahura Mazda emanated the [[Amesha Spenta]]s (&quot;Bounteous Immortals&quot;), that are each the [[hypostasis (philosophy)|hypostasis]] and representative of one aspect of that Creation. These Amesha Spenta are in turn assisted by a league of lesser principles, the [[Yazata]]s, each &quot;Worthy of Worship&quot; and each again a hypostasis of a moral or physical aspect of creation.

===Other characteristics===
&lt;!--[[Image:Zartosht.jpg|thumb|right|[[Zoroaster]]; portrayed here in a popular Parsi Zoroastrian depiction. This image emerged in the eighteenth century.{{deletable image-caption|Wednesday, 12 January 2011}}]]--&gt;
In Zoroastrianism, water (''[[aban|apo]]'', ''aban'') and fire (''[[atar]]'', ''adar'') are agents of ritual purity, and the associated purification ceremonies are considered the basis of ritual life. In Zoroastrian [[cosmogony]], water and fire are respectively the second and last primordial elements to have been created, and scripture considers fire to have its origin in the waters&lt;!--(Boyce supposes this idea is due to an identification of lightning with rain)--&gt;. Both water and fire are considered life-sustaining, and both water and fire are represented within the precinct of a [[fire temple]]. Zoroastrians usually pray in the presence of some form of fire (which can be considered evident in any source of light), and the [[Ab-Zohr|culminating rite]] of the principle act of worship constitutes a &quot;strengthening of the waters&quot;. Fire is considered a medium through which spiritual insight and wisdom is gained, and water is considered the source of that wisdom.

While the [[Parsi|Parsees]] in India have traditionally been opposed to [[proselytizing]], probably for historical reasons, and even considered it a crime for which the culprit may face expulsion,&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Khan|first=Roni K|edition=Online|year=1996|url=http://tenets.parsizoroastrianism.com/|accessdate=2009-10-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Iranian Zoroastrians have never been opposed to conversion, and the practice has been endorsed by the Council of Mobeds of [[Tehran]]. While the Iranian authorities do not permit proselytizing within Iran, Iranian Zoroastrians in exile have actively encouraged missionary activities, with The Zarathushtrian Assembly in [[Los Angeles]] and the International Zoroastrian Centre in [[Paris]] as two prominent centres.

As in many other faiths, Zoroastrians are encouraged to marry others of the same faith, but this is not a requirement. Rather, it is a creation of those in India. Some members of the Indian Zoroastrian community (the Parsis) contend that a child must have a Parsi father to be eligible for introduction into the faith, but this assertion is considered by most{{whom?|date=June 2012}} to be a violation of the Zoroastrian tenets of gender equality, and may be a remnant of an old Indian legal definition (since overruled) of ''Parsi''. This issue is a matter of debate within the Parsi community, but with the increasingly global nature of modern society and the dwindling number of Zoroastrians, such opinions are less vociferous.

In Zoroastrian tradition, life is a temporary state in which a mortal is expected to actively participate in the continuing battle between truth and falsehood. Prior to being born, the ''urvan'' (soul) of an individual is still united with its ''[[fravashi]]'' (guardian spirit), and which have existed since Mazda created the universe. During life, the ''fravashi'' acts as a guardian and protector. On the fourth day after death, the soul is reunited with its ''fravashi'', in which the experiences of life in the material world are collected for the continuing battle in the spiritual world. For the most part, Zoroastrianism does not have a notion of [[reincarnation]], at least not until the final renovation of the world. Despite this, followers of [[Ilm-e-Kshnoom]] in India believe in reincarnation and practice vegetarianism, two principles unknown to Orthodox Zoroastrianism.{{sfn|Boyce|2007|p=205}}&lt;!-- the final renovation of the world includes the revival of the dead, and this revival may (subject to which tradition is being followed) be interpreted as a revival in corporeal form--&gt;

In Zoroastrian scripture and tradition, a corpse is a host for decay, i.e., of ''druj''. Consequently, scripture enjoins the &quot;safe&quot; disposal of the dead in a manner such that a corpse does not pollute the &quot;good&quot; creation. These injunctions are the doctrinal basis of the fast-fading traditional practice of &quot;ritual exposure&quot;, most commonly identified with the so-called &quot;[[Tower of Silence|Towers of Silence]]&quot; for which there is no standard technical term in either scripture or tradition. The practice of ritual exposure is only practised by Zoroastrian communities of the [[Indian subcontinent]], where it is not illegal, but where alternative disposal methods are desperately sought after [[diclofenac]] poisoning has led to the virtual extinction of scavenger birds. Other Zoroastrian communities either [[cremation|cremate]] their dead, or bury them in graves that are cased with [[lime mortar]].

==History==

===Origins===
Zoroastrianism emerged out of a common prehistoric [[Indo-Iranian]] religious system dating back to the early 2nd millennium BCE.&lt;ref&gt;Foltz 2004, pp. 4–16&lt;/ref&gt; According to Zoroastrian tradition, [[Zoroaster]] was a reformer who exalted the deity of Wisdom, [[Ahura Mazda]], to the status of Supreme Being and Creator, while demoting various other deities and rejecting certain rituals.

===Classical antiquity===
{{refimprove section|date=November 2011}}
{{See also|Zoroaster#Western perceptions|l1=Western Perceptions of Zoroastrianism}}
[[Image:Farvahar001.JPG|right|thumb|Farvahar. [[Persepolis]], Iran.]]
Although older, Zoroastrianism only enters recorded history in the mid-5th century BCE. [[Herodotus]]' ''[[Histories (Herodotus)|The Histories]]'' (completed ''c.'' 440&amp;nbsp;BCE) includes a description of [[Greater Iran]]ian society with what may be recognizably Zoroastrian features, including exposure of the dead.

''The Histories'' is a primary source of information on the early period of the [[Achaemenid Empire|Achaemenid era]] (648–330&amp;nbsp;BCE), in particular with respect to the role of the [[Magi]]. According to Herodotus i.101, the Magi were the sixth tribe of the [[Medes|Medians]] (until the unification of the Persian empire under [[Cyrus the Great]], all Iranians were referred to as &quot;Mede&quot; or &quot;Mada&quot; by the peoples of the Ancient World), who appear to have been the priestly caste of the Mesopotamian-influenced branch of Zoroastrianism today known as [[Zurvanism]], and who wielded considerable influence at the courts of the Median emperors.

Following the unification of the Median and Persian empires in 550 BCE, Cyrus the Great and, later, his son [[Cambyses II]] curtailed the powers of the Magi after they had attempted to sow dissent following their loss of influence. In 522 BCE, the Magi revolted and set up a rival claimant to the throne. The usurper, pretending to be Cyrus' younger son [[Smerdis]], took power shortly thereafter.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://books.google.com.ar/books?hl=es&amp;lr=&amp;id=dHIlhU4Gd5AC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA1&amp;dq=cambises+and+smerdis+&amp;ots=cxiuxNuULH&amp;sig=EaE-IEC2pxJVri0GaDVtM2ZmZ3A&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=cambises&amp;f=false |title=Resumen de la Historia Universal: escrito con su conocimiento, y aprobado ... - Joan Cortada i Sala - Google Libros |publisher=Books.google.com.ar |date= |accessdate=2012-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Owing to the [[despotism|despotic rule]] of [[Cambyses]] and his long absence in Egypt, &quot;the whole people, Persians, Medes and all the other nations&quot; acknowledged the usurper, especially as he granted a remission of taxes for three years (Herodotus iii. 68).

[[Image:Darius I the Great's inscription.jpg|left|thumb|The [[Behistun Inscription]], [[Iran]].]] According to the [[Behistun Inscription]], pseudo-Smerdis ruled for seven months before being overthrown by [[Darius I]] in 521 BCE. The &quot;Magi&quot;, though persecuted, continued to exist. A year following the death of the first pseudo-Smerdis (named Gaumata), a second pseudo-Smerdis (named Vahyazdāta) attempted a coup. The coup, though initially successful, failed.

Whether Cyrus II was a Zoroastrian is subject to debate. It did, however, influence him to the extent that it became the non-imposing religion of his empire, and its beliefs later allowed Cyrus to free the Jews and allow them to return to [[Judea]] when the emperor took [[Babylon]] in 539 BCE. Darius I was a devotee of [[Ahura Mazda]], as attested to several times in the [[Behistun]] inscription. However, whether he was a follower of Zoroaster has not been conclusively established, since devotion to Ahura Mazda was (at the time) not necessarily an indication of an adherence to Zoroaster's teaching.

Darius I and later [[Achaemenid dynasty|Achaemenid emperors]], though acknowledging their devotion to Ahura Mazda in inscriptions, appear to have permitted religions to coexist. Nonetheless, it was during the Achaemenid period that Zoroastrianism gained momentum. A number of the Zoroastrian texts that today are part of the greater compendium of the [[Avesta]] have been attributed to that period. It was also during the later Achaemenid era that many of the divinities and divine concepts of proto-Indo-Iranian religion(s) were incorporated in Zoroastrianism, in particular those to whom the days of the month of the [[Zoroastrian calendar]] are dedicated. This calendar is still used today, a fact that is attributed to the Achaemenid period. Additionally, the divinities, or [[yazata]]s, are present-day Zoroastrian [[angel]]s (Dhalla, 1938).

Almost nothing is known of the status of Zoroastrianism under the [[Seleucids]] and [[Parthians]], who ruled over Persia following [[Alexander the Great]]'s invasion in 330 BCE. According to later Zoroastrian legend (''[[Denkard]]'' and the ''[[Book of Arda Viraf]]''), many sacred texts were lost when Alexander's troops invaded [[Persepolis]] and subsequently destroyed the royal library there. [[Diodorus Siculus|Diodorus Siculus's]] ''Bibliotheca historica'', which was completed ''c.'' 60 BCE, appears to substantiate this Zoroastrian legend (Diod. 17.72.2–17.72.6). According to one archaeological examination, the ruins of the palace of [[Xerxes I|Xerxes]] bear traces of having been burned (Stolze, 1882). Whether a vast collection of (semi-)religious texts &quot;written on parchment in gold ink&quot;, as suggested by the ''Denkard'', actually existed remains a matter of speculation, but is unlikely. Given that many of the ''Denkard''s statements-as-fact have since been refuted among scholars, the tale of the library is widely accepted to be fictional (Kellens, 2002)

===Late antiquity===
When the [[Sassanid dynasty]] came into power in 228 CE, they aggressively promoted the [[Zurvanite]] form of Zoroastrianism and, in some cases, persecuted [[Christianity|Christians]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|page=34|author=Wigram, W. A.|title=An introduction to the history of the Assyrian Church, or, The Church of the Sassanid Persian Empire, 100&amp;ndash;640 A.D|publisher=Gorgias Press|isbn=1593331037|year=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; When the Sassanids captured territory, they often built fire temples there to promote their religion. After [[Emperor Constantine I|Constantine]], the Sassanids were suspicious of Christians, not least because of their perceived ties to the Christian [[Roman Empire]]. As such the [[Persian Church]] (the [[Church of the East]]) officially broke with [[Roman Christianity]], and was tolerated and even sometimes favored by the Sassanids.

A form of Zoroastrianism was also prominent in the pre-Christian [[Caucasus]] region (especially modern-day [[Azerbaijan]]). During the periods of their [[suzerainty]] over the Caucasus, the Sassanids made attempts to promote the religion there as well. 

Well before the 6th century CE, Zoroastrianism had spread to northern [[China]] via the [[Silk Road]], gaining official status in a number of Chinese states.{{citation needed|date=February 2011}} Remains of Zoroastrian temples have been found in [[Kaifeng]] and [[Zhenjiang]]. By the 13th century, the religion had faded from prominence in China. However, Zoroastrianism (as well as later [[Manicheism]]) may still have influenced elements of Buddhism, especially in terms of light symbolism.{{citation needed|date=February 2011}}

===Middle Ages===
{{See also|Persecution of Zoroastrians}}
[[File:Hamza Burns Zarthust’s Chest and Shatters the Urn with his Ashes.jpg|thumb|A scene from the [[Hamzanama]] where [[Hamza ibn ‘Abd al-Muttalib]] Burns Zarthust’s Chest and Shatters the Urn with his Ashes]]
In the 7th century, and over the course of at least 16 years (several decades in the case of some provinces), the [[Muslim conquest of Persia|Sassanid Empire was overthrown by the Arabs]]. Although the administration of the state was rapidly Islamicized and subsumed under the [[Umayyad Caliphate]], &quot;there was little serious pressure&quot; exerted on newly subjected people to adopt Islam.&lt;ref name=&quot;Boyce_1979_150&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Boyce|1979|p=150}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Islamic jurists considered only Muslims to be perfectly moral, and &quot;unbelievers might as well be left to their iniquities, so long as these did not vex their overlords.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Boyce_1979_146&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Boyce|1979|p=146}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

There were also practical considerations: &quot;because of their sheer numbers, the conquered Zoroastrians had to be treated as ''[[dhimmi]]s'' (despite doubts [of the validity of this identification] that persisted down the centuries),&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Boyce_1979_146&quot;/&gt; which made them eligible for protection. Thus, in the main, once the conquest was over and &quot;local terms were agreed on&quot;, the Arab governors protected the local populations in exchange for tribute.&lt;ref name=&quot;Boyce_1979_146&quot;/&gt; The Arabs adopted the Sassanid tax-system, both the land-tax levied on land owners and the [[poll-tax]] levied on individuals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Boyce_1979_146&quot;/&gt; This is called ''[[jizya]]'',&lt;!-- Boyce 1979:146 --&gt; a tax levied on non-Muslims living in Muslim Caliphates (i.e., the ''dhimmi''s). In time, this poll-tax came to be used as a means to humble the non-Muslims, and a number of laws and restrictions evolved to emphasize their inferior status. Under the early orthodox [[caliphs]], as long as the non-Muslims paid their taxes and adhered to the ''dhimmi'' laws, administrators were enjoined to leave non-Muslims &quot;in their religion and their land.&quot; ([[Abu Bakr|Caliph Abu Bakr]], qtd. in {{harvnb|Boyce|1979|p=146}}).

Thus, though subject to a new leadership and harassed, once the horrors of conquest were over, the Zoroastrians were able to continue in their former ways. There was, however, a slow but steady social and economic pressure to convert.&lt;ref name=&quot;Buillet_1979_37.138&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Buillet|1978|p=37,138}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Boyce_1979_147ff&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Boyce|1979|pp=147ff}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The nobility and city-dwellers were the first to convert, with Islam more slowly being accepted among the peasantry and landed gentry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Buillet_1979_59&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Buillet|1978|p=59}}.&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Power and worldly-advantage&quot; now lay with followers of Islam, and although the &quot;official policy was one of aloof contempt, there were individual Muslims eager to [[proselytize]] and ready to use all sorts of means to do so.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Boyce_1979_147&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Boyce|1979|p=147}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

In time, a tradition evolved by which Islam was made to appear as a partly Iranian religion. One example of this was a legend that [[Husayn ibn Ali|Husayn]], son the fourth caliph [[Ali Ibn Abi Talib|Ali]] and grandson of Islam's prophet [[Muhammad]], had married a captive Sassanid princess named [[Shahrbanu]]. This &quot;wholly fictitious figure&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Boyce_1979_151&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Boyce|1979|p=151}}.&lt;/ref&gt; was said to have borne Husayn a son, the historical fourth [[Shi'a]] [[Imamah (Shi'a doctrine)|imam]], who claimed that the [[caliphate]] rightly belonged to him and his descendants, and that the [[Umayyad]]s had wrongfully wrested it from him. The alleged descent from the Sassanid house counterbalanced the Arab nationalism of the Umayyads, and the Iranian national association with a Zoroastrian past was disarmed. Thus, according to scholar Mary Boyce, &quot;it was no longer the Zoroastrians alone who stood for patriotism and loyalty to the past.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Boyce_1979_151&quot;/&gt; The &quot;damning indictment&quot; that becoming Muslim was equivalent to becoming [[Aniran|Un-Iranian]] only remained an idiom in Zoroastrian texts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Boyce_1979_151&quot;/&gt;

With Iranian (especially Persian) support, the [[Abbasids]] overthrew the Umayyads in 750, and in the subsequent caliphate government&amp;mdash;that nominally lasted until 1258&amp;mdash;Muslim Iranians received marked favor in the new government, both in Iran and at the capital in [[Baghdad]]. This mitigated the antagonism between Arabs and Iranians, but sharpened the distinction between Muslims and non-Muslims. The Abbasids zealously persecuted [[heretics]], and although this was directed mainly at Muslim [[sectarians]], it also created a harsher climate for non-Muslims.&lt;ref name=&quot;Boyce_1979_152&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Boyce|1979|p=152}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Although the Abbasids were deadly foes of Zoroastrianism, the brand of Islam they propagated throughout Iran became in turn ever more &quot;Zoroastrianized&quot;, making it easier for Iranians to embrace Islam.&lt;!-- 152 --&gt;

The 9th century was the last in which Zoroastrians had the means to engage in creative work on a great scale, and the 9th century has come to define&lt;!--e.g., Bailey's ''Zoroastrian problems in the ninth-century books''--&gt; the great number of Zoroastrian texts that were composed or re-written during the 8th to 10th centuries (excluding copying and lesser amendments, which continue for some time thereafter). All of these works are in the [[Middle Persian]] dialect of that period (free of Arabic words), and written in the difficult [[Pahlavi script]] (hence the adoption of the term &quot;Pahlavi&quot; as the name of the variant of the language, and of the genre, of those Zoroastrian books). If read aloud, these books would still have been intelligible to the [[laity]]. Many of these texts are responses to the tribulations of the time, and all of them include exhortations to stand fast in their religious beliefs. Some, such as the &quot;[[Denkard]]&quot;, are doctrinal defenses of the religion, while others are explanations of theological aspects (such as the [[Bundahishn]]'s) or practical aspects (e.g., explanation of rituals) of it. About sixty such works are known to have existed, of which some are known only from references to them in other works.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}

Two decrees in particular encouraged the transition to a preponderantly Islamic society.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}} The first edict, adapted from an Arsacid and Sassanid one (but in those to the advantage of Zoroastrians), was that only a Muslim could own Muslim slaves or [[indentured servant]]s. Thus, a bonded individual owned by a Zoroastrian could automatically become a freeman by converting to Islam. The other edict was that if one male member of a Zoroastrian family converted to Islam, he instantly inherited all its property.

Under Abbasid rule, Muslim Iranians (who by then were in the majority) increasingly found ways to taunt Zoroastrians, and distressing them became a popular sport. For example, in the 9th century, a deeply venerated [[cypress tree]] in [[Greater Khorasan|Khorasan]] (which Parthian-era legend supposed had been planted by Zoroaster himself) was felled for the construction of a palace in Baghdad, {{convert|2000|mi|km}} away. In the 10th century, on the day that a Tower of Silence had been completed at much trouble and expense, a Muslim official contrived to get up onto it, and to call the ''[[adhan]]'' (the Muslim call to prayer) from its walls. This was made a pretext to annex the building.&lt;ref name=&quot;Boyce_1979_158&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Boyce|1979|p=158}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Another popular means to distress Zoroastrians was to maltreat dogs,&lt;!-- Boyce 158--&gt; as these animals are sacred in Zoroastrianism. Such baiting, which was to continue down the centuries, was indulged in by all; not only by high officials, but by the general uneducated population as well.

Despite these economic and social incentives to convert, Zoroastrianism remained strong in some regions, particularly in those furthest away from the Caliphate capital at Baghdad. In [[Bukhara]] (in present-day Uzbekistan), resistance to Islam required the 9th century Arab commander Qutaiba to convert his province four times. The first three times the citizens reverted to their old religion. Finally, the governor made their religion &quot;difficult for them in every way&quot;, turned the local fire temple into a mosque, and encouraged the local population to attend Friday prayers by paying each attendee two [[dirhams]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Boyce_1979_147&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Boyce|1979|pp=147}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The cities where Arab governors resided were particularly vulnerable to such pressures,&lt;!--147--&gt; and in these cases the Zoroastrians were left with no choice but to either conform or migrate to regions that had a more amicable administration.&lt;ref name=&quot;Boyce_1979_147&quot;/&gt;

Among these migrations were those to cities in (or on the margins of) the great salt deserts, in particular to [[Yazd]] and [[Kerman]], which remain centers of Iranian Zoroastrianism to this day. Yazd became the seat of the Iranian high priests during [[Ilkhanate|Mongol Il-Khanate]] rule, when the &quot;best hope for survival [for a non-Muslim] was to be inconspicuous.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Boyce_1979_163&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Boyce|1979|p=163}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Crucial to the present-day survival of Zoroastrianism was a migration from the northeastern Iranian town of [[Sanjan (Khorasan)|&quot;Sanjan in south&lt;!-- hyphen--&gt;-&lt;!--per literal quote--&gt;western Khorasan&quot;]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Boyce_1979_157&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Boyce|1979|p=157}}.&lt;/ref&gt; to [[Gujarat|Gujarat, in western India]]. The descendants of that group are today known as the ''[[Parsi]]s''&amp;mdash;&quot;as the [[Gujarati people|Gujaratis]], from long tradition, called anyone from Iran&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Boyce_1979_157&quot;/&gt;&amp;mdash;who today represent the larger of the two groups of Zoroastrians.

[[File:Map of the Achaemenid Empire.jpg|250px|thumb|right|The Zoroastrian [[Achaemenid Empire]] at its greatest extent was the largest ancient empire in recorded history at 8.0 million km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; (480 BCE).&lt;ref name=Vasseghi&gt;[http://www.persepolis3d.com/data_developers/biography_vasseghi.htm Vasseghi, Sheda], &quot;[http://www.worldtribune.com/worldtribune/WTARC/2009/me_iran0794_10_12.asp The other Iran story: Re-engineering the nation's cultural DNA]&quot;, ''Breaking... WorldTribune.com'' World Tribune News, (12 October 2009).&lt;/ref&gt;]]

Also in [[Greater Khorasan|Khorasan]] in the northeastern Iran, a 10th century Iranian nobleman brought together four Zoroastrian priests to transcribe a Sassanid-era Middle Persian work titled ''Book of the Lord'' (''Khwaday Namag'') from Pahlavi script into Arabic script. This transcription, which remained in Middle Persian prose (an Arabic version, by [[Abdullah Ibn al-Muqaffa|al-Muqaffa]], also exists), was completed in 957 and subsequently became the basis&lt;!-- so Boyce 159 --&gt; for [[Firdausi]]'s ''[[Shahnameh|Book of Kings]]''. It became enormously popular among both Zoroastrians and Muslims, and also served to propagate the Sassanid justification for overthrowing the Arsacids (i.e., that the Sassanids had restored the faith to its &quot;orthodox&quot; form after the Hellenistic Arsacids had allowed Zoroastrianism to become corrupt).

The struggle between Zoroastrianism and Islam declined in the 10th and 11th centuries, as, by then, most of the country{{which|date=June 2012}} was Islamic. Local Iranian dynasties, &quot;all vigorously Muslim,&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Boyce_1979_157&quot;/&gt; had emerged as largely independent [[vassals]] of the Caliphs. In the 16th century, in one of the early letters between Iranian Zoroastrians and their co-religionists in India, the priests of Yazd lamented that &quot;no period [in human history], not even [[Hellenistic period|that of Alexander]], had been more grievous or troublesome for the faithful than 'this millennium of the [[Aeshma|demon of &lt;!--caps cause hypostasis--&gt;Wrath&lt;!-- and because this is a literal quotation--&gt;]]'.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Boyce_1979_175&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Boyce|1979|p=175}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Relation to other religions and cultures==
[[File:Iran-achaemenids (darius the great).jpg|250px|thumb|right|The [[Achaemenid Empire]] in the 5th century BCE consisted of the largest empire in history by percentage of world population.&lt;ref name=Cook&gt;While estimates for the Achaemenid Empire range from 10–80+ million, most prefer 50 million. Prevas (2009, p. 14) estimates 10 million [http://books.google.com/books?id=1S-Q-6jDZ7AC&amp;pg=PA14&amp;dq=persian+empire+million+square+miles&amp;lr=#v=onepage&amp;q=persian%20empire%20million%20square%20miles&amp;f=false 1]. Langer (2001, p. 40) estimates around 16 million [http://books.google.com/books?id=MziRd4ddZz4C&amp;pg=PA40&amp;dq=persian+empire+million+people&amp;lr=#v=onepage&amp;q=persian%20empire%20million%20people&amp;f=false 2]. McEvedy and Jones (2001, p. 50) estimates 17 million [http://www.census.gov/ipc/www/worldhis.html 3]. Strauss (2004, p. 37) estimates about 20 million [http://books.google.com/books?id=nQFtMcD5dOsC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=battle+of+salamis+strauss&amp;lr= 4]. Ward (2009, p. 16) estimates at 20 million [http://books.google.com/books?id=8eUTLaaVOOQC&amp;pg=PA16&amp;dq=persian+empire+million+square+miles&amp;lr=#v=onepage&amp;q=persian%20empire%20million%20square%20miles&amp;f=false 5]. Aperghis (2007, p. 311) estimates 32 million [http://books.google.com/books?id=uug6VvJrxVYC&amp;pg=RA11-PT139&amp;dq=20-25+million+persian+empire 6]. Scheidel (2009, p. 99) estimates 35 million [http://books.google.com/books?id=6vnkts2rOJUC&amp;pg=PA99&amp;dq=scheidel+35+million+2009&amp;lr= 7]. Zeinert (1996, p. 32) estimates 40 million [http://books.google.com/books?id=JgNlG_AI7bkC&amp;pg=PA32&amp;dq=persian+empire+million+people&amp;lr=#v=onepage&amp;q=persian%20empire%20million%20people&amp;f=false 8]. Rawlinson and Schauffler (1898, p. 270) estimates possibly 50 million [http://books.google.com/books?id=_NpJAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA270&amp;dq=persian+empire+50+million+people&amp;lr=#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false 9]. Astor (1899, p. 56) estimates almost 50 million [http://books.google.com/books?id=DNwaAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA56&amp;dq=persian+empire+million+square+miles&amp;lr=#v=onepage&amp;q=persian%20empire%20million%20square%20miles&amp;f=false 10]. Lissner (1961, p. 111) estimates probably 50 million [http://books.google.com/books?lr=&amp;id=GQJIAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=Darius+twenty+million+people&amp;q=fifty+million+people 11]. Milns (1968, p. 51) estimates some 50 million [http://books.google.com/books?lr=&amp;id=aEobAAAAYAAJ&amp;dq=persian+empire+50+million+people&amp;q=fifty+million+people 12]. Hershlag (1980, p. 140) estimates nearly 50 million [http://books.google.com/books?id=awoVAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA140&amp;dq=persian+empire+50+million+people&amp;lr=#v=onepage&amp;q=persian%20empire%2050%20million%20people&amp;f=false 13]. Yarshater (1996, p. 47) estimates by 50 million [http://books.google.com/books?lr=&amp;id=KKkUAQAAIAAJ&amp;dq=persian+empire+50+million+people&amp;q=50+million+people 14]. Daniel (2001, p. 41) estimates at 50 million [http://books.google.com/books?id=AzqbYf9Q_2UC&amp;pg=PA41&amp;dq=persian+empire+million+people&amp;lr=#v=onepage&amp;q=persian%20empire%20million%20people&amp;f=false 15]. Meyer and Andreades (2004, p. 58) estimates to 50 million [http://books.google.com/books?id=Uwn9d01zMvAC&amp;pg=PA58&amp;dq=meyer+50+million+persian+empire&amp;lr= 16]. Pollack (2004, p. 7) estimates about 50 million [http://books.google.com/books?id=VtISTfUL-NAC&amp;pg=PA7&amp;dq=persian+empire+50+million+people&amp;lr=#v=onepage&amp;q=persian%20empire%2050%20million%20people&amp;f=false 17]. Jones (2004, p. 8) estimates over 50 million [http://books.google.com/books?id=75ueY2rqTYMC&amp;pg=PA8&amp;dq=persian+empire+million+square+miles&amp;lr=#v=onepage&amp;q=persian%20empire%20million%20square%20miles&amp;f=false 18]. Safire (2007, p. 627) estimates in 50 million [http://books.google.com/books?id=-BIGv9vIoqcC&amp;pg=PA627&amp;dq=persian+empire+million+square+miles&amp;lr=#v=onepage&amp;q=persian%20empire%20million%20square%20miles&amp;f=false 19]. Dougherty (2009, p. 6) estimates about 70 million [http://books.google.com/books?id=Hm_ZXXj-Lh0C&amp;pg=PT5&amp;dq=70+million+persian+empire#PPT5,M1 20]. Richard (2008, p. 34) estimates nearly 70 million [http://books.google.com/books?id=toJI-Z_WAC0C&amp;pg=PA34&amp;dq=persian+empire+million+square+miles&amp;lr=#v=onepage&amp;q=persian%20empire%20million%20square%20miles&amp;f=false 21]. Mitchell (2004, p. 16) estimates over 70 million [http://books.google.com/books?id=JqeIpyQM9OcC&amp;pg=PA16&amp;dq=70+million+persian+empire&amp;lr= 22]. Hanson (2001, p. 32) estimates almost 75 million [http://books.google.com/books?id=6p5mAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=70+million+persian+empire&amp;q=70+million+&amp;pgis=1 23]. West (1913, p. 85) estimates about 75 million [http://books.google.com/books?id=RWYAAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA85&amp;dq=persian+empire+million+people&amp;lr=#v=onepage&amp;q=persian%20empire%20million%20people&amp;f=false 24]. Zenos (1889, p. 2) estimates exactly 75 million [http://books.google.com/books?id=EzABAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA1&amp;dq=persian+empire+population&amp;lr= 25]. Cowley (1999 and 2001, p. 17) estimates possibly 80 million [http://books.google.com/books?id=l6JmAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=what+if%3F&amp;q=70+million&amp;pgis=1 26]. Cook (1904, p. 277) estimates exactly 80 million [http://books.google.com/books?id=258XAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA277&amp;dq=persian+empire+million+square+miles&amp;lr=#v=onepage&amp;q=persian%20empire%20million%20square%20miles&amp;f=false 27].&lt;/ref&gt; ]]

Most scholars believe&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/15283-zoroastrianism |title=ZOROASTRIANISM - JewishEncyclopedia.com |first= |last={{err|{{AUTHOR MISSING}}}} |work=jewishencyclopedia.com |year=2012 [last update] |accessdate=23 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; that key concepts of [[Zoroastrian eschatology]] and [[demonology]] influenced the [[Abrahamic religion]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;BlackRowley_1987_607b&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Black|Rowley|1987|p=607b}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Duchesne-Guillemin_1988_815&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Duchesne-Guillemin|1988|p=815}}.&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, Zoroastrianism itself inherited ideas from other belief systems and, like other &quot;practiced&quot; religions, accommodates some degree of [[syncretism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Boyce_1982_202&quot;&gt;e.g., {{harvnb|Boyce|1982|p=202}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many traits of Zoroastrianism can be traced back to the culture and beliefs of the prehistorical Indo-Iranian period, that is, to the time before the migrations that led to the [[Indo-Aryans|Indians]] and [[Iranian peoples|Iranians]] becoming distinct peoples. Zoroastrianism consequently shares elements with the [[historical Vedic religion]] that also has its origins in that era. An example is the relation of the Zoroastrian word ''Ahura'' (Ahura Mazda) and the Vedic word ''Asura'' (meaning demon). They are therefore thought{{by whom|date=November 2011}} to have descended from a common [[Proto-Indo-Iranian religion]]. However, Zoroastrianism was also strongly affected by the later culture of the Iranian [[Heroic Age (literary theory)|Heroic Age]] (1500 BCE onwards), an influence to which the Indic religions were not subject. Moreover, the other culture groups that the respective peoples came to interact with were different, for instance in 6th&amp;ndash;4th century BCE Western Iran with [[Fertile Crescent]] culture, with each side absorbing ideas from the other. Such inter-cultural influences notwithstanding, Zoroastrian &quot;scripture&quot; is essentially a product of (Indo-) Iranian culture, and representing the oldest and largest corpus pre-Islamic Iranian ideology—is considered{{by whom|date=November 2011}} a reflection of that culture. Then, together with the [[Vedas]], which represent the oldest texts of the Indian branch of Indo-Iranian culture, it is possible to reconstruct some facets of [[Proto-Indo-Iranian religion|prototypical Indo-Iranian beliefs]]. Since these two groups of sources also represent the oldest non-fragmentary evidence of [[Indo-European languages]], the analysis of them also motivated attempts to characterize an even earlier [[Proto-Indo-European religion]], and in turn influenced various unifying hypotheses like those of [[Carl Gustav Jung]] or [[James George Frazer]]{{Citation needed|date=December 2010}}. Although these unifying notions deeply influenced the [[modernism|modernists]] of the late 19th and early 20th century, they have not fared well under the scrutiny of more recent interdisciplinary peer review. The study of pre-Islamic Iran has itself undergone a radical change in direction since the 1950s, and the field is today disinclined to speculation.

Zoroastrianism is often compared with the [[Manichaeism]], which is nominally an Iranian religion but has its origins in the [[Middle-East]]ern [[Gnosticism]]. Superficially, such a comparison may be apt, as both are uncompromisingly dualistic, and Manichaeism nominally adopted many of the [[Yazata]]s for its own pantheon. Gherardo Gnoli, in ''The Encyclopaedia of Religion''&lt;!--MacMillan Library Reference USA, New York, 1993, volume 9, page 165--&gt;, says that &quot;we can assert that Manichaeism has its roots in the Iranian religious tradition and that its relationship to Mazdaism, or Zoroastrianism, is more or less like that of Christianity to Judaism&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Henning&quot;&gt;Contrast with Henning's observations: Henning, W.B., ''The Book of Giants'', BSOAS, Vol. XI, Part 1, 1943, pp. 52-74: 
''&quot;It is noteworthy that Mani, who was brought up and spent most of his life in a province of the Persian empire, and whose mother belonged to a famous Parthian family, did not make any use of the Iranian mythological tradition. There can no longer be any doubt that the Iranian names of Sām, Narīmān, etc., that appear in the Persian and Sogdian versions of the Book of the Giants, did not figure in the original edition, written by Mani in the Syriac language.&quot;''&lt;/ref&gt; As religious types, they are, however, quite different:&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Zaehner|1956|pp=53–54}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Manichaeism equated evil with matter and good with spirit, and was therefore particularly suitable as a doctrinal basis for every form of asceticism and many forms of mysticism. Zoroastrianism, on the other hand, rejects every form of asceticism, has no dualism of matter and spirit (only of good and evil), and sees the spiritual world as not very different from the natural one, and the word &quot;paradise&quot; (via Latin and Greek from Avestan ''pairi.daeza'', literally &quot;stone-bounded enclosure&quot;) applies equally to both. Manichaeism's basic doctrine was that the world and all corporeal bodies were constructed from the substance of Satan, an idea that is fundamentally at odds with the Zoroastrian notion of a world that was created by God and that is all good, and any corruption of it is an effect of the bad. From what may be inferred from many Manichean texts and a few Zoroastrian sources, the adherents of the two religions (or at least their respective priesthoods) despised each other intensely.

Many aspects of Zoroastrianism are present in the culture and mythologies of the peoples of the [[Greater Iran]], not least because Zoroastrianism was a dominant influence on the people of the cultural continent for a thousand years. Even after the rise of Islam and the loss of direct influence, Zoroastrianism remained part of the cultural heritage of the [[Iranian languages|Iranian language]]-speaking world, in part as festivals and customs, but also because [[Ferdowsi]] incorporated a number of the figures and stories from the [[Avesta]] in his epic ''[[Shahnameh|Shāhnāme]]'', which in turn is pivotal to Iranian identity.

Zoroastrianism is a tradition that has influenced the lives of its adherents for generations. It combines cosmogonic dualism and escathological monotheism. Zoroastrianism proclaims a movement through time from dualism to monotheism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title = Buddhism in China: A Historical Sketch | journal = The Journal of Religion| id =  | postscript = .}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Religious text==

===Avestan===
{{Main|Avesta|Avestan language}}
The Avesta is the religious book of Zoroastrians that contains a collection of sacred texts. The history of the Avesta is found in many [[Pahlavi scripts|Pahlavi texts]]. According to tradition, [[Ahura Mazda]] created the twenty-one nasks which [[Zoroaster]] brought to [[Vishtaspa]]. Here, two copies were created, one which was put in the house of archives, and the other put in the Imperial treasury. During Alexander's conquest of Persia, the Avesta was burned, and the scientific sections that the Greeks could use were dispersed among themselves. Under the reign of King Valax of the [[Arsacid Dynasty of Parthia|Arsacis Dynasty]], an attempt was made to restore the Avesta. During the [[Sassanid Empire]], Ardeshir ordered Tansar, [[Dastur|his high priest]], to finish the work that King Valax had started. [[Shapur I]] sent priests to locate the scientific text portions of the Avesta that were in the possession of the Greeks. Under [[Shapur II]], Arderbad Mahrespandand revised the canon to ensure its orthodox character, while under [[Khosrow I]], the Avesta was translated into Pahlavi.

The compilation of these ancient texts was successfully established underneath the Mazdean priesthood and the Sassanian emperors. Only a fraction of the texts survive today. The later manuscripts all date from this millennium, the latest being from 1288, 590 years after the fall of the Sassanian Empire. The texts that remain today are the [[Gathas]], [[Yasna]], [[Visperad]] and the [[Vendidad]]. Along with these texts is the communal household prayer book called the [[Khordeh Avesta]], which contains the [[Yasht]]s and the Siroza. The rest of the materials from the Avesta are called &quot;Avestan fragments&quot;.{{sfn|Bromiley|1995|p=124}}

=== Middle Persian/Pahlavi ===
Middle Persian and Pahlavi works created in the 9th and 10th century contain many religious Zoroastrian books, as most of the writers and copyists were part of the Zoroastrian clergy. The most significant and important books of this era include the [[Denkard]], [[Bundahishn]], [[Menog-i Khrad]], [[Selections of Zadspram]], [[Jamasp Namag]], [[Epistles of Manucher]], [[Rivayat]]s, [[Dadestan-i-Denig]], and [[Arda Viraf Namag]]. All Middle Persian texts written on Zoroastrianism during this time period are considered secondary works on the religion, and not [[scripture]]. Nonetheless, these texts have a strong influence on the religion.

==The Prophet Zoroaster==
Zoroastrianism was founded by the Prophet [[Zoroaster]] (or Zarathustra) in ancient Iran. Exactly when he lived is debated,{{by whom|date=June 2012}} as estimates range from 1700 BCE&lt;ref&gt;Boyce (1979), p. 2&lt;/ref&gt; to 500 BCE.&lt;ref&gt;Verlag (2008), p. 80&lt;/ref&gt; The precise date of the founding of Zoroastrianism is uncertain. An approximate date of 1500&amp;ndash;1200 BCE has been established through archaeological evidence and linguistic comparisons with the [[Hindu]] text, the [[Rig Veda]]. However there is no way of knowing exactly when Zoroaster lived, as he lived in what, to his people, were prehistoric times.&lt;ref&gt;Boyce (1979), p. 17&lt;/ref&gt;

Zoroaster was born in either Northeast Iran or Southwest Afghanistan. He was born into a [[Bronze Age]] culture with a [[polytheism|polytheistic]] religion, which included [[animal sacrifice]]&lt;ref&gt;Boyce (1979), p. 26&lt;/ref&gt; and the ritual use of intoxicants. This religion was quite similar to the early forms of [[Hinduism]] in India.
The name ''Zoroaster'' is a Greek rendering of the name ''Zarathustra''. He is known as ''Zarathusti'' in [[Persian language|Persian]] and ''Zaratosht'' in [[Gujarati language|Gujarati]].
Zoroaster's birth and early life are little documented. What is known is recorded in the [[Gathas]]&amp;mdash;the core of the Avesta, which contains hymns thought to be composed by Zoroaster himself. Born into the [[Spitama]] clan, he worked as a priest. He had a wife, three sons, and three daughters.
Zoroaster rejected the religion of the Bronze Age Iranians, with their many gods and oppressive [[Caste system|class structure]], in which the [[Karvis]] and [[Karapans]] (princes and priests) controlled the ordinary people. He also opposed animal sacrifices and the use of the [[hallucinogenic]] [[Haoma]] plant (possibly a species of [[Ephedra (genus)|ephedra]]) in rituals, but held the rooster as a &quot;symbol of light&quot;&lt;ref&gt;The Heretic's Feast: A History of Vegetarianism By Colin Spencer - May 15, 1995 page 60&lt;/ref&gt; and associated the [[Rooster|cock]] with &quot;good against evil&quot;&lt;ref&gt;The Heretic's Feast: A History of Vegetarianism By Colin Spencer - May 15, 1995 - page 60&lt;/ref&gt; because of his heraldic actions.

===The vision of Zoroaster===
According to Zoroastrian belief, when Zoroaster was 30 years old, he went into the [[Daiti river]] to draw water for a [[Haoma]] ceremony; when he emerged, he received a vision of Vohu Manah. After this, Vohu Manah took him to the other six Amesha Spentas, where he received the completion of his vision.&lt;ref&gt;Boyce (1979), p. 19&lt;/ref&gt; This vision radically transformed his view of the world, and he tried to teach this view to others.
Zoroaster believed in one creator God, teaching that only one God was worthy of worship. Furthermore, some of the deities of the old religion, the ''[[Daevas]]'' (''Devas'' in Sanskrit), appeared to delight in war and strife. Zoroaster said that these were evil spirits and were workers of Angra Mainyu, God's adversary.

Zoroaster's ideas did not take off quickly, and, at first, he only had one convert: his cousin Maidhyoimanha.&lt;ref&gt;Boyce (1979), pp. 30–31&lt;/ref&gt;
The local religious authorities opposed his ideas. They felt their own faiths, power, and particularly their rituals, were threatened because Zoroaster taught against over-ritualising religious ceremonies. Many ordinary people did not like Zoroaster's downgrading of the Daevas to evil spirits. After 12 years, Zoroaster left his home to find somewhere more open to new ideas. He found such a place in the country of King [[Vishtaspa]] (in [[Bactria]]). The King and his queen, Hutosa, heard Zoroaster debating with the religious leaders of his land, and decided to accept Zoroaster's ideas and make them the official religion of their kingdom. Zoroaster died in his late 70s. Very little is known of the time between Zoroaster and the [[Achaemenian]] period, except that, during this period, Zoroastrianism spread to Western Iran. By the time of the founding of the Achaemenid Empire, Zoroastrianism was already a well-established religion.

==Principal beliefs==
[[Image:Faravahar.svg|thumb|right|[[Faravahar]] (or Ferohar), one of the primary symbols of Zoroastrianism, believed to be the depiction of a ''Fravashi'' (guardian spirit)|right]]
In Zoroastrianism, [[Ahura Mazda]] is the beginning and the end, the creator of everything that can and cannot be seen, the Eternal, the Pure and the only Truth. In the [[Gathas]], the most sacred texts of Zoroastrianism thought to have been composed by Zoroaster himself, the prophet acknowledged devotion to no other divinity besides Ahura Mazda.

''Daena'' (''din'' in modern [[Persian language|Persian]]) is the eternal Law, whose order was revealed to humanity through the ''Mathra-Spenta'' (&quot;Holy Words&quot;). ''Daena'' has been used to mean religion, faith, law, and even as a translation for the Hindu and [[Buddhist]] term [[Dharma]]. The latter is often interpreted as &quot;duty&quot; but can also mean social order, right conduct, or virtue. The metaphor of the &quot;path&quot; of ''Daena'' is represented in Zoroastrianism by the [[muslin]] undershirt ''Sudra'', the &quot;Good/Holy Path&quot;, and the 72-thread ''[[Kushti]]'' girdle, the &quot;Pathfinder&quot;.

''Daena'' should not be confused with the fundamental principle ''[[asha]]'' (Vedic ''rta''), the equitable law of the universe, which governed the life of the ancient Indo-Iranians. For these, ''asha'' was the course of everything observable&amp;mdash;the motion of the planets and astral bodies; the progression of the seasons; and the pattern of daily nomadic herdsman life, governed by regular metronomic events such as sunrise and sunset. All physical creation (''geti'') was thus determined to run according to a master plan—inherent to Ahura Mazda—and violations of the order (''druj'') were violations against creation, and thus violations against Ahura Mazda. This concept of ''asha'' versus the ''druj'' should not be confused with the good-versus-evil battle evident in western religions, for although both forms of opposition express moral conflict, the ''asha'' versus ''druj'' concept is more systemic and less personal, representing, for instance, chaos (that opposes order); or &quot;uncreation&quot;, evident as natural decay (that opposes creation); or more simply &quot;the lie&quot; (that opposes truth and righteousness). Moreover, in his role as the one uncreated creator of all, Ahura Mazda is not the creator of ''druj'', which is &quot;nothing&quot;, anti-creation, and thus (likewise) uncreated. Thus, in Zoroaster's revelation, Ahura Mazda was perceived to be the creator of only the good (Yasna 31.4), the &quot;supreme benevolent providence&quot; (Yasna 43.11), that will ultimately triumph (Yasna 48.1).
[[File:Parsee Wedding 1905.jpg|thumb|left|A ''[[Parsi people|Parsi]]'' Wedding, 1905]]

In this [[Model (abstract)|schema]] of ''asha'' versus ''druj'', mortal beings (both humans and animals) play a critical role, for they too are created. Here, in their lives, they are active participants in the conflict, and it is their ''duty'' to defend order, which would decay without counter''action''. Throughout the [[Gathas]], Zoroaster emphasizes deeds and actions, and accordingly [[asceticism]] is frowned upon in Zoroastrianism. In later Zoroastrianism, this was explained as fleeing from the experiences of life, which was the very purpose that the ''urvan'' (most commonly translated as the &quot;soul&quot;) was sent into the mortal world to collect. The avoidance of any aspect of life, which includes the avoidance of the pleasures of life, is a shirking of the responsibility and duty to oneself, one's ''urvan'', and one's family and social obligations.

Central to Zoroastrianism is the emphasis on moral choice, to choose the responsibility and duty for which one is in the mortal world, or to give up this duty and so facilitate the work of ''druj''. Similarly, [[predestination]] is rejected in Zoroastrian teaching. Humans bear responsibility for all situations they are in, and in the way they act toward one another. Reward, punishment, happiness, and grief all depend on how individuals live their lives.&lt;ref name=Cavendish/&gt;

In Zoroastrianism, good transpires for those who do righteous deeds. Those who do evil have themselves to blame for their ruin. Zoroastrian morality is then to be summed up in the simple phrase, &quot;good thoughts, good words, good deeds&quot; (''Humata'', ''Hukhta'', ''Hvarshta'' in [[Avestan language|Avestan]]), for it is through these that ''asha'' is maintained and ''druj'' is kept in check.

Through accumulation, several other beliefs were introduced to the religion that, in some instances, supersede those expressed in the [[Gathas]]. In the late 19th century, the moral and immoral forces came to be represented by ''[[Spenta Mainyu]]'' and its [[antithesis]] ''[[Angra Mainyu]]'', the &quot;good spirit&quot; and &quot;evil spirit&quot; emanations of Ahura Mazda, respectively. Although the names are old, this opposition is a modern Western-influenced development popularized by [[Martin Haug]] in the 1880s, and was, in effect, a realignment of the precepts of [[Zurvanism]] (Zurvanite Zoroastrianism), which had invented a ''third'' deity, ''Zurvan'', to explain a mention of twinship (''Yasna'' 30.3) between the moral and immoral. Although Zurvanism had died out by the 10th century, the critical question of the &quot;twin brothers&quot; mentioned in ''Yasna'' 30.3 remained, and Haug's explanation provided a convenient defence against Christian missionaries, who disparaged the Parsis for their &quot;[[dualism]]&quot;. Haug's concept was subsequently disseminated as a Parsi interpretation, thus corroborating Haug's theory, and the idea became so popular that it is now almost universally accepted as doctrine.{{Citation needed|reason=Nov 2009|date=November 2009}}

Achaemenid era (648–330 BCE) Zoroastrianism developed the abstract concepts of heaven and hell, as well as personal and final judgment, all of which are only alluded to in the [[Gathas]]. ''Yasna'' 19, which has only survived in a [[Sassanid dynasty|Sassanid era]] (&lt;nowiki&gt;[&lt;/nowiki&gt;&amp;ndash;650 CE&lt;nowiki&gt;]&lt;/nowiki&gt; ''Zend'' commentary on the ''[[Ahuna Vairya]]'' invocation), prescribes a Path to [[Judgment]] known as the ''Chinvat Peretum'' or ''[[Chinvat bridge]]'' (''cf:'' [[As-Sirāt]] in Islam), which all souls had to cross, and judgment (over thoughts, words, and deeds performed during a lifetime) was passed as they were doing so. However, the Zoroastrian personal judgment is not final. At the end of time, when evil is finally defeated, all souls will be ultimately reunited with their [[Fravashi]]. Thus, Zoroastrianism can be said to be a [[Universalism|universalist]] religion with respect to salvation.

In addition, and strongly influenced by [[Babylonian]] and [[Akkadian]] practices, the Achaemenids popularized [[shrines]] and temples, hitherto alien forms of worship. In the wake of Achaemenid expansion, shrines were constructed throughout the empire and particularly influenced the role of [[Mithra]], [[Aredvi Sura Anahita]], [[Vahram|Verethregna]] and [[Tishtrya]], all of which, in addition to their original (proto-)Indo-Iranian functions, now also received Perso-Babylonian functions.

===Creation of the universe===
According to the Zoroastrian [[creation myth|story of creation]], [[Ahura Mazda]] existed in light in goodness above, while [[Angra Mainyu]] existed in darkness and ignorance below. They have existed independently of each other for all time, and manifest contrary substances. Ahura Mazda first created seven abstract heavenly beings called ''[[Amesha Spenta]]s'', who support him and represent beneficent aspects, along with numerous ''yazads'', lesser beings worthy of worship. He then created the universe itself in order to ensnare evil. Ahura Mazda created the floating, egg-shaped universe in two parts: first the spiritual (''menog'') and 3,000 years later, the physical (''getig''). Ahura Mazda then created [[Keyumars|Gayomard]], the archetypical perfect man, and the first bull.&lt;ref name=Cavendish&gt;{{Citation|title=Mythology: an Illustrated Encyclopedia |pages=40–45 |first1=Richard |last1=Cavendish |first2=Trevor Oswald |last2=Ling |publisher=Rizzoli |year=1980 |isbn=0847802868 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=GdEnAAAAYAAJ}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While Ahura Mazda created the universe and mankind, Angra Mainyu, whose instinct is to destroy, miscreated demons, evil ''yazads'', and noxious creatures (''khrafstar'') such as snakes, ants, and flies. Angra Mainyu created an opposite, evil being for each good being, except for humans, which he found he could not match. Angra Mainyu invaded the universe through the base of the sky, inflicting [[Keyumars|Gayomard]] and the bull with suffering and death. However, the evil forces were trapped in the universe and could not retreat. The dying primordial man and bull emitted seeds. From the bull's seed grew all beneficial plants and animals of the world, and from the man's seed grew a plant whose leaves became the first human couple. Man thus struggles in a two-fold universe trapped with evil. The evils of this physical world are not products of an inherent weakness, but are the fault of Angra Mainyu's assault on creation. This assault turned the perfectly flat, peaceful, and ever day-lit world into a mountainous, violent place that is half night.&lt;ref name=Cavendish/&gt;

===Renovation and judgment===
{{main|Frashokereti}}
Zoroastrianism also includes beliefs about the [[eschatology|renovation of the world]] and individual judgment (cf. [[general judgment|general]] and [[particular judgment]]), including the [[resurrection of the dead]]. 

Individual judgment at death is by the [[Chinvat Bridge|Bridge of Judgment]], which each human must cross, facing a spiritual judgment. Humans' actions under their free will determine the outcome. One is either greeted at the bridge by a beautiful, sweet-smelling maiden or by an ugly, foul-smelling old woman. The maiden leads the dead safely across the bridge to the [[Amesha Spenta]] Good Mind, who carries the dead to paradise. The old woman leads the dead down a bridge that narrows until the departed falls off into the abyss of hell.&lt;ref name=Cavendish/&gt;

Zoroastrian hell is reformative; punishments fit the crimes, and souls do not rest in eternal damnation. Hell contains foul smells and evil food, and souls are packed tightly together although they believe they are in total isolation.&lt;ref name=Cavendish/&gt;

In [[Frashokereti|Zoroastrian eschatology]], a 3,000-year struggle between good and evil will be fought, punctuated by evil's final assault. During the final assault, the sun and moon will darken and mankind will lose its reverence for religion, family, and elders. The world will fall into winter, and Angra Mainyu's most fearsome miscreant, Azi Dahaka, will break free and terrorize the world.&lt;ref name=Cavendish/&gt;

The final savior of the world, [[Saoshyant]], will be born to a virgin impregnated by the seed of Zoroaster while bathing in a lake. Saoshyant will raise the dead – including those in both heaven and hell – for final judgment, returning the wicked to hell to be purged of bodily sin. Next, all will wade through a river of molten metal in which the righteous will not burn. Heavenly forces will ultimately triumph over evil, rendering it forever impotent. Saoshyant and Ahura Mazda will offer a bull as a final sacrifice for all time, and all men will become immortal. Mountains will again flatten and valleys will rise; heaven will descend to the moon, and the earth will rise to meet them both.&lt;ref name=Cavendish/&gt;

Man requires two judgments because there are as many aspects to his being: spiritual (''menog'') and physical (''getig'').&lt;ref name=Cavendish/&gt;

===Head covering===
The Zarathushtri also practice traditional head covering ritual similar to that of Judaism (probably predating it). It is vital to the practice, and according to Dr. Hoshang Bhadha, {{quotation|A Zarathustri is enjoined to cover his head at all times. It is one of the basic disciplines for a Zarathustri. If you have ever look at the pictures of Zarathustris from the past, you will recognize them simply because they were wearing cap or turban covering their head. If you read the description of Parsees from the past... it is emphatically described that whether a child, female or male they all had their head(s) covered. It is unfortunate that our own community people laugh on us for wearing cap, which is the foundation of all our religion practices. Needless to say, today a Zarathustri wearing cap will get strange glances; he/she will evoke giggles and some people even consider them as one belonging to the Stone Age. However, such reactions are seldom seen when a Zarathustri will observe a Muslim or Jew demonstrating their practice of covering head during and out of their prayer area. It is a common sight to see a Zarathustri coming out from the Agiary with one hand over his head, not as a respect but to prepare himself/ herself to remove the cap/scarf before he/she reaches the main gate. Some people feel embarrassed to wear in public whereas some remove it to protect their hairstyle. My dear Zarathustris, wearing cap is not imposed upon us but it is a remedy to protect oneself from destructive thought process[es]...}}&lt;ref&gt;Hoshang, Dr. Bhadha. http://tenets.zoroastrianism.com/topi33.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Adherents==
[[Image:Ateshkadeh yazd.jpg|thumb|right|The Zoroastrian [[Fire temple#Atash Behram|Atash Behram]] of [[Yazd]], [[Iran]].]]
{{Main|List of Zoroastrians}}
India is considered to be home to the largest Zoroastrian population in the world. When the Islamic armies, under the first Caliphs, invaded Persia, those locals who were unwilling to convert to Islam sought refuge, first in the mountains of Northern Iran, then the regions of Yazd and its surrounding villages. Later, in the ninth century CE, a group sought refuge in the western coastal region of India, and also scattered to other regions of the world. In recent years, the United States has become a significant destination of Zoroastrian populations, holding the second largest population of Zoroastrians after India.

Small Zoroastrian communities may be found all over the world, with a continuing concentration in Western India, Central Iran, and Southern Pakistan. Zoroastrians of the [[diaspora]] are primarily located in [[Great Britain]] and the former British colonies—in particular [[Canada]] and [[Australia]]. Zoroastrian communities comprised two main groups of people: those of [[South Asian]] Zoroastrian background known as [[Parsi people|Parsis]] (or Parsees), and those of Central Asian background.

===Iran and Central Asia===
{{Main|Zoroastrians in Iran}}
Communities exist in [[Tehran]], as well as in [[Yazd]], [[Kerman]] and [[Kermanshah]], where many still speak an Iranian language distinct from the usual [[Persian language|Persian]]. They call their language [[Dari (Zoroastrian)|Dari]] (not to be confused with the [[Dari (Persian)|Dari of Afghanistan]]). Their language is also called ''Gabri'' or ''[[Bahdinan]]'' (also the name of a modern [[Kurdish language|Kurdish]] dialect), literally &quot;of the Good Religion&quot;. Sometimes their language is named for the cities in which it is spoken, such as ''Yazdi'' or ''Kermani''. Iranian Zoroastrians were historically called [[Gabr|''Gabr''s]], originally without a pejorative connotation but in the present-day derogatorily applied to all non-Muslims.

There is some interest among Iranians, as well as people in various Central Asian countries such as [[Tajikistan]] and [[Uzbekistan]], in their ancient Zoroastrian heritage; some people in these countries take notice of their Zoroastrian past{{Who|date=January 2010}}. At the request of the government of [[Tajikistan]], [[UNESCO]] declared 2003 a year to celebrate the &quot;3000th anniversary of Zoroastrian culture&quot;, with special events throughout the world.

===In South Asia===
{{Unreferenced section|date=November 2009}}
{{Main|Parsi|Irani (India)}}
[[Image:Parsi-navjote-sitting.jpg|thumb|right|upright|[[Parsi people|Parsi]] ''[[Navjote]]'' ceremony (rites of admission into the Zoroastrian faith)]]
Following the fall of the [[Sassanid Empire]] in 651 CE, many Zoroastrians migrated. Among them were several groups who ventured to [[Gujarat]] on the western shores of the [[Indian subcontinent]], where they finally settled. The descendants of those refugees are today known as the Parsis. The year of arrival on the subcontinent cannot be precisely established, and Parsi legend and tradition assigns various dates to the event.

In the Indian subcontinent, these Zoroastrians enjoyed tolerance and even admiration from other religious communities.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}} From the 19th century onward, the Parsis gained a reputation for their education and widespread influence in all aspects of society, partly due to the divisive strategy of [[British Empire|British colonialism]], which favored certain minorities. Parsis are stereotypically viewed as among the most Anglicised and &quot;Westernised&quot; of the various minority groups.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}} They have also played an instrumental role in the economic development of the region over many decades; several of the best-known business conglomerates of India are run by Parsi-Zoroastrians, including [[Tata Group|Tata]], [[Godrej family|Godrej]], and [[Wadia]] families.

===Demographics===
{{main|List of countries by Zoroastrian population}}
In 2004, the number of Zoroastrians worldwide was estimated at between 145,000 and 210,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/06/us/06faith.html|title=Zoroastrians Keep the Faith, and Keep Dwindling|publisher=The New York Times|date=2008-09-06|accessdate=2009-10-03 | first=Laurie | last=Goodstein}}&lt;/ref&gt; India's 2001 Census found 69,601 Parsi Zoroastrians. In [[Pakistan]], they number 5,000, mostly living in [[Karachi]]; they have been reinforced in recent years with a number of Zoroastrian refugees from Iran. [[North America]] is thought to be home to 18,000–25,000 Zoroastrians of both [[South Asian]] and [[Iran]]ian background. A further 3,500 live in [[Australia]] (mainly in [[Sydney]]). Iran's figures of Zoroastrians have ranged widely; the last census (1974) before the [[Iranian Revolution|revolution of 1979]] revealed 21,400 Zoroastrians.

Some 10,000 adherents remain in the [[Central Asia]]n regions that were once considered the traditional stronghold of Zoroastrianism, i.e., [[Bactria]] (see also [[Balkh]]), which is in Northern Afghanistan; [[Sogdiana]]; [[Margiana]]; and other areas close to [[Zoroaster#Place|Zoroaster's homeland]].

In the Indian census of 2001, the Parsis numbered 69,601, representing about 0.006% of the total population of India, with a concentration in and around the city of [[Mumbai]]. Due to a low birth rate and high rate of [[emigration]], demographic trends project that by 2020 the Parsis will number only about 23,000 or 0.002% of the total population of India. The Parsis would then cease to be called a community and will be labeled a &quot;tribe&quot;. By 2008, the birth-to-death ratio was 1:5; 200 births per year to 1,000 deaths.&lt;ref name=&quot;doomed&quot;&gt;{{Citation | title=Doomed by faith | url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/asia/doomed-by--faith-856095.html | publisher=Guardian | date=2008-06-28 | accessdate=2008-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Iran, emigration, out-marriage and low birth rates are likewise leading to a decline in the Zoroastrian population, which is currently estimated at under 20,000.&lt;ref&gt;[[Richard Foltz]], &quot;Zoroastrians in Iran: What Future in the Homeland?&quot; ''Middle East Journal'' 65/1 (2011): 73–84.&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

;Works cited
* {{citation|last=Khan|first=Roni K|year=1996|chapter=The Tenets of Zoroastrianism|url=http://tenets.parsizoroastrianism.com/}}
* {{citation|editor-last=Black|editor-first=Matthew|editor2-last=Rowley|editor2-first=H. H.|title=[[Peake's Commentary on the Bible]]|year=1982|publisher=Nelson|location=New York|isbn=0-415-05147-9}}
* {{citation|last=Boyce|first=Mary|title=Textual sources for the study of Zoroastrianism|location=Manchester|publisher=Manchester UP|year=1984|isbn=0-226-06930-3}}
* {{citation|last=Boyce|first=Mary|title=Zoroastrianism: A Shadowy but Powerful Presence in the Judaeo-Christian World|location=London|publisher=William's Trust|year=1987}}
* {{citation|last=Boyce|first=Mary|title=Zoroastrians: Their Religious Beliefs and Practices|publisher=Routledge|location=London|year=1979|isbn=0-415-23903-6}} (note to catalogue searchers: the spine of this edition misprints the title &quot;Zoroastrians&quot; as &quot;Zoroastians&quot;, and this may lead to catalogue errors)
* {{citation|last=Boyce|first=Mary|title=The History of Zoroastrianism|volume=1|year=1975|publisher=Brill|location=Leiden|id=(repr. 1996)|isbn=90-04-10474-7}}
* {{citation|last=Boyce|first=Mary|title=The History of Zoroastrianism|volume=2|year=1982|publisher=Brill|location=Leiden|id=(repr. 1997)|isbn=90-04-06506-7}}
* {{citation|last=Boyce|first=Mary|title=Zoroastrians: Their Religious Beliefs and Practices|publisher=Routledge|location=London|year=2007|isbn=978-0-415-23903-5}}* {{citation|last=Boyce|first=Mary|chapter=Ahura Mazdā|title=Encyclopaedia Iranica|location=New York|publisher=Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul|year=1983|volume=1}} pages 684–687
* {{citation|last=Bulliet|first=Richard W.|title=Conversion to Islam in the Medieval Period: An Essay in Quantitative History|year=1979|location=Cambridge|publisher=Harvard UP|isbn=0-674-17035-0}}
* {{citation|last=Carroll|first=Warren H.|year=1985|title=Founding Of Christendom: History Of Christendom|volume=1|publisher=Illinois UP|location=Urbana|id=(repr. 2004)|isbn=0-931888-21-2}}
* {{citation|last=Clark|first=Peter|title=Zoroastrianism. An Introduction to an Ancient Faith|location=Brighton|publisher=Sussex Academic Press|year=1998|isbn=1-898723-78-8}}
* {{citation|last=Dhalla|first=Maneckji Nusservanji|publisher=OUP|location=New York|year=1938| title=History of Zoroastrianism}}
* {{citation|last=Duchesne-Guillemin|first=Jacques|chapter=Zoroastrianism|title=Encyclopedia Americana|location=Danbury|publisher=Grolier|year=1988|volume=29}} pages 813–815
* {{citation|last=Duchesne-Guillemin|first=Jacques|chapter=Zoroastrianism: Relation to other religions|title=[[Encyclopædia Britannica]]|edition=Online|year=2006|url=http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9207|accessdate=2006-05-31}}
* {{citation|last=Eliade|first=Mircea|last2=Couliano|first2=Ioan P.|year=1991|title=The Eliade Guide to World Religions|location=New York|publisher=Harper Collins}}
* {{Citation |first=Richard |last=Foltz |authorlink=Richard Foltz |title=Spirituality in the Land of the Noble: How Iran Shaped the World's Religions |publisher=Oneworld publications |location=Oxford |year=2004 |isbn=1-85168-336-4}}
* {{citation|last=Kellens|first=Jean|chapter=Avesta|title=Encyclopaedia Iranica|volume=3|location=New York|publisher=Routledge and Kegan Paul}} pages 35–44.
* {{Citation|last=King|first=Charles William|year=1887|title=Gnostics and their Remains Ancient and Mediaeval|publisher=Bell &amp; Daldy|location=London|isbn=0-7661-0381-1 (repr. 1998)}}
* {{citation|last=Melton|first=J. Gordon|year=1996|title=Encyclopedia of American Religions|location=Detroit|publisher=Gale Research}}
* {{citation|last=Malandra|first=William W.|title=An Introduction to Ancient Iranian Religion. Readings from the Avesta and Achaemenid Inscriptions|location=Minneapolis|publisher=U. Minnesota Press|year=1983|isbn=0-8166-1114-9}}
* {{citation|last=Malandra|first=William W.|year=2005|chapter=Zoroastrianism: Historical Review|title=Encyclopaedia Iranica|location=New York|publisher=iranicaonline.org|chapter-url=http://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/zoroastrianism-i-historical-review}}
* {{citation|last=Moulton|first=James Hope|title=The Treasure of the Magi: A Study of Modern Zoroastrianism|publisher=OUP|location=London|year=1917|id=1-564-59612-5 (repr. 1997)}}
* {{citation|last=Russell|first=James R.|title=Zoroastrianism in Armenia (Harvard Iranian Series)|location=Oxford|publisher=[[Harvard University Press]]|year=1987|isbn=0-674-96850-6}}
* {{citation|editor-last=Simpson|editor-first=John A.|editor2-last=Weiner|editor2-first=Edmund S.|chapter=Zoroastrianism|title=Oxford English Dictionary|location=London|publisher=Oxford UP|year=1989|edition=2nd|isbn=0-19-861186-2}}
* {{citation|last=Stolze|first=Franz|title=Die Achaemenidischen und Sasanidischen Denkmäler und Inschriften von Persepolis, Istakhr, Pasargadae, Shâpûr|publisher=A. Asher|location=Berlin|year=1882}}
* {{citation|last=Zaehner|first=Robert Charles|title=The Dawn and Twilight of Zoroastrianism|location=London|publisher=Phoenix Press|year=1961|isbn=1-84212-165-0}}
{{Refend}}
* {{citation|last=Verlag|first=Chronik|publisher=Konecky and Konecky|location=United States|year=2008| title=The Chronicle of World History}}
* {{citation|last=Robinson|first=B.A.|year=2008|title=Zoroastrianism: Holy text, beliefs and practices|date=2010-03-01|accessdate=2010-03-01|url=http://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/zoroastrianism-i-historical-review}}
* [[Saga of the Aryans]], Historical novel on ancient Iranian migrations by Porus Homi Havewala, Published Mumbai, India (2005, 2010).

==External links==
{{Prone to spam|date=April 2012}}
{{Z148}}&lt;!--     {{No more links}}

       Please be cautious adding more external links.

Wikipedia is not a collection of links and should it be used for advertising. 

     Excessive or inappropriate links will be removed.   

 See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.

If there are already suitable links, propose additions or replacements on
the article's talk page, or submit your link to the relevant category at 
the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org) and link there  using {{Dmoz}}.

--&gt;
{{Portal|Zoroastrianism|Ancient Near East|Iran}}
{{Commons category|Zoroastrianism}}
* {{Dmoz|Society/Religion_and_Spirituality/Zoroastrianism|Zoroastrianism}}&lt;br /&gt;(includes a list of Zoroastrian organizations)

{{Religion topics|state=collapsed}}

&lt;!-- Note that the [*Category:Zoroastrianism] is already a sub-category under
[:Category:Indo-European], [:Category:Eastern culture] and various other categories.--&gt;

[[Category:Iranian religions]]
[[Category:Monotheistic religions]]
[[Category:Religion in Iran]]
[[Category:Zoroastrianism| ]]
[[Category:Greek loanwords]]

[[af:Zoroastrisme]]
[[als:Zoroastrismus]]
[[ar:زرادشتية]]
[[an:Zoroastrismo]]
[[ast:Zoroastrismu]]
[[az:Zərdüştilik]]
[[be:Зараастрызм]]
[[be-x-old:Зараастрызм]]
[[bg:Зороастризъм]]
[[bo:ཛོ་​ར་​སིའི་​ཆོས་​ལུགས།]]
[[bs:Zoroastrizam]]
[[br:Zoroastregezh]]
[[ca:Zoroastrisme]]
[[cv:Сăртăш]]
[[ceb:Sorowastrismo]]
[[cs:Zoroastrismus]]
[[cy:Zoroastriaeth]]
[[da:Zarathustrianisme]]
[[de:Zoroastrismus]]
[[dv:ފާރިސީދީން]]
[[et:Zoroastrism]]
[[el:Ζωροαστρισμός]]
[[es:Zoroastrismo]]
[[eo:Zaratuŝtrismo]]
[[eu:Zoroastrismo]]
[[fa:دین زردشتی]]
[[hif:Zoroastrianism]]
[[fr:Zoroastrisme]]
[[fy:Zoroastrisme]]
[[ga:An Sorastrachas]]
[[gl:Zoroastrismo]]
[[ko:조로아스터교]]
[[hy:Զրադաշտականություն]]
[[hi:पारसी धर्म]]
[[hr:Zoroastrizam]]
[[id:Zoroastrianisme]]
[[ia:Zoroastrismo]]
[[is:Sóróismi]]
[[it:Zoroastrismo]]
[[he:זורואסטריות]]
[[ka:ზოროასტრიზმი]]
[[kk:Заратуштрашылдық]]
[[sw:Uzoroastro]]
[[ku:Zerdeştîtî]]
[[ky:Зороастризм]]
[[lad:Zoroastrizmo]]
[[la:Zoroastrismus]]
[[lv:Zoroastrisms]]
[[lt:Zoroastrizmas]]
[[li:Zoroastrisme]]
[[hu:Zoroasztrizmus]]
[[mk:Зороастризам]]
[[ml:സൊറോസ്ട്രിയന്‍ മതം]]
[[mr:पारशी धर्म]]
[[ms:Majusi]]
[[mwl:Zoroastrismo]]
[[mdf:Зороастризма]]
[[my:ဇိုရိုရက်စထရာဘာသာ]]
[[nl:Zoroastrisme]]
[[ja:ゾロアスター教]]
[[no:Zoroastrisme]]
[[nn:Parsisme]]
[[oc:Zoroastrisme]]
[[uz:Zardushtiylik]]
[[pnb:پارسی]]
[[ps:زرتشتيت]]
[[nds:Zoroastrismus]]
[[pl:Zaratusztrianizm]]
[[pt:Zoroastrismo]]
[[ro:Zoroastrism]]
[[rue:Зороастрізм]]
[[ru:Зороастризм]]
[[sah:Зороастризм]]
[[sco:Zoroastrianism]]
[[simple:Zoroastrianism]]
[[sk:Zoroastrizmus]]
[[sl:Zaratustrstvo]]
[[ckb:ئایینی زەردەشتی]]
[[sr:Зороастризам]]
[[sh:Zoroastrizam]]
[[su:Zoroastrianisme]]
[[fi:Zarathustralaisuus]]
[[sv:Zoroastrism]]
[[tl:Soroastrismo]]
[[ta:சரத்துஸ்திர சமயம்]]
[[te:జొరాస్ట్రియన్ మతము]]
[[th:ศาสนาโซโรอัสเตอร์]]
[[tg:Дини зардуштӣ]]
[[tr:Zerdüştlük]]
[[uk:Зороастризм]]
[[ur:زرتشتیت]]
[[vi:Hỏa giáo]]
[[fiu-vro:Zoroastrism]]
[[war:Zoroastrianismo]]
[[yi:זאראאסטריזם]]
[[zh-yue:瑣羅亞斯德教]]
[[bat-smg:Zuoruoastrėzmos]]
[[zh:琐罗亚斯德教]]</text>
      <sha1>dfqdwfa69b8gkvn4h44spydjeo7l2zi</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
