<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Aspartame controversy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6821757</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521093362</id>
      <parentid>519597466</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T19:03:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mediclazarus</username>
        <id>7929318</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Weight change and hunger */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="57087">{{Use mdy dates|date=September 2011}}
The [[artificial sweetener]] '''aspartame''' has been the subject of several '''controversies''' since its initial approval by the [[U.S. Food and Drug Administration]] (FDA) in 1974. The FDA approval of [[aspartame]] was highly contested,&lt;ref name=60minutes/&gt; with critics alleging that the quality of the initial research supporting its safety was inadequate and flawed and that [[Conflict of interest|conflicts of interest]] marred the approval of aspartame.&lt;ref name=GAO87/&gt;&lt;!--First sentence of this document: &quot;Since 1974, aspartame, a food additive marketed under the brand name NutraSweetB, has been the subject of controversy.&quot;--&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/washingtonpost_historical/access/125899752.html?dids=125899752:125899752&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT |work=Washington Post |title=Controversy Surrounds Sweetener |first=Carole |last=Sugarman |date=1983-07-03 |accessdate=2008-11-25 |pages=D1–2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=pmid10628311&gt;{{cite journal |journal=FDA Consumer Magazine |last=Henkel |first=John |title=Sugar Substitutes: Americans Opt for Sweetness and Lite |year=1999 |volume=33 |issue=6 |pmid=10628311 |url=http://www.fda.gov/fdac/features/1999/699_sugar.html |archiveurl=http://replay.waybackmachine.org/20070102024642/http://www.fda.gov/fdac/features/1999/699_sugar.html |archivedate=January 2, 2007 |pages=12–6}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1987, the U.S. [[Government Accountability Office]] concluded that the food additive approval process had been followed properly for aspartame.&lt;ref name=GAO87&gt;{{cite book |chapterurl=http://www.gao.gov/docdblite/info.php?rptno=HRD-87-46 |chapter=Food Additive Approval Process Followed for Aspartame |url=http://archive.gao.gov/d28t5/133460.pdf |title=Food Additive Approval Process Followed for Aspartame GAO/HRD-87-46 |publisher=United States General Accounting Office |date=June 18, 1987}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=GAO86&gt;{{cite web |url=http://archive.gao.gov/d4t4/130780.pdf |title=Six Former HHS Employees' Involvement in Aspartame's Approval GAO/HRD-86-109BR |publisher=United States General Accounting Office |month=July |year=1986}}&lt;/ref&gt; In spite of this, critics such as activist Betty Martini&lt;ref&gt;Sometimes styled as &quot;Dr. Betty Martini&quot;.  Martini claims to have been awarded an honorary Doctor of Humanities degree at her site, http://www.mpwhi.com/, but does not specify by which institution.&lt;/ref&gt;  have promoted undocumented claims that numerous health risks (such as multiple sclerosis, systemic lupus, methanol toxicity, blindness, spasms, shooting pains, seizures, headaches, depression, anxiety, memory loss, birth defects and death&lt;ref name=MAN_Markle/&gt;) are associated with the consumption of aspartame in normal doses. These health risk claims have been examined and debunked by numerous scientific research projects, and are also generally dismissed by governments and major health and food safety organizations.&lt;ref name=GAO87/&gt;&lt;ref name=Magnuson/&gt;&lt;ref name=urbanlegends/&gt;

Publicity of this controversy has been spread through an elaborate [[health scare]]&lt;ref name=Flaherty/&gt; and &quot;Internet smear campaign&quot;&lt;ref name=Newton/&gt; involving [[hoax]]&lt;ref name=Flaherty/&gt;&lt;ref name=Newton/&gt;&lt;ref name=Edell/&gt; e-mails repeating Betty Martini's widely circulated [[conspiracy theory]]. Her undocumented claims are still repeated by thousands of [[self-published]] Web sites.

Aspartame has been found to be safe for human consumption by more than ninety countries worldwide,&lt;ref name=&quot;Health Canada&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hc-sc.gc.ca/fn-an/securit/addit/sweeten-edulcor/aspartame-eng.php |title=Aspartame |work=Sugar Substitutes |publisher=[[Health Canada]] |accessdate=2008-11-08| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20081009062350/http://www.hc-sc.gc.ca/fn-an/securit/addit/sweeten-edulcor/aspartame-eng.php| archivedate= October 09 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=FSANZ&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.foodstandards.gov.au/consumerinformation/aspartame.cfm |title=Food Standards Australia New Zealand: Aspartame |date= September 8, 2011 |publisher=[[Food Standards Australia New Zealand]] |accessdate= September 13, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; with FDA officials describing aspartame as &quot;one of the most thoroughly tested and studied food additives the agency has ever approved&quot; and its safety as &quot;clear cut&quot;.&lt;ref name=pmid10628311/&gt; The weight of existing scientific evidence indicates that aspartame is safe as a non-nutritive sweetener.&lt;ref name=Magnuson&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Magnuson |first1=B. A. |last2=Burdock |first2=G. A. |last3=Doull |first3=J. |last4=Kroes |first4=R. M. |last5=Marsh |first5=G. M. |last6=Pariza |first6=M. W. |last7=Spencer |first7=P. S. |last8=Waddell |first8=W. J. |last9=Walker |first9=R. |title=Aspartame: A Safety Evaluation Based on Current Use Levels, Regulations, and Toxicological and Epidemiological Studies |journal=Critical Reviews in Toxicology |volume=37 |issue=8 |pages=629–727 |year=2007 |pmid=17828671 |doi=10.1080/10408440701516184}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History of approval and controversies over safety ==
The controversy over aspartame safety originated in perceived irregularities in the aspartame approval process during the 1970s and early 1980s, including allegations of conflicts of interest and claims that aspartame producer [[G. D. Searle &amp; Company|G.D. Searle]] had withheld and falsified safety data. In 1996, the controversy reached a wider audience with a ''[[60 Minutes]]'' report&lt;ref name=60minutes&gt;{{cite news|work=[[60 Minutes]]|url=http://video.google.com/videoplay?docid=5805190307148690830#|title=How Sweet Is It?|date=December 29, 1996|accessdate=February 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; that discussed criticisms of the FDA approval process and concerns that aspartame could cause brain tumors in humans. The ''60 Minutes'' special stated that &quot;aspartame's approval was one of the most contested in FDA history.&quot;&lt;ref name=60minutes/&gt;

Around the same time, one of many [[Usenet]] posts authored by Betty Martini was possibly slightly altered (but still largely identical with originals) and then widely circulated under the pen name &quot;Nancy Markle&quot;, creating the basis for a misleading and unverifiable hoax [[chain letter]] that was spread through the Internet.&lt;ref name=urbanlegends&gt;{{cite web|url=http://urbanlegends.about.com/library/blasp.htm|title= Aspartame Warning|publisher=[[About.com]]}} – the Nancy Markle chain email.&lt;/ref&gt; Numerous websites have spread the email's claims, which were not backed by scientific evidence, about safety issues purportedly linked to aspartame, including [[Gulf War Syndrome]] and [[lupus]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Should You Sour on Aspartame?|url=http://www.tuftshealthletter.com/ShowArticle.aspx?rowId=347|publisher=Tufts University Health and Nutrition Letter|accessdate=February 4, 2011| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20101224173306/http://tuftshealthletter.com/ShowArticle.aspx?rowId=347| archivedate= December 24, 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== USFDA approval ===
Aspartame was originally approved for use in dry foods in 1974 by then FDA Commissioner Alexander Schmidt after review by the FDA's Center for Food Safety and Applied Nutrition. Searle had submitted 168 studies&lt;ref name=GAO87/&gt;{{Rp|20|date=May 2009}} on aspartame, including seven animal studies that were considered crucial by the FDA.&lt;ref name=GAO87/&gt;{{Rp|21|date=May 2009}} Soon afterwards, [[John Olney]], a professor of psychiatry and prominent critic of [[Monosodium glutamate|MSG]], along with James Turner, a public-interest lawyer and author of an anti-food-additive book, filed a petition for a public hearing, citing safety concerns.&lt;ref name=GAO87/&gt;{{Rp|38|date=May 2009}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Cockburn A.|year=2007|title=Rumsfeld: His Rise, Fall, and Catastrophic Legacy|url=http://books.google.com/?id=2Di2D4R25bEC&amp;printsec=frontcover#PPA63,M1|publisher=Simon and Schuster|isbn=978-1-4165-3574-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Rp|63–4|date=May 2009}} Other criticisms (presented in the 1996 ''60 Minutes'' special) of the Searle studies included assertions of unreported medical treatments that may have affected the study outcomes and discrepancies in the reported data.&lt;ref name=60minutes/&gt; Schmidt agreed, pending an investigation into alleged improprieties in safety studies for aspartame and several drugs.
&lt;!-- Pulled for now, see below comment and talk page.  The [[United States Department of Justice]] instituted [[grand jury]] proceedings against Searle for fraud in one of its drug studies.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}} --&gt;
In December 1975, the FDA placed a stay on the aspartame approval, preventing Searle from marketing aspartame.&lt;ref name=GAO87/&gt;{{Rp|28|date=May 2009}} The Searle studies were criticized by the FDA commissioner as &quot;...&amp;nbsp;at best&amp;nbsp;... sloppy and suffering from &quot;...&amp;nbsp;a pattern of conduct which compromises the scientific integrity of the studies.&quot;&lt;ref name=60minutes/&gt;
&lt;!--

There is a substantial difference between what we have stated (&quot;...&amp;nbsp;instituted [[grand jury]] proceedings&quot; and &quot;one&quot;&amp;nbsp;... &quot;drug studies&quot;) and the following. The discrepancy needs to be cleared up:

&quot;In response to the report, the F.D.A. asked the Justice Department to open a grand jury investigation into whether two of Searle's aspartame studies had been falsified or were incomplete. In a 33-page letter in 1977, Richard A. Merrill, the F.D.A.'s chief counsel at the time, recommended to Samuel K. Skinner, then the United States attorney for the Northern District of Illinois, that a grand jury investigate the company, which was based in the Chicago suburb of Skokie, for &quot;concealing material facts and making false statements in reports of animal studies conducted to establish the safety of the drug Aldactone and the food additive aspartame.&quot;&lt;br&gt; A grand jury was never convened, however.&quot;&lt;ref name=lowdown/&gt;

--&gt;

U.S. Attorney [[Samuel Skinner]] was requested to &quot;open a grand jury investigation into whether two of Searle's aspartame studies had been falsified or were incomplete&quot;.&lt;ref name=lowdown/&gt; Skinner withdrew from the case when he was considering a job offer from the law firm [[Sidley &amp; Austin]], Searle's Chicago-based law firm, a job he later took.&lt;ref name=60minutes/&gt; The investigation was delayed and eventually the [[statute of limitations]] on the charges against Searle expired&lt;ref name=60minutes/&gt; and a grand jury was never convened.&lt;ref name=lowdown/&gt;

In 1977 and 1978, an FDA task force and a panel of academic pathologists reviewed 15 aspartame studies by Searle, and concluded that, although minor inconsistencies were found, they would not have affected the studies' conclusions.&lt;ref name=GAO87/&gt;{{Rp|4|date=May 2009}} In 1980, a Public Board of Inquiry (PBOI) heard testimony from Olney and disagreed with his claims that aspartame could cause brain damage, including in the developing fetus.&lt;ref name=GAO87/&gt;{{Rp|40–41|date=May 2009}} The board decided that further study was needed on a postulated connection between aspartame and brain tumors, and revoked approval of aspartame.&lt;ref name=GAO87/&gt;{{Rp|47|date=May 2009}}

In 1981, FDA Commissioner [[Arthur Hull Hayes]] sought advice on the issue from a panel of FDA scientists and a lawyer. The panel identified errors underlying the PBOI conclusion that aspartame might cause brain tumors, and presented arguments both for and against approval.&lt;ref name=GAO87/&gt;{{Rp|53|date=May 2009}} Hayes approved the use of aspartame in dry foods. Hayes further justified his approval with a Japanese brain tumor study,&lt;ref name=Ishii1981&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Hiroyuki |first1=I |title=Incidence of brain tumors in rats fed aspartame |journal=Toxicology Letters |volume=7 |issue=6 |pages=433–7 |year=1981 |pmid=7245229 |doi=10.1016/0378-4274(81)90089-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; the results of which, the PBOI chairman later said, would have resulted in an &quot;unqualified approval&quot; from the PBOI panel.&lt;ref name=FDA1996&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20041128020903/www.fda.gov/bbs/topics/answers/ans00772.html FDA Statement on Aspartame], November 18, 1996&lt;/ref&gt; Several objections followed, but all were denied.&lt;ref name=GAO87/&gt;{{Rp|13|date=May 2009}} In November 1983, a little more than a year after approving aspartame Hayes left the FDA and joined public-relations firm [[Burson-Marsteller]], Searle's public relations agency at the time, as a senior medical adviser.&lt;ref name=&quot;GAO86&quot;/&gt;

The actions of Samuel Skinner, in taking a job with a law firm retained by Searle during an investigation into Searle, and Arthur Hull Hayes, in taking a job with Searle's public relations agency following aspartame's approval, fueled conspiracy theories.&lt;ref name=lowdown/&gt;

Because of the approval controversy, Senator [[Howard M. Metzenbaum]] requested an investigation by the U.S. [[Government Accountability Office]] (GAO) of aspartame's approval. In 1987, the GAO reported that protocol had been followed and provided a time-line of events in the approval process.&lt;ref name=GAO87&gt;{{Cite web | title = U.S. GAO – HRD-87-46 Food and Drug Administration: Food Additive Approval Process Followed for Aspartame, June 18, 1987 | accessdate = 2008-09-05 | url = http://www.gao.gov/docdblite/info.php?rptno=HRD-87-46 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Rp|13|date=May 2009}} The GAO review included a survey of scientists who had conducted safety reviews; of the 67 scientists who responded to a questionnaire, 12 had major concerns about aspartame's safety, 26 were somewhat concerned but generally confident in aspartame safety, and 29 were very confident in aspartame safety.&lt;ref name=GAO87/&gt;{{Rp|16,76–81|date=May 2009}}

Food additive safety evaluations by many countries have led to approval of aspartame, citing the general lack of adverse effects following consumption in reasonable quantities.&lt;ref name=FSANZ2&gt;[[Food Standards Australia New Zealand]]: {{cite web |url=http://www.nzfsa.govt.nz/consumers/chemicals-nutrients-additives-and-toxins/aspartame/ |title=Food Standards Australia New Zealand: Aspartame – what it is and why it's used in our food |accessdate=2008-12-09| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20081216093929/http://www.nzfsa.govt.nz/consumers/chemicals-nutrients-additives-and-toxins/aspartame/| archivedate= December 16, 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Based on government research reviews and recommendations from advisory bodies such as those listed above, aspartame has been found to be safe for human consumption by more than ninety countries worldwide.&lt;ref name=&quot;Health Canada&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=FSANZ/&gt;

=== Alleged conflict of interest prior to 1996 ===
In 1976, the FDA notified then-U.S. attorney for Chicago, Sam Skinner, of the ongoing investigation of Searle, and in January 1977, formally requested that a grand jury be convened. In February, 1977, Searle's law firm, [[Sidley &amp; Austin]] offered Skinner a job and Skinner recused himself from the case.&lt;ref name=CongRec1989&gt;{{cite journal|url= http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/F?r101:7:./temp/~r101nc8vPN:e1:|periodical=Congressional Record 101st congress 1st session |title=DEPARTMENT OF TRANSPORTATION|page=s832|volume=135|date=January 31, 1989|issue=8}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mr. Skinner's successor was in place several months later, and the statute of limitations for the alleged offenses expired in October 1977. Despite complaints and urging from DOJ in Washington, neither the interim U.S. attorney for Chicago, William Conlon, nor Skinner's successor, Thomas Sullivan, convened a grand jury.&lt;ref name=WSJ1986&gt;{{cite news|title=Two Ex-U.S. Prosecutors' Roles in Case Against Searle Are Questioned in Probe|author=Andy Pasztor and Joe Davidson|periodical=Wall Street Journal|date=February 7, 1986}}&lt;/ref&gt; In December, 1977, Sullivan ordered the case dropped for lack of evidence. Conlon was later{{When|date=February 2011}} hired by Searle's law firm. Concern about conflict of interest in this case inflamed the controversy, and Senator Metzenbaum investigated in 1981 Senate Hearings.&lt;ref name=GAO87 /&gt; In 1989, the U.S. Senate approved the nomination of Sam Skinner to be Secretary of Transportation, noting that both Sullivan and Senator Metzenbaum had concluded that Skinner had not acted improperly.&lt;ref name=CongRec1989 /&gt;

Ralph G. Walton, a psychologist at Northeastern Ohio Universities College of Medicine, stated in a self-published 1996 analysis of aspartame research that industry-funded studies found no safety concerns while 84 of 92 independent studies did identify safety concerns.&lt;ref name=lowdown&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/12/business/yourmoney/12sweet.html?ei=5090&amp;en=f5f173a4cc33d534&amp;ex=1297400400&amp;partner=rssuserland&amp;emc=rss&amp;pagewanted=all &quot;The Lowdown on Sweet?&quot;] ''[[The New York Times]]'', February 12, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/politics/2005/dec/15/foodanddrink.immigrationpolicy &quot;Safety of artificial sweetener called into question by MP&quot;] ''[[The Guardian]]'', December 15, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; This analysis by Walton was submitted to the television show ''[[60 Minutes]]'' and has been extensively discussed on the Internet. An analysis of Walton's claims showed that Walton left out at least 50 peer-reviewed safety studies from his review of the literature and that most of the research he cites as non-industry funded were actually letters to the editors, case reports, review articles or book chapters rather than published studies.&lt;ref name=Kotsonis&gt;{{cite book |last1=Kotsonis |first1=Frank | last2= Mackey |first2= Maureen |title= Nutritional toxicology |edition= 2nd | year=2002 |isbn= 0-203-36144-X |page= 299}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a rebuttal to Walton's statements, the Aspartame Information Service (a service provided by [[Ajinomoto]], a primary producer and supplier of aspartame), reviewed the publications Walton cites as critical of aspartame, arguing that most of them do not involve aspartame or do not draw negative conclusions, are not peer-reviewed, are anecdotal, or are duplicates.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Aspartame Information replies to the New York Times | url=http://www.aspartame.info/mediarch/medit053.html | publisher=Aspartame Information Service | date=2006-02-16 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Internet hoax conspiracy theory ===
An elaborate [[health scare]],&lt;ref name=Flaherty&gt;{{Cite news | last=Flaherty|first=Megan|title=Harvesting Kidneys and other Urban Legends|url=http://www.nurseweek.com/features/99-4/myths.html|newspaper=NurseWeek|date=1999-04-12|accessdate=2011-02-12 | postscript=. {{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; involving a hoax [[conspiracy theory]] disseminated on many Internet websites, attributes a host of deleterious medical effects to aspartame. This theory claims that the FDA approval process of aspartame was tainted&lt;!-- does not support ref name=MAN_Markle/ --&gt;&lt;ref name=urbanlegends/&gt;&lt;ref name=Hawaii&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ctahr.hawaii.edu/oc/freepubs/pdf/FST-3.pdf |title=Falsifications and Facts about Aspartame – An analysis of the origins of aspartame disinformation|author=the University of Hawaii}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=time-web-of-deceit&gt;{{Cite journal|title=A Web of Deceit |journal=TIME |month=February |accessdate = 2009-01-19 | url = http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,990167,00.html | quote = In this and similar cases, all the Nancy Markles of the world have to do to fabricate a health rumor is post it in some Usenet news groups and let ordinary folks, who may already distrust artificial products, forward it to all their friends and e-mail pals. | work=Time | date=1999-02-08| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20090129164127/http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,990167,00.html| archivedate= January 29, 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; and cites as its source an email based upon a supposed talk by a &quot;Nancy Markle&quot; (whose existence has never been confirmed) at a &quot;World Environmental Conference.&quot;&lt;ref name=urbanlegends/&gt;&lt;ref name=Hawaii/&gt;&lt;ref name=MSF&gt;[http://www.msfocus.org/article-details.aspx?articleID=40 Examining the Safety of Aspartame], ''Multiple Sclerosis Foundation''&lt;/ref&gt; Specifically, the hoax websites allege that aspartame is responsible for [[multiple sclerosis]], systemic [[Systemic lupus erythematosus|lupus]], and [[methanol]] toxicity, causing &quot;blindness, spasms, shooting pains, seizures, headaches, depression, anxiety, memory loss, birth defects&quot; and death.&lt;ref name=MAN_Markle/&gt;

The &quot;Markle&quot; email was in large parts identical to many messages posted by Betty Martini to Usenet newsgroups in late 1995 and early 1996 about her claimed talk at a &quot;World Environmental Conference&quot;.&lt;ref name=urbanlegends/&gt; Although the content was traced back to her, Martini claims that an unknown person combined her original letter with other information and redistributed it as &quot;Nancy Markle&quot;.&lt;ref name=NOMARKLE&gt;{{cite web |author=Betty Martini |title=Not Nancy Markle |url=http://www.dorway.com/nomarkle.html |accessdate=2009-01-30 |year=2001| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20090225051555/http://www.dorway.com/nomarkle.html| archivedate= February 25, 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=WEC95MartiniLetter&gt;{{cite web |author=Betty Martini |title=World Environmental Conference &amp; Multiple Sclerosis |date=1995-12-03 |accessdate=2009-01-30 |url=http://www.dorway.com/environ.html| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20090311004053/http://www.dorway.com/environ.html| archivedate= March 11, 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Monroe&gt;Doug Monroe, [http://books.google.com/books?id=0g4AAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA56&amp;lpg=PA56&amp;dq=markle+martini+aspartame&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Sy9WR_nRrE&amp;sig=TTbcwAP5IfV7l0-Wql9os3UrLVE&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=-LdLTa-4PIO2sAPBvoXZCg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CCEQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=markle%20martini%20aspartame&amp;f=false &quot;Tenacious B. Is Betty Martini's War On Diet Coke An Internet Hoax Or The Real Thing?&quot; |quote= Ultimately the e-mail was traced back to Betty Martini.]. ''[[Atlanta (magazine)|Atlanta magazine]]'', August 2007&lt;/ref&gt; Martini's email has been described as an &quot;Internet smear campaign&amp;nbsp;... Its contents were entirely false, misleading, and defamatory to various popular products and their manufacturers, with no basis whatever in fact.&quot;&lt;ref name=Newton&gt;{{cite book|last=Newton|first=Michael|title=The encyclopedia of high-tech crime and crime-fighting|year=2004|publisher=Infobase Publishing|isbn=0-8160-4979-3|pages=25–27|url=http://books.google.com/?id=sAK6_W7lLkoC&amp;pg=PA25&amp;dq=aspartame+hoax#v=onepage&amp;q=aspartame%20hoax&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Martini says that there is a conspiracy between the FDA and the producers of aspartame,&lt;!-- Markle is not Martini. Use ref to Martini's own work ref name=MAN_Markle/ --&gt; and her conspiracy theory (repeated by &quot;Markle&quot;) has become a canonical example discussed on several Internet conspiracy theory and [[urban legend]] websites.&lt;ref name=urbanlegends/&gt;&lt;ref name=Snopes1&gt;[http://www.snopes.com/medical/toxins/aspartame.asp Kiss My Aspartame]. False. [[Snopes.com]]&lt;/ref&gt; Although most of the allegations of this theory contradict the bulk of medical evidence,&lt;ref name=Hawaii/&gt; this misinformation has spread around the world as [[chain email]]s since mid-December 1998,&lt;ref name=urbanlegends/&gt; influencing many websites&lt;ref name=Snopes1/&gt; as an [[urban legend]] that continues to scare consumers.&lt;ref name=Hawaii/&gt;

The dissemination of the &quot;Nancy Markle&quot; letter was considered so notable that the [[Media Awareness Network]] featured one version of it in a tutorial on how to determine the credibility of a web page. The tutorial implied that the &quot;Markle&quot; letter was not credible and stated that it should not be used as an authoritative source of information.&lt;ref name=MAN_Markle&gt;[http://www.media-awareness.ca/english/resources/educational/teaching_backgrounders/internet/decon_web_pages.cfm Deconstructing Web Pages] – An exercise in deconstructing a web page to determine its credibility as a source of information, using the aspartame controversy as the example. [[Media Awareness Network]].&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Dean Edell]] warned very strongly against the &quot;Markle&quot; letter:

: Beware The E-Mail Hoax: The Evils Of Nutrasweet (Aspartame)

: A highly inaccurate &quot;chain letter&quot; is being circulated via e-mail warning the reader of the health dangers of aspartame (Nutrasweet) diet drinks. There is so much scientific untruth in it, it's scary. Be careful, because others know how to manipulate you by this. Just because something is beyond your comprehension doesn't mean it is scientific. The e-mail is outrageous enough to state that the Multiple Sclerosis Foundation is suing the FDA for collusion with Monsanto&amp;nbsp;... Bogus, totally bogus. You've got to be careful of these Internet hoaxes. When you read health information online, be sure to know the source of the information you are reading, okay?&lt;ref name=Edell&gt;[[Dean Edell]], [http://web.archive.org/web/20040205093914/http://www.healthcentral.com/DrDean/DeanFullTextTopics.cfm?ID=8134 &quot;Beware The E-Mail Hoax: The Evils Of Nutrasweet (Aspartame)&quot;], ''[[HealthCentral]]'' December 18, 1998&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Government action and voluntary withdrawals ===

In 1997, due to public concerns the UK government introduced a new regulation obliging food makers who use sweeteners to state clearly next to the name of their product the phrase &quot;with sweeteners&quot;.&lt;ref name=UK1998&gt;{{cite news|publisher=BBC |url=http://news2.thls.bbc.co.uk/hi/english/health/newsid_194000/194938.stm |title=Sweeteners, sweeteners everywhere|date=October 16, 1998 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20000517011001/http://news2.thls.bbc.co.uk/hi/english/health/newsid_194000/194938.stm |archivedate = May 17, 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, the Indonesian government considered banning aspartame.&lt;ref name=Indonesia2007&gt;{{cite news |last= Patton |first= Dominique |work=AP-Foodtechnology.com |url= http://www.foodnavigator-asia.com/Formulation/Indonesia-consults-on-aspartame-sweetener-use-in-food |title= Indonesia consults on aspartame, sweetener use in food |date= January 9, 2007 |accessdate= August 23, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the Philippines, the small political party Alliance for Rural Concerns introduced House Bill 4747 in 2008 with the aim of having aspartame banned from the food supply.&lt;ref name=Phillipines2004&gt;{{cite news|work=SunStar (Philippines)|url=http://www.sunstar.com.ph/static/net/2008/09/04/lawmaker.wants.artificial.sweeteners.banned.(3.53.p.m.).html|title=Lawmaker wants artificial sweeteners banned|date=September 4, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In the U.S. state of [[New Mexico]] a bill to ban aspartame was introduced in 2007, and subsequently rejected.&lt;ref name=NM2007bill&gt;{{cite web|publisher=State of New Mexico Legislature |url=http://www.nmlegis.gov/lcs/_session.aspx?chamber=H&amp;legtype=B&amp;legno=391&amp;year=07|title= House bill 391: Relating to food; Banning the use of the artificial sweetener Aspartame in food products|year= 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=NM2006OCS&gt;{{cite news|work=Organic Consumers Association|url=http://www.organicconsumers.org/articles/article_2880.cfm|title=New Mexico State Senator Calls for Ban on Aspartame Artificial Sweetener|date=September 28, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=NM2007bakers&gt;{{cite news|work=American Bakers Association|url=http://www.americanbakers.org/State_2007.htm#NM |title=New Mexico – Bill Introduced to Ban Aspartame in Foods|year=2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; A similar 2008 Hawaiian bill stalled in committee for lack of evidence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Hawaiian aspartame ban stalls on lack of science |first= Chris |last= Jones |url= http://www.foodnavigator-usa.com/Regulation/Hawaiian-aspartame-ban-stalls-on-lack-of-science |agency=FOODNavigator.com |date= February 21, 2008 |accessdate= September 6, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |year= 2008 |title= HB2680 |volume= 2008 Archives |publisher= Hawaii State Legislature |url= http://www.capitol.hawaii.gov/Archives/measure_indiv_Archives.aspx?billtype=HB&amp;billnumber=2680&amp;year=2008 |accessdate= August 18, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In March 2009, the California OEHHA identified aspartame as a chemical for consultation by its Carcinogen Identification Committee, in accordance with [[California Proposition 65 (1986)|California state Proposition 65]].&lt;ref name=prop65_2009&gt;{{cite press| url=http://oehha.ca.gov/prop65/CRNR_notices/state_listing/prioritization_notices/prior030509.html| title=Prioritization: Chemicals for Consultation by the Carcinogen Identification Committee|publisher=California EPA Office of Environmental Health Hazard Assessment|date=March 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; So far no conclusions or updates have been published on the OEHHA website.&lt;ref&gt;http://oehha.ca.gov Search on 'Aspartame' August 23, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, the UK supermarket chains [[Sainsbury's]],&lt;ref name=Sainsbury2007&gt;{{cite news|work=Daily Mail |location=UK|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-450254/Sainsburys-takes-chemicals-cola.html|title=Sainsbury's takes the chemicals out of cola|date=April 23, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Marks &amp; Spencer|M&amp;S]],&lt;ref name=AsdaMS2007&gt;{{cite news|work=The Daily Telegraph |location=London |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/1551684/MandampS-and-Asda-to-axe-E-numbers.html|title= M&amp;S and Asda to axe E-numbers|date=May 17, 2007  | accessdate=2010-04-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Wal-Mart]] subsidiary [[Asda]],&lt;ref name=Asda2007&gt;{{cite news|work=Daily Mail |location=UK|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-454878/Asda-supermarket-axe-artificial-flavourings-colours-brand-foods.html|title=Asda becomes first supermarket to axe all artificial flavourings and colours in own brand foods|date=May 14, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; announced that they would no longer use aspartame in their own label products.&lt;ref name=MS2007&gt;{{cite news|work=Daily Mail |location=UK|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-455107/M-S-joins-race-ban-artificial-additives-food.html|title= M&amp;S joins race to ban artificial additives from their food|date=May 15, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; In April 2009, [[Ajinomoto]] Sweeteners Europe, one of the makers of [[aspartame]] in Europe, responded to Asda's &quot;no nasties&quot; campaign by filing a complaint of malicious falsehood against Asda in the English courts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bailii.org/ew/cases/EWHC/QB/2009/781.html|title=Ajinomoto Sweetners Europe SAS vs. Asda Stores Limited}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.flex-news-food.com/pages/16188/Ajinomoto/ASDA/Aspartame/UK/ajinomoto-sue-asda-aspartame-slur.html |title=Ajinomoto to Sue Asda over Aspartame Slur|work=FLEXNEWS|date=May 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2009, Asda initially won the legal case after the trial judge construed the &quot;no nasties&quot; labelling to &quot;not mean that aspartame was potentially harmful or unhealthy&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.yorkshireeveningpost.co.uk/news/Sweet-court-victory-for-Asda.5465237.jp&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.foodnavigator.com/On-your-radar/Artificial-additives/Asda-claims-victory-in-aspartame-nasty-case&lt;/ref&gt; The decision was reversed in June 2010, upon appeal,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.foodbev.com/news/court-of-appeal-rules-in-ajinomotoasda-aspartame-case |title=FoodBev.com |publisher=foodbev.com |accessdate=2010-06-23|unused_data=Court of Appeal rules in Ajinomoto/Asda aspartame case }}&lt;/ref&gt; and was settled in 2011 with ASDA removing references to aspartame from its packaging.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Asda settles 'nasty' aspartame legal battle with Ajinomoto |first= Ben |last= Bouckley |url= http://www.foodnavigator.com/Financial-Industry/Asda-settles-nasty-aspartame-legal-battle-with-Ajinomoto |agency=FOODNavigator.com|date=May 18, 2011 |accessdate= September 6, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, the South African retailer [[Woolworths (South Africa)|Woolworths]] announced it was removing aspartame from its own-brand foods.&lt;ref name=Woolworths2009&gt;{{cite news|url=http://foodstuffsa.co.za/index.php/Latest/Woolies-ousts-aspartame-in-own-foods.html|title=Woolies ousts aspartame in own foods|date=July 2, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010, the British Food Standards Agency launched an investigation into aspartame amid claims that some people experience side-effects after consuming the substance. A significant proportion of volunteers participating in the study are those who have claimed to experience side-effects.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/science/2009/sep/23/sweetener-aspartame-side-effects |work=The Guardian |location=London  | title=Sweetener aspartame to be investigated for possible side-effects | first=Ian | last=Sample | date=2009-09-23 | accessdate=2010-04-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; The study has not yet been concluded, as the FSA had trouble finding enough volunteers.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.food.gov.uk/about-us/how-we-work/workingwithothers/stakeholder-forums/consumer-stakeholder-forum/30-november-2011&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2011, the [[European Food Safety Authority]] (EFSA), which is due to release the findings of its full re-evaluation of aspartame in May 2013, made all 600 datasets it is using in its full re-evaluation available publicly. This includes previously unpublished scientific data, &quot;including the 112 original studies on aspartame which were submitted to support the request for authorisation of aspartame in Europe in the early 1980s.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/dataclosed/call/110601.htm |title=EFSA Call: Call for scientific data on Aspartame (E 951) |first= |last= |work=efsa.europa.eu |year=2011 [last update] |accessdate=November 25, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.foodnavigator.com/Legislation/EFSA-makes-aspartame-studies-available |title=EFSA makes aspartame studies available |work=foodnavigator.com |year=2011 [last update] |accessdate=November 25, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.foodnavigator.com/Legislation/EFSA-delay-Aspartame-review-findings-until-2013 |title=http://www.foodnavigator.com/Legislation/EFSA-delay-Aspartame-review-findings-until-2013 |work= foodnavigator.com |date= August 8, 2012 |accessdate= August 14, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Safety and health effects==
The safety of aspartame has been studied extensively since its discovery with research that includes animal studies, clinical and epidemiological research, and post-marketing surveillance,&lt;ref name=EFSAExperts&gt;{{Cite web | last = EFSA National Experts | title = Report of the meetings on aspartame with national experts | publisher=EFSA | date = May 2010 | url = http://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/scdocs/scdoc/1641.htm | accessdate = January 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; with aspartame being one of the most rigorously tested food ingredients to date.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last = Mitchell | first = Helen | title = Sweeteners and sugar alternatives in food technology | place = Oxford, UK | publisher=Wiley-Blackwell | year = 2006 | page = 94| isbn = 1-4051-3434-8 | postscript = &lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; Peer-reviewed comprehensive review articles and independent reviews by governmental regulatory bodies have analyzed the published research on the safety of aspartame and have found aspartame is safe for consumption at current levels.&lt;ref name=Magnuson/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;FSANZ2&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=EFSAExperts/&gt;&lt;ref name=Butchko&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Butchko |first1=H |last2=Stargel |first2=WW |last3=Comer |first3=CP |last4=Mayhew |first4=DA |last5=Benninger |first5=C |last6=Blackburn |first6=GL |last7=De Sonneville |first7=LM |last8=Geha |first8=RS |last9=Hertelendy |first9=Z |title=Aspartame: Review of Safety |journal=Regulatory Toxicology and Pharmacology |volume=35 |issue=2 Pt 2 |pages=S1–93 |year=2002 |pmid=12180494 |doi=10.1006/rtph.2002.1542}}&lt;/ref&gt; Aspartame has been deemed safe for human consumption by over 100 regulatory agencies in their respective countries,&lt;ref name=Butchko/&gt; including the UK [[Food Standards Agency]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | title = Aspartame | publisher=UK FSA | date = June 17, 2008 | url = http://www.food.gov.uk/safereating/chemsafe/additivesbranch/sweeteners/55174#h_2 | accessdate = September 23, 2010| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20101007120121/http://www.food.gov.uk/safereating/chemsafe/additivesbranch/sweeteners/55174| archivedate= October 07 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[European Food Safety Authority]] (EFSA)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Aspartame | publisher=EFSA | url = http://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/anstopics/topic/aspartame.htm | accessdate = September 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Health Canada]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | title = Aspartame | publisher=Health Canada | url = http://www.hc-sc.gc.ca/fn-an/securit/addit/sweeten-edulcor/aspartame-eng.php | accessdate = September 23, 2010| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20100922181732/http://www.hc-sc.gc.ca/fn-an/securit/addit/sweeten-edulcor/aspartame-eng.php| archivedate= September 22, 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Intake===
The [[acceptable daily intake]] (ADI) value for aspartame, as well as other food additives studied, is defined as the &quot;amount of a food additive, expressed on a body weight basis, that can be ingested daily over a lifetime without appreciable health risk.&quot;&lt;ref name=WHO1987&gt;{{Cite journal | last = WHO | title = Principles for the safety assessment of food additives and contaminants in food | journal=Environmental health criteria 70 | year = 1987 | url = http://www.inchem.org/documents/ehc/ehc/ehc70.htm | postscript = &lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Joint FAO/WHO Expert Committee on Food Additives]] (JECFA) and the [[European Commission]]'s [[Scientific Committee on Food]] has determined this value is 40&amp;nbsp;mg/kg of body weight for aspartame,&lt;ref name=Renwick&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Renwick |first1=Andrew |title=The intake of intense sweeteners – an update review |journal=Food Additives &amp; Contaminants |volume=23 |pages=327–38 |year=2006 |doi=10.1080/02652030500442532}}&lt;/ref&gt; while FDA has set its ADI for aspartame at 50&amp;nbsp;mg/kg.&lt;ref name=NCIFAQ&gt;{{Cite web | title = Aspartame and Cancer: Questions and Answers | publisher=[[National Cancer Institute]] | date = September 12, 2006 | url = http://www.cancer.gov/cancertopics/factsheet/AspartameQandA|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20090212130028/http://cancer.gov/cancertopics/factsheet/AspartameQandA|archivedate=February 12, 2009|accessdate = August 29, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The primary source for exposure to aspartame in the United States is diet [[soft drinks]], though it can be consumed in other products, such as pharmaceutical preparations, fruit drinks, and chewing gum among others in smaller quantities.&lt;ref name=Magnuson/&gt; A 12 US fluid ounce (355 ml) can of diet soda contains {{convert|180|mg|oz}} of aspartame, and for a 75&amp;nbsp;kg (165&amp;nbsp;lb) adult, it takes approximately 21 cans of diet soda daily to consume the {{convert|3750|mg|oz}} of aspartame that would surpass the FDA's 50&amp;nbsp;milligrams per kilogram of body weight ADI of aspartame from diet soda alone.&lt;ref name=NCIFAQ/&gt;

Reviews have analyzed studies which have looked at the consumption of aspartame in countries worldwide, including the United States, countries in Europe and Australia, among others. These reviews have found that the even high levels of intake of aspartame, studied across multiple countries and different methods of measuring aspartame consumption, is well below the ADI for safe consumption of aspartame.&lt;ref name=Magnuson/&gt;&lt;ref name=EFSAExperts/&gt;&lt;ref name=Butchko/&gt;&lt;ref name=Renwick/&gt; Reviews have also found that populations that are believed to be especially high consumers of aspartame such as children and diabetics are below the ADI for safe consumption, even considering very conservative worst-case scenario calculations of consumption.&lt;ref name=Magnuson/&gt;&lt;ref name=EFSAExperts/&gt;

=== Metabolites ===
Hypotheses of adverse health effects have focused on the three [[Metabolite#Metabolites|metabolites]] of aspartame, which are [[aspartic acid]], [[methanol]] and [[phenylalanine]]. Aspartame is rapidly [[hydrolyzed]] in the [[small intestines]]. Even with ingestion of very high doses of aspartame (over 200&amp;nbsp;mg/kg), no aspartame is found in the blood due to the rapid breakdown.&lt;ref name=Magnuson/&gt; These metabolites have been studied in a wide range of populations including infants, children, adolescents, and healthy adults. In healthy adults and children, even enormous doses of aspartame do not lead to plasma levels of metabolites that are a concern for safety.

====Aspartate====
Aspartic acid (aspartate) is one of the most common [[amino acid]]s in the typical diet. As with methanol and phenylalanine, intake of aspartic acid from aspartame is less than would be expected from other dietary sources. At the 90th percentile of intake, aspartame provides only between 1% and 2% of the daily intake of aspartic acid. There has been some speculation that aspartame, in conjunction with other amino acids like [[glutamate]], may lead to [[excitotoxicity]], inflicting damage on brain and nerve cells. However, clinical studies have shown no signs of neurotoxic effects,&lt;ref name=Magnuson/&gt; and studies of metabolism suggests it is not possible to ingest enough aspartic acid and glutamate through food and drink to levels that would be expected to be toxic.&lt;ref name=Butchko/&gt;

====Methanol====
The methanol produced by the metabolism of aspartame is absorbed and quickly converted into [[formaldehyde]] and then completely converted to [[formic acid]], which, due to its long half life, is considered the primary mechanism of toxicity in [[methanol poisoning]].  The methanol from aspartame is unlikely to be a safety concern for several reasons. The amount of methanol in aspartame is less than that found in fruit juices and citrus fruits, and there are other dietary sources for methanol such as [[Fermentation (food)|fermented]] beverages. Therefore, the amount of methanol produced from aspartame is likely to be less than that from natural sources. With regards to formaldehyde, it is rapidly converted in the body, and the amounts of formaldehyde from the metabolism of aspartame is trivial when compared to the amounts produced routinely by the human body and from other foods and drugs.  At the highest expected human doses of consumption of aspartame, there are no increased blood levels of methanol or formic acid,&lt;ref name=Magnuson/&gt; and ingesting aspartame at the 90th percentile of intake would produce 25 times less methanol than would be considered toxic.&lt;ref name=Butchko/&gt;

====Phenylalanine====
People with the genetic disorder [[phenylketonuria]] are advised to avoid aspartame as they have a decreased ability to metabolize phenylalanine. Common foods such as milk, meat, and fruits provide far greater amounts of these metabolites in a diet than aspartame.&lt;ref name=Butchko/&gt;

Phenylalanine is one of the [[essential amino acid]]s and is required for normal growth and maintenance of life. Concerns about the safety of phenylalanine from aspartame center largely around hypothetical changes in [[neurotransmitter]] levels as well as ratios of neurotransmitters to each other in the blood and brain that could lead to neurological symptoms. Reviews of the literature have found no consistent findings to support such concerns,&lt;ref name=Butchko/&gt; and while high doses of aspartame consumption may have some biochemical effects, these effects are not seen in toxicity studies to suggest aspartame can adversely affect neuronal function.&lt;ref name=Magnuson/&gt; Like methanol, the typical diet will lead to ingestion of significantly higher amounts of phenylalanine than would be expected from aspartame consumption.&lt;ref name=Butchko/&gt;

=== Cancer ===
Reviews have found no association between aspartame and cancer. These reviews have looked at numerous carcinogenicity studies in animals, epidemiologic studies in humans, as well as ''in vitro'' [[genotoxicity]] studies. These studies have found no significant evidence that aspartame causes cancer in animals, damages the genome, or causes cancer in humans at doses currently used.&lt;ref name=Magnuson/&gt;&lt;ref name=EFSAExperts/&gt;&lt;ref name=Butchko/&gt; This position is supported by multiple regulatory agencies like the FDA&lt;ref name=FDAstatement&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fda.gov/Food/FoodIngredientsPackaging/FoodAdditives/ucm208580.htm |title=US FDA/CFSAN – FDA Statement on European Aspartame Study |accessdate=September 23, 2010| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20100923210555/http://www.fda.gov/Food/FoodIngredientsPackaging/FoodAdditives/ucm208580.htm| archivedate= September 23, 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; and EFSA as well as scientific bodies such as the [[National Cancer Institute]].&lt;ref name=NCIFAQ/&gt;

Concern about possible [[carcinogen]]ic properties of aspartame was originally raised and popularized in the mainstream media by [[John Olney]] in 1970s and again in 1996 by suggesting that aspartame may be related to brain tumors. Reviews have found that these concerns were flawed, due to reliance on the [[ecological fallacy]]&lt;ref name=Weihrauch&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Weihrauch |first1=M. R. |last2=Diehl |first2=V |title=Artificial sweeteners—do they bear a carcinogenic risk? |journal=Annals of Oncology |volume=15 |issue=10 |pages=1460–5 |year=2004 |pmid=15367404 |doi=10.1093/annonc/mdh256}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the purported mechanism of causing tumors being unlikely to actually cause cancer. Independent agencies such as the FDA and National Cancer Institute have reanalyzed multiple studies based on these worries and found no association between aspartame and brain cancer.&lt;ref name=Butchko/&gt;

====Ramazzini studies====
The Cesare Maltoni Cancer Research Center of the European Ramazzini Foundation of Oncology and Environmental Sciences has released several studies which claim that aspartame can increase several malignancies in rats, concluding that aspartame is a potential carcinogen at normal dietary doses.&lt;ref name=Magnuson/&gt; Although thirteen [[occupational safety and health]] experts signed an open letter from CSPI to the FDA expressing that the 2007 ERF study merited a reevaluation of aspartame's safety in humans,&lt;ref name=CSPItoFDA&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Abdo |first1=KM |last2=Camargo Jr |first2=CA |last3=Davis |first3=D |last4=Egilman |first4=D |last5=Epstein |first5=SS |last6=Froines |first6=J |last7=Hattis |first7=D |last8=Hooper |first8=K |last9=Huff |first9=J |title=Letter to U.S. FDA commissioner. Questions about the safety of the artificial sweetener aspartame. |journal=International journal of occupational and environmental health |volume=13 |issue=4 |pages=449–50 |year=2007 |pmid=18085059}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Couzin&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Couzin |first1=J. |title=Souring on Fake Sugar |journal=Science |volume=317 |pages=29c |year=2007 |doi=10.1126/science.317.5834.29c |issue=5834}}&lt;/ref&gt; these studies have been widely criticized and discounted by the FDA and other food safety agencies:

After reviewing the foundation's claims, the EFSA&lt;ref name=EFSAreport&gt;{{cite journal |author=Panel on Food Additives and Nutrient Sources added to Food |title=Opinion of the Scientific Panel on food additives, flavourings, processing aids and materials in contact with food (AFC) related to a new long-term carcinogenicity study on aspartame |journal=The EFSA Journal |year=2006 |volume=356 |pages=1–44 |doi=10.2903/j.efsa.2006.356}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the FDA&lt;ref name=FDAstatement/&gt; discounted the study results and found no reason to revise their previously established acceptable daily intake levels for aspartame. Reported flaws were numerous and included, but were not limited to, the following: comparing cancer rates of older aspartame-consuming rats to younger control rats; unspecified composition of the &quot;Corticella&quot; diet and method of adding aspartame, leading to possible nutritional deficiencies; unspecified aspartame storage conditions; lack of animal randomization; overcrowding and a high incidence of possibly carcinogenic infections; and the U.S. [[National Toxicology Program]]'s finding that the ERF had misdiagnosed [[hyperplasia]]s as malignancies.&lt;ref name=Magnuson/&gt; Reviews by the FDA and EFSA were hampered by the refusal of the Ramazzini Foundation to release all data and pathology slides, but from the materials received, the FDA&lt;ref name=FDAstatement/&gt; and EFSA&lt;ref name=EFSAReview2&gt;{{cite journal |author=Panel on Food Additives and Nutrient Sources added to Food |title=Updated opinion on a request from the European Commission related to the 2nd ERF carcinogenicity study on aspartame, taking into consideration study data submitted by the Ramazzini Foundation in February 2009 |journal=The EFSA Journal |year=2009 |volume=1015 |pages=1–18 |doi=10.2903/j.efsa.2009.1015}}&lt;/ref&gt; found that the data did not support the researcher's published conclusions. Evaluation of this research by Health Canada&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Health Canada Comments on the Recent Study Relating to the Safety of Aspartame|url=http://www.hc-sc.gc.ca/fn-an/securit/addit/sweeten-edulcor/aspartame_statement-eng.php|publisher=Health Canada|accessdate=February 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the British government's Committee on Carcinogenicity of Chemicals in Food, Consumer Products and the Environment&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Statement on a Carcinogenicity Study of Aspartame by the European Ramazzini Foundation|url=http://www.iacoc.org.uk/statements/documents/COC06S2AspartamestatementDec2006_000.pdf|publisher=Committee on Carcinogenicity of Chemicals in Food, Consumer Products and the Environment|accessdate=February 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; likewise found methodological problems with the research and did not recommend any further reconsideration of the recommended intake of aspartame in their respective countries.  

A review of the literature concurred with these evaluations, finding many possible flaws in the study's design and conclusions. These conclusions are also contradicted by other carcinogenicity studies which found no significant danger.  This review therefore concluded this research did not constitute credible evidence for the carcinogenicity of aspartame.&lt;ref name=Magnuson /&gt; Another review criticized the Ramazzini Foundation for relying on &quot;[[science by press conference]]&quot; with its release of results through the media before being published in a proper [[peer-review]]ed journal, thus helping fuel the controversy and publicity about the study in the media.&lt;ref name=Lofstedt&gt;{{cite journal |last1= Lofstedt |first1= Ragnar E |authorlink= Ragnar Löfstedt |title=Risk Communication, Media Amplification and the Aspartame Scare |journal=Risk Management |volume=10 |pages=257–84 |year=2008 |doi=10.1057/rm.2008.11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another carcinogenicity study in rodents published by this foundation in 2010 was evaluated by the EFSA and was found to have multiple significant design flaws and could not be interpreted. The EFSA therefore concluded this study did not provide enough evidence to reconsider previous evaluation of aspartame safety.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=EFSA reviews two publications on the safety of artificial sweeteners|url=http://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/press/news/ans110228.htm|publisher=EFSA|accessdate=February 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Neurological and psychiatric symptoms ===
Numerous allegations have been made on the Internet and in consumer magazines purporting neurotoxic effects of aspartame leading to neurological or psychiatric symptoms such as [[seizures]], [[headaches]], and [[mood changes]].&lt;ref name=Magnuson/&gt; Review of the biochemistry of aspartame have found no evidence that the doses consumed would plausibly lead to neurotoxic effects.&lt;ref name=Lathja&gt;{{cite journal 
|last1=Lajtha |first1=A 
|title=Aspartame consumption: lack of effects on neural function |journal=The Journal of Nutritional Biochemistry 
|volume=5 |pages=266–83 |year=1994 |doi=10.1016/0955-2863(94)90032-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Comprehensive reviews have not found any evidence for aspartame as a cause for these symptoms.&lt;ref name=Magnuson/&gt;&lt;ref name=EFSAExperts/&gt;&lt;ref name=Butchko/&gt;
One review did provide a theoretical biochemical background of neurotoxicity and suggested further testing.&lt;ref name=Humphries&gt;{{cite journal 
|last1=Humphries |first1=P |last2=Pretorius |first2=E |last3=Naudé |first3=H 
|title=Direct and indirect cellular effects of aspartame on the brain 
|journal=European Journal of Clinical Nutrition |volume=62 |issue=4 |pages=451–62 |year=2007 |pmid=17684524 |doi=10.1038/sj.ejcn.1602866}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
However, a panel of EFSA experts noted that this review's conclusions were partially based on Internet sources and therefore were not scientifically robust. These experts also concurred with a critique that significant scientific errors were made in the critical review that led to unsubstantiated and misleading interpretations.&lt;ref name=EFSAExperts/&gt; A review of the [[pediatric]] literature did not show any significant findings for safety concerns with regards to neuropsychiatric conditions such as [[panic attacks]], mood changes, [[hallucinations]] or with [[ADHD]] or seizures.&lt;ref name=PediatricsReview/&gt;

====Headaches====
Headaches are the most common symptom reported by consumers.&lt;ref name=Magnuson/&gt; While one small review noted aspartame is likely one of many dietary triggers of [[migraine]]s, in a list that includes &quot;cheese, chocolate, [[citrus fruits]], [[hot dogs]], [[monosodium glutamate]], aspartame, fatty foods, [[ice cream]], [[caffeine withdrawal]], and alcoholic drinks, especially [[red wine]] and beer,&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Millichap-2003&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Millichap |first1=J |last2=Yee |first2=MM 
|title=The diet factor in pediatric and adolescent migraine 
|journal=Pediatric Neurology |volume=28 |issue=1 |pages=9–15 |year=2003 |pmid=12657413 |doi=10.1016/S0887-8994(02)00466-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
other reviews have noted conflicting studies about headaches&lt;ref name=Magnuson/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal 
|last1=Sun-Edelstein |first1=Christina |last2=Mauskop |first2=Alexander 
|title=Foods and Supplements in the Management of Migraine Headaches 
|journal=The Clinical Journal of Pain |volume=25 |issue=5 |pages=446–52 |year=2009 |pmid=19454881 |doi=10.1097/AJP.0b013e31819a6f65}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
and still more reviews lack any evidence and references to support this claim.&lt;ref name=EFSAExperts/&gt;&lt;ref name=Butchko/&gt;&lt;ref name=PediatricsReview&gt;{{cite journal 
|title=&quot;Inactive&quot; Ingredients in Pharmaceutical Products: Update (Subject Review) 
|journal=Pediatrics |volume=99 |issue=2 |pages=268–78 |year=1997 |pmid=9024461 |doi=10.1542/peds.99.2.268}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Weight change and hunger===
Since the caloric contribution of aspartame is negligible, it has been used as a means for weight loss through its role as a sugar substitute, with reviews finding that aspartame may aid in weight loss as part of a multidisciplinary weight loss program.&lt;ref name=Magnuson/&gt;&lt;ref name=Butchko/&gt; Claims that aspartame contributes to weight gain and [[obesity]] are not supported by the medical literature.&lt;ref name=Magnuson/&gt;&lt;ref name=Butchko/&gt;  Although there have also been claims that aspartame contributes to [[hunger]] or increased appetite,&lt;ref name=Magnuson/&gt; there have been few studies directly addressing the effect of aspartame on appetite.  The data that is available shows no increased appetite with aspartame use, and this is an area of possible future research.&lt;ref name=Magnuson/&gt;&lt;ref name=EFSAExperts/&gt; Studies looking at caloric intake found that aspartame consumers consumed as many or fewer calories than non-aspartame consumers, but not more.&lt;ref name=Magnuson/&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Canderel]]
* [[Equal (sweetener)]]
* [[NutraSweet]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
&lt;!--======================== {{No more links}} ============================
    | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. Wikipedia  |
    | is not a collection of links nor should it be used for advertising. |
    |                                                                     |
    |           Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.         |
    | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.  |
    |                                                                     |
    | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or   |
    | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
    | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)   |
    | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.         |
    ======================= {{No more links}} =============================--&gt;
*[[Centers for Disease Control]]: [http://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/preview/mmwrhtml/00000426.htm Evaluation of Consumer Complaints Related to Aspartame Use]
*[[International Programme on Chemical Safety]]: [http://www.inchem.org/documents/jecfa/jecmono/v15je03.htm Aspartame toxicology evaluation] and [http://www.inchem.org/documents/jecfa/jecmono/v16je03.htm further evaluation]

{{Consumer Food Safety}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Aspartame Controversy}}
[[Category:Medical controversies]]
[[Category:Fringe theories]]
[[Category:Food safety]]

[[ar:جدل الأسبرتام]]
[[es:Aspartamo#Controversias]]</text>
      <sha1>qqi89fg0jfwhxsbdhhkd4m7ywy3k1u9</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
