<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Biology and sexual orientation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>51614</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520238221</id>
      <parentid>520140827</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-28T09:06:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Papajohnin</username>
        <id>1353555</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Chromosome linkage studies */ Maintenance tagged &quot;SHH gene&quot;</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="68987">{{sexual orientation}}

'''Biology and sexual orientation''' is the subject of research into the role of biology in the development of human [[sexual orientation]]. No simple, single cause for sexual orientation has been conclusively demonstrated. Various studies point to different, even conflicting positions, such as a combination of genetic, hormonal, and environmental influences,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|doi=10.1542/peds.113.6.1827|url=http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/cgi/content/full/113/6/1827?maxtoshow=&amp;hits=10&amp;RESULTFORMAT=&amp;fulltext=%22Sexual+orientation+and+adolescents%22&amp;searchid=1&amp;FIRSTINDEX=0&amp;sortspec=relevance&amp;resourcetype=HWCIT |author=Frankowski BL |author2=American Academy of Pediatrics Committee on Adolescence |title=Sexual orientation and adolescents |journal=Pediatrics |volume=113 |issue=6 |pages=1827–32 |year=2004 |month=June|pmid=15173519}}&lt;/ref&gt; with biological factors involving a complex interplay of genetic factors and the early uterine environment,&lt;ref&gt;Royal College of Psychiatrists: [http://www.rcpsych.ac.uk/pdf/Submission%20to%20the%20Church%20of%20England.pdf Submission to the Church of England’s Listening Exercise on Human Sexuality.]&lt;/ref&gt; or no genetic influence.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bearman&quot;/&gt; Biological factors which may be related to the development of a [[heterosexual]], [[homosexual]], [[bisexual]] or [[asexual]] orientation include [[gene]]s, [[Prenatal hormones and sexual orientation|prenatal hormones]], and [[Human brain|brain]] structure.

==Empirical studies==
=== Twin studies ===
A number of [[twin study|twin studies]] have attempted to compare the relative importance of genetics and environment in the causation of sexual orientation. In a 1991 study, Bailey and Pillard found that 52% of [[Twin#Monozygotic_.28.22identical.22.29_twins|monozygotic (MZ)]] brothers and 22% of the [[Twin#Fraternal_.28sororal.2Fdizygotic.29_twins|dizygotic (DZ)]] twins were concordant for homosexuality.&lt;ref&gt;cited in Wilson and Rahman 2005, p47&lt;/ref&gt; 'MZ' indicates [[Twin#Monozygotic_.28.22identical.22.29_twins|identical twins]] with the same sets of genes and 'DZ' indicates [[Twin#Fraternal.2FSororal_.28dizygotic.29_twins|fraternal twins]] where genes are mixed to a similar extent as non-twin siblings. In 2000 Bailey, Dunne and Martin found similar results from a larger sample of 4,901 Australian twins.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Bailey JM, Dunne MP, Martin NG |title=Genetic and environmental influences on sexual orientation and its correlates in an Australian twin sample |journal=J Pers Soc Psychol |volume=78 |issue=3 |pages=524–36 |year=2000 |month=March |pmid=10743878 |doi=10.1037/0022-3514.78.3.524 |url=http://content.apa.org/journals/psp/78/3/524}}&lt;/ref&gt; Self reported [[zygosity]], sexual attraction, fantasy and behaviours were assessed by questionnaire and zygosity was [[Serology|serologically]] checked when in doubt. They found 20% concordance in the male identical or MZ twins and 24% concordance for the female identical or MZ twins. A meta-study by Hershberger (2001)&lt;ref&gt;Hershberger, Scott L. 2001. Biological Factors in the Development of Sexual Orientation. Pp. 27–51 in Lesbian, Gay, and Bisexual Identities and Youth: Psychological Perspectives, edited by Anthony R. D’Augelli and Charlotte J. Patterson. Oxford, New York: Oxford University Press. Quoted in Bearman and Bruckner, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; compares the results of eight different twin studies: among those, all but two showed MZ twins having much higher concordance of sexual orientation than DZ twins, suggesting a non-negligible genetic component.

Bearman and Bruckman (2002) criticized early studies of concentrating on small, select samples&lt;ref name=Bearman&gt;This work was published in the ''American Journal of Sociology'' (Bearman, P. S. &amp; Bruckner, H. (2002) Opposite-sex twins and adolescent same-sex attraction. American Journal of Sociology 107, 1179–1205.) and is available only to subscribers. However, a final draft of the paper is available [http://iserp.columbia.edu/content/opposite-sex-twins-and-adolescent-same-sex-attraction here] – there are no significant differences on the points cited between the final draft and the published version.&lt;/ref&gt; and non-representative selection of their subjects.&lt;ref&gt;While inconsistent with modern findings, the first relatively large-scale twin study on sexual orientation was reported by [[Franz Josef Kallmann|Kallman]] in 1952. (''See:'' {{Cite journal|author=Kallmann FJ |title=Comparative twin study on the genetic aspects of male homosexuality |journal=J. Nerv. Ment. Dis. |volume=115 |issue=4 |pages=283–97 |year=1952 |month=April |pmid=14918012 |doi= |url=}}). Examining only male twin pairs, he found a 100% concordance rate for homosexuality among 37 monozygotic (MZ) twin pairs, compared to a 12%–42% concordance rate among 26 dizygotic (DZ) twin pairs, depending on definition. In other words, every identical twin of a homosexual subject was also homosexual, while this was not the case for non-identical twins. This study was criticized for its vaguely described method of recruiting twins and for a high rate of [[mental illness|psychiatric disorders]] among its subjects. (''See'' Rosenthal, D., &quot;Genetic Theory and Abnormal Behavior&quot; 1970, New York: McGraw-Hill.)&lt;/ref&gt; They studied 289 pairs of identical twins (monozygotic or from one fertilized egg) and 495 pairs of fraternal twins (dizygotic or from two fertilized eggs) and found [[Concordance (genetics)|concordance rates]] for same-sex attraction of only 7.7% for male identical twins and 5.3% for females, a pattern which they say &quot;does not suggest genetic influence independent of social context.&quot;&lt;ref name=Bearman/&gt;

A 2010 study of all adult twins in Sweden (more than 7,600 twins)&lt;ref name=&quot;karolinska&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Långström N, Rahman Q, Carlström E, Lichtenstein P |title=Genetic and environmental effects on same-sex sexual behavior: a population study of twins in Sweden |journal=Arch Sex Behav |volume=39 |issue=1 |pages=75–80 |year=2010 |month=February |pmid=18536986 |doi=10.1007/s10508-008-9386-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; found that same-sex behavior was explained by both heritable factors and individual-specific environmental sources (such as prenatal environment, experience with illness and trauma, as well as peer groups, and sexual experiences), while influences of shared-environment variables such as familial environment and societal attitudes had a weaker, but significant effect.  Women showed a statistically non-significant trend to weaker influence of hereditary effects, while men showed no effect of shared environmental effects.  The use of all adult twins in Sweden was designed to address the criticism of volunteer studies, in which a potential bias towards participation by gay twins may influence the results (see below). 

:{{bquote|Overall, the environment shared by twins (including familial and societal attitudes) explained 0–17% of the choice of sexual partner, genetic factors 18–39% and the unique environment 61–66%. The individual's unique environment includes, for example, circumstances during pregnancy and childbirth, physical and [[psychological trauma]] (e.g., accidents, violence, and disease), peer groups (other than those shared with a twin), and sexual experiences. In men, genetic effects explained .34–.39 of the [[variance]], the shared environment .00, and the individual-specific environment .61–.66 of the variance. Corresponding estimates among women were .18–.19 for genetic factors, .16–.17 for shared environmental, and .64–.66 for unique environmental factors.}}

====Criticisms====
Twin studies have received a number of criticisms including [[self-selection bias]] where homosexuals with gay siblings are more likely to volunteer for studies. Nonetheless, it is possible to conclude that, given the difference in sexuality in so many sets of identical twins, sexual orientation cannot be purely caused by genetics.&lt;ref&gt;Schacter, Daniel L., Gilbert, Daniel T., and Wegner, Daniel M. (2009) &quot;Psychology&quot;. ''Worth Publishers'': 435.&lt;/ref&gt;

Another issue is the recent finding that even monozygotic twins can be different and there is a mechanism which might account for monozygotic twins being discordant for homosexuality. Gringas and Chen (2001) describe a number of mechanisms which can lead to differences between monozygotic twins, the most relevant here being chorionicity and amniocity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.1016/S0378-3782(01)00171-2 | last1 = Gringas | first1 = P. | last2 = Chen | first2 = W. | year = 2001 | title = Mechanisms for difference in monozygous twins | url = | journal = Early Human Development | volume = 64 | issue = 2| pages = 105–117 | pmid = 11440823 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Dichorionic twins]] potentially have different hormonal environments and receive maternal blood from separate placenta. Monoamniotic twins share a hormonal environment, but can suffer from the 'twin to twin transfusion syndrome' in which one twin is &quot;relatively stuffed with blood and the other exsanguinated&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Rutter, M. (2006). Genes and Behavior. Oxford, UK: Blackwell Publishing.&lt;/ref&gt; If one twin receives less testosterone and the other more, this could result in different levels of brain masculinisation.	{{citation needed|date=March 2012}}

===Chromosome linkage studies===
Chromosome linkage studies of sexual orientation have indicated the presence of multiple contributing genetic factors throughout the genome.  In 1993, [[Dean Hamer]] and colleagues published findings from a linkage analysis of a sample of 76 gay brothers and their families.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Hamer DH, Hu S, Magnuson VL, Hu N, Pattatucci AM |title=A linkage between DNA markers on the X chromosome and male sexual orientation |journal=Science |volume=261 |issue=5119 |pages=321–7 |year=1993 |month=July |pmid=8332896 |doi=10.1126/science.8332896 |url=http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;pmid=8332896}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hamer ''et al.'' found that the gay men had more gay male uncles and cousins on the maternal side of the family than on the paternal side. Gay brothers who showed this maternal pedigree were then tested for X chromosome linkage, using twenty-two markers on the X chromosome to test for similar alleles.  In another finding, thirty-three of the forty sibling pairs tested were found to have similar alleles in the distal region of [[Xq28]], which was significantly higher than the expected rates of 50% for fraternal brothers. This was popularly dubbed as the &quot;'''gay gene'''&quot; in the media, causing significant controversy.  Sanders ''et al.'' in 1998 reported on their similar study, in which they found that 13% of uncles of gay brothers on the maternal side were homosexual, compared to 6% on the paternal side.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wilson and Rahman 2005&quot;&gt;Wilson, G.D., &amp; Rahman, Q. (2005). Born Gay: The Biology of Sex Orientation. London: Peter Owen Publishers.&lt;/ref&gt;

A later analysis by Hu ''et al.'' replicated and refined the earlier findings.  This study revealed that 67% of gay brothers in a new saturated sample shared a marker on the X chromosome at Xq28.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Hu S, Pattatucci AM, Patterson C, ''et al.'' |title=Linkage between sexual orientation and chromosome Xq28 in males but not in females |journal=Nat. Genet. |volume=11 |issue=3 |pages=248–56 |year=1995 |month=November |pmid=7581447 |doi=10.1038/ng1195-248 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Although two other studies (Bailey ''et al.'', 1999; McKnight and Malcolm, 2000) failed to find a preponderance of gay relatives in the maternal line of homosexual men,&lt;ref name=&quot;Wilson and Rahman 2005&quot;/&gt; a rigorous replication of the maternal loading was reported on samples in Italy in England.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}} One study by Rice ''et al.'' in 1999 failed to replicate the Xq28 linkage results.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Vilain E |title=Genetics of sexual development |journal=Annu Rev Sex Res |volume=11 |issue= |pages=1–25 |year=2000 |pmid=11351829 |doi= |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Meta-analysis of all available linkage data indicates a significant link to Xq28, but also indicates that additional genes must be present to account for the full heritability of sexual orientation.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}} A recent study of 894 heterosexual and 694 homosexual men found no evidence of sex linkage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1007/s10508-009-9499-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Mustanski ''et al.'' (2005) performed a full-genome scan (instead of just an X chromosome scan) on individuals and families previously reported on in Hamer ''et al.'' (1993) and Hu ''et al.'' (1995), as well as additional new subjects.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Mustanski BS, Dupree MG, Nievergelt CM, Bocklandt S, Schork NJ, Hamer DH |title=A genomewide scan of male sexual orientation |journal=Hum. Genet. |volume=116 |issue=4 |pages=272–8 |year=2005 |month=March |pmid=15645181 |doi=10.1007/s00439-004-1241-4 |url=http://mypage.iu.edu/~bmustans/Mustanski_etal_2005.pdf|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;  With the larger sample set and complete genome scan, the study found somewhat reduced linkage for Xq28 than reported by Hamer ''et al.'' However, they did find other markers with a likelihood score falling just short of significance at 7q36 and likelihood scores approaching significance at 8p12 and 10q26. Interestingly, 10q26 showed highly significant maternal loading, thus further supporting the previous family studies.

In July 2010 a group of geneticists at the Korea Advanced Institute of Science an Technology altered the sexual preferences of female mice by removing a single gene linked to reproductive behavior. Without the gene, the mice exhibited masculine sexual behavior and attraction toward urine of other female mice. Those mice who retained the gene fucose mutarotase (FucM) were attracted to male mice.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |pmid=20609214 |year=2010 |last1=Park |first1=D |last2=Choi |first2=D |last3=Lee |first3=J |last4=Lim |first4=DS |last5=Park |first5=C |title=Male-like sexual behavior of female mouse lacking fucose mutarotase |volume=11 |pages=62 |doi=10.1186/1471-2156-11-62 |pmc=2912782 |journal=BMC genetics}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2011, Binbin Wang ''et al.'' followed up on the SHH gene{{inconsistent|date=October 2012}}, and a publish-ahead-of-print article was published in the ''Journal of Andrology'' showing positive results in a study that found statistically significant differences in allele types between 361 identified homosexual subjects and 319 heterosexual control subjects.&lt;ref&gt;{{ Cite journal|author=Wang |title=Association Analysis Between the Tag SNP for Sonic Hedgehog rs9333613 Polymorphism and Male Sexual Orientation |journal=Journal of Andrology |year=2011 |month=September url=http://www.andrologyjournal.org/cgi/rapidpdf/jandrol.110.012849v1|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Epigenetics studies===
A recent study suggests linkage between a mother's genetic make-up and homosexuality of her sons.  Women have two X chromosomes, one of which is &quot;switched off&quot;. The inactivation of the X chromosome occurs randomly throughout the embryo, resulting in cells that are mosaic with respect to which chromosome is active. In some cases though, it appears that this switching off can occur in a non-random fashion. Bocklandt et al. (2006) reported that,  in mothers of homosexual men, the number of women with extreme skewing of X chromosome inactivation is significantly higher than in mothers without gay sons. Thirteen percent of mothers with one gay son, and 23% of mothers with two gay sons showed extreme skewing, compared to 4% percent of mothers without gay sons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bocklandt et al. 2006&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Bocklandt S, Horvath S, Vilain E, Hamer DH |title=Extreme skewing of X chromosome inactivation in mothers of homosexual men |journal=Hum. Genet. |volume=118 |issue=6 |pages=691–4 |year=2006 |month=February |pmid=16369763 |doi=10.1007/s00439-005-0119-4 |url=http://repositories.cdlib.org/postprints/1413}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Birth order===
{{Main|Fraternal birth order and sexual orientation}}
Blanchard and Klassen (1997) reported that each older brother increases the odds of a man being gay by 33%.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blanchard and Klassen 1997&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Blanchard R, Klassen P |title=H-Y antigen and homosexuality in men |journal=J. Theor. Biol. |volume=185 |issue=3 |pages=373–8 |year=1997 |month=April |pmid=9156085 |doi=10.1006/jtbi.1996.0315 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/health/10gene.html?ex=1187236800&amp;en=b8ee8ae30451c2e9&amp;ei=5070  Pas de Deux of Sexuality Is Written in the Genes]&lt;/ref&gt; This is now &quot;one of the most reliable epidemiological variables ever identified in the study of sexual orientation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Blanchard R |title=Birth order and sibling sex ratio in homosexual versus heterosexual males and females |journal=Annu Rev Sex Res |volume=8 |issue= |pages=27–67 |year=1997 |pmid=10051890 |doi= |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; To explain this finding, it has been proposed that male fetuses provoke a maternal immune reaction that becomes stronger with each successive male fetus. 
This maternal immunization hypothesis (MIH) begins when cells from a male fetus enter the mother's circulation during pregnancy or while giving birth.&lt;ref name=&quot;Anthony2011&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal
 | author = [[Anthony F. Bogaert]] &amp; [[Malvina Skorska]]
 | title = Sexual orientation, fraternal birth order, and the maternal immune hypothesis: a review
 | journal = [[Frontiers in neuroendocrinology]]
 | volume = 32
 | issue = 2
 | pages = 247–254
 | year = 2011
 | month = April
 | doi = 10.1016/j.yfrne.2011.02.004
 | pmid = 21315103
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Male fetuses produce HY antigens which are &quot;almost certainly involved in the sexual differentiation of vertebrates.&quot;
These Y-linked proteins would not be recognized in the mother's immune system due to the fact that she is female, causing her to develop antibodies which would travel through the placental barrier into the fetal compartment. From here, the anti-male bodies would then cross the blood/brain barrier (BBB) of the developing fetal brain, altering sex-dimorphic brain structures relative to sexual orientation, increasing the likelihood that the exposed son will be more attracted to men than women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Anthony2011&quot; /&gt;
It is this antigen which maternal H-Y antibodies are proposed to both react to and 'remember'. Successive male fetuses are then attacked by H-Y antibodies which somehow decrease the ability of H-Y antigens to perform their usual function in brain masculinisation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blanchard and Klassen 1997&quot; /&gt; However the theory has been criticized because symptoms which would be typical of such effects are rare compared with prevalence of homosexuality&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Whitehead NE |title=An antiboy antibody? Re-examination of the maternal immune hypothesis |journal=J Biosocial Sci |volume=39 |issue=6 |pages=905–921 |year=2007 |pmid=17316469 |doi= 10.1017/S0021932007001903|url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Female fertility===
In 2004, Italian researchers conducted a study of about 4,600 people who were the relatives of 98 homosexual and 100 heterosexual men. Female relatives of the homosexual men tended to have more offspring than those of the heterosexual men. Female relatives of the homosexual men on their mother's side tended to have more offspring than those on the father's side. The researchers concluded that there was genetic material being passed down on the X chromosome which both promotes fertility in the mother and homosexuality in her male offspring. The connections discovered would explain about 20% of the cases studied, indicating that this is a highly significant but not the sole genetic factor determining sexual orientation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Camperio-Ciani et al. 2004&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Camperio-Ciani A, Corna F, Capiluppi C |title=Evidence for maternally inherited factors favouring male homosexuality and promoting female fecundity |journal=Proc. Biol. Sci. |volume=271 |issue=1554 |pages=2217–21 |year=2004 |month=November |pmid=15539346 |pmc=1691850 |doi=10.1098/rspb.2004.2872}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Pheromone studies===
Recent research conducted in Sweden&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15883379&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Savic I, Berglund H, Lindström P |title=Brain response to putative pheromones in homosexual men |journal=Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. |volume=102 |issue=20 |pages=7356–61 |year=2005 |month=May |pmid=15883379 |pmc=1129091 |doi=10.1073/pnas.0407998102 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; has suggested that gay and straight men respond differently to two odors that are believed to be involved in [[sexual arousal]]. The research showed that when both heterosexual women (lesbians were included in the study, but the results regarding them were &quot;somewhat confused&quot;) and gay men are exposed to a testosterone derivative found in men's sweat, a region in the hypothalamus is activated. Heterosexual men, on the other hand, have a similar response to an estrogen-like compound found in women's urine.&lt;ref&gt;Wade, Nicholas. (May 9, 2005). &quot;[http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/09/science/09cnd-smell.html?ei=5065&amp;en=bf437458d36709cf&amp;ex=1116302400&amp;partner=MYWAY&amp;pagewanted=print Gay Men Are Found to Have Different Scent of Attraction].&quot; ''New York Times''.&lt;/ref&gt; The conclusion is that sexual attraction, whether same-sex or opposite-sex oriented, operates similarly on a biological level. Researchers have suggested that this possibility could be further explored by studying young subjects to see if similar responses in the hypothalamus are found and then correlating these data with adult sexual orientation.{{Citation needed|date=March 2007}}

===Studies of brain structure===
A number of sections of the [[Human brain|brain]] have been reported to be sexually dimorphic; that is, they vary between men and women. There have also been reports of variations in brain structure corresponding to sexual orientation. In 1990, Swaab and Hofman reported a difference in the size of the [[suprachiasmatic nucleus]] between homosexual and heterosexual men.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Swaab DF, Hofman MA |title=An enlarged suprachiasmatic nucleus in homosexual men |journal=Brain Res. |volume=537 |issue=1–2 |pages=141–8 |year=1990 |month=December |pmid=2085769 |doi= 10.1016/0006-8993(90)90350-K|url=http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/0006-8993(90)90350-K}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1992, Allen and Gorski reported a difference related to sexual orientation in the size of the [[anterior commissure]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid1496013&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Allen LS, Gorski RA |title=Sexual orientation and the size of the anterior commissure in the human brain |journal=Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. |volume=89 |issue=15 |pages=7199–202 |year=1992 |month=August |pmid=1496013 |pmc=49673 |doi= 10.1073/pnas.89.15.7199|url=http://www.pnas.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;pmid=1496013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Sexually dimorphic nuclei in the anterior hypothalamus====
[[Simon LeVay]], too, conducted some of these early researches. He studied four groups of [[neuron]]s in the [[hypothalamus]] called INAH1, INAH2, INAH3 and INAH4. This was a relevant area of the brain to study, because of evidence that it played a role in the regulation of [[sexual behaviour in animals]], and because INAH2 and INAH3 had previously been reported to differ in size between men and women.&lt;ref name=&quot;LeVay 1991&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=LeVay S |title=A difference in hypothalamic structure between heterosexual and homosexual men |journal=Science |volume=253 |issue=5023 |pages=1034–7 |year=1991 |month=August |pmid=1887219 |doi=10.1126/science.1887219 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

He obtained brains from 41 deceased hospital patients. The subjects were classified into three groups. The first group comprised 19 gay men who had died of [[AIDS]]-related illnesses. The second group comprised 16 men whose sexual orientation was unknown, but whom the researchers presumed to be heterosexual. Six of these men had died of AIDS-related illnesses. The third group was of six women whom the researchers presumed to be heterosexual. One of the women had died of an AIDS-related illness.&lt;ref name=&quot;LeVay 1991&quot; /&gt;

The [[HIV-positive people]] in the presumably-heterosexual patient groups were all identified from medical records as either [[intravenous drug abuse]]rs or recipients of [[blood transfusion]]s. Two of the men who identified as heterosexual specifically denied ever engaging in a homosexual sex act. The records of the remaining heterosexual subjects contained no information about their sexual orientation; they were assumed to have been primarily or exclusively heterosexual &quot;on the basis of the numerical preponderance of heterosexual men in the population.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;LeVay 1991&quot; /&gt;

LeVay found no evidence for a difference between the groups in the size of INAH1, INAH2 or INAH4. However, the INAH3 group appeared to be twice as big in the heterosexual male group as in the gay male group; the difference was highly significant, and remained significant when only the six AIDS patients were included in the heterosexual group. The size of INAH3 in the homosexual men's brains was comparable to the size of INAH3 in the heterosexual women's brains.

William Byne and colleagues attempted to identify the size differences reported in INAH 1-4 by replicating the experiment using brain sample from other subjects: 14 HIV-positive homosexual males, 34 presumed heterosexual males (10 HIV-positive), and 34 presumed heterosexual females (9 HIV-positive). The researchers found a significant difference in INAH3 size between heterosexual men and heterosexual women. The INAH3 size of the homosexual men was apparently smaller than that of the heterosexual men, and larger than that of the heterosexual women, though neither difference quite reached statistical significance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Byne 2001&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Byne W, Tobet S, Mattiace LA, ''et al.'' |title=The interstitial nuclei of the human anterior hypothalamus: an investigation of variation with sex, sexual orientation, and HIV status |journal=Horm Behav |volume=40 |issue=2 |pages=86–92 |year=2001 |month=September |pmid=11534967 |doi=10.1006/hbeh.2001.1680 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Byne and colleagues also weighed and counted numbers of neurons in INAH3, tests not carried out by LeVay. The results for INAH3 weight were similar to those for INAH3 size; that is, the INAH3 weight for the heterosexual male brains was significantly larger than for the heterosexual female brains, while the results for the gay male group were between those of the other two groups but not quite significantly different from either. The neuron count also found a male-female difference in INAH3, but found no trend related to sexual orientation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Byne 2001&quot; /&gt;

A 2010 study, Garcia-Falgueras and Swaab asserted that &quot;the fetal brain develops during the intrauterine period in the male direction through a direct action of testosterone on the developing nerve cells, or in the female direction through the absence of this hormone surge. In this way, our gender identity (the conviction of belonging to the male or female gender) and sexual orientation are programmed or organized into our brain structures when we are still in the womb. There is no indication that social environment after birth has an effect on gender identity or sexual orientation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Garcia-Falgueras A, Swaab DF |title=Sexual Hormones and the Brain: An Essential Alliance for Sexual Identity and Sexual Orientation |journal=Endocr Dev |volume=17 |issue= |pages=22–35 |year=2010 |pmid=19955753 |doi=10.1159/000262525|series=Endocrine Development|isbn=978-3-8055-9302-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====The ovine model====
The [[domestic ram]] is used as an experimental model to study early programming of the neural mechanisms which underlie homosexuality, developing from the observation that approximately 8% of domestic rams are sexually attracted to other rams (male-oriented) when compared to the majority of rams which are female-oriented. In many species, a prominent feature of sexual differentiation is the presence of a sexually dimorphic nucleus (SDN) in the preoptic hypothalamus, which is larger in males than in females. 

Roselli ''et al.'' discovered an ovine SDN (oSDN) in the preoptic hypothalamus that is smaller in male orientated rams than in female oriented rams, but similar in size to the oSDN of females. Neurons of the oSDN show aromatase expression which is also smaller in male-oriented rams versus female-oriented rams, suggesting that sexual orientation is neurologically hard-wired and may be influenced by hormones. However, results failed to associate the role of neural aromatase in the sexual differentiation of brain and behavior in the sheep, due to the lack of defeminization of adult sexual partner preference or oSDN volume as a result of aromatase activity in the brain of the fetuses during the critical period. Having said this, it is more likely that oSDN morphology and homosexuality may be programmed through an androgen receptor that does not involve aromatisation. Most of the data suggests that homosexual rams, like female-oriented rams, are masculinized and defeminized with respect to mounting, receptivity, and gonadotrophin secretion, but are not defeminized for sexual partner preferences, also suggesting that such behaviors may be programmed differently. Although the exact function of the oSDN is not fully known, its volume, length, and cell number seem to correlate with sexual orientation, and a dimorphism in its volume and of cells could bias the processing cues involved in partner selection. More research is needed in order to understand the requirements and timing of the development of the oSDN and how prenatal programming effects the expression of mate choice in adulthood.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal
 | author = [[C. E. Roselli]] &amp; [[F. Stormshak]]
 | title = Prenatal programming of sexual partner preference: the ram model
 | journal = [[Journal of Neuroendocrinology]]
 | volume = 21
 | issue = 4
 | pages = 359–364
 | year = 2009
 | month = March
 | doi = 10.1111/j.1365-2826.2009.01828.x
 | pmid = 19207819
 | pmc = 2668810
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biological theories of etiology of sexual orientation==
=== Early fixation hypothesis ===
{{Main|Prenatal hormones and sexual orientation}}
The early fixation hypothesis includes research into prenatal development and the environmental factors that control masculinization of the brain. Some studies have seen pre-natal hormone exposures as the primary factor involved in determining sexual orientation.&lt;ref&gt;Garcia-Falgueras, Alicia, &amp; Swaab, Dick F., Sexual Hormones and the Brain: An Essential Alliance for Sexual Identity and Sexual Orientation, in Endocrine Development, vol. 17, pp. 22–35 (2010) (ISSN 1421-7082) (authors are of Netherlands Institute for Neuroscience, of Royal Netherlands Academy of Arts and Sciences) (author contact is 2d author) (vol. 17 is Sandro Loche, Marco Cappa, Lucia Ghizzoni, Mohamad Maghnie, &amp; Martin O. Savage, eds., Pediatric Neuroendocrinology).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, G.D. &amp; Rahman, Q (2005) Born Gay: The Psychobiology of Sex Orientation, Peter Owen, London&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | pmid = 4808435 | volume=131 | issue=1 | title=Plasma testosterone levels in heterosexual and homosexual men | year=1974 | month=January | journal=Am J Psychiatry | pages=82–3 | author=Brodie HK, Gartrell N, Doering C, Rhue T}}&lt;/ref&gt; This hypothesis is supported by both the observed differences in brain structure and cognitive processing between homosexual and heterosexual men. One explanation for these differences is the idea that differential exposure to hormone levels in the womb during fetal development may change the masculinization of the brain in homosexual men. The concentrations of these chemicals is thought to be influenced by fetal and maternal immune systems, maternal consumption of certain drugs, maternal stress, and direct injection. This hypothesis is also connected to the [[Fraternal birth order and sexual orientation|fraternal birth order research]].

===Imprinting/critical period===
This type of theory holds that the formation of gender identity occurs in the first few years of life after birth. It argues that individuals can be predisposed to homosexual orientation by biological factors but are triggered in some cases by upbringing. Part of adopting a gender identity involves establishing the gender(s) of sexual attraction. This process is analogous to the &quot;imprinting&quot; process observed in animals. A baby duckling may be genetically programmed to &quot;imprint&quot; on a mother, but what entity it actually imprints upon depends on what objects it sees immediately after hatching. Most importantly, once this process has occurred, it cannot be reversed, any more than the duckling can hatch twice.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}}

A sort of reverse sexual imprinting has been observed in heterosexual humans; see the section on the &quot;Westermarck effect&quot; in [[Behavioral imprinting#Westermarck effect|Behavioral imprinting]].

Several different triggers for imprinting upon a particular sexual orientation have been proposed, but there is no empirical evidence to support any of them.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}}

===Exotic becomes erotic===
[[Daryl Bem]], a social psychologist at [[Cornell University]], has theorized that the influence of biological factors on sexual orientation may be mediated by experiences in childhood. A child's temperament predisposes the child to prefer certain activities over others. Because of their temperament, which is influenced by biological variables such as genetic factors, some children will be attracted to activities that are commonly enjoyed by other children of the same gender. Others will prefer activities that are typical of another gender. This will make a gender-conforming child feel different from opposite-gender children, while gender-nonconforming children will feel different from children of their own gender. According to Bem, this feeling of difference will evoke physiological arousal when the child is near members of the gender which it considers as being 'different'. Bem theorizes that this physiological arousal will later be transformed into sexual arousal: children will become sexually attracted to the gender which they see as different (&quot;exotic&quot;). This theory is known as Exotic Becomes Erotic theory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bem&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Bem DJ, Herdt G, McClintock M |title=Exotic becomes erotic: interpreting the biological correlates of sexual orientation |journal=Arch Sex Behav |volume=29 |issue=6 |pages=531–48 |year=2000 |month=December |pmid=11100261 |doi= 10.1023/A:1002050303320|url=http://www.kluweronline.com/art.pdf?issn=0004-0002&amp;volume=29&amp;page=531}} [http://dbem.ws/Exotic%20Becomes%20Erotic.pdf PDF]&lt;/ref&gt;

The theory is based in part on the frequent finding that a majority of gay men and lesbians report being gender-nonconforming during their childhood years. A meta-analysis of 48 studies showed [[childhood gender nonconformity]] to be the strongest predictor of a homosexual orientation for both men and women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Bailey | first1 = J.M. | last2 = Zucker | first2 = K.J. | year = 1995 | title = Childhood sex-typed behavior and sexual orientation: A conceptual analysis and quantitative review | url = http://content.apa.org/journals/dev/31/1/43 | journal = Developmental Psychology | volume = 31 | issue = 1| pages = 43–55 | doi = 10.1037/0012-1649.31.1.43 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Fourteen studies published since Bailey &amp; Zucker's 1995 also show the same results.&lt;ref&gt;Zucker, K.J. (2005) Commentary on Gottschalk’s (2003) ‘Same-sex sexuality and childhood gender non-conformity: A spurious connection’ Journal of Gender Studies, 14:55–60.&lt;/ref&gt; In one study by the Kinsey Institute of approximately 1000 gay men and lesbians (and a control group of 500 heterosexual men and women), 63% of both gay men and lesbians reported that they were gender nonconforming in childhood (i.e., did not like activities typical of their sex), compared with only 10–15% of heterosexual men and women. There are also six &quot;prospective&quot; studies—that is longitudinal studies that begin with gender-nonconforming boys at about age 7 and follow them up into adolescence and adulthood. These also show that a majority (63%) of the gender nonconforming boys become gay or bisexual as adults.&lt;ref&gt;Zucker, K.J. (1990) Gender identity disorders in children: clinical descriptions and natural history. p.1–23 in R. Blanchard &amp; B.W. Steiner (eds) Clinical management of gender identity disorders in children and adults. Washington DC, American Psychiatric Press.&lt;/ref&gt; There are very few prospective studies of gender nonconforming girls.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Green R |title=Childhood cross-gender behavior and subsequent sexual preference |journal=Am J Psychiatry |volume=136 |issue=1 |pages=106–8 |year=1979 |month=January |pmid=758811 |doi= |url=http://ajp.psychiatryonline.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;pmid=758811}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Cohen-Kettenis PT |title=Gender identity disorder in DSM? |journal=J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry |volume=40 |issue=4 |pages=391 |year=2001 |month=April |pmid=11314563 |doi= 10.1097/00004583-200104000-00006|url=http://meta.wkhealth.com/pt/pt-core/template-journal/lwwgateway/media/landingpage.htm?issn=0890-8567&amp;volume=40&amp;issue=4&amp;spage=391}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a group of eighteen behaviorally masculine girls (mean age of assessment: 9 years), all reported a homosexual sexual orientation at adolescence, and eight had requested sex reassignment.&lt;ref&gt;Cohen-Kettenis, P. T. (2001) Gender identity disorder in DSM? [Letter to the editor], Journal of the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, 40, p. 391. and comments reported in: Zucker, K.J. (2005) Commentary on Gottschalk’s (2003) ‘Same-sex sexuality and childhood gender non-conformity: A spurious connection’ Journal of Gender Studies, 14:55–60.&lt;/ref&gt;

William Reiner, a psychiatrist and urologist with the [[University of Oklahoma]] has evaluated more than a hundred cases of children born with sexual differentiation disorders. In the 1960s and '70s, it was common in [[developed countries]] for doctors to [[castration|castrate]] boys born with a [[micropenis]] and have them raised as girls. However, this practice has come under attack, because even though these boys were raised as girls, they nearly all report as adults that they are sexually attracted to women. This suggests that their sexual orientation was determined at birth.{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}}

==Sexual orientation and evolution==
Sexual practices that significantly reduce the frequency of heterosexual intercourse also significantly decrease the chances of successful reproduction, and for this reason, they would appear to be [[adaptation|maladaptive]] in an [[evolution]]ary context following a simple Darwinian model of natural selection—on the assumption that homosexuality would reduce this frequency.  Several theories have been advanced to explain this contradiction, and new experimental evidence has demonstrated their feasibility.&lt;ref name=&quot;MacIntyre F, Estep KW 1993 223-33&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|doi=10.1016/0303-2647(93)90051-D |author=MacIntyre F, Estep KW |title=Sperm competition and the persistence of genes for male homosexuality |journal=BioSystems |volume=31 |issue=2–3 |pages=223–33 |year=1993 |pmid=8155854}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some scholars&lt;ref name=&quot;MacIntyre F, Estep KW 1993 223-33&quot;/&gt; have suggested that homosexuality is adaptive in a non-obvious way. By way of analogy, the [[allele]] (a particular version of a gene) which causes [[Sickle-cell disease|sickle-cell anemia]] when two copies are present may also confer resistance to [[malaria]] with a lesser form of [[anemia]] when one copy is present (this is called [[heterozygous advantage]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;swars&quot;&gt;Baker, Robin (1996) Sperm Wars: The Science of Sex, p.241 ff.&lt;/ref&gt;

The so-called &quot;gay uncle&quot; hypothesis posits that people who themselves do not have children may nonetheless increase the prevalence of their family's genes in future generations by providing resources (food, supervision, defense, shelter, etc.) to the offspring of their closest relatives. This hypothesis is an extension of the theory of kin selection. [[Kin selection]] was originally developed to explain apparent altruistic acts which seemed to be maladaptive. The initial concept was suggested by [[J.B.S. Haldane]] in 1932 and later elaborated by many others including [[John Maynard Smith]], [[W. D. Hamilton]] and [[Mary Jane West-Eberhard]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Mayr 1982&quot;&gt;Mayr, E. (1982). The Growth of Biological Thought: Diversity, Evolution, and Inheritance. Cambridge: Harvard University Press. p598.&lt;/ref&gt; This concept was also used to explain the patterns of certain social insects where most of the members are non-reproductive.

Brendan Zietsch of the Queensland Institute of Medical Research proposes the alternative theory that men exhibiting female traits become more attractive to females and are thus more likely to mate, provided the genes involved do not drive them to complete rejection of heterosexuality.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.economist.com/science/displaystory.cfm?story_id=12465295 How homosexuality may have evolved]&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 2008 study, its authors stated that &quot;There is considerable evidence that human sexual orientation is genetically influenced, so it is not known how homosexuality, which tends to lower reproductive success, is maintained in the population at a relatively high frequency.&quot; They hypothesized that &quot;while genes predisposing to homosexuality reduce homosexuals' reproductive success, they may confer some advantage in heterosexuals who carry them.&quot; and their results suggested that &quot;genes predisposing to homosexuality may confer a mating advantage in heterosexuals, which could help explain the evolution and maintenance of homosexuality in the population.&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Zietsch, B., Morley, K., Shekar, S., Verweij, K., Keller, M., Macgregor, S., et al. |year=2008 |month=November |title=Genetic factors predisposing to homosexuality may increase mating success in heterosexuals |journal=Evolution and Human Behavior |volume=29 |issue=6 |pages=424–433 |doi=10.1016/j.evolhumbehav.2008.07.002}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in the same study, the authors noted that &quot;nongenetic alternative explanations cannot be ruled out&quot; as a reason for the heterosexual in the homosexual-heterosexual twin pair having more partners, specifically citing &quot;social
pressure on the other twin to act in a more heterosexual way&quot; (and thus seek out a greater number of sexual partners) as an example of one alternative explanation. Also, the authors of the study acknowledge that a large number of sexual partners may not lead to greater reproductive success, specifically noting there is an &quot;absence of evidence relating the number of sexual partners and actual reproductive success,either in the present or in our evolutionary past.&quot;

Important new evidence on a plausible mechanism for the evolution of &quot;gay genes&quot; has emerged from the work of Camperio-Ciani.&lt;ref name=&quot;Camperio-Ciani et al. 2004&quot; /&gt;  They found in two large, independent studies that the female relatives of homosexual men tended to have significantly more offspring than those of the heterosexual men. Female relatives of the homosexual men on their mother's side tended to have more offspring than those on the father's side. This indicates that females carrying a putative &quot;[[androphilia]] genes&quot; complex are more fecund than women lacking this complex of genes, and thereby can compensate for any decreased fertility of the males carrying the genes. This is a well known phenomenon in evolution known as &quot;sexual antagonism,&quot;{{Citation needed|date=December 2010}} and has been widely documented for many traits that are advantageous in one sex but not in the other.{{Citation needed|date=December 2010}} This provides solid experimental evidence of how &quot;gay genes&quot; could not only survive but thrive over the course of evolution.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}}

==Biological differences in gay men and lesbians==
=== Physiological ===

Some studies have found correlations between physiology of people and their sexuality. These studies provide evidence which they claim suggests that:

* Gay men report, on an average, slightly longer and thicker penises than non-gay men.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Bogaert AF, Hershberger S |title=The relation between sexual orientation and penile size |journal=Arch Sex Behav |volume=28 |issue=3 |pages=213–21 |year=1999 |pmid=10410197 |doi=10.1023/A:1018780108597}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Gay men and straight women have, on average, equally proportioned brain hemispheres. Lesbian women and straight men have, on average, slightly larger right brain hemispheres.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/7456588.stm Scans see 'gay brain differences' – BBC News]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The VIP SCN nucleus of the hypothalamus is larger in men than in women, and larger in gay men than in heterosexual men.&lt;ref&gt;Evolution's Rainbow: Diversity, Gender, and Sexuality in Nature and People. Contributors: Joan Roughgarden – author. Publisher: University of California Press. Place of Publication: Berkeley, CA. Publication Year: 2004. Page Number: 245.&lt;/ref&gt;
* The average size of the [[INAH 3|INAH-3]] in the brains of gay men is approximately the same size as INAH 3 in women, which is significantly smaller, and the cells more densely packed, than in heterosexual men's brains.&lt;ref name=&quot;LeVay 1991&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=LeVay S |title=A difference in hypothalamic structure between heterosexual and homosexual men |journal=Science |volume=253 |issue=5023 |pages=1034–7 |year=1991 |pmid=1887219 |doi=10.1126/science.1887219}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[anterior commissure]] is larger in women than men and was reported to be larger in gay men than in non-gay men,&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid1496013&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Allen LS, Gorski RA |title=Sexual orientation and the size of the anterior commissure in the human brain |journal=Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. |volume=89 |issue=15 |pages=7199–202 |year=1992 |pmid=1496013 |doi=10.1073/pnas.89.15.7199 |pmc=49673}}&lt;/ref&gt; but a subsequent study found no such difference.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Lasco | first1 = M. S. | last2 = Jordan | first2 = T. J. | last3 = Edgar | first3 = M. A. | last4 = Petito | first4 = C. K. | last5 = Byne | first5 = W. | year = 2002 | title = A lack of dimorphism of sex or sexual orientation in the human anterior commissure | url = | journal = Brain Research | pmid = 11988236 | volume = 936 | issue = 1–2| pages = 95–98 | doi = 10.1016/S0006-8993(02)02590-8 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Gay men's brains respond differently to [[fluoxetine]], a [[selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Kinnunen LH, Moltz H, Metz J, Cooper M |title=Differential brain activation in exclusively homosexual and heterosexual men produced by the selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor, fluoxetine |journal=Brain Res. |volume=1024 |issue=1–2 |pages=251–4 |year=2004 |pmid=15451388 |doi=10.1016/j.brainres.2004.07.070}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The functioning of the inner ear and the central auditory system in lesbians and bisexual women are more like the functional properties found in men than in non-gay women (the researchers argued this finding was consistent with the [[Prenatal hormones and sexual orientation|prenatal hormonal theory of sexual orientation]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;mcf&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=McFadden D |title=Masculinization effects in the auditory system |journal=Arch Sex Behav |volume=31 |issue=1 |pages=99–111 |year=2002 |pmid=11910797 |doi=10.1023/A:1014087319682}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[suprachiasmatic nucleus]] was found by Swaab and Hopffman to be larger in gay men than in non-gay men,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dafml.unito.it/anatomy/panzica/pubblicazioni/pdf/1995PanzicaJEI.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; the suprachiasmatic nucleus is also known to be larger in men than in women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Swaab DF, Zhou JN, Ehlhart T, Hofman MA |title=Development of vasoactive intestinal polypeptide neurons in the human suprachiasmatic nucleus in relation to birth and sex |journal=Brain Res. Dev. Brain Res. |volume=79 |issue=2 |pages=249–59 |year=1994 |pmid=7955323 |doi=10.1016/0165-3806(94)90129-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[startle response]] (eyeblink following a loud sound) is similarly masculinized in lesbians and bisexual women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Rahman Q, Kumari V, Wilson GD |title=Sexual orientation-related differences in prepulse inhibition of the human startle response |journal=Behav. Neurosci. |volume=117 |issue=5 |pages=1096–102 |year=2003 |pmid=14570558 |doi=10.1037/0735-7044.117.5.1096}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Gay and non-gay people's brains respond differently to two putative sex pheromones (AND, found in male armpit secretions, and EST, found in female urine).&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid15883379&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Savic I, Berglund H, Gulyas B, Roland P |title=Smelling of odorous sex hormone-like compounds causes sex-differentiated hypothalamic activations in humans |journal=Neuron |volume=31 |issue=4 |pages=661–8 |year=2001 |pmid=11545724 |doi=10.1016/S0896-6273(01)00390-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Berglund H, Lindström P, Savic I |title=Brain response to putative pheromones in lesbian women |journal=Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. |volume=103 |issue=21 |pages=8269–74 |year=2006 |pmid=16705035 |doi=10.1073/pnas.0600331103 |pmc=1570103}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[amygdala]], a region of the brain, is more active in gay men than non-gay men when exposed to sexually arousing material.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Safron A, Barch B, Bailey JM, Gitelman DR, Parrish TB, Reber PJ |title=Neural correlates of sexual arousal in homosexual and heterosexual men |journal=Behav. Neurosci. |volume=121 |issue=2 |pages=237–48 |year=2007 |pmid=17469913 |doi=10.1037/0735-7044.121.2.237}}. The authors of the study caution that any interpretation of this finding must take into account that the group difference in brain activation between heterosexual men and homosexual men in the amygdala region is not large and that the most robust finding is that both heterosexual and homosexual men used the same areas when they reacted to sexually preferred stimuli. &quot;''For the most part, homosexual and heterosexual men showed very similar patterns of activation (albeit to different erotic stimuli). One possible exception was the amygdala, in which homosexual men showed greater activational differences between preferred and nonpreferred erotic stimuli compared with heterosexual men. However, this difference was not hypothesized a priori, was not large, and was the only group difference found out of many tested. Thus, this finding needs replication.''&quot;(Debra A. Hope (editor), ''What is Sexual Orientation and Do Women Have One?'' (presentation by J.M. Bailey), Nebraska Symposium on Motivation, Volume 54 p. 47, Springer Science, 2009.)&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Digit ratio|Finger length ratios]] between the index and ring fingers may be different between non-gay and lesbian women.&lt;ref name=&quot;mcf&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Brown WM, Hines M, Fane BA, Breedlove SM |title=Masculinized finger length patterns in human males and females with congenital adrenal hyperplasia |journal=Horm Behav |volume=42 |issue=4 |pages=380–6 |year=2002 |pmid=12488105 |doi=10.1006/hbeh.2002.1830}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Hines M, Johnston KJ, Golombok S, Rust J, Stevens M, Golding J |title=Prenatal stress and gender role behavior in girls and boys: a longitudinal, population study |journal=Horm Behav |volume=42 |issue=2 |pages=126–34 |year=2002 |pmid=12367566 |doi=10.1006/hbeh.2002.1814}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Rahman Q, Wilson GD |title=Sexual orientation and the 2nd to 4th finger length ratio: evidence for organising effects of sex hormones or developmental instability? |journal=Psychoneuroendocrinology |volume=28 |issue=3 |pages=288–303 |year=2003 |pmid=12573297 |doi=10.1016/S0306-4530(02)00022-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Brown WM, Finn CJ, Cooke BM, Breedlove SM |title=Differences in finger length ratios between self-identified &quot;butch&quot; and &quot;femme&quot; lesbians |journal=Arch Sex Behav |volume=31 |issue=1 |pages=123–7 |year=2002 |pmid=11910785 |doi=10.1023/A:1014091420590}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Hall LS, Love CT |title=Finger-length ratios in female monozygotic twins discordant for sexual orientation |journal=Arch Sex Behav |volume=32 |issue=1 |pages=23–8 |year=2003 |pmid=12597269 |doi=10.1023/A:1021837211630}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Gay men and lesbians are significantly [[Handedness and sexual orientation|more likely to be left-handed or ambidextrous]] than non-gay men and women;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Lalumière ML, Blanchard R, Zucker KJ |title=Sexual orientation and handedness in men and women: a meta-analysis |journal=Psychol Bull |volume=126 |issue=4 |pages=575–92 |year=2000 |pmid=10900997 |doi=10.1037/0033-2909.126.4.575}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Mustanski BS, Bailey JM, Kaspar S |title=Dermatoglyphics, handedness, sex, and sexual orientation |journal=Arch Sex Behav |volume=31 |issue=1 |pages=113–22 |year=2002 |pmid=11910784 |doi=10.1023/A:1014039403752}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Lippa RA |title=Handedness, sexual orientation, and gender-related personality traits in men and women |journal=Arch Sex Behav |volume=32 |issue=2 |pages=103–14 |year=2003 |pmid=12710825 |doi=10.1023/A:1022444223812}}&lt;/ref&gt; Simon LeVay argues that because &quot;[h]and preference is observable before birth&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Hepper PG, Shahidullah S, White R |title=Handedness in the human fetus |journal=Neuropsychologia |volume=29 |issue=11 |pages=1107–11 |year=1991 |pmid=1775228 |doi=10.1016/0028-3932(91)90080-R}}&lt;/ref&gt;... [t]he observation of increased non-right-handness in gay people is therefore consistent with the idea that sexual orientation is influenced by prenatal processes,&quot; perhaps heredity.&lt;ref name=&quot;LeVay 1991&quot;/&gt;
* A study of 50 gay men found 23% had counterclockwise [[hair whorl]], as opposed to 8% in the general population.  This may correlate with left-handedness.&lt;ref name=&quot;nymag&quot;&gt;[http://nymag.com/news/features/33520/ The Science of Gaydar] by David France.  New York Magazine.  18 June 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Gay men have increased ridge density in the fingerprints on their left thumbs and pinkies.&lt;ref name=&quot;nymag&quot; /&gt;
* Length of limbs and hands of gay men is smaller compared to height than the general population, but only among white men.&lt;ref name=&quot;nymag&quot; /&gt;

===Cognitive===
Recent studies suggest the presence of subtle differences in the way gay people and non-gay people process certain kinds of information. Researchers have found that:
* Gay men&lt;ref&gt;Geoff Sanders, Ph.D. and Marian Wright, B.Sc.(1997), Sexual Orientation Differences in Cerebral Asymmetry and in the Performance of Sexually Dimorphic Cognitive and Motor Tasks&lt;/ref&gt; and lesbians are more verbally [[fluency|fluent]] than heterosexuals of the same sex&lt;ref&gt;[http://inductivist.blogspot.com/2007/09/homosexuality-and-iq-looking-at.html GSS data on verbal performance of homosexual, heterosexual, and bisexual males and females]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=McCormick CM, Witelson SF |title=A cognitive profile of homosexual men compared to heterosexual men and women |journal=Psychoneuroendocrinology |volume=16 |issue=6 |pages=459–73 |year=1991 |pmid=1811244 |doi=10.1016/0306-4530(91)90030-W}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Rahman Q, Abrahams S, Wilson GD |title=Sexual-orientation-related differences in verbal fluency |journal=Neuropsychology |volume=17 |issue=2 |pages=240–6 |year=2003 |pmid=12803429 |doi=10.1037/0894-4105.17.2.240}}&lt;/ref&gt; (but two studies did not find this result).&lt;ref&gt;Gladue, B. A., W. W. Beatty, et al. (1990). &quot;[http://doi.apa.org/?uid=1990-24416-001 Sexual orientation and spatial ability in men and women.]&quot; Psychobiology 18: 101–108.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Neave N, Menaged M, Weightman DR |title=Sex differences in cognition: the role of testosterone and sexual orientation |journal=Brain Cogn |volume=41 |issue=3 |pages=245–62 |year=1999 |pmid=10585237 |doi=10.1006/brcg.1999.1125}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Gay men may receive higher scores than non-gay men on tests of object location memory (no difference was found between lesbians and non-gay women).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Rahman Q, Wilson GD, Abrahams S |title=Sexual orientation related differences in spatial memory |journal=J Int Neuropsychol Soc |volume=9 |issue=3 |pages=376–83 |year=2003 |pmid=12666762 |doi=10.1017/S1355617703930037}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Political aspects==
{{Main|LGBT social movements|LGBT rights opposition}}
Whether genetic or other physiological determinants form the basis of sexual orientation is a highly politicized issue. ''[[The Advocate]]'', a U.S. gay and lesbian newsmagazine, reported in 1996 that 61% of its readers believed that &quot;it would mostly help gay and lesbian rights if homosexuality were found to be biologically determined&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;The Advocate (1996, February 6). Advocate Poll Results. p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt; A cross-national study in the [[United States]], the [[Philippines]], and [[Sweden]] found that those who believed that &quot;homosexuals are born that way&quot; held significantly more positive attitudes toward homosexuality than those who believed that &quot;homosexuals choose to be that way&quot; or &quot;learn to be that way&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Ernulf KE, Innala SM, Whitam FL |title=Biological explanation, psychological explanation, and tolerance of homosexuals: a cross-national analysis of beliefs and attitudes |journal=Psychol Rep |volume=65 |issue=3 Pt 1 |pages=1003–10 |year=1989 |month=December |pmid=2608821 |doi= 10.2466/pr0.1989.65.3.1003|url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Whitley B. E. Jr | year = 1990 | title = The relationship of heterosexuals' attributions for the causes of homosexuality to attitudes toward lesbians and gay men | url = | journal = [[Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin]] | volume = 16 | issue = | pages = 369–377 | doi = 10.1177/0146167290162016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Equal Protection Clause|Equal protection]] analysis in U.S. law determines what groups are considered [[suspect classification|suspect classes]] and therefore eligible for heightened [[strict scrutiny|scrutiny]] based on several factors, one of which is [[Immutable characteristic|immutability]]. Evidence that sexual orientation is biologically determined (and therefore perhaps immutable in the legal sense) would strengthen the legal case for heightened scrutiny of laws discriminating on that basis.&lt;ref&gt;Balog, Kari (2005–2006) &quot;Equal Protection for Homosexuals: Why the Immutability Argument is Necessary and How it is Met.&quot;, Cleveland St. L. Rev. 545–573.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Is Sexuality Immutable?&quot;, Margaret Talbot, The New Yorker, January 25, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/USA/Justice/2010/0125/Prop.-8-trial-defenders-of-gay-marriage-ban-make-their-case
|title=Prop. 8 trial: defenders of gay-marriage ban make their case
|accessdate=27 January 2010
|publisher=[[Christian Science Monitor]]
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The perceived causes of sexual orientation have a significant bearing on the status of sexual minorities in the eyes of social conservatives. The [[Family Research Council]], a [[Christian right|conservative Christian]] [[think tank]] in Washington, D.C., argues in the book ''Getting It Straight'' that finding people are born gay &quot;would advance the idea that sexual orientation is an innate characteristic, like race; that homosexuals, like African-Americans, should be legally protected against 'discrimination;' and that disapproval of homosexuality should be as socially stigmatized as racism. However, it is not true.&quot;, but did not give any further explanations. On the other hand, some [[social conservatives]] such as Reverend Robert Schenck have argued that people can accept the &quot;inevitable... scientific evidence&quot; while still morally opposing homosexuality.&lt;ref name=neil&gt;[http://www.boston.com/news/globe/magazine/articles/2005/08/14/what_makes_people_gay/ What Makes People Gay?] By Neil Swidey. ''[[The Boston Globe]]''. Published August 14, 2005. Accessed June 18, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; As well, [[National Organization for Marriage]] board member and fiction writer [[Orson Scott Card]] has supported biological research on homosexuality, writing that &quot;our scientific efforts in regard to homosexuality should be to identify genetic and uterine causes... so that the incidence of this dysfunction can be minimized.... [However, this should not be seen] as an attack on homosexuals, a desire to 'commit genocide' against the homosexual community.... There is no 'cure' for homosexuality because it is not a disease. There are, however, different ways of living with homosexual desires.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;choice&quot;&gt;{{Cite news
|url=http://www.mormontimes.com/content/single/10235
|title=Science on gays falls short
|publisher=[[Deseret Morning News]]
|date=August 7, 2008
|last=Card
|first=Orson Scott
|accessdate=June 12, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some advocates for the rights of sexual minorities resist linking that cause with the concept that sexuality is biologically determined or fixed at birth. They argue that sexual orientation can shift over the course of a person's life.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.queerbychoice.com/myths.html Myths About Queer by Choice People]. [http://www.queerbychoice.com/ Queer by Choice]. Accessed March 6, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, others resist any attempts to pathologise or medicalise 'deviant' sexuality, and choose to fight for acceptance in a moral or social realm.&lt;ref name=neil/&gt; [[Chandler Burr]] writing for ''[[The Atlantic Monthly]]'' has stated that &quot;[s]ome, recalling earlier psychiatric &quot;treatments&quot; for homosexuality, discern in the biological quest the seeds of genocide. They conjure up the specter of the surgical or chemical &quot;rewiring&quot; of gay people, or of abortions of fetal homosexuals who have been hunted down in the womb.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theatlantic.com/doc/199706/homosexuality-biology/4 Homosexuality and Biology]. By Chandler Burr. ''[[The Atlantic Monthly]]''. June 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Simon LeVay]] has said, in response to letters from gays and lesbians making such criticisms, that the research &quot;has contributed to the status of gay people in society.&quot;&lt;ref name=neil/&gt;

==See also==
* ''[[Against Nature?]]''
* [[Alfred Kinsey]]
* [[Arnold Aletrino]]
* [[Norms of reaction]]
* [[Xq28]]
* [[Environment and sexual orientation]]
* [[Gay bomb]]
* [[Neuroscience and sexual orientation]]
* [[Mental roots of sexual orientation]]
* [[Homosexual behavior in animals]]

==References==
;Notes
{{Reflist|2}}

;Bibliography
* Anders Agmo [http://www.elsevier.com/wps/find/bookdescription.cws_home/712200/description#description Functional and dysfunctional sexual behavior] Elsevier 2007
* Serge Wunsch [http://psychobiologie.ouvaton.org/telechargement/these_comportement_reproduction.pdf PhD thesis about sexual behavior] Paris [http://www.ephe.sorbonne.fr/ Sorbonne] 2007
* BBC (April 23, 1999). [http://news.bbc.co.uk/hi/english/sci/tech/newsid_325000/325979.stm Doubt cast on 'gay gene']. ''BBC News''.
* Articles by Dr. [[Daryl Bem]] will be found at [http://dbem.ws/online_pubs.html], including several on his EBE theory
* {{cite journal | doi = 10.1038/scientificamerican0594-50 | last1 = Byne | first1 = William | author-separator =, | author-name-separator= | year = 1994 | title = The Biological Evidence Challenged | url = http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/assault/genetics/biochallenge.html | journal = Scientific American | volume = 270 | issue = 5| pages = 50–55 | pmid = 8197445 }}
* Trisha Macnair (undated). [http://www.bbc.co.uk/health/features/genes_behaviour.shtml Genetics and human behaviour]. ''BBC Health''.
* Timothy F. Murphy (Fall 2000). [http://www.apa.udel.edu/apa/publications/newsletters/v00n1/lgbt/04.asp Now What? The Latest Theory of Homosexuality]. ''APA Newsletter on Philosophy and Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual and Transgender Issues''.
* {{cite journal | last1 = Muscarella | first1 = F. | last2 = Fink | first2 = B. | last3 = Grammer | first3 = K. | last4 = Kirk-Smith | first4 = M. | year = 2001 | title = Homosexual Orientation in Males: Evolutionary and Ethological Aspects | url = http://evolution.anthro.univie.ac.at/institutes/urbanethology/resources/pdf/NEL220601R01_Muscarella_.pdf | format = PDF | journal = Neuroendocrinology Letters | volume = 22 | issue = 6| pages = 393–400 | pmid = 11781535 }}
* Nuffield Council on Bioethics (2002). ''[http://www.nuffieldbioethics.org/publications/geneticsandhb/rep0000001098.asp Genetics and human behaviour]''. London: Author. [http://www.nuffieldbioethics.org/publications/geneticsandhb/rep0000001031.asp Chapter 10] discusses sexual orientation.
* [http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0422898 Out in Nature: Homosexual Behaviour in the Animal Kingdom], a documentary by Stéphane Alexandresco, Bertrand Loyer and Jessica Menendez
* Rahman Q. (2005). The neurodevelopment of human sexual orientation. ''Neuroscience and Biobehavioral Reviews'' '''29 ''':1057–1066.
* {{Cite journal|author=Rines JP, vom Saal FS |title=Fetal effects on sexual behavior and aggression in young and old female mice treated with estrogen and testosterone |journal=Horm Behav |volume=18 |issue=2 |pages=117–29 |year=1984 |month=June |pmid=6539747 |doi=10.1016/0018-506X(84)90037-0 |url=http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/0018-506X(84)90037-0}}
* {{cite journal | doi = 10.1111/0022-4537.00165 | last1 = Veniegas | first1 = Rosemary C. | last2 = Conley | first2 = Terri D. | year = 2000 | title = Biological Research on Women's Sexual Orientations: Evaluating the Scientific Evidence | url = http://www.findarticles.com/cf_0/m0341/2_56/66419866/print.jhtml | journal = Journal of Social Issues | volume = 56 | issue = 2| pages = 267–282 }}
* {{Cite journal|author=Ryan BC, Vandenbergh JG |title=Intrauterine position effects |journal=Neurosci Biobehav Rev |volume=26 |issue=6 |pages=665–78 |year=2002 |month=October |pmid=12479841 |doi=10.1016/S0149-7634(02)00038-6 |url=http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0149763402000386}}
* {{cite journal | doi = 10.1038/scientificamerican0594-44 | last1 = LeVay | first1 = Simon | authorlink = Simon LeVay | last2 = Hamer | first2 = Dean H. | year = 1994 | title = Evidence for a Biological Influence in Male Homosexuality | url = | journal = Scientific American | volume = 270 | issue = 5| pages = 44–49 | pmid = 8197444 }}
* T. J. Taylor (1992). ''[http://www.tim-taylor.com/papers/twin_studies/ Twin Studies of Homosexuality]''. Part II Experimental Psychology Dissertation (unpublished), University of Cambridge, UK.
* {{Cite journal|author=vom Saal FS |title=Sexual differentiation in litter-bearing mammals: influence of sex of adjacent fetuses in utero |journal=J. Anim. Sci. |volume=67 |issue=7 |pages=1824–40 |year=1989 |month=July |pmid=2670873 |doi= |url=http://jas.fass.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;pmid=2670873}}
* {{Cite journal|author=vom Saal FS, Bronson FH |title=Sexual characteristics of adult female mice are correlated with their blood testosterone levels during prenatal development |journal=Science |volume=208 |issue=4444 |pages=597–9 |year=1980 |month=May |pmid=7367881 |doi=10.1126/science.7367881 |url=http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;pmid=7367881}}
* McCarty, Linda. &quot;Wearing my identity: a transgender teacher in the classroom.&quot; Equity &amp; Excellence in Education 36.2 (June 2003): 170–183. Expanded Academic ASAP. Gale. UC Santa Barbara. 10 December 2007 [http://find.galegroup.com/itx/start.do?prodId=EAIM].
*Begley, Sharon. &quot;Nature plus nurture.&quot; Newsweek 126.n20 (Nov 13, 1995): 72(1). Expanded Academic ASAP. Gale. UC Santa Barbara. 10 December 2007 [http://find.galegroup.com/ips/start.do?prodId=IPS].
*Jones, Steve. &quot;Ys and wherefores.&quot; New Statesman &amp; Society 6.n256 (June 11, 1993): 30(2). Expanded Academic ASAP. Gale. UC Santa Barbara. 10 December 2007 [http://find.galegroup.com/ips/start.do?prodId=IPS].
* Dr. Gregory Cochran (July 2005). [http://zero.poynt.zero.googlepages.com/home An Evolutionary Look At Human Homosexuality].
* Caleb Crain (August 1999). [http://www.steamthing.com/gaygerm.html Did a Germ Make You Gay?]. ''Out Magazine''.

==External links==
*[http://www.gaybros.com Molecular Genetic Study of Sexual Orientation] A genetic study of gay brothers at Northwestern University.

&lt;!--spacing--&gt;

{{human group differences}}
{{LGBT|orientation=yes}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Biology And Sexual Orientation}}
[[Category:Sexual orientation and science]]
[[Category:Biology of gender]]

[[cy:Bioleg a chyfeiriadedd rhywiol]]
[[es:Biología y orientación sexual]]
[[pt:Biologia e orientação sexual]]
[[ru:Биология и сексуальная ориентация]]
[[tr:Biyoloji ve cinsel yönelim]]
[[vi:Yếu tố sinh học trong thiên hướng tình dục]]
[[zh:性傾向和生物學]]</text>
      <sha1>qo0cztltwfch47s9ssj76ong5ki5sjk</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
