<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Conjoined twins</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>95801</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520741260</id>
      <parentid>520383414</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-31T13:05:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>109.104.81.29</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Born 19th century and earlier */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24396">{{Redirect|Siamese twins}}

{{Infobox disease
| Name           = Conjoined twins
| Image          = Chang-eng-bunker-PD.gif
| Caption        = A painting of Chang and Eng Bunker, circa 1836
| DiseasesDB     = 34474
| ICD10          = {{ICD10|O|33|7|o|30}}, {{ICD10|Q|89|4|q|80}}
| ICD9           = {{ICD9|678.1}}, {{ICD9|759.4}}
| ICDO           =
| OMIM           =
| MedlinePlus    =
| eMedicineSubj  = ped
| eMedicineTopic = 2936
| MeshID         = D014428
}}
'''Conjoined twins''' are [[Twin#Identical_twins|identical twins]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Conjoined Twins Facts|url=http://www.umm.edu/conjoined_twins/facts.htm|publisher=University of Maryland Medical Center|accessdate=6 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  whose bodies are joined in utero. A rare phenomenon, the occurrence is estimated to range from 1 in 50,000 births to 1 in 100,000 births, with a somewhat higher incidence in Southwest Asia and Africa.&lt;ref name=&quot;scielo.br&quot;&gt;[http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?pid=S1807-59322006000200013&amp;script=sci_arttext Importance of angiographic study in preoperative planning of conjoined twins]&lt;/ref&gt; Approximately half are [[stillbirth|stillborn]], and a smaller fraction of pairs born alive have abnormalities incompatible with life. The overall survival rate for conjoined twins is approximately 25%.&lt;ref&gt;The craniopagus malformation: classification and implications for surgical separation. James L. Stone and James T. Goodrih. Brain 2006 129(5):1084-1095 [http://brain.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/129/5/1084 Abstract and free fullt text PDF]&lt;/ref&gt;  The condition is more frequently found among females, with a ratio of 3:1.&lt;ref name=&quot;scielo.br&quot;/&gt;

Two contradicting theories exist to explain the origins of conjoined twins. The older theory is ''fission'', in which the fertilized egg splits partially. The second and more generally accepted theory is fusion, in which a fertilized egg completely separates, but [[stem cell]]s (which search for similar cells) find like-stem cells on the other twin and fuse the twins together. Conjoined twins share a single common [[chorion]], [[placenta]], and [[amniotic sac]], although these characteristics are not exclusive to conjoined twins as there are some monozygotic but non-conjoined twins that also share these structures in utero.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite book
  | last1 = Le | first1 = Tao
  | first2 = Vikas | last2 = Bhushan
  | first3 = Neil | last3 = Vasan
  | title = [[First Aid for the USMLE Step 1: 2010 20th Anniversary Edition]]
  | location = USA
  | publisher = [[The McGraw-Hill Companies, Inc.]]
  | year= 2010
  | pages = 121
  | isbn = 978-0-07-163340-6 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

The most famous pair of conjoined twins was [[Chang and Eng Bunker]] (Thai: อิน-จัน, In-Chan) (1811&amp;ndash;1874), [[Thailand|Thai]] brothers born in Siam, now [[Thailand]]. They traveled with [[P.T. Barnum]]'s circus for many years and were billed as the '''Siamese Twins'''. Chang and Eng were joined by a band of flesh, cartilage, and their fused livers at the torso. In modern times, they could have been easily separated.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/dna/h2g2/alabaster/A369434 BBC - h2g2 - Twins - A369434&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  Due to the brothers' fame and the rarity of the condition, the term &quot;Siamese twins&quot; came to be used as a [[synonym]] for conjoined twins.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.umm.edu/conjoined_twins/facts.htm|title=Conjoined Twins |date=January 8, 2010|publisher=University of Maryland Medical Center|accessdate=February 9, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Types of conjoined twins ==
Conjoined twins are typically classified by the point at which their bodies are joined. The most common types of conjoined twins are:
* '''Thoraco-omphalopagus''' (28% of cases):&lt;ref name=embryology&gt;[http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15278382 The embryology of conjoined twins], 2008-06-21&lt;/ref&gt; Two bodies fused from the upper chest to the lower chest. These twins usually share a heart, and may also share the [[liver]] or part of the [[digestive system]].&lt;ref name=duplicata&gt;[http://www.thefetus.net/page.php?id=1494 Duplicata incompleta, dicephalus dipus dibrachius], 2008-06-20&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Thoracopagus''' (18.5%):&lt;ref name=embryology/&gt; Two bodies fused from the upper [[thorax]] to lower belly. The [[heart]] is always involved in these cases.&lt;ref name=duplicata/&gt;
* '''Omphalopagus''' (10%):&lt;ref name=embryology/&gt;  Two bodies fused at the lower [[chest]]. Unlike thoracopagus, the heart is never involved in these cases; however, the twins often share a [[liver]], [[digestive system]], [[diaphragm (anatomy)|diaphragm]] and other organs.&lt;ref name=duplicata/&gt;
* '''[[Parasitic twins]]''' (10%):&lt;ref name=embryology/&gt; Twins that are asymmetrically conjoined, resulting in one twin that is small, less formed, and dependent on the larger twin for survival.
* '''Craniopagus''' (6%):&lt;ref name=embryology/&gt; Fused [[human skull|skull]]s, but separate bodies. These twins can be conjoined at the back of the head, the front of the head, or the side of the head, but not on the face or the base of the skull.&lt;ref name=duplicata/&gt;

Other less-common types of conjoined twins include:
* '''Cephalopagus''': Two faces on opposite sides of a single, conjoined head; the upper portion of the body is fused while the bottom portions are separate. These twins generally cannot survive due to severe malformations of the brain. Also known as janiceps (after the two-faced god [[Janus (mythology)|Janus]]) or syncephalus.&lt;ref name=duplicata/&gt;
* '''Synecephalus''': One head with a single face but four ears, and two bodies.&lt;ref name=duplicata/&gt;
* '''Cephalothoracopagus''': Bodies fused in the head and thorax. In this type of twins, there are two faces facing in opposite directions, or sometimes a single face and an enlarged skull.&lt;ref name=duplicata/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.collphyphil.org/virt_tour/museum_8.htm Collphyphil.org]&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Xiphopagus''': Two bodies fused in the [[Xyphoid process|xiphoid cartilage]], which is approximately from the navel to the lower breastbone. These twins almost never share any vital organs, with the exception of the liver.&lt;ref name=duplicata/&gt; A famous example is Chang and Eng Bunker.
* '''[[Ischiopagi|Ischiopagus]]''': Fused lower half of the two bodies, with [[Vertebral column|spines]] conjoined end-to-end at a 180° angle. These twins have four arms; two, three or four legs; and typically one external set of [[genitalia]] and [[anus]].&lt;ref name=duplicata/&gt;
* '''Omphalo-Ischiopagus''': Fused in a similar fashion as ischiopagus twins, but facing each other with a joined abdomen akin to omphalopagus. These twins have four arms, and two, three, or four legs.&lt;ref name=duplicata/&gt;
* '''Parapagus''': Fused side-by-side with a shared [[human pelvis|pelvis]]. Twins that are '''dithoracic parapagus''' are fused at the abdomen and pelvis, but not the thorax. Twins that are '''[[diprosopic parapagus]]''' have one trunk and '''dicephalic'''. Twins that are '''dicephalic parapagus''' are '''[[dicephalic]]''', and have two (dibrachius), three (tribrachius), or four (tetrabrachius) arms.&lt;ref name=duplicata/&gt;
* '''[[Craniopagus parasiticus]]''': Like craniopagus, but with a second bodiless head attached to the dominant head.
* '''[[Pygopagus]] (Iliopagus)''': Two bodies joined at the [[human pelvis|pelvis]].&lt;ref name=duplicata/&gt;
* '''Rachipagus''': twins joined along the dorsal aspect (back) of their bodies, with fusion of the vertebral arches and the soft tissue from the head to the buttocks &lt;ref&gt;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8711621&lt;/ref&gt;

==Separation==
Surgery to separate conjoined twins may range from relatively simple to extremely complex, depending on the point of attachment and the internal parts that are shared. Most cases of separation are extremely risky and life-threatening. In many cases, the surgery results in the death of one or both of the twins, particularly if they are joined at the head. This makes the [[ethics]] of surgical separation, where the twins can survive if not separated, contentious. Dreger found the quality of life of twins who remain conjoined to be higher than is commonly supposed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0674018257  ''One of Us: Conjoined Twins and the Future of Normal''] by Alice Dreger, [[Harvard University Press|Harvard]], 2004&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Lori and George Schappell]] are a good  example.

Recent successful separations of conjoined twins include that of the separation of [[Ganga &amp; Jamuna Shreshta]] in 2001, who were born in [[Kathmandu, Nepal]] in 2000. The 97-hour surgery on the pair of [[craniopagus twins]] was a landmark one which took place in [[Singapore]]; the team was led by neurosurgeons, [[Dr. Chumpon Chan]] and Dr. Keith Goh.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.channelnewsasia.com/cna/analysis_prog/incon/incon_doc2.htm | work=Channel News Asia Singapore | title=
In Conversation with Medicine's Miracle Workers -- Dr Chumpon Chan and Dr Keith Goh | date=April 19, 2001 | accessdate=March 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ganga Shrestha died at the Model Hospital in Katmandu in July 2009, at the age of 8, three days after being admitted for treatment of a severe chest infection.

Notable also is the success of Dr. Ben Carson. In 1987, Carson made medical history by being the first surgeon in the world to successfully separate siamese twins (the Binder twins) conjoined at the back of the head (craniopagus twins). Operations to separate twins joined in this way had always failed, resulting in the death of one or both of the infants. Carson agreed to undertake the operation. The 50-member surgical team, led by Carson, worked for 22 hours. At the end, the twins were successfully separated and can now survive independently. 

Carson recalls: 
{{quote|I looked at that situation. I said, ‘Why is it that this is such a disaster?’ and it was because they would always exsanguinate. They would bleed to death, and I said, ‘There's got to be a way around that. These are modern times.’ This was back in 1987. I was talking to a friend of mine, who was a cardiothoracic surgeon, who was the chief of the division, and I said, ‘You guys operate on the heart in babies, how do you keep them from exsanguinating’ and he says, ‘Well, we put them in hypothermic arrest.’ I said, ‘Is there any reason that— if we were doing a set of Siamese twins that were joined at the head—that we couldn't put them into hypothermic arrest, at the appropriate time, when we're likely to lose a lot of blood?’ and he said, ‘No way .’ I said, ‘Wow, this is great.’ Then I said, ‘Why am I putting my time into this? I'm not going to see any Siamese twins.’ So I kind of forgot about it, and lo and behold, two months later, along came these doctors from Germany, presenting this case of Siamese twins. And, I was asked for my opinion, and I then began to explain the techniques that should be used, and how we would incorporate hypothermic arrest, and everybody said ‘Wow! That sounds like it might work.’ And, my colleagues and I, a few of us went over to Germany. We looked at the twins. We actually put in scalp expanders, and five months later we brought them over and did the operation, and lo and behold, it worked.&lt;ref&gt;[http://achievement.org/autodoc/page/car1int-1 Biography and Video Interview of Benjamin Carson at Academy of Achievement.]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In 2003 two women from Iran, [[Ladan and Laleh Bijani]], who were joined at the head but had separate brains (craniopagus) were surgically separated in Singapore, despite surgeons' warnings that the operation could be fatal to one or both. Both women died during surgery on July 8, 2003.

A case of particular interest was that of infants Rose and Gracie (&quot;Mary&quot; and &quot;Jodie&quot;) Attard, conjoined twins from Malta who were separated by court order in Great Britain over the religious objections of their parents, Michaelangelo and Rina Attard.  The surgery took place in November, 2000, at [[St Mary's Hospital, Manchester|St Mary's Hospital]] in [[Manchester]].  The operation was controversial because Rose, the weaker twin, would die as a result of the procedure as her heart and lungs were dependent upon Gracie's.  (The twins were attached at the lower abdomen and spine.)  However, if the operation had not taken place, it was certain that both twins would die.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/1292681.stm | work=BBC News | title=Siamese twin Jodie 'to go home soon' | date=April 23, 2001 | accessdate=March 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Appel, Jacob M.  Ethics: English high court orders separation of conjoined twins.  Journal of Law Medicine &amp; Ethics. 2000 Fall;28(3):312-3.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Conjoined twins in history ==
[[Image:Nuremberg chronicles - Female Siamese Twins (CLXXXIIv).jpg|thumb|upright|left|Conjoined twin sisters from  ''[[Nuremberg Chronicle]]'' (1493).]]
[[Image:Conjoinedtwinslarcomuseum.jpg|thumb|Moche ceramics depicting conjoined twins. 300 CE [[Larco Museum|Larco Museum Collection]] Lima, Peru.]]
The [[Moche]] culture of ancient [[Peru]] depicted conjoined twins in their ceramics dating back to 300 CE.&lt;ref&gt;Berrin, Katherine &amp; Larco Museum. ''The Spirit of Ancient Peru:Treasures from the [[Larco Museum|Museo Arqueológico Rafael Larco Herrera]].'' New York: [[Thames and Hudson]], 1997.&lt;/ref&gt; Writing around 415CE, [[Augustine of Hippo|St. Augustine of Hippo]] in his book ''[[City of God (book)|City of God]]'' refers to a man &quot;double in his upper, but single in his lower half--having two heads, two chests, four hands, but one body and two feet like an ordinary man.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;City of God, Book XVI, chap. 8: http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/120116.htm&lt;/ref&gt; The earliest known documented case of conjoined twins dates from the year 942, when a pair of conjoined twin brothers from [[Armenia]] were brought to [[Constantinople]] for medical evaluation.

In Arabia, the twin brothers [[Hashim ibn Abd Manaf]] and [['Abd Shams]] were born with Hashim's leg attached to his twin brother's head. Legend says that their father, [[Abd Manaf ibn Qusai]], separated his conjoined sons with a sword and that some priests believed that the blood that had flowed between them signified wars between their progeny (confrontations did occur between Banu al'Abbas and Banu Ummaya ibn 'Abd Shams in the year 750 AH).&lt;ref name=&quot;pg69&quot;&gt;The Life of the Prophet Muhammad: Al-Sira Al-Nabawiyya By Ibn Kathir, Trevor Le Gassick, Muneer Fareed, pg. 132&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Muslim]] [[polymath]] [[Abū al-Rayhān al-Bīrūnī]] described Siamese twins in his book ''Kitab-al-Saidana''.&lt;ref name=Zahoor&gt;Dr. A. Zahoor (1997), [http://www.unhas.ac.id/rhiza/arsip/saintis/biruni.html Abu Raihan Muhammad al-Biruni], [[Hasanuddin University]].&lt;/ref&gt;

The English twin sisters [[Mary and Eliza Chulkhurst]], who were conjoined at the back (pygopagus), lived from 1100 to 1134 (or 1500 to 1534) and were perhaps the best-known early historical example of conjoined twins. Other early conjoined twins to attain notice were the &quot;Scottish brothers&quot;, allegedly of the [[dicephalus]] type, essentially two heads sharing the same body (1460&amp;ndash;1488, although the dates vary); the pygopagus Helen and Judith of Szőny, Hungary (1701&amp;ndash;1723), who enjoyed a brief career in music before being sent to live in a [[convent]]; and Rita and Cristina of Parodi of [[Sardinia]], born in 1829. Rita and Cristina were dicephalus tetrabrachius (one body with four arms) twins and although they died at only eight months of age, they gained much attention as a curiosity when their parents exhibited them in Paris.

[[Image:Bunker Grave.jpg|right|thumb|Grave of Eng and Chang Bunker near [[Mt. Airy, North Carolina]]]]Several sets of conjoined twins lived during the nineteenth century and made careers for themselves in the [[performing arts]], though none achieved quite the same level of fame and fortune as Chang and Eng. Most notably, [[Millie and Christine McCoy]] (or McKoy), pygopagus twins, were born into slavery in North Carolina in 1851. They were sold to a [[showman]], J.P. Smith, at birth, but were soon [[kidnap]]ped by a rival showman. The kidnapper fled to England but was thwarted because England had already banned slavery. Smith traveled to England to collect the girls and brought with him their mother, Monimia, from whom they had been separated. He and his wife provided the twins with an education and taught them to speak five languages, play music, and sing. For the rest of the century the twins enjoyed a successful career as &quot;The Two-Headed Nightingale&quot; and appeared with the Barnum Circus. In 1912 they died of [[tuberculosis]], 17 hours apart.

Giovanni and Giacomo Tocci, from [[Locana]], Italy, were immortalized in [[Mark Twain]]'s short story &quot;Those Extraordinary Twins&quot; as fictitious twins Angelo and Luigi. The Toccis, born in 1877, were dicephalus tetrabrachius twins, having one body with two legs, two heads, and four arms. From birth they were forced by their parents to perform and never learned to walk, as each twin controlled one leg (in modern times [[physical therapy]] allows twins like the Toccis to learn to walk on their own). They are said to have disliked show business. In 1886, after touring the United States, the twins returned to Europe with their family, where they fell very ill. They are believed to have died around this time, though some sources claim they survived until 1940, living in seclusion in Italy.

==List of notable conjoined twins==
{{prose|date=December 2011}}
{{example farm|date=December 2011}}
Names listed in '''[[boldface]]''' are of twins who have been separated.

===Born 19th century and earlier===
*[[Mary and Eliza Chulkhurst]] (born 1100, also known as the Biddenden Maids) from England. They are the earliest set of conjoined twins whose names are known.
*[[Lazarus and Joannes Baptista Colloredo]] (1617-164-?)
*[[Helen and Judith of Szony]] ([[Hungary]], 1701–1723)
*[[Chang and Eng Bunker]] (1811–1874), from [[Thailand]] (formerly [[Rattanakosin Kingdom|Siam]]), joined by the areas around their [[xiphoid process|xiphoid cartilage]]s, but over time the join stretched; the expression ''Siamese twins'' is derived from their case
*[[Millie and Christine McCoy]] (July 11, 1851 - October 8, 1912) were American conjoined twins who went by the stage names &quot;The Two-Headed Nightingale&quot; and &quot;The Eighth Wonder of the World&quot;.
*[[Giacomo and Giovanni Battista Tocci]] (1875?-1912?)

=== Born 20th century===
*[[Daisy and Violet Hilton]] of [[Brighton, East Sussex|Brighton]], England (1908&amp;ndash;1969), actresses, appeared in the movies ''[[Freaks]]'' and ''[[Chained for Life]]''.
*'''[[Lucio and Simplicio Godina]]''' of Samar, [[Philippines]] (1908&amp;ndash;1936)
*[[Masha and Dasha Krivoshlyapova]] of [[Moscow]], [[Russia]] (1950&amp;ndash;2003), rarest form of conjoined twins, only known case of dicephalus tetrabrachius tripus (two heads, four arms, three legs).
*[[Ronnie and Donnie Galyon]] of [[Ohio]] (1951&amp;ndash;), currently the world's oldest living conjoined twins, Omphalopagus.
*[[Lori and George Schappell]] born September 18, 1961 in [[Reading, Pennsylvania]], American entertainers, craniopagus.
*'''[[Ladan and Laleh Bijani]]''' of [[Shiraz]], [[Iran]] (1974&amp;ndash;2003); died during separation surgery in [[Singapore]].
*'''[[Viet and Duc Nguyen]]''', born on February 25, 1981 in [[Kon Tum Province]], [[Vietnam]], and separated in 1988 in [[Ho Chi Minh City]]. Viet died on October 6, 2007.
*[[Abigail and Brittany Hensel]] are dicephalic parapagus twins born March 7, 1990 in [[Carver County]], [[Minnesota]].

=== Born 21st century===
*[[Carmen and Lupita Andrade-Solis]], born in [[Mexico]] in 2000 with Dicephalus Tetrabrachius Dipus (2 heads, 4 arms and 2 legs). Separation was not possible.
*'''[[Carl and Clarence Aguirre]]''', born vertical craniopagus in Manila on 21 April 2002, successfully separated in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;DA Staffenberg and JT Goodrich. Separation of craniopagus conjoined twins: an evolution in thought. Clin Plast Surg. 2005 Jan;32(1):25-34.&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Kendra and Maliyah Herrin]]''', ischiopagus twins separated in 2006 at age 4.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.herrintwins.com Herrintwins.com]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Anastasia and Tatiana Dogaru]], born outside [[Rome]], [[Italy]] on January 13, 2004. As [[Craniopagus twins]], the top of Tatiana's head is attached to the back of Anastasias's head.
*'''[[Lakshmi Tatma]]''' (born 2005) was an ischiopagus conjoined twin born in [[Araria]] district in the state of [[Bihar]], [[India]]. She had four arms and four legs, resulting from a joining at the pelvis with a headless undeveloped parasitic twin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/south_asia/7080326.stm|date=2007-11-06|title=Many-limbed India girl in surgery|publisher=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[Vani and Veena](Warangal,Andhra Pradesh) craniopagus twins, attached at the back of the skull.  
*[[Krista and Tatiana Hogan]], [[Canada|Canadian]] twins conjoined at the head. Born October 25, 2006. Share part of their brain and can pass sensory information and thoughts between each other.
*{{anchor|Trishna and Krishna}}'''[[Moira Kelly, AO#Trishna and Krishna|Trishna and Krishna]]''' from [[Bangladesh]] were born in December, 2006, Craniopagus twins, joined on the tops of their skulls, and sharing a small amount of brain tissue. In 2009, they were separated in [[Melbourne]], [[Australia]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/body/separating-twins.html Separating Twins&lt;/ref&gt;

== Films of conjoined twins ==

* ''[[Twin Falls Idaho (film)]]'' starring ''[[Mark Polish]]'' and ''[[Michael Polish]]''
* ''[[Stuck on You (film)]]'' starring ''[[Matt Damon]]'' and ''[[Greg Kinnear]]''
* ''[[Brothers of the Head]]'' starring ''[[Harry Treadaway]]'' and ''[[Luke Treadaway]]''
* ''[[Maattrraan]]'' starring ''[[Suriya]]'' and ''[[Kajal Agarwal]]''
* ''[[Charulatha]]''  starring ''[[Priyamani]]''

==See also==
*[[Medical law]]
*[[Monoamniotic twins]]
*[[Polycephaly]]
*[[Biddenden Maids]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Conjoined twins}}
* [http://zygote.swarthmore.edu/cleave4.html Types and social history of conjoined twins]
* [http://www.life.com/gallery/60321/conjoined-twins#index/0 Conjoined Twins] - slideshow by ''[[Life magazine]]''
* [http://www.conjoinedtwins.med.sa The site of the medical Saudi team responsible for numerous successful separation surgeries]
* [http://www.lib.unc.edu/ncc/gallery/twins.html Eng and Chang - The Original Siamese Twins; The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, The North Carolina Collection Gallery]
* [http://www.thehumanmarvels.com/ The Human Marvels: A Historical Reference Site run by J. Tithonus Pednaud, Teratological Historian]
* [http://www.phreeque.com/ Cases of conjoined and incomplete twins]
* [http://profiles.nlm.nih.gov/QQ/B/B/Y/Q/_/qqbbyq.pdf Clara and Alta Rodriguez], joined at the pelvis and successfully separated in 1974 at Children's Hospital of Philadelphia by surgeons including [[C. Everett Koop]]
* [http://www.nlm.nih.gov/hmd/conjoined National Library of Medicine: Selected Moments in the History of Conjoined Twins]
* [http://www.emedicine.com/ped/topic2936.htm Emedicine article]
* [http://www3.telus.net/tyee/multiples/conjoined.html Facts About Multiples: Conjoined Records and stats]

{{Situs inversus and conjoined twins}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Conjoined Twins}}
[[Category:Conjoined twins| ]]
[[Category:Twins]]
[[Category:Rare diseases]]

[[ar:التوائم الملتصقة]]
[[be:Сіямскія блізняты]]
[[bg:Сиамски близнаци]]
[[cs:Siamská dvojčata]]
[[da:Siamesiske tvillinger]]
[[de:Siamesische Zwillinge]]
[[es:Siameses]]
[[eo:Siamaj dunaskitoj]]
[[fr:Jumeaux siamois]]
[[fy:Siameeske twilling]]
[[ko:결합 쌍둥이]]
[[id:Kembar siam]]
[[it:Gemelli siamesi]]
[[he:תאומים סיאמיים]]
[[kn:ಸಯಾಮಿ ಅವಳಿಗಳು]]
[[lt:Siamo dvyniai]]
[[hu:Sziámi ikrek]]
[[ms:Kembar siam]]
[[nl:Siamese tweeling]]
[[ja:結合双生児]]
[[no:Siamesiske tvillinger]]
[[pl:Bliźnięta nierozdzielone]]
[[pt:Gêmeos xifópagos]]
[[ru:Сиамские близнецы]]
[[simple:Conjoined twins]]
[[sl:Zraščena dvojčka]]
[[fi:Siamilaiset kaksoset]]
[[sv:Siamesiska tvillingar]]
[[ta:ஒட்டிப் பிறந்த இரட்டையர்]]
[[th:แฝดติดกัน]]
[[uk:Сіамські близнюки]]
[[vi:Sinh đôi dính liền]]
[[zh:連體雙胞胎]]</text>
      <sha1>1fhu0hi8kjsq0w19x6nfsfz36vxnrlp</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
