<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Eugenics</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9737</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520804210</id>
      <parentid>519859652</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-31T21:18:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>86.167.109.145</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* History */ removed &lt;/ref&gt; left by someone in the text.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="42298">{{pp-move-indef}}
[[Image:Eugenics congress logo.png|right|thumb|275px|&quot;Eugenics is the self-direction of human evolution&quot;: Logo from the [[Second International Eugenics Conference]], 1921, depicting Eugenics as a tree which unites a variety of different fields.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | last = Currell
  | first = Susan
  | coauthors = Christina Cogdell
  | title = Popular Eugenics: National Efficiency and American Mass Culture in The 1930s
  | publisher = [[Ohio University Press]]
  | year = 2006
  | location = Athens, OH
  | page = 203
  | url =
  | doi =
  | isbn = 0-8214-1691-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

'''Eugenics''' is the [[applied science]] of the bio-[[social movement]] which advocates the use of practices aimed at improving the [[Population genetics|genetic composition of a population]], usually a human population.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ghr.nlm.nih.gov/glossary=eugenics &quot;Eugenics&quot;], Unified Medical Language System (Psychological Index Terms) National Library of Medicine, 26 Sep. 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Galton1904&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Galton, Francis |authorlink=Francis Galton |year=1904 |month=July |title=Eugenics: Its Definition, Scope, and Aims |journal=The American Journal of Sociology |volume=X |issue=1 |at=1st paragraph |accessdate=2010-12-27 |url=http://www.mugu.com/galton/essays/1900-1911/galton-1904-am-journ-soc-eugenics-scope-aims.htm |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20071103082723/galton.org/essays/1900-1911/galton-1904-am-journ-soc-eugenics-scope-aims.htm |archivedate=2007-11-17 |quote=Eugenics is the science which deals with all influences that improve the inborn qualities of a race; also with those that develop them to the utmost advantage. |bibcode=1904Natur..70...82 |pages=82 |doi=10.1038/070082a0 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It is a social [[philosophy]] for the improvement of [[human]] [[hereditary]] traits through the promotion of higher reproduction of certain people and traits, and the reduction of reproduction of other people and traits.&lt;ref name=&quot;Osborn1937&quot;&gt;The exact definition of ''eugenics'' has been a matter of debate since the term was coined. In the definition of it as a &quot;social philosophy&quot; — that is, a philosophy with implications for social order — is not meant to be definitive, and is taken from {{cite journal |last=Osborn |first=Frederick |authorlink=Frederick Osborn |title=Development of a Eugenic Philosophy |journal=[[American Sociological Review]] |volume=2 |issue=3 |pages=389–397 |date=June 1937 |doi=10.2307/2084871 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{Main|History of eugenics}}
Throughout history (from shortly after its creation) and until even today, eugenics remains a controversial concept.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Blom|2008|p=336}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a social movement, eugenics reached its greatest popularity in the early decades of the 20th century. At this point in time, eugenics was practiced around the world and was promoted by governments, and influential individuals and institutions. Many countries enacted various eugenics policies and programs, including:
genetic screening, [[birth control]], promoting differential birth rates, marriage restrictions, segregation (both [[racial segregation]] and segregation of the mentally ill from the rest of the population), [[compulsory sterilization]], forced abortions or forced pregnancies and [[genocide]]. Most of these policies were later regarded as coercive and/or restrictive, and now few jurisdictions implement policies that are explicitly labeled as eugenic or unequivocally eugenic in substance.

The way in how eugenics was practiced in this period involved &quot;interventions&quot;, which is a euphemistic name for the identification and classification of individuals and their families, including the poor, mentally ill, blind, deaf, developmentally disabled, [[promiscuous]] women, [[homosexuals]] and entire [[Race (classification of human beings)|racial groups]] — such as the [[Romani people|Roma]] and [[Jews]] — as &quot;degenerate&quot; or &quot;unfit&quot;; the segregation or institutionalisation of such individuals and groups, their sterilization, euthanasia, and in the extreme case of Nazi Germany, their mass extermination.&lt;ref&gt;See for example, {{harvnb|Black|2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Eugenics became an academic discipline at many colleges and universities, and received funding from many sources.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Allen, Garland E. |title=Was Nazi eugenics created in the US? |journal=EMBO Rep. |volume=5 |issue=5 |pages=451–2 |year=2004 |doi=10.1038/sj.embor.7400158 |url=http://www.nature.com/embor/journal/v5/n5/full/7400158.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Three [[International Eugenics Conference]]s presented a global venue for eugenicists with meetings in 1912 in London, and in 1921 and 1932 in New York. Eugenic policies were first implemented in the early 1900s in the [[United States]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Barrett, Deborah; Kurzman, Charles |title=Globalizing Social Movement Theory: The Case of Eugenics |journal=Theory and Society |volume=33 |issue=5 |pages=505 |date=October 2004 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Later, in the 1920s and 30s, the eugenic policy of [[compulsory sterilization|sterilizing]] certain mental patients was implemented in a variety of other countries, including [[Belgium]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=The National OFfice of Eugenics in Belgium |journal=Science  |volume=57 |issue=1463 |page=46 |date=12 January 1923 |doi=10.1126/science.57.1463.46 |url=http://www.sciencemag.org/content/57/1463/46.2.full.pdf |format=PDF|bibcode = 1923Sci....57R..46. }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Brazil]],&lt;ref&gt;Sales Augusto dos Santos and Laurence Hallewell. Jan., 2002. ''Historical Roots of the &quot;Whitening&quot; of Brazil.'' Latin American Perspectives, Vol. 29, No. 1, Brazil: The Hegemonic Process in Political and Cultural Formation, pp. 81&lt;/ref&gt; [[Canada]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=McLaren |first=Angus |title=Our Own Master Race: Eugenics in Canada, 1885–1945 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Toronto |year=1990 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Sweden]],&lt;ref name=&quot;wsws&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Social Democrats implemented measures to forcibly sterilise 62,000 people|publisher=World Socialist Web Site|url=http://www.wsws.org/articles/1999/mar1999/euge-19m.shtml|ref=harv|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; among others. The scientific reputation of eugenics started to decline in the 1930s, a time when [[Ernst Rüdin]] used eugenics as a justification for the [[Racial policy of Nazi Germany|racial policies]] of [[Nazi Germany]], and when proponents of eugenics among scientists and thinkers prompted a backlash in the public. Nevertheless, in Sweden the eugenics program continued until 1975.&lt;ref name=&quot;wsws&quot;/&gt;

In addition to being practiced in a number of countries it was internationally organized through the International Federation of Eugenic Organizations. {{harv|Black|2003|p=240}} Its scientific aspects were carried on through research bodies such as the [[Kaiser Wilhelm Institute of Anthropology, Human Heredity, and Eugenics]] {{harv|Black|2003|p=286}}, the Cold Spring Harbour Carnegie Institution for Experimental Evolution {{harv|Black|2003|p=40}} and the [[Eugenics Record Office]] {{harv|Black|2003|p=45}}. Its political aspects involved successful advocacy for changes of law to pursue eugenic objectives, for instance sterilization laws (e.g. U.S. sterilization laws, (Black, see Chapter 6 The United States of Sterilization)). Its moral aspects included rejection of the doctrine that all human beings are born equal and redefining morality purely in terms of genetic fitness {{harv|Black|2003|p=237}}. Its racist elements included pursuit of a pure &quot;[[Nordic race]]&quot; or &quot;[[Aryan]]&quot; genetic pool and the eventual elimination of less fit races (see Black, Chapter 5 Legitimizing Raceology and Chapter 9 Mongrelization).

By the end of [[World War II]] eugenics had been largely abandoned, having become associated with [[Nazi-Germany]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Black|2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lynn2001&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Lynn|first=Richard|authorlink=Richard Lynn|title=Eugenics: a reassessment|year=2001|publisher=Praeger|location=New York|isbn=0-275-95822-1|page=18|quote=By the middle decades of the twentieth century, eugenics had become widely accepted throughout the whole of the economically developed world, with the exception of the Soviet Union.}}&lt;/ref&gt;This country's approach to genetics and eugenics was focused on [[Eugen Fischer]]'s concept of ''[[phenogenetics]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Schmuhl, Hans-Walter |title=The Kaiser Wilhelm Institute for Anthropology, Human Heredity and Eugenics, 1927–1945 |journal=Boston Studies in the Philosophy of Science |volume=259 |page=245 |year=2003 |publisher=Wallstein Verlag |location=Göttengen}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Nazi twin study]] methods of Fischer and [[Otmar Freiherr von Verschuer]]. Both the public and some elements of the scientific community have associated eugenics with [[Nazi Party|Nazi]] abuses, such as enforced &quot;[[racial hygiene]]&quot;, [[Nazi human experimentation|human experimentation]], and the [[Genocide|extermination]] of &quot;undesired&quot; population groups.{{Citation needed|date=October 2012}},  However, developments in [[Genetic engineering|genetic]], [[Genetic testing|genomic]], and [[Human cloning|reproductive technologies]] at the end of the 20th century are raising new questions regarding the ethical status of eugenics, effectively creating a [[Eugenics#Modern_eugenics.2C_genetic_engineering.2C_and_ethical_re-evaluation|resurgence of interest]] in the subject.

Today it is still widely regarded as a brutal movement which inflicted massive [[human rights]] violations on millions of people.&lt;ref&gt;See for example {{cite journal |author=Weigmann K |title=In the name of science. The role of biologists in Nazi atrocities: lessons for today's scientists |journal=EMBO Rep. |volume=2 |issue=10 |pages=871–5 |year=2001 |month=October |pmid=11600445 |pmc=1084095 |doi=10.1093/embo-reports/kve217 |publisher=European Molecular Biology Organization}} It concludes, &quot;It was scientists who interpreted racial differences as the justification to murder ... It is the responsibility of today's scientists to prevent this from happening again.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;The practices engaged in by eugenicists involving violations of privacy, attacks on reputation, violations of the right to life, to found a family, to freedom from discrimination are all today classified as violations of [[human rights]]. 

The practice of negative racial aspects of eugenics, after World War II, fell within the definition of the new international crime of [[genocide]], set out in the [[Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide]].&lt;ref&gt;Article 2 of the Convention defines genocide as any of the following acts committed with [[Genocidal intent to destroy|intent to destroy]], [[Genocide#In part|in whole or in part]], a national, ethnic, racial or religious group, as such:
:(a) Killing members of the group;
:(b) Causing serious bodily or mental harm to members of the group;
:(c) Deliberately inflicting on the group conditions of life calculated to bring about its physical destruction in whole or in part;
:(d) Imposing measures intended to prevent births within the group;
:(e) Forcibly transferring children of the group to another group.
See [[Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide]].&lt;/ref&gt;

However, developments in genetic, genomic, and reproductive technologies at the end of the 20th century have raised new questions and concerns about what exactly constitutes the meaning of ''eugenics'' and what its ethical and moral status is in the modern era.

==Meanings and types==
The modern field and term were first formulated by Sir [[Francis Galton]] in 1883,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book

  | last = Galton
  | first = Francis
  | authorlink = Francis Galton
  | coauthors =
  | title = Inquiries into Human Faculty and its Development
  | publisher = Macmillan
  | year = 1883
  | location = London
  | page = 199
  | url =
  | doi =
  | isbn = }}&lt;/ref&gt; drawing on the recent work of his half-cousin [[Charles Darwin]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://galton.org/letters/darwin/correspondence.htm |title=Correspondence between Francis Galton and Charles Darwin |publisher=Galton.org |accessdate=2011-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/correspondence-volume-17 |title=Darwin Correspondence Project » The correspondence of Charles Darwin, volume 17: 1869 |publisher=Darwinproject.ac.uk |accessdate=2011-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;He wrote down many of his observations and conclusions in a book, ''[[Inquiries into Human Faculty and Its Development]]''.

The origins of the concept began with certain interpretations of [[Mendelian inheritance]], and the theories of [[August Weismann]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Blom|first=Philipp|authorlink=Philipp Blom|title=The Vertigo Years: Change and Culture in the West, 1900-1914|year=2008|publisher=McClelland &amp; Stewart |location=Toronto|isbn=978-0-7710-1630-1|pages=335–6 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The word ''eugenics'' [[Etymology|derives]] from the [[Greek language|Greek]] word ''eu'' (''good'' or ''well'') and the suffix ''-genēs'' (''born''), and was coined by [[Sir Francis Galton]] in 1883 to replace the word [[stirpiculture]] (also see: [[Oneida stirpiculture]]) which he had used previously but which had come to be mocked by people of culture due to its perceived sexual overtones.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Lester Frank Ward|author2=Emily Palmer Cape|author3=Sarah Emma Simons|title=Glimpses of the cosmos|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=KDEZAQAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA382|accessdate=11 April 2012|year=1918|publisher=G. P. Putnam's sons|pages=382– |chapter=Eugenics, Euthenics and Eudemics}}&lt;/ref&gt; Galton defined eugenics as &quot;the study of all agencies under human control which can improve or impair the racial quality of future generations&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;cited in {{harvnb|Black|2003|p=18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eugenics has, from the very beginning, meant many different things to many different people. Historically, the term has referred to everything from prenatal care for mothers to forced sterilization and [[euthanasia]]. To [[Population genetics|population geneticists]] the term has included the avoidance of [[inbreeding]] without necessarily altering [[allele]] frequencies; for example, [[J. B. S. Haldane]] wrote that &quot;the motor bus, by breaking up inbred village communities, was a powerful eugenic agent&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Haldane, J. |title=Lysenko and Genetics |journal=Science and Society |volume=4 |issue=4 |year=1940 |url=http://www.marxists.org/archive/haldane/works/1940s/lysenko.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; Much debate has taken place in the past, as it does today, as to what exactly counts as eugenics.&lt;ref&gt;A discussion of the shifting meanings of the term can be found in {{cite book |author=Paul, Diane |title=Controlling human heredity: 1865 to the present |publisher=Humanities Press |location=New Jersey |year=1995 |isbn=1-57392-343-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Some types of eugenics deal only with perceived beneficial and/or detrimental genetic traits.  These are sometimes called &quot;pseudo-eugenics&quot; by proponents of strict eugenics.

The term ''eugenics'' is often used to refer to movements and social policies influential during the early 20th century. In a historical and broader sense, eugenics can also be a study of &quot;improving human genetic qualities&quot;. It is sometimes broadly applied to describe any human action whose goal is to improve the [[gene pool]]. Some forms of [[infanticide]] in ancient societies, present-day [[reprogenetics]], preemptive abortions and [[designer babies]] have been (sometimes controversially) referred to as eugenic. Because of its [[Norm (philosophy)|normative]] goals and historical association with [[scientific racism]], as well as the development of the science of [[genetics]], the western scientific community has mostly disassociated itself from the term &quot;eugenics&quot;, although one can find advocates of what is now known as ''[[liberal eugenics]]''.  Despite its ongoing criticism in the United States, several regions globally practice different forms of eugenics.

Eugenicists advocate specific policies that (if successful) they believe will lead to a perceived improvement of the human gene pool. Since defining what improvements are desired or beneficial is perceived by many as a [[cultural]] choice rather than a matter that can be determined objectively (e.g., by empirical, scientific inquiry), eugenics has often been deemed a [[pseudoscience]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| publisher = Thunder's Mouth Press| isbn = 1-56858-321-4, 9781568583211| page = 370| last = Black| first = Edwin| title = War Against the Weak| year = 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; The most disputed aspect of eugenics has been the definition of &quot;improvement&quot; of the human gene pool, such as what is a beneficial characteristic and what is a defect. This aspect of eugenics has historically been tainted with [[scientific racism]].

Early eugenicists were mostly concerned with perceived [[intelligence (trait)|intelligence]] factors that often correlated strongly with [[social class]]. Many eugenicists took inspiration from the [[selective breeding]] of animals (where [[purebred]]s are often strived for) as their analogy for improving human society. The mixing of races (or [[miscegenation]]) was usually considered as something to be avoided in the name of [[racial purity]]. At the time this concept appeared to have some scientific support, and it remained a contentious issue until the advanced development of [[genetics]] led to a scientific consensus that the division of the human species into unequal races is unjustifiable.

Eugenics has also been concerned with the elimination of [[hereditary diseases]] such as [[Haemophilia|hemophilia]] and [[Huntington's disease]]. However, there are several problems with labeling certain factors as genetic defects. In many cases there is no scientific consensus on what a genetic defect is. It is often argued that this is more a matter of social or individual choice. What appears to be a genetic defect in one context or environment may not be so in another. This can be the case for genes with a [[heterozygote advantage]], such as [[sickle-cell disease]] or [[Tay-Sachs disease]], which in their [[Zygosity|heterozygote]] form may offer an advantage against, respectively, [[malaria]] and [[tuberculosis]]. Although some birth defects are uniformly lethal, disabled persons can succeed in life. Many of the conditions early eugenicists identified as inheritable ([[pellagra]] is one such example) are currently considered to be at least partially, if not wholly, attributed to environmental conditions. Similar concerns have been raised when a [[prenatal diagnosis]] of a [[congenital disorder]] leads to [[abortion]] (see also [[preimplantation genetic diagnosis]]).

Eugenic policies have been conceptually divided into two categories. Positive eugenics is aimed at encouraging reproduction among the genetically advantaged. Possible approaches include financial and political stimuli, targeted demographic analyses, ''in vitro'' fertilization, egg transplants, and cloning.&lt;ref name = &quot;mywdhq&quot;&gt;Glad, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Negative eugenics is aimed at lowering fertility among the genetically disadvantaged. This includes abortions, sterilization, and other methods of family planning.&lt;ref name = &quot;mywdhq&quot;/&gt; Both positive and negative eugenics can be coercive. Abortion by [[Fitness (biology)|fit]] women was illegal in [[Nazi Germany]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Lisa Pine|title=Nazi Family Policy, 1933–1945|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=nW2aE5-rAMsC&amp;pg=PA19|accessdate=11 April 2012|year=1997|publisher=Berg|isbn=978-1-85973-907-5|pages=19–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Implementation methods===
There are three main ways by which the methods of eugenics can be applied.{{Citation needed|date=May 2008}} One is mandatory eugenics or authoritarian eugenics, in which the government mandates a eugenics program. Policies and/or legislation are often seen as being coercive and restrictive.  Another is promotional voluntary eugenics, in which eugenics is voluntarily practiced and promoted to the general population, but not officially mandated. This is a form of non-state enforced eugenics, using a liberal or democratic approach, which can mostly be seen in the 1900s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Rose | first = Nikolas | authorlink = Nikolas Rose | title = The Politics of Life Itself: Biomedicine, Power, and Subjectivity in the Twenty-First Century | publisher = [[Princeton University Press]] | year = 2007 | location = Princeton, New Jersey | page = 372 | isbn = 0-691-12191-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The third is private eugenics, which is practiced voluntarily by individuals and groups, but not promoted to the general population.

==Dysgenics==
{{Main|Dysgenics|Fertility and intelligence}}

Research has suggested that in the modern world, the relationship between [[fertility and intelligence]] is such that those with higher intelligence have fewer children, one possible reason being more [[unintended pregnancies]] for those with lower intelligence. Several researchers have argued that the average [[genotypic]] intelligence of the United States and the world are declining which is a [[dysgenic]] effect. This has been masked by the [[Flynn effect]] for [[phenotypic]] intelligence. The Flynn effect may have ended in some developed nations, causing some to argue that phenotypic intelligence will or has started to decline.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1017/S0021932009003344}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;{{cite doi|10.1016/j.intell.2007.03.004}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Van Court, Marian (1983). &quot;Unwanted Births And Dysgenic Reproduction In The United States&quot;. Eugenics Bulletin.&lt;/ref&gt;

Similarly, [[Richard Lynn]] has in the book ''[[Dysgenics: Genetic Deterioration in Modern Populations]]'' argued that genetic [[health]] (due to modern health care) and genetic [[conscientiousness]] (criminals have more children than non-criminals) are declining in the modern world. This has caused some, like Lynn, to argue for voluntary eugenics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Richard |last=Lynn|title=Dysgenics: genetic deterioration in modern populations|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=NGMSAQAAIAAJ |year=1996|publisher=Praeger|isbn=978-0-275-94917-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lynn and Harvey (2008) suggest that [[designer babies]] may have an important eugenic effect in the future. Initially this may be limited to wealthy couples, who may possibly travel abroad for the procedure if prohibited in their own country, and then gradually spread to increasingly larger groups. Alternatively, authoritarian states may decide to impose measures such as a licensing requirement for having a child, which would only be given to persons of a certain minimum intelligence. The Chinese [[one-child policy]] is an example of how fertility can be regulated by authoritarian means.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;

==Criticism==
{{criticism section|date=November 2011}}

===Pseudoscientific notions of racial supremacy===
Current trends in genetics have raised questions amongst critical academics concerning parallels between pre-war attitudes about eugenics and current &quot;utilitarian&quot; and social theories allegedly related to Darwinism,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Duster, Troy |title=Backdoor to Eugenics |publisher=Routledge |year=1990 }}&lt;/ref&gt; they are, in fact, only superficially related and somewhat contradictory to one another.&lt;ref name=&quot;Donald MacKenzie 1975&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=MacKenzie, Donald |title=Eugenics in Britain |journal=Social Studies of Science |volume=6 |issue=3 |page=503 |year=1975 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  At its pre-war height, the movement often pursued [[pseudoscientific]] notions of racial supremacy and purity.&lt;ref&gt;See generally {{harvnb|Black|2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

===Doubts on genetic mutation triggered by inheritance===
The first major challenge to conventional eugenics based upon genetic inheritance was made in 1915 by [[Thomas Hunt Morgan]], who demonstrated the event of [[Mutation|genetic mutation]] occurring outside of inheritance involving the discovery of the hatching of a [[Drosophila melanogaster|fruit fly]] with white eyes from a family and ancestry of the red-eyed ''[[Drosophila melanogaster]]'' species of fruit fly.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blom&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Blom|2008|pp=336–7}}&lt;/ref&gt; Morgan claimed that this demonstrated that major genetic changes occurred outside of inheritance and that the concept of eugenics based upon genetic inheritance was severely flawed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blom&quot;/&gt;

===Diseases vs. traits===
{{See also|List of congenital disorders}}

While the science of [[genetics]] has increasingly provided means by which certain characteristics and conditions can be identified and understood, given the complexity of human genetics, culture, and psychology there is at this point no agreed objective means of determining which traits might be ultimately desirable or undesirable. Some diseases such as sickle-cell disease and cystic fibrosis respectively confer immunity to malaria and resistance to cholera when a single copy of the recessive allele is contained within the genotype of the individual. Reducing the instance of sickle-cell disease in Africa where malaria is a common and deadly disease could indeed be a net negative effect. On the other hand, [[Genetic disorder|genetic diseases]] like [[haemochromatosis]] can increase susceptibility to illness, cause physical deformities, and other dysfunctions.

===Ethics===
A common criticism of eugenics is that &quot;it inevitably leads to measures that are unethical&quot; (Lynn 2001). A hypothetical scenario posits that if one racial [[minorities|minority]] group is perceived on average less intelligent than the racial majority group, then it is more likely that the racial minority group will be submitted to a eugenics program rather than the least intelligent members of the whole population. In addition eugenics advocates are unlikely to support a system under which they themselves would be subject to culling.{{Citation needed|date=October 2011}}   H. L. Kaye wrote of &quot;the obvious truth that eugenics has been discredited by Hitler's crimes&quot; (Kaye 1989). R. L. Hayman argued &quot;the eugenics movement is an anachronism, its political implications exposed by the Holocaust&quot; (Hayman 1990).

[[Steven Pinker]] has stated that it is &quot;a conventional wisdom among left-leaning academics that genes imply genocide&quot;. He has responded to this &quot;conventional wisdom&quot; by comparing the history of [[Marxism]], which had the opposite position on genes to that of Nazism:

&lt;Blockquote&gt;But the 20th century suffered &quot;two&quot; ideologies that led to genocides. The other one, Marxism, had no use for race, didn't believe in genes and denied that human nature was a meaningful concept. Clearly, it's not an emphasis on genes or evolution that is dangerous. It's the desire to remake humanity by coercive means (eugenics or [[Social engineering (political science)|social engineering]]) and the belief that humanity advances through a struggle in which superior groups (race or classes) triumph over inferior ones.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://pinker.wjh.harvard.edu/books/tbs/media_articles/2002_10_30_upi.html | title=United Press International: Q&amp;A: Steven Pinker of 'Blank Slate | accessdate=2006-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/Blockquote&gt;

===Genetic diversity===
Eugenic policies could also lead to loss of [[genetic diversity]], in which case a culturally accepted improvement of the gene pool could very likely, as evidenced in numerous instances in isolated island populations (e.g. the [[Dodo]], ''Raphus cucullatus'', of Mauritius) result in extinction due to increased vulnerability to disease, reduced ability to adapt to environmental change and other factors both known and unknown. A long-term species-wide eugenics plan might lead to a scenario similar to this because the elimination of traits deemed undesirable would reduce genetic diversity by definition. (Galton 2001, 48{{Citation needed|date=April 2009}}).

Proponents of eugenics argue that in any one generation any realistic program would make only minor changes in a fraction of the gene pool, giving plenty of time to reverse direction if [[unintended consequence]]s emerge, reducing the likelihood of the elimination of desirable genes. Proponents of eugenics argue that any appreciable reduction in diversity is so far in the future that little concern is needed for now.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Miller, Edward M. |title=Eugenics: Economics for the Long Run |journal=Research in Biopolitics |volume=5 |pages=391–416 |year=1997 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The possible reduction of [[autism]] rates through selection against the [[Heritability of autism|genetic predisposition to autism]] is a significant political issue in the [[autism rights movement]], which claims autism is a form of [[neurodiversity]]. Many advocates of [[Down syndrome]] rights also consider Down syndrome (Trisomy-21) a form of neurodiversity.{{Citation needed|date=August 2007}}

===Heterozygous recessive traits===
In some instances efforts  to eradicate certain single-gene mutations would be nearly impossible. In the event the condition in question was a [[Zygosity|heterozygous]] [[recessive trait]], the problem is that by eliminating the visible unwanted trait, there are still many carriers for the genes without, or with fewer, phenotypic effects due to that gene. With [[genetic testing]] it may be possible to detect all of the heterozygous recessive traits, but only at great cost with the current technology. Under normal circumstances it is only possible to eliminate a dominant allele from the gene pool. Recessive traits can be severely reduced, but never eliminated unless the complete genetic makeup of all members of the pool was known, as aforementioned. As only very few undesirable traits, such as [[Huntington's disease]], are dominant, the practical value for &quot;eliminating&quot; traits is quite low.{{citation needed|date=October 2010}}

There are examples of eugenic acts that managed to lower the prevalence of recessive diseases, although not influencing the prevalence of heterozygote carriers of those diseases. The elevated prevalence of certain genetically transmitted diseases among the [[Ashkenazi Jew]]ish population ([[Tay-Sachs]], [[cystic fibrosis]], [[Canavan's disease]] and [[Gaucher's disease]]), has been decreased in current populations by the application of genetic screening.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishpress.com/page.do/18624/The_Book_Shelf.html Title: Fatal Gift: Jewish Intelligence and Western Civilization]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Supporters and critics==
At its peak of popularity eugenics was supported by a wide variety of prominent people, including [[Winston Churchill]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.winstonchurchill.org/support/the-churchill-centre/publications/finest-hour-online/594-churchill-and-eugenics |title=Winston Churchill and Eugenics |publisher=Winstonchurchill.org |date=2009-05-31 |accessdate=2011-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Margaret Sanger]],&lt;ref&gt;Margaret Sanger, quoted in {{cite book|last=Katz|first=Esther|coauthors =Engelman, Peter|title=The Selected Papers of Margaret Sanger|publisher=University of Illinois Press|location=Champaign, IL|year=2002|page=319|isbn=978-0-252-02737-6|quote=Our...campaign for Birth Control is not merely of eugenic value, but is practically identical in ideal with the final aims of Eugenics}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Franks|first=Angela|title=Margaret Sanger's eugenic legacy|publisher=McFarland|location=Jefferson, NC|year=2005|page=30|isbn=978-0-7864-2011-7|quote=...her commitment to eugenics was constant...until her death}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Marie Stopes]], [[H. G. Wells]], [[Theodore Roosevelt]], [[George Bernard Shaw]], [[John Maynard Keynes]], [[John Harvey Kellogg]], [[Linus Pauling]]&lt;ref&gt;Everett Mendelsohn, Ph.D. [http://harvardmagazine.com/2000/03/the-eugenic-temptation.html Pauling's Eugenics], ''The Eugenic Temptation'', Harvard Magazine, March–April 2000&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Sidney Webb]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | last =Gordon
  | first =Linda
  | coauthors =
  | title =The Moral Property of Women: A History of Birth Control Politics in America
  | publisher =University of Illinois Press
  | year =2002
  | page =196
  | url =
  | doi =
  | isbn =0-252-02764-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Opening remarks: The Galton Lecture |journal=[[The Eugenics Review]]|author=Keynes, John Maynard|volume=38|year=1946|pages=39–40|issue=1|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Okuefuna&gt;{{cite web
  | last =Okuefuna
  | first =David
  | coauthors =
  | title =Racism: a history
  | work =
  | publisher =[[British Broadcasting Corporation]]
  | date =
  | url =http://www.bbc.co.uk/bbcfour/documentaries/features/racism-history.shtml
  | doi =
  | accessdate = 2007-12-12 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Many members of the American [[Progressive Movement]] supported eugenics, enticed by its scientific trappings and its promise to cure social ills. Its most infamous proponent and practitioner was, however, [[Adolf Hitler]] who praised and incorporated eugenic ideas in [[Mein Kampf]] and emulated Eugenic legislation for the sterilization of &quot;defectives&quot; that had been pioneered in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Black|2003|pp=274–295}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The American sociologist [[Lester Frank Ward]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Joan |last=Ferrante|title=Sociology: A Global Perspective|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=AwnIIXI6y38C&amp;pg=PA259 |date=1 January 2010|publisher=Cengage Learning|isbn=978-0-8400-3204-1|pages=259–}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the English writer [[G. K. Chesterton]] were early critics of the philosophy of eugenics. Ward's 1913 article &quot;Eugenics, Euthenics, and Eudemics&quot; and Chesterton's 1917 book ''[[s:Eugenics and other Evils|Eugenics and Other Evils]]'' were harshly critical of the rapidly growing eugenics movement.

==In popular media==
Galton and many others claimed that the less intelligent were more fertile than the more intelligent of his time. This is the basis of the movie ''[[Idiocracy]],'' in which five hundred years in the future (2505) the dysgenic pressure has resulted in a uniformly stupid human society.

In ''[[Star Trek]],'' there are conflicts known as the Eugenics Wars (or the Great Wars) which were a series of conflicts fought on Earth between 1993 and 1996. The result of a scientific attempt to improve the Human race through selective breeding and genetic engineering, the wars devastated parts of Earth, by some estimates officially causing some 30 million deaths, and nearly plunging the planet into a new Dark Age. (TOS: &quot;[[Space Seed]]&quot;; ENT: &quot;[[Borderland (Enterprise episode)|Borderland]]&quot;)

Also, in the movie ''[[Gattaca]],'' a dystopian set of events is portrayed through the application of &quot;artificial selection&quot;.  This is then shown to be misused by employer and insurance companies and even schools, screening out the &quot;in-valids&quot;.  Through this, the protagonist, an &quot;in-valid&quot;, is shown to go to great heights to reach his dreams of being an astronaut.

In the video game ''[[Grand Theft Auto IV]]'', one of the many in-game advertisements is for &quot;Eugenics Incorporated,&quot; a firm that purports to adjust the genetic makeup of a fetus to ensure that all characteristics are ideal.

&quot;Eugenics&quot; is the name of an album, released in 2012, by the technical death metal band [[Malignancy (band)|Malignancy]]

==See also==
* [[Aktion T4]]
* [[Biological determinism]]
* [[Dysgenics]]
* [[Eugenics in the United States]]
* [[Sperm bank]]
* [[Ova bank]]
* [[Euthenics]]
* [[Genetic determinism]]
* [[Genism]]
* [[History of the race and intelligence controversy]]
* [[Race_and_genetics#Ancestral_populations]]
* [[International Federation of Eugenics Organizations]]
* [[Kaiser Wilhelm Institute of Anthropology, Human Heredity, and Eugenics]]
* [[Life unworthy of life]]
* [[Oneida stirpiculture]]
* [[Racial hygiene]]
* [[Social Darwinism]]

'''Individuals:'''
* [[Karl Binding]]
* [[John Glad]]
* [[Alfred Hoche]]
* [[John M. MacEachran]]
* [[Bénédict Morel]]
* [[Alfred Ploetz]]
* [[Ernst Rüdin]]
* [[Margaret Sanger]]
* [[Katherine M. H. Blackford]]

'''Organisations:'''
* [[Alberta Eugenics Board]]
* [[Repository for Germinal Choice]], a [[Intelligence quotient|high IQ]] [[sperm bank]].

==References==
{{Citation style|date=August 2009}}
{{Reflist|colwidth=35em}}

==Sources==
* {{Cite journal
 | last1     = Larson
 | given       = Edward J.
 | authorlink  = Edward J. Larson
 | year        = 2004
 | title       = Evolution
 | publisher   = Modern Library
 | ref     = harv
 | postscript     = &lt;!--None--&gt;
 | isbn     = 0-679-64288-9
 }}
;Histories of eugenics (academic accounts)
*{{cite book |author=Carlson, Elof Axel |title=The Unfit: A History of a Bad Idea |publisher=Cold Spring Harbor Press |location=Cold Spring Harbor NY |year=2001 |isbn=0-87969-587-0 |pages= |url=}}
*{{cite book |first=Daniel J. |last=Kevles |title=In the Name of Eugenics: Genetics and the Uses of Human Heredity |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=8esnhRxBomMC |year=1985 |publisher=University of California Press |isbn=978-0-520-05763-0 |authorlink=Daniel Kevles |ref=harv}}
* Dieter Kuntz, ed., ''Deadly medicine: creating the master race'' (Washington, DC: United States Holocaust Memorial Museum, 2004). [http://www.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/online/deadlymedicine/ online exhibit]
*{{cite book | last = Largent | first = Mark | title = Breeding Contempt: The History of Coerced Sterilization in the United States | publisher = Rutgers University Press | location = New Brunswick | year = 2008 | isbn = 978-0-8135-4183-9}}
*{{cite book |first=Ruth C. |last=Engs |authorlink=Ruth C. Engs |title=The Eugenics Movement: An Encyclopedia |publisher=Greenwood Publishing |location=Westport CT |year=2005 |isbn=0-313-32791-2 |pages= |url=}}
*{{cite book |first=John |last=Glad |authorlink=John Glad |title=Future Human Evolution: Eugenics in the Twenty-First Century |publisher=Hermitage Publishers |location= |year=2008 |isbn=1-55779-154-6 |pages= |url=http://www.whatwemaybe.org/txt/txt0000/Glad.John.2008.FHE.Meisenberg-abridgement.en.pdf |format=PDF}}

;Histories of hereditarian thought
*{{cite book |first=Elazar |last=Barkan |title=The retreat of scientific racism: changing concepts of race in Britain and the United States between the world wars |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=New York |year=1992 |isbn= |pages= |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Gould |first=Stephen Jay |authorlink=Stephen Jay Gould |title=The mismeasure of man |publisher=Norton |location=New York |year=1981 |isbn=0-393-01489-4 |ref=harv }}
* Ewen &amp; Ewen, ''Typecasting: On the Arts and Sciences of Human Inequality'' (New York, Seven Stories Press, 2006).
;Criticisms of eugenics, historical and modern
*{{cite book |last=Black |first=Edwin |authorlink=Edwin Black |title=War Against the Weak: Eugenics and America's Campaign to Create a Master Race |publisher=Four Walls Eight Windows |year=2003 |isbn=1-56858-258-7 |url=http://www.waragainsttheweak.com/ |ref=harv}}
* [[Dinesh D'Souza]], ''The End of Racism'' (Free Press, 1995) ISBN 0-02-908102-5
* [[David Galton]], ''Eugenics: The Future of Human Life in the 21st Century'' (Abacus, 2002) ISBN 0-349-11377-7
* [[Jonah Goldberg]], [[Liberal Fascism]]: The Secret History of the American Left, from Mussolini to the Politics of Meaning (ISBN 0-385-51184-1)
*{{cite journal |author=Hayman, Robert L. |title=Presumptions of justice: Law, politics, and the mentally retarded parent |journal=Harvard Law Review |volume=103 |issue= 6|pages=1202–71 |year=1990 |doi= 10.2307/1341412|url=}} (p.&amp;nbsp;1209)
* Joseph, J. (2004)[http://www.jayjoseph.net/GeneIllusion.html . ''The Gene Illusion: Genetic Research in Psychiatry and Psychology Under the Microscope''.] New York: Algora. (2003 United Kingdom Edition by PCCS Books)
* —— (2005). The 1942 &quot;Euthanasia&quot; Debate in the American Journal of Psychiatry. ''History of Psychiatry, 16'', 171–179.
* —— (2006). [http://www.jayjoseph.net/MissingGene.html ''The Missing Gene: Psychiatry, Heredity, and the Fruitless Search for Genes''.] New York: Algora.
* H. L. Kaye, ''The social meaning of modern biology'' 1987, New Haven, CT [[Yale University Press]]. (p.&amp;nbsp;46)
*{{cite book|last=Maranto|first=Gina|title=Quest for perfection : the drive to breed better human beings|year=1996|publisher=Scribner|location=New York|isbn=0-684-80029-2}}
*{{cite journal |author=Wahlsten, D. |title=Leilani Muir versus the Philosopher King: eugenics on trial in Alberta |journal=Genetica |volume=99 |issue= 2–3|pages=185–198 |year=1997 |doi=10.1007/BF02259522 |pmid=9463073 }}
*{{cite journal |author=Shakespeare, Tom |authorlink=Tom Shakespeare |title=Back to the Future? New Genetics and Disabled People |journal=Critical Social Policy |volume=46 |issue= 44–45|pages=22–35 |year=1995 |doi= 10.1177/026101839501504402|url=}}
* [[Tom Shakespeare]], ''Genetic Politics: from Eugenics to Genome'', with Anne Kerr (New Clarion Press, 2002).
* Nancy Ordover, ''American Eugenics: Race, Queer Anatomy, and the Science of Nationalism'' (Minneapolis: [[University of Minnesota|University of Minneapolis Press]], 2003). ISBN 0-8166-3559-5
* Andrea Smith, ''Conquest: Sexual Violence and the American Indian Genocide'' (Cambridge, MA: South End Press, 2005).

==External links==
{{commons}}
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Wikisourcecat}}

{{Genetic engineering}}

[[Category:Eugenics| ]]
[[Category:Applied genetics]]
[[Category:Bioethics]]
[[Category:Health movements]]
[[Category:Human evolution]]
[[Category:Scientific racism]]
[[Category:Core issues in ethics]]

[[af:Eugenetika]]
[[ar:تحسين النسل]]
[[az:Yevgenika]]
[[zh-min-nan:Iu-seng-ha̍k]]
[[bg:Евгеника]]
[[bs:Eugenika]]
[[ca:Eugenèsia]]
[[cs:Eugenika]]
[[da:Eugenik]]
[[de:Eugenik]]
[[et:Eugeenika]]
[[es:Eugenesia]]
[[eo:Eŭgeniko]]
[[eu:Eugenesia]]
[[fa:به‌نژادی]]
[[fr:Eugénisme]]
[[gl:Euxenesia]]
[[ko:우생학]]
[[hr:Eugenika]]
[[id:Eugenika]]
[[is:Arfbætur]]
[[it:Eugenetica]]
[[he:אאוגניקה]]
[[jv:Eugenetika]]
[[kk:Еугеника]]
[[la:Eugenica]]
[[lt:Eugenika]]
[[hu:Eugenika]]
[[mk:Евгеника]]
[[nl:Eugenetica]]
[[ja:優生学]]
[[no:Rasehygiene]]
[[pl:Eugenika]]
[[pt:Eugenia]]
[[ro:Eugenism]]
[[ru:Евгеника]]
[[simple:Eugenics]]
[[sk:Eugenika]]
[[sl:Evgenika]]
[[sr:Еугеника]]
[[sh:Eugenika]]
[[fi:Eugeniikka]]
[[sv:Rashygien]]
[[tr:Öjenik]]
[[uk:Євгеніка]]
[[vi:Thuyết ưu sinh]]
[[zh:優生學]]</text>
      <sha1>3iqk5kcjvxwpxov696gjbzzm7pjydic</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
