<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Flat Earth Society</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>103123</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520781057</id>
      <parentid>520517463</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-31T18:17:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>212.22.231.19</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */ I think this fits the category</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24625">{{For|the Belgian band|Flat Earth Society (band)}}

[[Image:Flat_earth.jpg|thumb|A Flat Earth model depicting [[Antarctica]] as an ice wall surrounding a disk-shaped Earth.]]

The '''Flat Earth Society''' (also known as the '''International Flat Earth Society''' or the '''International Flat Earth Research Society''') is an organization that seeks to further the belief that the [[Flat Earth|Earth is flat]] instead of an [[Oblate spheroid|oblate]] [[Spherical Earth|spheroid]]. The modern organization was founded by Englishman [[Samuel Shenton]] in 1956&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://science.howstuffworks.com/space-conspiracy-theory8.htm |title= Flat Earth Society |publisher=howstuffworks.com |date= |accessdate=2009-06-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was later led by [[Charles K. Johnson]], who based the organization in his home in [[Lancaster, California#Recreation and culture|Lancaster]], [[California]]. The formal society was inactive after Johnson’s death in 2001 but was resurrected in 2004 by its new president Daniel Shenton.&lt;ref name=&quot;daniel_shenton_guardian&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=David Adam|publisher=[[The Guardian]]|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/global/2010/feb/23/flat-earth-society |title=The Earth is flat? What planet is he on?|date=February 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origins—the Zetetic societies==
{{Main|Flat Earth}}
The belief that the Earth was flat was typical of ancient [[cosmology|cosmologies]] until about the 4th century BC, when the Ancient Greek philosophers proposed the idea that the Earth was a sphere, or at least rounded in shape.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Wherefore he made the world in the form of a globe, round as from a lathe, having its extremes in every direction equidistant from the centre, the most perfect and the most like itself of all figures...&quot;{{cite|author=Plato|url=http://classics.mit.edu/Plato/timaeus.html|title=Timaeus|accessdate=2011-01-29|year=c. 360 BC.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Aristotle was one of the first thinkers to propose a spherical Earth in 330 BC. By the early [[Middle Ages]], it was widespread knowledge throughout Europe that the Earth was a sphere.&lt;ref name=&quot;magazine1&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|last=O'Neill |first=Brendan |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/magazine/7540427.stm |title=UK &amp;#124; Magazine &amp;#124; Do they really think the earth is flat? |publisher=BBC News |date=2008-08-04 |accessdate=2009-06-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Modern hypotheses supporting a flat Earth originated with English inventor [[Samuel Rowbotham]] (1816–1884). Based on his incorrect interpretation of [[Bedford Level experiment|experiments on the Bedford Level]], Rowbotham published a 16-page pamphlet, called &quot;Zetetic Astronomy&quot;, which he later expanded into a 430-page book, ''Earth Not a Globe'', expounding his views. According to Rowbotham's system, the earth is a flat disc centred at the North Pole and bounded along its southern edge by a wall of ice ([[Antarctica]]), with the sun and moon 3,000 miles (4,800&amp;nbsp;km) and the &quot;cosmos&quot; 3,100 miles (5,000&amp;nbsp;km) above earth.&lt;ref&gt;Schick, Theodore; Lewis Vaughn ''How to think about weird things: critical thinking for a new age'' Houghton Mifflin (Mayfield) (31 October 1995) ISBN 978-1-55934-254-4 p.197&lt;/ref&gt; He also published a leaflet entitled &quot;''The inconsistency of Modern Astronomy and its Opposition to the Scriptures!!''&quot; which argued that the &quot;Bible, alongside our senses, supported the idea that the earth was flat and immovable and this essential truth should not be set aside for a system based solely on human conjecture&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Garwood|2007|p=46}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Rowbotham and his followers, like [[William Carpenter (1830-1896)|William Carpenter]] who continued his work, gained attention by engaging in public debates with leading scientists of the day. One such debate, involving the prominent naturalist [[Alfred Russel Wallace]], concerned the [[Bedford Level experiment]] (and later led to several lawsuits for [[fraud]] and [[libel]]).&lt;ref&gt;[[Nature (journal)|''Nature'']] April 7, 1870.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |title =The Form of the Earth—A Shock of Opinions |journal=[[New York Times]] |date=1871-08-10 |url=http://query.nytimes.com/mem/archive-free/pdf?_r=1&amp;res=9C00EFDF113EEE34BC4852DFBE66838A669FDE&amp;oref=slogin |accessdate= 2007-11-02 |format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hampden, John (1870): The Bedford Canal swindle detected &amp; exposed. A. Bull, London.&lt;/ref&gt; Rowbotham created a Zetetic Society in England and New York, shipping over a thousand copies of ''Zetetic Astronomy''. Council members in New York included the US Consul to China and the superintendent of Baltimore public schools. He also edited &quot;''The Zetetic and Anti-Theorist: a monthly journal of practical cosmography''&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Garwood|2007|p=133}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After Rowbotham's death, Lady Elizabeth Blount, wife of the explorer Sir Walter de Sodington Blount, established a Universal Zetetic Society, whose objective was &quot;''the propagation of knowledge related to Natural [[Cosmogony]] in confirmation of the Holy Scriptures, based on practical scientific investigation''&quot;. The society published a magazine entitled ''The Earth Not a Globe Review'', and remained active well into the early part of the 20th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;speakvenusian&quot;/&gt; A flat Earth journal, ''Earth: a Monthly Magazine of Sense and Science'', was published between 1901–1904, edited by Lady Blount.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Garwood|2007|pp=155–159}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1901, she repeated Rowbotham's Bedford Level Experiment and photographed the effect, sparking a correspondence in the magazine ''[[English Mechanic]]'' with several counter-claims. Later it achieved some notoriety by being involved in a scam involving dental practices.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Garwood|2007|pp=182–6}}&lt;/ref&gt; After [[World War I]], the movement underwent a slow decline.

==Modern incarnation==
In 1956, Samuel Shenton, a signwriter by trade, created the International Flat Earth Society as a successor to the Universal Zetetic Society and ran it as &quot;organizing secretary&quot; from his home in [[Dover]], in [[United Kingdom|Britain]].&lt;ref name=&quot;speakvenusian&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last= Moore |first= P |authorlink= Patrick Moore |title= Can You Speak Venusian? |year= 1972 |isbn= 0-352-39776-4 |chapterurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20070927051349/http://www.theflatearthsociety.org/docs/better_and_flatter_earths.pdf |format= pdf |chapter= Better and Flatter Earths }}&lt;/ref&gt; Because of Shenton's interest in alternative science and technology, the emphasis on religious arguments was less than in the predecessor society.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Garwood|2007|pp=220–225}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This was just before the launch of the first artificial satellite, and when satellite images taken from outer space showed the Earth as a sphere rather than flat, the society was undaunted; Shenton remarked: &quot;It's easy to see how a photograph like that could fool the untrained eye.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|author= Schadewald RJ |url= http://ncse.com/cej/3/3/six-flood-arguments-creationists-cant-answer |title= Six &quot;Flood&quot; Arguments Creationists can't answer |publisher= [[National Center for Science Education]] |accessdate=2010-04-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However it was not until the advent of manned spaceflight that Shenton managed to attract wide publicity, being featured in ''[[The New York Times]]'' in January and June 1964, when the epithet &quot;flat-earther&quot; was also slung across the floor of the [[House of Commons of the United Kingdom]] in both directions.

The society also took the position that the [[Apollo Moon Landing hoax conspiracy theories|Apollo Moon landings were a hoax]] staged by Hollywood, a position also held by others not connected to the Flat Earth Society.

In 1969, Shenton persuaded Ellis Hillman, a [[North East London Polytechnic|Polytechnic]] lecturer, to become president of the Flat Earth Society, but there is little evidence of any activity on his part until after Shenton's death, when he added most of Shenton's library to the archives of the [[Science Fiction Foundation]] which he helped to establish.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Garwood|2007|pp=320}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Shenton died in 1971 and Charles K. Johnson, inheriting part of Shenton's library from Shenton's wife, established and became the president of the International Flat Earth Research Society of America and Covenant People's Church in [[California]]. Under his leadership, over the next three decades, the Flat Earth Society grew in size from a few members to about 3,000. Johnson distributed newsletters, flyers, maps, and other promotional materials to anyone who asked for them, and managed all membership applications together with his wife, Marjory, who was also a flat-earther. The most famous of these newsletters was ''Flat Earth News''. Johnson paid for these publications through annual dues of members, which ranged from [[United States dollar|US$]]6 to $10 over the course of his leadership.&lt;ref name=&quot;dsimanek1&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|author= Schadewald RJ |url=http://www.lhup.edu/~dsimanek/fe-scidi.htm |title=The Flat-out Truth |publisher=Lhup.edu |date=July 1980 |accessdate=2009-06-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Flag of the United Nations.svg|thumb|right|[[United Nations flag]]]]
The most recent world model propagated by the Flat Earth Society holds that humanity lives on a disc, with the [[North Pole]] at its center and a 150-foot (45 m) high wall of [[ice]] at the outer edge.&lt;ref name=&quot;whirling&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://theflatearthsociety.org/library/Flat_Earth_Society_Newsletter_-_1979_March.pdf |title=Is the Earth a Whirling Globe? |first=Wilbur Glenn |last=Voliva |month=Mar. |year=1979 |work=Flat Earth News |publisher=International Flat Earth Research Society |location=Lancaster, CA |page=2 |accessdate=May 21, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The resulting [[map]] resembles the symbol of the [[United Nations]], which Johnson used as evidence for his position.&lt;ref name=&quot;fesn_d78p2&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://theflatearthsociety.org/library/Flat_Earth_Society_Newsletter_-_1978_December.pdf |title=News of the World's Children |first=Charles K. |last=Johnson |month=Dec. |year=1978 |work=Flat Earth News |publisher=International Flat Earth Research Society |location=Lancaster, CA |page=2 |accessdate=May 21, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In this model, the [[sun]] and [[moon]] are each a mere 32 miles (52&amp;nbsp;km) in diameter.&lt;ref name=&quot;sun32&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://theflatearthsociety.org/library/Flat_Earth_Society_Newsletter_-_1978_December.pdf |title=Sun is a Light 32 Miles Across |first=Charles K. |last=Johnson |month=Dec. |year=1978 |work=Flat Earth News |publisher=International Flat Earth Research Society |location=Lancaster, CA |page=1 |accessdate=May 21, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A newsletter from the society gives some insight into Johnson's thinking:
:Aim: To carefully observe, think freely, rediscover forgotten fact and oppose theoretical dogmatic assumptions. To help establish the United States...of the world on this flat earth. Replace the science religion...with SANITY.

:The International Flat Earth Society is the oldest continuous Society existing in the world today. It began with the Creation of the Creation. First the water...the face of the deep...without form or limits...just Water. Then the Land sitting in and on the Water, the Water then as now being flat and level, as is the very Nature of Water. There are, of course, mountains and valleys on the Land but since most of the World is Water, we say, &quot;The World is Flat&quot;. Historical accounts and spoken history tell us the Land part may have been square, all in one mass at one time, then as now, the magnetic north being the Center. Vast cataclysmic events and shaking no doubt broke the land apart, divided the Land to be our present continents or islands as they exist today. One thing we know for sure about this world...the known inhabited world is Flat, Level, a Plain World.

:We maintain that what is called 'Science' today and 'scientists' consist of the same old gang of witch doctors, sorcerers, tellers of tales, the 'Priest-Entertainers' for the common people. 'Science' consists of a weird, way-out occult concoction of gibberish theory-theology...unrelated to the real world of facts, technology and inventions, tall buildings and fast cars, airplanes and other Real and Good things in life; technology is not in any way related to the web of idiotic scientific theory. ALL inventors have been anti-science. The Wright brothers said: &quot;Science theory held us up for years. When we threw out all science, started from experiment and experience, then we invented the airplane.&quot; By the way, airplanes all fly level on this Plane earth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.talkorigins.org/faqs/flatearth.html | title = Documenting the Existence of &quot;The International Flat Earth Society&quot; | publisher = [[talk.origins]] | accessdate=2010-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Flat Earth Society recruited members by attacking the [[United States government]] and all of its agencies, particularly NASA. Much of the society’s literature in its early days focused on interpreting the Bible literally to mean that the Earth is flat, although they did attempt to offer scientific explanations and evidence.&lt;ref name=&quot;dsimanek1&quot;/&gt;

===''Flat Earth News''===
''Flat Earth News,'' was a quarterly, four-page [[Tabloid (paper size)|tabloid]].&lt;ref name=&quot;dsimanek1&quot; /&gt;

Some headlines from ''Flat Earth News'' during the '70s and early '80s:&lt;ref name=&quot;feslibrary&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://theflatearthsociety.org/cms/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=47&amp;Itemid=62 |title=Flat Earth Society Library |date=[n.d.] |accessdate=May 21, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;Whole World Deceived... Except the Very Elect&quot; (Dec. 1977)
* &quot;Australia Not Down Under&quot; (May 1978)
* &quot;Sun Is a Light 32 Miles Across&quot; (Dec. 1978)
* &quot;The Earth Has No Motion&quot; (Jun. 1979)
* &quot;Nikita Krushchev Father of NASA&quot; (Mar. 1980)
* &quot;Galileo Was a Liar&quot; (Dec. 1980)
* &quot;Science Insults Your Intelligence&quot; (Sep. 1980)
* &quot;World IS Flat, and That's That&quot; (Sep. 1980)
* &quot;The Earth Is Not a Ball; Gravity Does Not Exist&quot; (Mar. 1981)

===Peak and decline===
The group rose to about 2,000 members during its peak under Charles K. Johnson. The organization faced overwhelming scientific evidence and public opinion that maintained that the Earth is a sphere. The term &quot;flat-earther&quot; became commonly used to refer to an individual who stubbornly adheres to discredited or outmoded ideas.

The society fell to around 200 members by 1980. These members still held the belief that the Earth is flat. [[Eugenie Scott]] called the society an example of &quot;extreme Biblical-literalist theology: The earth is flat because the Bible says it is flat, regardless of what science tells us.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Scott|first=Eugenie|title=Antievolution and Creationism in the United States|journal=Annual Review of Anthropology|year=1997|volume=26|pages=263–289|url=http://www.kean.edu/~bregal/docs/Scott.history%20of%20creat.pdf|accessdate=Dec 8, 2011|doi=10.1146/annurev.anthro.26.1.263}}&lt;/ref&gt; The society was further affected by a fire at the house of Charles K. Johnson which destroyed all of the records and contacts of members of the Flat Earth Society. Johnson’s wife, who helped manage the database, died shortly thereafter.&lt;ref name=&quot;president1&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|author=Author(s):&amp;nbsp;John R. Cole, Contributing Editor |url=http://ncse.com/rncse/21/3-4/flat-earth-society-president-dies |title=Flat Earth Society President Dies &amp;#124; NCSE |publisher= [[National Center for Science Education]] |year=2001 |accessdate=2009-06-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Charles K. Johnson himself died on March 19, 2001.

==Canadian branch==
The Flat Earth Society of Canada was set up by Leo Ferrari (1927–2010), a philosophy professor at the [[St. Thomas University (New Brunswick)|St Thomas University]] in 1970, together with [[Raymond Fraser]] and [[Alden Nowlan]] and was active till about 1984. Their aims were quite different from other flat earth societies. With obvious humorous overtones, they claimed a prevailing problem of the new technological age was the willingness of people to accept theories &quot;on blind faith and to reject the evidence of their own senses.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.lib.unb.ca/archives/finding/ferrari/s2.html|title=UNB Archives|accessdate=2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; They did not actually believe Flat Earth theories, considering their proponents to be cranks, and indeed did not accept such people into their society, which was composed of quite a few prominent members of Canadian literary and political circles.

They published a newsletter, ''The Official Chronicle'' and promoted their ideas more widely through television and press. Its primary aims were &quot;to combat the fallacious deification of the circle,&quot; &quot;to restore man's confidence in the validity of his own perceptions&quot;, and &quot;to spearhead man's escape from his metaphysical and geometrical prison.&quot;

==Modern activities==
[[Image:FESlogo.gif|thumb|The logo of the modern Flat Earth Society]]
In 2004, Daniel Shenton (not related to Samuel&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://elpais.com/diario/2010/03/19/tentaciones/1269026579_850215.html|title=Miedo a un planeta esférico|date=2010-03-19|accessdate=2012-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;) resurrected the Flat Earth Society, basing it around a web-based discussion forum.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://theflatearthsociety.org/forum/ |title=The Flat Earth Society forum}}&lt;/ref&gt; This eventually led to the official relaunch of the society in October 2009,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theflatearthsociety.org/library/flat_earth_society_press_release.pdf |title=Relaunch of the Flat Earth Society (press release)}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the creation of a new website, featuring the largest public collection of Flat Earth literature in the world and a user-edited encyclopaedia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://theflatearthsociety.org/cms/ |title=The Flat Earth Society Homepage}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, the society began accepting new members for the first time since 2001, with musician [[Thomas Dolby]] becoming the first member to join the newly reconvened society. As of March 2012, around 420 people have become members.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://theflatearthsociety.org/cms/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=56&amp;Itemid=73 |title=Flat Earth Society Membership Register}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shenton has also conducted several interviews since the society's relaunch, including in ''[[The Guardian]]'' newspaper.&lt;ref name=&quot;daniel_shenton_guardian&quot; /&gt;

A related forum of the International Alliance of Flat Earth Groups is currently inactive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theflatearthsociety.net/forum/ |title=www.theflatearthsociety.net/forum/}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Flat Earth Society is also represented on Twitter&lt;ref&gt;http://twitter.com/FlatEarthToday&lt;/ref&gt; and Facebook.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.facebook.com/#/group.php?gid=23033272998|title=Flat Earth Society}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Current proponents of the Flat Earth Society do not have a central alternative theory; different members have unique ideas on how the Earth is constructed. Some claim that it is a finite plane of unknown extent accelerating upwards at 9.8 m/s&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, whilst others claim it is an infinite plane.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theflatearthsociety.org/forum/index.php?topic=46458.0|title=Flat Earth Society Forum Thread}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In popular culture==
*English musician [[Thomas Dolby]] released an album called ''[[The Flat Earth]]'', has used the name Flat Earth Society for his website forums, and has linked to information relating to the flat earth myth.
*In the film ''[[Hopscotch (film)|Hopscotch]],'' Miles Kendig ([[Walter Matthau]]) jokes that he is bequeathing all his money to the Flat Earth Society.
*In the 1980s, talk show host [[Wally George]] often sparred with and ridiculed members of the Flat Earth Society on his show ''[[Hot Seat (talk show)|Hot Seat]].'' [[Australia]]n talk show host [[Don Lane]] also had Flat Earth Society advocates on his show.
*A tourism commercial for [[Newfoundland and Labrador]] states that the Flat Earth Society claimed that Newfoundland and Labrador was one of the four corners of the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.newfoundlandlabrador.com/SightsAndSounds/VideoClips.aspx?videoID=3 |title=Newfoundland and Labrador Video Gallery |publisher=NewfoundlandLabrador.com |date= |accessdate=2009-06-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*California-based [[punk rock]] band [[Bad Religion]] include a song entitled &quot;Flat Earth Society&quot;, written by [[Brett Gurewitz]], on their album ''[[Against the Grain (Bad Religion album)|Against the Grain]]'' (1990). A prominent feature of the song is the refrain &quot;lie, lie, lie,&quot; indicating a strong denunciation of the society and its theories. The band has produced similar songs criticizing other movements it views as [[Pseudoscience|pseudoscientific]].
*English band [[Carter USM]] make reference to the Flat Earth Society in the song &quot;Senile Delinquent&quot; on their album ''[[Worry Bomb]]'' (1995)
*[[Klutz Press]] mention the Flat Earth Society in the book ''Mother Nature Goes Nuts!'' in a section about the argument on [[global warming]], saying how it is practically impossible to get everyone on earth to agree on one thing.
*In [[Stephen King]]'s novella ''[[The Mist]],'' the main character uses the name Flat Earth Society to describe a group that refuse to accept the presence of monsters in the mist outside.
* [[Richard A. Lupoff]]'s novel ''Circumpolar!'' describes a flat planet much like the Earth as described by the Flat Earth Society, except it has a hole at the centre instead of a North Pole, and the underside contains fictional lands such as Atlantis and Lemuria.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.fantasticfiction.co.uk/l/richard-a-lupoff/circumpolar.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
*In the [[Monty Python]] short &quot;[[The Crimson Permanent Assurance]]&quot;, business clerks-turned-pirates sail a pirated building and attack competing businesses to build a business empire, when the narrator reads &quot;or so it would have been, if certain modern theories concerning the shape of the world had not proved to be disastrously wrong—&quot; just as the building tumbles off the edge of the earth.
*In [[Lawrence Block]]'s novel ''The Canceled Czech'' (1966), secret agent Evan Tanner writes an article for the quarterly bulletin of the Flat Earth Society of England.
*In the [[Asterix]] adventure ''[[The Mansions of the Gods]]'', the leader of the slaves is &quot;[[Flaturtha]], the Numidian&quot;, who is subsequently shown to be the crows-nest lookout for the pirates in other Asterix adventures.

==See also==
*[[Wilbur Glenn Voliva]]
*[[Flying Spaghetti Monster]]

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
*{{cite book|last=Garwood|first=Christine|title=Flat Earth: the History of an infamous idea|publisher=Macmillan|year=2007|ref=harv}}

==Further reading==
* [[Raymond Fraser]] (2007). ''When The Earth Was Flat: Remembering Leonard Cohen, Alden Nowlan, the Flat Earth Society, the King James monarchy hoax, the Montreal Story Tellers and other curious matters.'' Black Moss Press, ISBN 978-0-88753-439-3
* Christine Garwood (2007) ''Flat Earth: The History of an Infamous Idea'', Pan Books, ISBN 1-4050-4702-X

==External links==
*{{Official website|http://www.theflatearthsociety.org/}}
*[http://www.lhup.edu/~dsimanek/flat/flateart.htm The Flat Earth, by Donald E. Simanek a history of Flat Earth movements]
*[http://www.loc.gov/rr/scitech/SciRefGuides/flatearth.html References to the Flat Earth Society by the [[Library of Congress]]]
* [http://archiveshub.ac.uk/features/06101601.html Archival documents]: The Papers of the Flat Earth Society at the [[University of Liverpool]] library
* [http://www.lhup.edu/~dsimanek/fe-scidi.htm The Flat-out Truth: Earth Orbits? Moon Landings? A Fraud! Says This Prophet], a detailed look at the ''Society'' by [[Robert Schadewald]]
* [http://www.talkorigins.org/faqs/flatearth.html The International Flat Earth Society], documentation of the ''Flat Earth Society'' newsletter at [[talk.origins]]

[[Category:Conspiracy theorists]]
[[Category:Anti-intellectualism]]
[[Category:Denialism]]
[[Category:Organizations established in 1956]]
[[Category:1956 establishments in England]]
[[Category:Flat Earth theory]]

[[ar:مجتمع الأرض البسيطة]]
[[da:Flat Earth Society]]
[[de:Flat Earth Society]]
[[es:Flat Earth Society]]
[[fr:Flat Earth Society]]
[[gl:Flat Earth Society]]
[[ko:평평한 지구 학회]]
[[id:Flat Earth Society]]
[[it:Flat Earth Society]]
[[he:אגודת הארץ השטוחה]]
[[hu:Flat Earth Society]]
[[ja:地球平面協会]]
[[pl:Towarzystwo Płaskiej Ziemi]]
[[pt:Flat Earth Society]]
[[ro:Flat Earth Society]]
[[ru:Общество плоской Земли]]
[[simple:Flat Earth Society]]
[[sv:Flat Earth Society]]
[[tr:Flat Earth Society]]
[[uk:Товариство пласкої Землі]]
[[zh:地平說學會]]</text>
      <sha1>st2h92kfdsojlca1acqxhbuvz8ybowq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
