<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Human cloning</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>14094</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520792532</id>
      <parentid>520792459</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-31T19:44:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Philip Trueman</username>
        <id>3150196</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Help:Reverting|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/199.0.202.100|199.0.202.100]] ([[User talk:199.0.202.100|talk]]) to last version by ClueBot NG</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24133">'''Human cloning''' is the creation of a genetically identical copy of a human. It does not refer to [[monozygotic]] [[multiple birth]]s or the reproduction of humans/animals [[Cell (biology)|cells]] or [[Tissue (biology)|tissue]]. The ethics of cloning is an extremely controversial issue. The term is generally used to refer to artificial human cloning; human clones in the form of identical [[twins]] are commonplace, with their cloning occurring during the natural process of reproduction.

There are two commonly discussed types of human cloning: ''therapeutic cloning'' and ''reproductive cloning''. Therapeutic cloning involves cloning cells from an adult for use in medicine  and transplants, and is an active area of research. Reproductive cloning would involve making cloned humans, for couples wanting to have a child, but cannot naturally. 

A third type of cloning called replacement cloning is a theoretical possibility, and would be a combination of therapeutic and reproductive cloning. Replacement cloning would entail the replacement of an extensively damaged, failed, or failing body through cloning followed by whole or partial brain transplant.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

==History==
Although the possibility of [[cloning]] humans had been the subject of speculation for much of the twentieth century, scientists and policy makers began to take the prospect seriously in the 1960s. 

Nobel Prize winning geneticist [[Joshua Lederberg]] advocated cloning and [[genetic engineering]] in a [[Wiktionary:seminal#English|seminal]] article in [[The American Naturalist]] in 1966 and again, the following year, in [[The Washington Post]].&lt;ref&gt;Joshua Lederberg. (1966). Experimental Genetics and Human Evolution. The American Naturalist 100, 915, pp. 519-531.&lt;/ref&gt; He sparked a debate with conservative bioethicist [[Leon Kass]], who wrote at the time that &quot;the programmed reproduction of man will, in fact, dehumanize him.&quot; Another [[List of Nobel laureates|Nobel Laureate]], [[James D. Watson]], publicized the potential and the perils of cloning in his [[Atlantic Monthly]] essay, &quot;Moving Toward the Clonal Man&quot;, in 1971.&lt;ref&gt;Watson, James. &quot;Moving Toward a Clonal Man: Is This What We Want?&quot; The Atlantic Monthly (1971).&lt;/ref&gt;

The technology of cloning mammals, although far from reliable, has reached the point where many scientists are knowledgeable, the literature is readily available, and the implementation of the technology is not very expensive compared to many other scientific processes. For that reason Lewis D. Eigen has argued that human cloning attempts will be made in the next few years and may well have been already begun.&lt;ref name=whois&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scriptamus.wordpress.com/2010/01/03/human-clones-may-be-among-us-now-who-is-ready|title=''Scriptamus'', Human Clones May Be Among Us Now! Who Is Ready?|author=Lewis D. Eigen|year=2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
''&quot;By waiting until the first clone is among us or about to be born, we complicate the problem immensely and guarantee that we will not be able to have the national and international conversation and debate to arrive at particularly good decisions like using protection.&quot;''&lt;ref name=whois /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

=== Notable cloning attempts and claims ===
* Dr. [[Panayiotis Zavos]], a Greek-American fertility doctor, revealed on 17 January 2004 at a London press conference that he had transferred a freshly cloned embryo into a 35-year-old woman. On 4 February 2004, it emerged that the attempt had not worked and the woman did not become pregnant.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/health/article-207372/Human-clone-attempt-fails.html|title=Human clone attempt fails | location=London | work=Daily Mail}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/3459009.stm|title=Human cloning attempt has failed | work=BBC News | date=4 February 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Popularization==
There are two types of popularization of human cloning; the popularization that critiques its ethics and implications, and the ones that advocate its uses and benefits to society. Popular media has a strong hold on its coverage, and can sometimes sway views{{citation needed|date=November 2011}}. In an article in the November 8, 1993 article of [[Time Magazine]], cloning was portrayed in a negative way, modifying Michelangelo's ''[[Creation of Adam]]'' to depict Adam with five identical hands. [[Newsweek Magazine]]'s March 10, 1997 issue also critiqued the ethics of human cloning, and included a graphic depicting identical babies in beakers.  There are also many books that critique the ethics of human cloning. One such book is [[Aldous Huxley]]'s [[Brave New World]], which satirically describes a world in which gene therapy and human cloning have destroyed any sense of individuality. On the other hand, there are organizations  that attempt to portray cloning more positively, through such ideas as organ donation from cloned species. Groups like these advocate human cloning's uses and benefits to the majority of society.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Hopkins|first=Patrick|title=How Popular media represent cloning as an ethical problem|jstor=3527566|publisher=The Hastings Center}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ethical implications==
{{See also|Ethics of cloning}}
Advocates of human [[Somatic cell nuclear transfer|therapeutic cloning]] believe the practice could provide genetically identical cells for [[regenerative medicine]], and tissues and organs for transplantation. Such cells, tissues and organs would neither trigger an immune response nor require the use of [[Immunosuppressive drug]]s&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Lanza RP, Chung HY, Yoo JJ, ''et al.'' |title=Generation of histocompatible tissues using nuclear transplantation |journal=Nat. Biotechnol. |volume=20 |issue=7 |pages=689–96 |year=2002 |month=July |pmid=12089553 |doi=10.1038/nbt703}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both basic research and therapeutic development for serious diseases such as [[cancer]], [[heart disease]] and [[Diabetes mellitus|diabetes]], as well as improvements in burn treatment and reconstructive and [[Plastic surgery|cosmetic surgery]], are areas that might benefit from such new technology.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ornl.gov/sci/techresources/Human_Genome/elsi/cloning.shtml#organsQ Cloning Fact Sheet&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Trying to find compatible donors is difficult and can take a long time, but with therapeutic cloning, the speed of this process would increase and compatibility would not be an issue.  

Proponents claim that human [[Cloning#Reproductive cloning|reproductive cloning]] would also produce benefits. [[Severino Antinori]] and [[Panayiotis Zavos]] hope to create a fertility treatment that allows parents who are both infertile to have children with at least some of their DNA in their offspring.&lt;ref&gt;Scientists Prepare To Clone a Human; Experiment Aims to Help Infertile. ''Washington Post'', March 10, 2001&lt;/ref&gt;
Some scientists, including Dr. [[Richard Seed]], suggest that human cloning might obviate the human aging process.&lt;ref&gt;
Cloning touted as infertility solution, Washington Times, December 11, 1997&lt;/ref&gt; Dr. [[Preston Estep]] has suggested the terms &quot;replacement cloning&quot; to describe the generation of a clone of a previously living person, and &quot;persistence cloning&quot; to describe the production of a cloned body for the purpose of obviating aging, although he maintains that such procedures currently should be considered science fiction {{Citation needed|date=August 2007}} and current cloning techniques risk producing a prematurely aged child.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newscientist.com/article/dn3393-dolly-the-sheep-dies-young.html|title=Dolly the sheep dies young|author=Will Knight}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Aubrey de Grey]]'s proposed [[Strategies for Engineered Negligible Senescence|SENS]] (Strategies for Engineered Negligible Senescence), one of the considered options to repair the cell depletion related to cellular [[senescence]] is to grow replacement tissues from stem cells harvested from a cloned embryo.

Human cloning also raises implications of a socio-ethical nature, particularly concerning the role that cloning might play in changing the shape of [[family]] structure by complicating the role of parenting within a family of convoluted kinship relations. For example, a female DNA donor would be the clone's genetic twin, rather than mother, complicating the genetic and social relationships between mother and child as well as the relationships between other family members and the clone.&lt;ref&gt;McGee, Glenn (2000). 'The Perfect Baby: Parenthood in the New World of Cloning and Genetics.' Lanham: Rowman &amp; Littlefield.&lt;/ref&gt;

The high expectations that could be placed on cloned individuals raises questions pertaining the ethics of human cloning and whether these issues are morally problematic as well.  Expectations that the cloned individuals act identically to the human they were cloned could greatly infringe on the right to self-determination.  This term means that all humans should have the right to decide who and what they want to be to some extent.  The cloned children would be violated in knowing that they were genetically induced to act a certain way.  The cloned children may also feel that they are expected to live a life that was predetermined.  &lt;ref name=&quot;Human Cloning Ethics&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Havstad|first=Joyce|title=HUMAN REPRODUCTIVE CLONING: A CONFLICT OF LIBERTIES|work=San Diego State University|publisher=Blackwell Publishing Limited|accessdate=3 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Current law==

===United Nations===
On December 13, 2001, the [[United Nations General Assembly]] began elaborating an international convention against the reproductive cloning of humans. A broad coalition of States, including [[Spain]], [[Italy]], the [[Philippines]], the [[United States]], [[Costa Rica]] and the [[Holy See]] sought to extend the debate to ban all forms of human cloning, noting that, in their view, therapeutic human cloning violates human dignity. Costa Rica proposed the adoption of an international convention to ban all forms of human cloning. Unable to reach a consensus on a binding convention, in March 2005 a non-binding ''[http://www.bioeticaweb.com/content/view/1267/765/lang,es/ United Nations Declaration on Human Cloning]'' calling for the ban of all forms of Human Cloning contrary to human dignity, was adopted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.un.org/law/cloning/
 |title=Ad Hoc Committee on an International Convention against the Reproductive Cloning of Human Beings
 |accessdate=2007-01-28 |date=18 May 2005
 |publisher=United Nations}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Australia===
Australia had prohibited human cloning,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nhmrc.gov.au/publications/synopses/prohibitsyn.htm Prohibition of Human Cloning for Reproduction Act 2002] ''National Health and Medical Research Council'', 12 June 2007&lt;/ref&gt; though as of December 2006, a bill legalising therapeutic cloning and the creation of human embryos for stem cell research passed the House of Representatives. Within certain regulatory limits, and subject to the effect of state legislation, therapeutic cloning is now legal in some parts of Australia.

===European Union===
The European Convention on Human Rights and Biomedicine prohibits human cloning in one of its additional protocols, but this protocol has been ratified only by [[Greece]], [[Spain]] and [[Portugal]]. The [[Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European Union]] explicitly prohibits reproductive human cloning. The charter is legally binding for the institutions of the [[European Union]] under the [[Treaty of Lisbon]].

===United States===
In 1998, 2001, 2004 and 2007, the [[United States House of Representatives]] voted whether to ban all human cloning, both reproductive and therapeutic. Each time, divisions in the Senate over therapeutic cloning prevented either competing proposal (a ban on both forms or reproductive cloning only) from passing. On March 10, 2010 a bill (HR 4808) was introduced with a section banning federal funding for human cloning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/z?c111:H.R.4808:|title=H. R. 4808 Stem Cell Research Advancement Act of 2009 -- SEC. 498F. Prohibition Against Funding For Human Cloning | date= Mar 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Such a law, if passed, would not prevent research from occurring in private institutions (such as universities) that have both private and federal funding. There are currently no federal laws in the United States which ban cloning completely, and any such laws would raise difficult [[United States Constitution|Constitutional]] questions similar to the issues raised by [[abortion]]. Thirteen American states ([[Arkansas]], [[California]], [[Connecticut]], [[Iowa]], [[Indiana]], [[Massachusetts]], [[Maryland]], [[Michigan]], [[North Dakota]], [[New Jersey]], [[Rhode Island]], [[South Dakota]], [[Virginia]]) ban reproductive cloning and three states ([[Arizona]], [[Maryland]], [[Missouri]]) prohibit use of public funds for such activities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.ncsl.org/default.aspx?tabid=14284 | title=Human Cloning Laws | publisher=National Conference of State Legislatures (NCSL) | date=Jan 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
On January 14, 2001 the [[Government of the United Kingdom|British government]] passed The Human Fertilisation and Embryology (Research Purposes) Regulations 2001&lt;ref&gt;{{UK-LEG|title=Human Fertilisation and Embryology (Research Purposes) Regulations 2001 (No. 188)|path=uksi/2001/188/contents/made|asmade=yes)}}&lt;/ref&gt; to amend the [[Human Fertilisation and Embryology Act 1990]] by extending allowable reasons for embryo research to permit research around stem cells and cell nuclear replacement, thus allowing [[Somatic cell nuclear transfer|therapeutic cloning]]. However, on 15 November 2001, a [[Pro-life movement|pro-life]] group won a [[High Court of Justice|High Court]] legal challenge, which struck down the regulation and effectively left all forms of cloning unregulated in the UK. Their hope was that Parliament would fill this gap by passing prohibitive legislation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite |title=Medical Law and Ethics |author=SD Pattinson |year=2006 |publisher=Sweet &amp; Maxwell |isbn=978-0-421-88950-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/sci/tech/1657707.stm |title=Campaigners win cloning challenge |publisher=BBC News |date=15 November 2001 |accessdate=2008-09-06 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Parliament was quick to pass the [[Human Reproductive Cloning Act 2001]] which explicitly prohibited reproductive cloning. The remaining gap with regard to therapeutic cloning was closed when the appeals courts reversed the previous decision of the High Court.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/2846265.stm|title=Lords uphold cloning law|newspaper=[[BBC News Online]]|date=13 March 2003 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first licence was granted on August 11, 2004 to researchers at the [[Newcastle University|University of Newcastle]] to allow them to investigate treatments for [[Diabetes mellitus|diabetes]], [[Parkinson's disease]] and [[Alzheimer's disease]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hfea.gov.uk/en/1048.html |publisher=[[Human Fertilisation and Embryology Authority|HFEA]] |title=HFEA grants the first therapeutic cloning licence for research |date=11 August 2004 |accessdate=2008-09-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Human Fertilisation and Embryology Act 2008]], a major review of fertility legislation, repealed the 2001 Cloning Act by making amendments of similar effect to the 1990 Act. The 2008 Act also allows experiments on hybrid human-animal embryos.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/politics/7682722.stm|title=MPs support embryology proposals|newspaper=[[BBC News Online]]|date=23 October 2008 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Canada===
Canadian law prohibits the following: cloning humans, cloning stem cells, growing human embryos for research purposes, sex selection, and buying or selling of embryos, sperm, eggs or other human reproductive material. It also bans making changes to human DNA that would pass from one generation to the next, including use of animal DNA in humans.  Surrogate mothers are legally allowed, as is donation of sperm or eggs for reproductive purposes.  Human embryos and stem cells are also permitted to be donated for research.

There have been consistent calls in Canada to ban human reproductive cloning since the 1993 Report of the Royal Commission on New Reproductive Technologies. Polls have indicated that an overwhelming majority of Canadians oppose human reproductive cloning, though the regulation of human cloning continues to be a significant national and international policy issue.  The notion of &quot;human dignity&quot; is commonly used to justify cloning laws. The basis for this justification is that reproductive human cloning necessarily infringes notions of human dignity.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Overview of World Human Cloning Policies.&quot; Connexions - Sharing Knowledge and Building Communities. N.p., n.d. Web. 29 Nov. 2011. http://cnx.org/content/m14834/latest/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Canada Bans Human Cloning - Research and Read Books, Journals, Articles at Questia Online Library.&quot; Questia - The Online Library of Books and Journals. N.p., n.d. Web. 7 Dec. 2011. http://www.questia.com/googleScholar.qst?docId=5006805131.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Canada Closes Door on Cloning .&quot; Wired.com . N.p., n.d. Web. 29 Nov. 2011. &lt;http://www.wired.com/medtech/health/news/2004/03/62695&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Regulating and treating conception problems - Health - CBC News.&quot; CBC.ca - Canadian News Sports Entertainment Kids Docs Radio TV. N.p., n.d. Web. 7 Dec. 2011. http://www.cbc.ca/news/health/story/2009/02/05/f-reprotech.html.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Religious objections==
The Roman Catholic Church, under the papacy of [[Benedict XVI]], has condemned the practice of human cloning, in the magisterial instruction [[Dignitas Personae]], stating that it represents a &quot;grave offense to the dignity of that person as well as to the fundamental equality of all people.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/12/12/AR2008121200774.html | work=The Washington Post | first1=Rob | last1=Stein | first2=Michelle | last2=Boorstein | title=Vatican Ethics Guide Stirs Controversy | date=13 December 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Sunni Muslims]] can potentially subscribe to considering human cloning to be forbidden by [[Islam]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.islamonline.net/servlet/Satellite?pagename=IslamOnline-English-Ask_Scholar/FatwaE/FatwaE&amp;cid=1119503544346&lt;/ref&gt; The [[International Islamic Fiqh Academy, Jeddah|Islamic Fiqh Academy]], in its Tenth Conference proceedings, which was convened in [[Jeddah]], [[Saudi Arabia]] in the period from June 28, 1997 to July 3, 1997, issued a [[Fatwā]] stating that human cloning is [[haraam]] (sinful).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.islamonline.net/servlet/Satellite?cid=1237705860017&amp;pagename=IslamOnline-English-Ask_Scholar%2FFatwaE%2FFatwaEAskTheScholar&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.islam-qa.com/en/ref/21582/clone Islam Question and Answer - Ruling on cloning of human beings&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  Importantly, it is not incumbent upon Muslims to subscribe to the [[Fatwa]] of any authority they do not themselves choose to accept as legally binding.

==In popular culture==
 
Cloning is a recurring theme in a wide variety of contemporary [[science fiction]], ranging from action films such as the 2000 film ''[[The 6th Day]]'' to comedies such as [[Woody Allen]]'s 1973 film ''[[Sleeper (1973 film)|Sleeper]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0070707/ IMDB]&lt;/ref&gt;

Cloning has been used in fiction as a way of recreating historical figures. In the 1976 [[Ira Levin]] novel ''[[The Boys from Brazil (novel)|The Boys from Brazil]]'' and its [[The Boys from Brazil (film)|1978 film adaptation]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0077269/ IMDB]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Josef Mengele]] uses cloning to create copies of [[Adolf Hitler]]. ''A Parade of Mirrors and Reflections'', a novella by [[Anatoly Kudryavitsky]], centers on the cloning of deceased Soviet premier [[Yuri Andropov]].&lt;!-- suspected spam reference here as the webpage is unrelated and sells fiction books and so has been commented out &lt;ref&gt;[http://honeycombpress.webs.com/ Honeycomb Press]&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

Several works of fiction portray a future in which human cloning has become the normal process of reproduction for various reasons. [[Aldous Huxley]]'s 1932 novel ''[[Brave New World]]'' envisions a futuristic world in which large numbers of clones are cultivated industrially and conditioned before birth for specific [[castes]].

The implications of using clones to replace deceased loved ones are explored in several works of fiction. In [[Margaret Peterson Haddix]]'s novel ''[[Double Identity (novel)|Double Identity]]'', the main character discovers that she is a clone of her deceased older sister.

A recurring sub-theme of cloning fiction is the use of clones as a supply of [[Organ (anatomy)|organs]] for [[Organ transplant|transplantation]]. The 2005 [[Kazuo Ishiguro]] novel ''[[Never Let Me Go (novel)|Never Let Me Go]]'' and the [[Never Let Me Go (2010 film)|2010 film adaption]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1334260/ IMDB]&lt;/ref&gt; are set in an [[alternate history]] in which cloned humans are created for the sole purpose of providing organ donations to naturally born humans, despite the fact that they are fully sentient and self-aware. The 2005 film ''[[The Island (2005 film)|The Island]]''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0399201/ IMDB]&lt;/ref&gt; revolves around a similar plot, with the exception that the clones are unaware of the reason for their existence.

The use of human cloning for military purposes has also been explored in several works. The [[Clone Wars (Star Wars)|Clone Wars]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1185834/ IMDB]&lt;/ref&gt; portrayed in the ''[[Star Wars]]'' franchise depicts the use of clones to rapidly create a well-trained and expendable army (Specified as being more adaptive than the droids used by the opposing military force for the same purpose).

The exploitation of human clones for dangerous and undesirable work was examined in the 2009 British science fiction film [[Moon (film)|Moon]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1182345/ IMDB]&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* [[Robert Araujo (Jurist)|Araujo, Robert John]], “The UN Declaration on Human Cloning: a survey and assessment of the debate,” 7 The National Catholic Bioethics Quarterly 129 - 149 (2007).

==External links==
{{Wikibooks|Genes, Technology and Policy}}
*[http://www.biomedcentral.com/1472-6939/5/9 &quot;Variations and voids: the regulation of human cloning around the world&quot;] academic article by S. Pattinson &amp; T. Caulfield
*[http://www.theatlantic.com/unbound/flashbks/cloning/watson.htm Moving Toward the Clonal Man]
*[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/jacob-m-appel/should-we-really-fear-rep_b_183308.html Should We Really Fear Reproductive Human Cloning]
*[http://www.philforhumanity.com/Human_Cloning.html The Pros and Cons of Human Cloning]
*[http://www.buzzle.com/articles/ethical-issues-of-cloning.html]
*[http://www.articlesbase.com/diseases-and-conditions-articles/disadvantages-of-human-cloning-461241.html]
* [http://www.jura.uni-augsburg.de/forschung/medizinrecht/medienverzeichnis/pdf_datein_fuer_downloads/uno_klonkonvention.pdf United Nation declares law against cloning.]
* [http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2005/ga10333.doc.htm GENERAL ASSEMBLY ADOPTS UNITED NATIONS DECLARATION ON HUMAN CLONING BY VOTE OF 84-34-37]
*[http://www.ornl.gov/sci/techresources/Human_Genome/elsi/cloning.shtml Cloning Fact Sheet]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Human Cloning}}
[[Category:Biotechnology]]
[[Category:Cloning]]

[[bn:মানব ক্লোনিং]]
[[eu:Giza klonazio]]
[[fa:تاگ‌سازی انسان]]
[[fr:Clonage humain]]
[[it:Clonazione umana]]
[[lt:Žmogaus klonavimas]]
[[pl:Klonowanie ludzi]]
[[pt:Clonagem humana]]
[[ru:Клонирование человека]]
[[simple:Human cloning]]
[[sh:Ljudsko kloniranje]]
[[ta:மாந்தர் படியாக்கம்]]
[[uk:Клонування людини]]
[[zh:克隆人]]</text>
      <sha1>hrpbnr3f0w5sbf0wydjjxlg1avs8jjs</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
