<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Race and intelligence</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>26494</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520980216</id>
      <parentid>520970885</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T00:18:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>FiachraByrne</username>
        <id>13948933</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted to revision 520517318 by 176.250.183.220: Edit is nonsensical - possibly just poor grammar. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="121909">{{Multiple issues|pov=October 2012|unbalanced=October 2012|disputed=October 2012}}

{{human intelligence}}
{{Race}}
The connection between '''race and intelligence''' has been a subject of debate in both [[popular science]] and [[academic research]] since the inception of [[intelligence quotient]] (IQ) testing in the early 20th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hunt &amp; Carlson 2007&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Hunt|Carlson|2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is no widely accepted formal definition of either [[Race (classification of humans)|race]] or [[intelligence]] in academia,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Sternberg|first=Robert J.|title=The Cambridge Handbook of Intelligence|year=2011|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=9780521518062|pages=295|url=http://books.google.ie/books?id=FtYeTcNwzQ4C&amp;pg=PA295&amp;lpg=PA295&amp;dq=%22As+with+race,+there+is+no+universally+accepted+definition+of+intelligence.%22#v=onepage&amp;q=%22As%20with%20race%2C%20there%20is%20no%20universally%20accepted%20definition%20of%20intelligence.%22&amp;f=false|coauthors=Scott Barry Kaufman}}&lt;/ref&gt;  and any discussion of their connection involves studies from multiple disciplines, including [[psychology]], [[anthropology]], [[biology]], and [[sociology]].

IQ tests performed in the United States have proved inconsistent demonstrating a significant degree of variation between different [[Race in the United States|racial groups]], with average scores varying, between those with African ancestry, European and East Asian. While the existence of racial IQ gaps is well-documented and not subject to much dispute, there is no consensus among researchers as to their cause. Research into potential genetic causes for intellectual differences between races is controversial and has generated heated debate.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Regalado|2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some researchers fear that the findings could be misused to perpetuate racial stereotypes, while others contend that the politicization of the field threatens to stifle important avenues of research.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Ramos|first=Edward|coauthors=Knerr, Sarah; Nowinski, Juleigh; Dixon, Keianna; Bonham, Vence L.|title=Human difference in the genomic era: Facilitating a socially responsible dialogue|journal=BMC Medical Genomics|date=26 May 2010|year=2010|month=May|volume=3|doi=10.1186/1755-8794-3-20|url=http://www.biomedcentral.com/1755-8794/3/20/|accessdate=18 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ceci &amp; Williams 2009&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Ceci|Williams|2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Four contemporary classifications of position regarding study of differences in IQ based on race/ethnicity are seen. The first is that these gaps reflect a real difference in average group intelligence, which is caused by a combination of environmental factors and heritable differences in brain function. A second position is that differences in average cognitive ability between races exist and are caused entirely by social and/or environmental factors. A third position holds that differences in average cognitive ability between races do not exist, and that the differences in average test scores are the result of inappropriate use of the tests themselves. Finally, a fourth position is that either or both of the concepts of [[race (classification of humans)|race]] and [[general intelligence factor|general intelligence]] are poorly constructed and therefore any comparisons between races are meaningless.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hunt &amp; Carlson 2007&quot;/&gt;

The [[American Psychological Association]] has said that while there are differences in average IQ between racial groups, and there is no conclusive evidence for environmental explanations, &quot;there is certainly no [direct empirical] support for a genetic interpretation,&quot; and no adequate explanation for the racial IQ gap is presently available.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schacter, Gilbert &amp; Wegner 2007&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schacter|Gilbert|Wegner|2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Neisser et al. 1996&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Neisser et al.|1996}} &quot;The differential between the mean intelligence test scores of Blacks and Whites (about one standard deviation, although it may be diminishing) does not result from any obvious biases in test construction and administration, nor does it simply reflect differences in socio-economic status. Explanations based on factors of caste and culture may be appropriate, but so far have little direct empirical support. There is certainly no such support for a genetic interpretation. At present, no one knows what causes this differential.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The position of the [[American Anthropological Association]] is that intelligence cannot be biologically determined by race.&lt;ref name=&quot;AAA 1994&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|AAA|1994}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to a 1996 statement from the [[American Association of Physical Anthropologists]], although heredity influences behavior in individuals, it does not affect the ability of a population to function in any social setting, all peoples &quot;possess equal biological ability to assimilate any human culture&quot; and &quot;racist political doctrines find no foundation in scientific knowledge concerning modern or past human populations.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;AAPA 1996&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|AAPA|1996}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History of the debate==
{{summarize|from|History of the race and intelligence controversy|date=March 2011}}
{{Main|History of the race and intelligence controversy}}
{{See also|Scientific racism}}
[[File:Alfred Binet.jpg|160px|thumb|[[Alfred Binet]] (1857–1911), inventor of the first intelligence test.]]
The history of the race and intelligence controversy concerns the historical development of a debate, primarily in the United States, concerning possible explanations of group differences in scores on intelligence tests. Historically there have been differences among average scores in IQ tests of different population groups; these have sometimes been called &quot;racial IQ gaps&quot;. Researchers believe that environmental (socioeconomic and cultural) factors contribute to this, but have not agreed on whether the gaps are due to environmental factors alone, or whether there is any genetic contribution that can be substantiated.

Claims of races having different intelligence were used to justify [[colonialism]], [[slavery]], [[social darwinism]], and racial [[eugenic]]s. In the late 19th and early 20th centuries, group differences in intelligence were assumed to be due to race and, apart from intelligence tests, research relied on measurements such as brain size or reaction times. The first IQ test was created between 1905 and 1908 and revised in 1916 (the [[Stanford–Binet Intelligence Scales]]). [[Alfred Binet]], the developer of these tests, warned that these should not be used to measure innate intelligence or to label individuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Plotnik|Kouyoumdjian|2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, at the time there was great concern in the United States about the abilities and skills of recent immigrants. Different nationalities were sometimes thought to comprise different races, such as [[Slavs]]. The tests were used to evaluate draftees for World War I, and researchers found that people of southern and eastern Europe scored lower than native-born Americans. At the time, such data was used to construct an ethnically based social hierarchy, one in which immigrants were rejected as unfit for service and mentally defective. It was not until later that researchers realized that lower language skills by new English speakers affected their scores on the tests.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Gould|1981}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1920s, many scientists reacted to [[eugenicist]] claims linking abilities and moral character to racial or genetic ancestry. Despite that, states like Virginia enacted laws based in eugenics, such as its [[1924 Racial Integrity Act]], which established the [[one-drop rule]] as law.  Generally, understanding grew about the contribution of environment to test-taking and results (such as having English as a second language).&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Pickren|Rutherford|2010|p=163}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the mid-1930s most US psychologists had adopted the view that environmental and cultural factors played a dominant role. In addition, psychologists were reluctant to risk being associated with the [[Germans|German]] [[Nazi]] claims of a &quot;[[master race]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ludy 2006&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Ludy|2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1969, [[Arthur Jensen]] revived the hereditarian point of view in the article, &quot;[[How Much Can We Boost IQ and Scholastic Achievement?]]&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jensen 1969&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Jensen|1969|p=82}}&lt;/ref&gt; It followed changes in public programs introduced to try to correct decades of discrimination against poor African Americans.  In 1954, the US Supreme Court ruled in ''[[Brown v. Board of Education]]'' that public school segregation was unconstitutional. As part of the [[Great Society]] programs under President [[Lyndon Johnson]], the [[Head Start Program]] was started with the goal of early intervention to help socially disadvantaged children succeed by providing remedial education. Given the effects of segregation and discrimination into the 1960s, many Head Start programs served African-American children.

Jensen's article questioned remedial education for African-American children; he suggested their poor educational performance reflected an underlying genetic cause rather than lack of stimulation at home.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Alland|2002|pages=79–80}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jensen's work, publicized by the Nobel laureate physicist [[William Shockley]], sparked controversy amongst the academic community and student protests.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tucker 2002&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Tucker|2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Wooldridge|1995}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In their 1988 book ''[[The IQ Controversy, the Media and Public Policy (book)|The IQ Controversy, the Media, and Public Policy]]'', Mark Snyderman and Stanley Rothman claimed to document a liberal bias in the media coverage of scientific findings regarding IQ. The book builds on the results of a survey of more than 600 psychologists, sociologists and educationalists. 45 percent of those surveyed thought that black-white differences in IQ were the product of both genetic and environmental variation, while 15 percent believed that the differences were entirely due to environmental factors; the rest either declined to answer the question, or thought that there was insufficient evidence to give an answer.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Snyderman|Rothman|1987|pages=137–144}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another debate followed the appearance of ''[[The Bell Curve]]'' (1994), a book by [[Richard Herrnstein]] and [[Charles Murray (author)|Charles Murray]], who argued in favor of the hereditarian viewpoint. It provoked the publication of several interdisciplinary books representing the environmental point of view, as well as some in [[popular science]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Mackintosh 1998&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Mackintosh|1998}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Maltby, Day &amp; Macaskill 2007&quot;/&gt; They include ''[[The Bell Curve Debate]]'' (1995), ''[[Inequality by Design: Cracking the Bell Curve Myth]]'' (1996) and a second edition of ''[[The Mismeasure of Man]]'' (1996) by [[Steven J. Gould]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Maltby, Day &amp; Macaskill 2007&quot;/&gt; One book written from the hereditarian point of view at this time was ''[[The g Factor|The g Factor: The science of mental ability]]'' (1998) by Jensen. In 1994 a group of 52 scientists, including leading hereditarians, signed the statement &quot;[[Mainstream Science on Intelligence]]&quot;. ''The Bell Curve'' also led to a 1995 report from the [[American Psychological Association]], &quot;[[Intelligence: Knowns and Unknowns]]&quot;, acknowledging a gap between average IQ scores of whites and blacks as well as the absence of any adequate explanation of it, either environmental or genetic.

The review article &quot;Thirty Years of Research on Race Differences in Cognitive Ability&quot; by Rushton and Jensen was published in 2005.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rushton &amp; Jensen 2005&quot;/&gt; The article was followed by a series of responses, some in support, some critical.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ludy 2006&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Rouvroy|2008|p=86}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Richard Nisbett]], another psychologist who had also commented at the time, later included an amplified version of his critique as part of the book ''Intelligence and How to Get It: Why Schools and Cultures Count'' (2009).&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Nisbett|2009|pp=209–36}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rushton and Jensen in 2010 made a point-for-point reply to this and again summarized the hereditarian position.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rushton &amp; Jensen 2010&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Rushton|Jensen|2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Two public figures claimed in interviews that one of the main causes for poverty in [[Africa]] is a low average intelligence, an idea which caused great controversy. Following an interview in the monthly supplement of ''[[Helsingin Sanomat]]'', Lynn's coauthor [[Tatu Vanhanen]], a [[political science|political scientist]] and father of the [[Prime Minister of Finland]] [[Matti Vanhanen]], was investigated by the Finnish police between 2002 and 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Helsingin Sanomat|2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007 [[James D. Watson]], Nobel laureate in biology, gave a controversial interview to the [[Sunday Times Magazine]] during a book tour in the [[United Kingdom]]. This interview resulted in the cancellation of a [[Royal Society]] lecture, along with other public engagements, and his suspension from his administrative position at [[Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory]]. He subsequently cancelled the tour and resigned from his position.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|CNN|2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many of the leading hereditarians, mostly psychologists, have received funding from the [[Pioneer Fund]] with Rushton as its current head.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tucker 2002&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Maltby, Day &amp; Macaskill 2007&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Maltby|Day|Macaskill|2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Graves 2002a&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Graves|2002a}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Grossman|Kaufman|2001}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Southern Poverty Law Center]] lists the Pioneer Fund as a [[hate group]], citing the fund's history, its funding of race and intelligence research, and its connections with [[racist]] individuals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Berlet 2003&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Berlet|2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, [[Ulrich Neisser]] writes that &quot;Pioneer has sometimes sponsored useful research—research that otherwise might not have been done at all.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Neisser|2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other sources and researches have criticized the Pioneer Fund for promoting [[scientific racism]], [[eugenics]] and [[white supremacy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Tucker 2002&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pioneerfund.org/Board.html Pioneer Fund Board]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Falk|2008|p=18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Wroe|2008|p=81}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ethics of research==
The 1996 report of the APA had comments on the [[ethics]] of research on race and intelligence.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hunt &amp; Carlson 2007&quot;/&gt; {{harvtxt|Gray|Thompson|2004}} as well as {{harvtxt|Hunt|Carlson|2007}} have also discussed different possible ethical guidelines.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hunt &amp; Carlson 2007&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Gray|Thompson|2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Nature (journal)|''Nature'']] in 2009 featured two editorials on the ethics of research in race and intelligence by [[Steven Rose]] (against) and [[Stephen J. Ceci]] and Wendy M. Williams (for).&lt;ref name= &quot;Rose 2009&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Rose|2009|pp=786–88}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ceci &amp; Williams 2009&quot; /&gt;

According to critics, research will run the risk of simply reproducing the horrendous effects of the social ideologies (such as [[Nazism]] or [[Social Darwinism]]) justified in part on claimed hereditary racial differences.&lt;ref name=&quot;AAA 1994&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=American Anthropological Association |title=Statement on &quot;Race&quot; and Intelligence |year=1994 |url=http://www.aaanet.org/stmts/race.htm |accessdate=March 31, 2010 |ref=harv |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AAA&quot;/&gt; [[Steven Rose]] maintains that the history of [[eugenics]] makes this field of research difficult to reconcile with current ethical standards for science.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rose 2009&quot;/&gt;

[[Linda Gottfredson]] argues that suggestion of higher ethical standards for research into group differences in intelligence is a [[double standard]] applied in order to undermine disliked results.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Gottfredson|2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Flynn, a non-hereditarian, has argued that had there been a ban on research on possibly poorly conceived ideas, much valuable research on intelligence testing (including his own discovery of the [[Flynn effect]]) would not have occurred.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Flynn|2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Validity of &quot;race&quot; and &quot;IQ&quot;==
{{Undue|section|date=April 2011}}
{{Main|Race (classification of humans)|Race and genetics|Intelligence quotient|Intelligence}}

The concept of intelligence and the degree to which it is measurable is and has been a matter of discussion. In ''Psychology'', a psychology textbook by [[Daniel Schacter|Schacter]] [[Daniel Wegner|et]] [[Daniel Gilbert (psychologist)|al.]], the argument is made that while there is a general consensus within western science about how to define intelligence, the concept of intelligence as something that can be unequivocally measured by a single figure is not universally accepted.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schacter, Gilbert &amp; Wegner 2007, pp 350-1&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schacter|Gilbert|Wegner|2007|pp=350–1}}&lt;/ref&gt; A recurring criticism is that different societies value and promote different kinds of skills and that the concept of intelligence is therefore culturally variable and cannot be measured the same in different societies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schacter, Gilbert &amp; Wegner 2007, pp 350-1&quot;/&gt; Consequently, some critics argue that proposed relationships to other variables are necessarily tentative.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sternberg, Grigorenko &amp; Kidd 2005&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Sternberg|Grigorenko|Kidd|2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In fields such as psychology, medicine, economics, political science, criminology, and other research on group differences, [[intelligence]] is commonly measured using [[intelligence quotient]] (IQ) tests.{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}} The statement &quot;[[Mainstream Science on Intelligence]]&quot; argued that &quot;IQ is strongly related, probably more so than any other single measurable human trait, to many important educational, occupational, economic, and social outcomes ... Whatever IQ tests measure, it is of great practical and social importance&quot;. Most of the research on intelligence differences between racial groups is based on IQ testing. These tests are highly correlated with the [[psychometric]] variable ''[[general intelligence factor|g]]'' (for ''general intelligence factor''). Other tests that are also highly correlated with ''g'' are also seen as measures of cognitive ability and have sometimes been used in the research. US examples include the [[Armed Services Vocational Aptitude Battery|Armed Forces Qualifying Test]]; [[SAT]]; [[Graduate Record Examination|GRE]]; [[Graduate Management Admissions Test|GMAT]]; and [[Law School Admission Test|LSAT]]. International student assessment tests that have been used include the [[Trends in International Mathematics and Science Study]], [[Programme for International Student Assessment]], and [[Progress in International Reading Literacy Study]].

Also the concept of race as a meaningful category of analysis is hotly contested. The authors of two articles in two encyclopedias, the ''Encyclopædia Britannica'' and the ''Encyclopedia of Race, Ethnicity and Society'', argue that today the mainstream view is that race is a social construction that is based not mainly in actual biological differences but rather on folk ideologies that construct groups based on social disparities and superficial physical characteristics.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Britannica|2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Schaefer|2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--Britannica is fine. Schaefer unconfirmed--&gt; {{harvtxt|Sternberg|Grigorenko|Kidd|2005}} state that the overwhelming portion of the literature correlating race with identity has tacitly adopted folk definitions of race.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sternberg, Grigorenko &amp; Kidd 2005&quot;/&gt; The [[American Anthropological Association]] in 1998 published a &quot;Statement on 'Race'&quot; which rejected the existence of &quot;races&quot; as unambiguous, clearly demarcated, biologically distinct groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;AAA&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|AAA|1998}}&lt;/ref&gt; Others argue that this view is restricted to certain fields, while in other fields, race is still seen as a valid biological category.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Kaszycka|Štrkalj|Strzałko| 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--Kaszycka unconfirmed.--&gt;

Race in the studies is almost always determined using self-reports, rather than based on analyses of the genetic history of the tested individuals. According to psychologist David Rowe, self-report is the preferred method for racial classification in studies of racial differences because classification based on genetic markers alone ignore the &quot;cultural, behavioral, sociological, psychological, and epidemiological variables&quot; that distinguish racial groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rowe 2005&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Rowe|2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hunt and Carlson write that &quot;Nevertheless, self-identification is a surprisingly reliable guide to genetic composition. {{harvtxt|Tang et al.|2005}} applied mathematical clustering techniques to sort genomic markers for over 3,600 people in the United States and Taiwan into four groups. There was almost perfect agreement between cluster assignment and individuals' self-reports of racial/ethnic identification as White, Black, East Asian, or Latino.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hunt &amp; Carlson 2007&quot;/&gt;

The notions that cluster analysis and the correlation between self-reported race and genetic ancestry support a view of race as primarily based in biology is contradicted by most anthropologists. For example [[C. Loring Brace]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Brace 2005&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Brace|2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; and geneticist [[Joseph L. Graves|Joseph Graves]],&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Graves|2001}}&lt;/ref&gt; have argued that while it is certainly possible to find biological and genetic variation that corresponds roughly to the groupings normally defined as races, this is true for almost all geographically distinct populations. The cluster structure of the genetic data is dependent on the initial hypotheses of the researcher and the populations sampled. When one samples continental groups, the clusters become continental; if one had chosen other sampling patterns, the clusters would be different. {{harvnb|Kaplan|2011}} therefore concludes that while racial groups are characterized by different allele frequencies, this does not mean that racial classification is a natural taxonomy of the human species, because multiple other genetic patterns can be found in human populations that crosscut racial distinctions. In this view, racial groupings are social constructs that have also a biological reality which is largely an artifact of how the category has been constructed.

[[Earl Hunt]] agrees that racial categories are defined by social conventions, though he points out that they also correlate with clusters of both genetic traits and cultural traits. Hunt explains that due to this, racial IQ gaps are caused by these variables that correlate with race, and race itself is rarely a causal variable. Researchers who study racial disparities in test scores are studying the relationship between the scores and the many race-related  factors which could potentially affect performance. These factors include health and wealth, biological differences, and education.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hunt 2010, pp 408–10&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Hunt|2010|pp=408–10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Group differences==

===US test scores===
{{main|Achievement gap in the United States}}
{{harvtxt|Rushton|Jensen|2005}} write that in the [[United States]], self-identified blacks and whites have been the subjects of the greatest number of studies. They state that the black-white IQ difference is about 15 to 18 points or 1 to 1.1 [[standard deviation]]s (SDs), which implies that between 11 and 16 percent of the black population have an IQ above 100 (the white mean). The black-white IQ difference is largest on those components of IQ tests that best represent the [[general intelligence factor]] ''g''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rushton &amp; Jensen 2005&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Rushton|Jensen|2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 1996 APA report &quot;[[Intelligence: Knowns and Unknowns]]&quot; and the 1994 editorial statement &quot;Mainstream Science on Intelligence&quot; gave more or less similar estimates.&lt;ref name=&quot;Neisser et al. 1996&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Gottfredson|1997}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{harvtxt|Roth et al.|2001}}, in a review of the results of a total of 6,246,729 participants on other tests of cognitive ability or aptitude, found a black-white gap of 1.1 SD. Consistent results were found for college and university application tests such as the [[Scholastic Aptitude Test]] (N = 2.4 million) and [[Graduate Record Examination]] (N = 2.3 million), as well as for tests of job applicants in corporate sections (N = 0.5 million) and in the military (N = 0.4 million).&lt;ref name=&quot;Roth et al. 2001&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Roth et al.|2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2006 study by Dickens and Flynn estimated that the black-white gap closed by about 5 or 6 IQ points between 1972 and 2002,&lt;ref name=&quot;Dickens &amp; Flynn 2006&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Dickens|Flynn|2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; which would be a reduction of about one-third. However this was challenged by Rushton &amp; Jensen who claim the gap remains stable.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rushton &amp; Jensen 2006&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Rushton|Jensen|2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a 2006 study, Murray agreed with Dickens and Flynn that there has been a narrowing of the gap; &quot;Dickens' and Flynn's estimate of 3–6 IQ points from a base of about 16–18 points is a useful, though provisional, starting point&quot;. But he argued that this has stalled and that there has been no further narrowing for people born after the late 1970s.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Murray|2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Murray found similar results in a 2007 study.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Murray|2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The IQ distributions of other racial and ethnic groups in the United States are less well-studied. ''The Bell Curve'' (1994) stated that the average IQ of African Americans was 85, Latino 89, White 103, Asian 106, and Jews 113. Asians score relatively higher on visuospatial than on verbal subtests. The few [[Amerindian]] populations who have been systematically tested, including Arctic Natives, tend to score worse on average than white populations but better on average than black populations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Roth et al. 2001&quot;/&gt;

According to several studies, [[Ashkenazi Jew]]s score 0.75 to 1.0 standard deviations above the general European average. This corresponds to an IQ of 112–115. Other studies have found somewhat lower values. During the 20th century, this population made up about 3% of the total US population, but won 27% of the US science [[Nobel Prize]]s and 25% of the [[Turing Award]]s. They have high verbal and mathematical scores, while their visuospatial abilities are typically somewhat lower, by about one half standard deviation, than the European average.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cochran, Hardy &amp; Harpending 2006&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Cochran|Hardy|Harpending|2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; See also [[Ashkenazi Jewish intelligence]].

The racial groups studied in the United States and Europe are not necessarily [[sampling (statistics)|representative samples]] for populations in other parts of the world. Cultural differences may also factor in IQ test performance and outcomes. Therefore, results in the United States and Europe do not necessarily correlate to results in other populations.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Niu|Brass|2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===International comparisons===
{{main|Nations and intelligence}}
The validity and reliability of IQ scores obtained from outside of the United States and Europe have been questioned due to the possibility of test bias as discussed in a later section. Nevertheless, some researchers have attempted to measure IQ variation in a global context.

===Flynn effect===
{{Main|Flynn effect}}

Raw scores on IQ tests have been rising. This score increase, primarily in the lower end of the distribution, is known as the &quot;Flynn effect,&quot; named for [[James R. Flynn]], who did much to document it and promote awareness of its implications. In the United States, the increase has been continuous and approximately linear from the earliest years of testing to the present. For example, in the United States the average scores of blacks on some IQ tests in 1995 were the same as the scores of whites in 1945.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Mackintosh|1998|p=162}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Potential environmental causes==
The following environmental factors are some of those suggested as explaining a portion of the differences in average IQ between races. These factors are not mutually exclusive with one another, and some may in fact contribute directly to others. Furthermore, the relationship between genetics and environmental factors may be complicated. For example, the differences in socioeconomic environment for a child may be due to differences in genetic IQ for the parents,&lt;ref name=&quot;Neisser et al. 1996&quot;/&gt; and the differences in average brain size between races could be the result of nutritional factors.&lt;ref name=&quot;Neisser 1997&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Neisser|1997}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Test bias===
Studies on other groups and in other nations have argued that IQ tests may be biased against certain groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Cronshaw et al.|2006|p=278}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Verney et al.|2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Borsboom|2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Shuttleworth-Edwards et al.|2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; The validity and reliability of IQ scores obtained from outside the United States and Europe have been questioned, in part because of the inherent difficulty of comparing IQ scores between cultures.&lt;ref name=&quot;Richardson 2004&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Richardson|2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hunt &amp; Wittmann 2008&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Hunt|Wittmann|2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Several researchers have argued that cultural differences limit the appropriateness of standard IQ tests in non-industrialized communities.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Irvine|1983}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Irvine|Berry|1988}} a collection of articles by several authors discussing the limits of assessment by intelligence tests in different communities in the world. In particular, {{harvtxt|Reuning|1988}} describes the difficulties in devising and administering tests for Kalahari bushmen.&lt;/ref&gt; In the mid-1970s, for example, the Soviet psychologist [[Alexander Luria]] concluded that it was impossible to devise an IQ test to assess peasant communities in Russia because [[taxonomy]] was alien to their way of reasoning.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Mackintosh|1998|pp=180–2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 1996 report by the [[American Psychological Association]] states that controlled studies show that the black-white IQ gaps are not substantially due to bias in the content or administration of the IQ tests. Furthermore, the tests are equally valid predictors of future achievement for black and white Americans.&lt;ref name=&quot;Neisser et al. 1996&quot;/&gt; This view is reinforced by [[Nicholas Mackintosh]] in his 1998 book ''IQ and Human Intelligence'',&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Mackintosh|1998|p=174}}: &quot;Despite widespread belief to the contrary, however, there is ample evidence, both in Britain and the USA, that IQ tests predict educational attaintment just about as well in ethnic minorities as in the white majority.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; and by a 1999 literature review by {{harvtxt|Brown|Reynolds|Whitaker|1999}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brown|Reynolds|Whitaker|1999}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Stereotype threat===
{{Main|Stereotype threat}}
[[Stereotype threat]] is the fear that one's behavior will confirm an existing [[stereotype]] of a group with which one identifies or by which one is defined; this fear may in turn lead to an impairment of performance.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Aronson|Wilson|Akert| 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Testing situations that highlight the fact that intelligence is being measured tend to lower the scores of individuals from racial-ethnic groups who already score lower on average or are expected to score lower. Stereotype threat conditions cause larger than expected IQ differences among groups, but do not explain the gaps found in non-threatening test conditions.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

===Socioeconomic environment===
According to the report of a 1996 APA task force regarding the US gaps, socioeconomic status (SES) cannot account for all the observed racial-ethnic group differences in IQ. Their first reason for this conclusion is that the black-white test score gap is not eliminated when individuals and groups are matched on SES. Second, excluding extreme conditions, nutritional and biological factors that may vary with SES have shown little effect on IQ. Third, the relationship between IQ and SES is not simply one in which SES determines IQ, but differences in intelligence, particularly parental intelligence, also cause differences in SES, making separating the two factors difficult.&lt;ref name=&quot;Neisser et al. 1996&quot;/&gt;

===Health and nutrition===
&lt;!--Sources cited here should be double-checked for potential SYNTH--&gt;
{{Main|Health and intelligence}}
[[Image:Lead levels children.png|thumb|right|Percentage of children aged 1-5 with blood lead levels ''at least'' 10 µg/dL. Black and Hispanic children have much higher levels than white children. A 10 µg/dL increase in blood lead at 24 months is associated with a 5.8-point decline in IQ.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bellinger, Stiles &amp; Needleman 1992&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Bellinger|Stiles|Needleman|1992}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the Geometric Mean Blood Lead Levels (GM BLL) are declining, a CDC report (2002) states that: &quot;However, the GM BLL for non-Hispanic black children remains higher than that for Mexican-American and non-Hispanic white children, indicating that differences in risk for exposure still persist.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|MMWR|2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

Environmental factors including [[lead]] exposure,&lt;ref name=&quot;Bellinger, Stiles &amp; Needleman 1992&quot;/&gt; [[breast feeding]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Campbell et al. 2002&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Campbell et al.|2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[nutrition]]&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Ivanovic et al.|2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Saloojee| Pettifor|2001}}&lt;/ref&gt; can significantly affect cognitive development and functioning. For example, [[Cretinism|iodine deficiency causes a fall]], on average, of 12 IQ points.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Qian et al.|2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Such impairments may sometimes be permanent, sometimes be partially or wholly compensated for by later growth. The first two years of life is the critical time for malnutrition, the consequences of which are often irreversible and include poor cognitive development, educability, and future economic productivity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thelancet.com/series/maternal-and-child-undernutrition The Lancet Series on Maternal and Child Undernutrition], 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--Which paper? Link points only to to listed series of papers--&gt; The African American population of the United States is statistically more likely to be exposed to many detrimental environmental factors such as poorer neighborhoods, schools, nutrition, and prenatal and postnatal health care.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Nisbett|2009|p=101}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cooper 2005&quot;/&gt;

The [[Copenhagen consensus]] in 2004 stated that lack of both iodine and iron has been implicated in impaired brain development, and this can affect enormous numbers of people: it is estimated that one-third of the total global population are affected by [[iodine deficiency]]. In developing countries, it is estimated that 40% of children aged four and under suffer from [[anaemia]] because of insufficient iron in their diets.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Behrman|Alderman|Hoddinott|2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{harvtxt|Eppig|Fincher|Thornhill|2010}} argue that &quot;From an energetics standpoint, a developing human will have difficulty building a brain and fighting off [[infectious disease]]s at the same time, as both are very metabolically costly tasks&quot; and that differences in prevalence of infectious diseases (such as [[malaria]]) may be an important explanation for differences in IQ between different regions of the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eppig|Fincher|Thornhill|2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; They tested other hypotheses as well, including genetic explanations, concluding that infectious disease was &quot;the best predictor&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eppig 2011&quot;/&gt; Christopher Hassall and Thomas Sherratt repeated the analysis, and concluded &quot;that infectious disease may be the only really important predictor of average national IQ&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eppig 2011&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Eppig|2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In order to mitigate the effects of education on IQ, {{harvtxt|Eppig|Fincher|Thornhill|2010}} repeated their analysis across the United States where standardized and compulsory education exists.&lt;ref name = &quot;Eppig 2011&quot;/&gt; The correlation between infectious disease and average IQ was confirmed, and they concluded that the &quot;evidence suggests that infectious disease is a primary cause of the global variation in human intelligence&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eppig 2011&quot;/&gt;

===Education===
Several studies have proposed that a large part of the gap can be attributed to differences in quality of education.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Manly et al.|2002}} and {{harvnb|Manly et al.|2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Racial discrimination]] in education has been proposed as one possible cause of differences in educational quality between races.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Mickelson|2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to a paper by Hala Elhoweris, Kagendo Mutua, Negmeldin Alsheikh and Pauline Holloway, teachers' referral decisions for students to participate in [[gifted education|gifted and talented]] educational programs were influenced in part by the students' ethnicity.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Elhoweris et al.|2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Abecedarian Early Intervention Project]], an intensive early childhood education project, was also able to bring about an average IQ gain of 4.4 points at age 21 in the black children who participated in it compared to controls.&lt;ref name=&quot;Campbell et al. 2002&quot;/&gt; Arthur Jensen agreed that the Abecedarian project demonstrates that education can have a significant effect on IQ, but also said that no educational program thus far has been able to reduce the Black-White IQ gap by more than a third, and that differences in education are thus unlikely to be its only cause.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Miele|2002|p=133}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Rushton and Jensen argue that long-term follow-up of the [[Head Start Program]] found large immediate gains for blacks and whites but that these were quickly lost for the blacks although some remained for whites. They argue that also other more intensive and prolonged educational interventions have not produced lasting effects on IQ or scholastic performance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rushton &amp; Jensen 2005&quot;/&gt; Nisbett argues that they ignore studies such as {{harvtxt|Campbell|Ramey|1994}} which found that at the age 12, 87% black of infants exposed to an intervention had IQs in the normal range (above 85) compared to 56% of controls, and none of the intervention-exposed children were mildly retarded compared to 7% of controls. Other early intervention programs have shown IQ effects in the range of 4–5 points, which are sustained until at least age 8–15. Effects on academic achievement can also be substantial. Nisbett also argues that not only early age intervention can be effective, citing other successful intervention studies from infancy to college.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Nisbett|2005|pp=303–4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Logographic writing system===
Complex [[Logogram|logographic]] writing systems have been proposed as an explanation for the higher visuospatial IQ scores of [[East Asians]]. Critics argue that the causation may be reversed with higher visuospatial ability causing the development of pictorial symbols in writing rather than alphabetic ones. Another argument is that East Asians adopted at birth also score high on IQ tests. Similar relatively higher visuospatial abilities are also found among Inuit and Native Americans whose ancestors migrated from East Asia to the Americas.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Demetriou et al.|2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Bower|2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Caste-like minorities===
A large number of studies have shown that systemically disadvantaged minorities, such as the African American minority of the United States generally perform worse in the educational system and in intelligence tests than the majority groups or less disadvantaged minorities such as immigrant or &quot;voluntary&quot; minorities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Neisser et al. 1996&quot;/&gt; The explanation of these findings may be that children of caste-like minorities, due to the systemic limitations of their prospects of social advancement, do not have &quot;[[effort optimism]]&quot;, i.e. they do not have the confidence that acquiring the skills valued by majority society, such as those skills measured by IQ tests, is worthwhile. They may even deliberately reject certain behaviors seen as &quot;acting white&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Neisser et al. 1996&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ogbu 1978&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Ogbu|1978}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= &quot;Ogbu 1994&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Ogbu|1994}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Goleman|1988}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This argument is also explored in the book ''[[Inequality by Design: Cracking the Bell Curve Myth]]'' (1996) which argues that it is not lower average intelligence that leads to the lower status of racial and ethnic minorities, it is instead their lower status that leads to their lower average intelligence test scores. One example being Jews in the early 20th century in the US who, the authors argue, scored low on IQ tests. To substantiate this claim, the book presents a table comparing social status or caste position with test scores and measures of school success in several countries around the world. Examples include [[Koreans in Japan|Koreans]], [[Peruvians in Japan|Peruvians]] and [[Brazilians in Japan|Brazilians]] in Japan, [[Burakumin]] in Japan, [[Australian Aborigines]], [[Romani people|Romani]] in Czechoslovakia, [[Māori people|Maori]] in New Zealand, [[Afro-Brazilian]]s, [[Indigenous Brazilian]]s, [[Pardo]]s and [[Rural exodus|Rural Exiles]] (as, but not limited to, people from [[Northeast Region, Brazil|Northeast]] in [[Brasília]], [[São Paulo]] and [[Rio de Janeiro]] metropolitan areas, and including [[White Brazilian|a minority of poors of European descent]]) in Brazil, [[Afrikaners]] in South Africa, Catholics in North Ireland, Irish and Scottish in Great Britain, Arabs and [[Sephardi Jews]] in Israel, and [[Dalit]], low caste, and tribal people in India. The authors note, however, that the comparisons made in the table do not represent the results of all relevant findings, that sometimes studies have shown more mixed findings, that the tests and procedures varied greatly from study to study, and that there is no simple way to compare the size of group differences. The statement regarding Arabs in Israel, for example, is based on a news report that, in 1992, 26% of Jewish high school, predominantly Ashkenazim, students passed their matriculation exam as opposed to 15% of Arab students.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer et al.  1996&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Fischer et al.|1996|pp=191–2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jay Gould in the ''The Mismeasure of Man'' also argued that Jews in the early 20th century scored low on IQ tests. Rushton as well as Cochran, Hardy &amp; Harpending have argued that this is a misrepresentation of the studies and that also the early testing support a high average Jewish IQ.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cochran, Hardy &amp; Harpending 2006&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Rushton|1997b|pages=169–80}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Murray replies that purely sociocultural factors like this cannot explain the gap, because the size of the gap on any test is dependent on that test's degree of g-loading. As an example, Murray notes that the test of reciting a string of digits backwards is much more g-loaded than reciting it forwards, and the black-white gap is around twice as large on the first test as on the second. According to Murray, there is no way that culture or motivation could systematically encourage black performance on one test while decreasing it on another, when both tests are provided by the same examiner in the same setting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Murray 2005&quot;/&gt;

===Cultural traditions valuing education===
Nisbett argues cultural traditions valuing education can explain the high results in the US for Ashkenazi Jews ([[Talmud#Talmud scholarship|Talmud scholarship]]) and East Asians ([[Confucianism]] and the [[Imperial examination]] system).&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Nisbett|2009|pp=158–9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Black subculture===

JR Harris suggested in ''[[The Nurture Assumption]]'' that different peer group cultures may contribute to the black-white IQ gap. She cites the work of Thomas Kindermann, whose [[longitudinal studies]] find that peer groups significantly affect scholastic achievement.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Kindermann|1993}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Genetic arguments==
{{POV-section|date=December 2011}}A number of scientists, supported by the American Anthropological Association,&lt;ref name=&quot;AAA 1994&quot;/&gt; reject any genetic contribution to racial IQ gaps.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Nisbett|2009|p=198}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name =&quot;Mountain &amp; Risch 2004&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Mountain|Risch|2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; The American Psychological Association, while maintaining the causes of the gap are presently unknown, stated that &quot;what little [direct evidence] there is fails to support the genetic hypothesis.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Neisser et al. 1996&quot;/&gt; Jensen &amp; Rushton and Herrnstein &amp; Murray, however, argue that there is a substantial (50–80% in the US according to Rushton and Jensen) genetic contribution to the black-white IQ gap.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rushton &amp; Jensen 2005&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rushton &amp; Jensen 2010&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Herrnstein|Murray|1994}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Evolutionary theories===
{{undue|date=December 2011}}
{{see also|Evolution of human intelligence}}

One explanation for racial IQ gaps advanced by some researchers is that they are partly the result of evolutionary pressures that varied between geographic regions. [[C. Loring Brace]] has argued that such a [[Cline (biology)|clinal]] distribution in the trait is highly improbable, because the evolution of human intelligence is founded on the development of human linguistic behavior, and intelligence is therefore of equal survival value to all human groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brace|1999}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, cultural psychologist Richard Nisbett has argued that &quot;(t)here are a hundred ways that a genetic difference in intelligence could have arisen – either in favor of whites or in favor of blacks.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Nisbett|2009|p=94}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Arthur Jensen explains in ''The g Factor'' how evolutionary factors could have potentially contributed to racial IQ gaps.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Jensen|1998|pp=434–6}}&lt;/ref&gt; J. Philippe Rushton carries this idea a step further in ''[[Race, Evolution, and Behavior]]'', proposing that human groups differ in intelligence due to [[r/K selection theory]], with Africans being more r-selected and Asians more K-selected.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Rushton|1995}}&lt;/ref&gt;

C. Loring Brace regards evolutionary explanations for racial IQ gaps as unfounded speculation.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Brace|2005|pp=265–6}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Regarding Rushton’s application of r/K selection to human groups, [[Joseph L. Graves]] argues that not only is r/K selection theory considered to be virtually useless when applied to human life history evolution, but Rushton himself does not apply the theory correctly, and displays a lack of understanding evolution in general.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Graves|2002b}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Genetics of Race and intelligence===
{{main|Race and genetics|Genetics and intelligence}}
{{Undue|section|date=April 2011}}
The decoding of the [[human genome]] has enabled scientists to search for sections of the genome that contribute to cognitive abilities, and there are also ways to study whether the differences in frequency of particular genetic variants between populations contribute to differences in average cognitive abilities. However the geneticist, [[Alan R. Templeton]] has argued that this question is muddled by the general focus on &quot;race&quot; rather than on populations defined by gene frequency or by geographical proximity, and by the general insistence on phrasing the question in terms of heritability of intelligence. Templeton argues that racial groups neither represent [[sub-species]] or distinct [[Lineage (evolution)|evolutionary lineage]]s, and that therefore there is no basis for making claims about the general intelligence of races. He also argues that phrasing the question in terms of heritability is useless since heritability applies only within groups, but cannot be used to compare traits across groups. Templeton argues that the only way to design a study of the genetic contribution to intelligence is to the correlation between degree of geographic ancestry and cognitive abilities. He argues that this would require a [[Gregor Mendel|Mendelian]] experimental design where specimens with different hybrid compositions are subjected to the same environmental influences, and he further argues that when this design has been carried out, it has shown no significant correlation between any cognitive ability and the degree of African or European ancestry.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Templeton|2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Intelligence is both a quantitative and [[polygenic trait]]. This means that intelligence is under the influence of several genes, possibly several thousand. The effect of most individual genetic variants on intelligence is thought to be very small, well below 1% of the variance in ''g''. Current studies using [[quantitative trait loci]] have yielded little success in the search for genes influencing intelligence. [[Robert Plomin]] is confident that QTLs responsible for the variation in IQ scores exist, but due to their small effect sizes, more powerful tools of analysis will be required to detect them.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Plomin|Kennedy|Craig|2005|p=513}}&lt;/ref&gt; Others assert that no useful answers can be reasonably expected from such research before an understanding of the relation between DNA and human phenotypes emerges.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cooper 2005&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Cooper|2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some researchers have expressed reluctance to investigate possible links between genes and intelligence, due to the controversy it can produce.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Regalado|2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2005 literature review article on the links between race and intelligence in ''[[American Psychologist]]'' stated that no gene has been shown to be linked to intelligence, &quot;so attempts to provide a compelling genetic link of race to intelligence are not feasible at this time&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Sternberg|Grigorenko|Kidd|2005|p=46}}&lt;/ref&gt; Several candidate genes have been proposed to have a relationship with intelligence.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Zinkstok et al.|2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Dick et al.|2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, a review of candidate genes for intelligence published in {{harvtxt|Deary|Johnson|Houlihan|2009}} failed to find evidence of an association between these genes and general intelligence, stating &quot;there is still almost no replicated evidence concerning the individual genes, which have variants that contribute to intelligence differences&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deary, Johnson &amp; Houlihan 2009&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Deary|Johnson|Houlihan|2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Heritability within and between groups===
[[Image:Heritability plants.jpeg|thumb| A frequently cited example of an X-factor from [[Richard Lewontin]] describes two populations of corn, one grown in a normal environment, and the other in a nutrient-deficient environment. The height of this corn is 100% heritable when grown in a uniform environment. Therefore, in such a scenario the within-group heritability of height is 100% in both populations, but the substantial differences between groups are due entirely to environmental factors.&lt;ref name=&quot;Block 2002&quot;/&gt; Another example is [[human height]] which is 85-90% heritable but still has increased by a standard deviation or more in a generation or less in several countries of the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rushton &amp; Jensen 2010&quot;/&gt;]]

[[Heritability]] is defined as the proportion of interindividual [[variance]] in a [[trait (biology)|trait]] which is attributable to [[genotype]] within a defined population in a specific environment. A heritability of 1 indicates that variation correlates fully with genetic variation and a heritability of 0 indicates that there is no correlation between the trait and genes at all. There is broad agreement that individual variation in intelligence is neither fully genetic nor fully environmental, but there is little agreement on the relative contribution of genes and environment on individual intelligence.

It has been argued that intelligence is substantially heritable within populations, with 30–50% of variance in IQ scores in early childhood being attributable to genetic factors in analyzed US populations, increasing to 75–80% by late adolescence.&lt;ref name=&quot;Neisser et al. 1996&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Deary, Johnson &amp; Houlihan 2009&quot;/&gt; High heritability does not imply that a trait is genetic or unchangeable, however, as environmental factors that affect all group members equally will not be measured by heritability (see the figure) and the heritability of a trait may also change over time in response to changes in the distribution of genes and environmental factors.&lt;ref name=&quot;Neisser et al. 1996&quot;/&gt; High heritability also doesn't imply that all of the heritability is genetically determined, but can also be due to environmental differences that affect only a certain genetically defined group (indirect heritability).&lt;ref name=&quot;Block 2002&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Block|2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Jensen and Rushton have argued that there may be environmental factors (&quot;X factors&quot;) that are not measured by the heritability figure, but such factors must have the properties of not affecting whites while at the same time affecting all blacks equally, but, the hereditarians argue, no such plausible factors have been found and other statistical tests for the presence of such an influence in the US are negative.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rushton &amp; Jensen 2010&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jensen 1998&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Jensen|1998}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This argument has been criticized by other researchers using several different arguments. Firstly, as noted earlier, Templeton argues that heritability is relevant only for explaining within group variance, cannot be used to explain variation between groups. Secondly the heritability figure of .8 for White American populations have been frequently been criticized as being highly inflated. Another is arguing that there are many environmental factors, sometimes small and subtle, that together add up to a large difference between blacks and whites. Dickens and Flynn argue that the conventional interpretation ignores the role of [[feedback]] between factors, such as those with a small initial IQ advantage, genetic or environmental, seeking out more stimulating environments which will gradually greatly increase their advantage, which, as one consequence in their alternative model, would mean that the &quot;heritability&quot; figure is only in part due to direct effects of genotype on IQ.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hunt &amp; Carlson 2007&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Nisbett|2009|p=212}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dickens &amp; Flynn 2001&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Dickens|Flynn|2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Spearman's hypothesis===
{{Main|Spearman's hypothesis}}
Spearman's hypothesis states that the magnitude of the black-white difference in tests of cognitive ability is entirely or mainly a function of the extent to which a test measures general mental ability, or g. The hypothesis, first formalized by Arthur Jensen in the 1980s based on Charles Spearman's earlier comments on the topic, argues that differences in g are the sole or major source of differences between blacks and whites observed in many studies of race and intelligence. Various criticisms have been advanced and the validity of the arguments remain unresolved.

===Regression toward the mean===
{{undue|date=December 2011}}
Jensen and Rushton argue that [[regression toward the mean]] effects observed in studies comparing blacks and whites with high and low IQs to the IQs of their close relatives provide evidence of a [[polygene]]tic basis for the black/white IQ gap.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Jensen|1973|pp=107–9}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Rushton|2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, other researchers have found Jensen's arguments to be unpersuasive,&lt;ref name=&quot;Flynn 2010&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Flynn|2010|pp=363–6}}&lt;/ref&gt; noting that regression to the mean is merely a statistical artifact and cannot be used to isolate potential causal factors.&lt;ref&gt;''See:''
*{{harvnb|Munsinger|1975}}
*{{harvnb|Horn|1989}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Gradual gap appearance===
{{harvtxt|Fryer|Levitt|2006}} found in test of children aged eight to twelve months only minor differences (0.06 SD) between blacks and whites that disappeared with the inclusion of a limited set of controls including social-economic status.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Fryer|Levitt|2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Flynn has argued that the U.S. black-white gap appear gradually which suggests environmental causes. &quot;At just 10 months old, the average score is only one point behind; by the age of 4, it is 4.6 points behind, and by the age of 24, the gap is 16.6 points. This could be due to genes, but the steady rate after the age of 4 (about 0.6 IQ points lost every year) suggests otherwise, since genetically driven differences such as height differences between males and females tend to kick in at a certain age.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Flynn 2008&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Flynn|2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Rushton and Jensen argue that the black-white IQ difference of one standard deviation is present at the age of 3 and does not change significantly afterward.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rushton &amp; Jensen 2005&quot;/&gt; Murray, also a hereditarian, argues that the heritability of IQ increases with age which is reflected in the racial IQ gaps gradually increasing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Murray 2005&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Murray|2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Uniform rearing conditions===
Several studies have been done on the effect of similar rearing conditions on children from different races.

The [[Minnesota Transracial Adoption Study]] (1976) examined the [[intelligence quotient|IQ test scores]] of 122 [[adopted]] children and 143 nonadopted children reared by advantaged white families. The children were restudied ten years later.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Weinberg|Scarr|Waldman|1992}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Loehlin|2000|p=185}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Three other studies found opposing evidence with none finding higher intelligence in white children than in black children.

{{harvtxt|Moore|1986}} compared black and mixed-race children adopted by either black or white middle-class families in the US. Moore observed that 23 black and interracial children raised by white parents had a significantly higher mean score than 23 age-matched children raised by black parents (117 vs 104), and argued that differences in early socialization explained these differences.

{{harvtxt|Eyferth|1961}} studied the out-of-wedlock children of black and white soldiers stationed in Germany after World War 2 and then raised by white German mothers and found no significant differences. 

{{harvtxt|Tizard et al.|1972}} studied black (African and West Indian), white, and mixed-race children raised in British long-stay residential nurseries. Three out of four tests found no significant differences. One test found higher scores for non-whites.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tizard et al.&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Tizard et al.|1972}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The data is summarized below:
{| align=&quot;center&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! align=&quot;center&quot; | Biological parents
! align=&quot;center&quot; |Number of children
! align=&quot;center&quot; |Average IQ
! align=&quot;center&quot; |Raised by
|-
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; | [[Minnesota Transracial Adoption Study]] (1976) United States
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; |Black
| align=&quot;center&quot; |21
| align=&quot;center&quot; |95/89
| align=&quot;center&quot; |White non-biological couple
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; |Black-white
| align=&quot;center&quot; |55
| align=&quot;center&quot; |110/99
| align=&quot;center&quot; |White non-biological couple
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; |White
| align=&quot;center&quot; |16
| align=&quot;center&quot; |118/106
| align=&quot;center&quot; |White non-biological couple
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; |Asian or Amerindian
| align=&quot;center&quot; |12
| align=&quot;center&quot; |101/99
| align=&quot;center&quot; |White non-biological couple
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; |White
| align=&quot;center&quot; |104
| align=&quot;center&quot; |116/109
| align=&quot;center&quot; |White biological couple
|-
|-
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; | {{harvtxt|Moore|1986}} United States
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; |Black
| align=&quot;center&quot; |17
| align=&quot;center&quot; |102.9
| align=&quot;center&quot; |Black non-biological couple
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; |Black-white
| align=&quot;center&quot; |6
| align=&quot;center&quot; |105.7
| align=&quot;center&quot; |Black non-biological couple
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; |Black
| align=&quot;center&quot; |9
| align=&quot;center&quot; |118.0
| align=&quot;center&quot; |White non-biological couple
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; |Black-white
| align=&quot;center&quot; |14
| align=&quot;center&quot; |116.5
| align=&quot;center&quot; |White non-biological couple
|-
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; | {{harvtxt|Eyferth|1961}} Germany
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; |Black-white
| align=&quot;center&quot; |98
| align=&quot;center&quot; |96.5
| align=&quot;center&quot; |White biological single mother
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; |White
| align=&quot;center&quot; |83
| align=&quot;center&quot; |97.2
| align=&quot;center&quot; |White biological single mother
|-
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; | {{harvtxt|Tizard et al.|1972}} United Kingdom
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; |Black
| align=&quot;center&quot; |15
| align=&quot;center&quot; |105.7
| align=&quot;center&quot; |Long-stay residential nurseries
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; |Black-white
| align=&quot;center&quot; |15
| align=&quot;center&quot; |109.8
| align=&quot;center&quot; |Long-stay residential nurseries
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; |White
| align=&quot;center&quot; |25
| align=&quot;center&quot; |101.3
| align=&quot;center&quot; |Long-stay residential nurseries
|}

===Racial admixture studies===
Many people have an ancestry from different geographic regions. For example, African Americans typically have ancestors from both Africa and Europe, with, on average, 20% of their genome inherited from European ancestors.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Bryc et al.|2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; If racial IQ gaps have a partially genetic basis, blacks with a higher degree of European ancestry should on average have higher IQ, because the genes inherited from European ancestors would likely include some genes with a positive effect on IQ.&lt;ref name=&quot;Loehlin 2000&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Loehlin|2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[John C. Loehlin]] describes several studies that have examined the relationship between ancestry levels and IQ. A 1936 study by Witty and Jenkins examined ancestry among African-Americans with very high IQ, and found that they did not have a higher degree of European ancestry than unselected African-Americans.&lt;ref name=&quot;Loehlin 2000&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Loehlin|2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;  More recent studies have compared IQ to ancestry estimates based on skin color, and found the correlation of skin color to higher IQ (0.1-0.15) to be very low.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nisbett 2009, p 227&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Nisbett|2009|p=227}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nisbett and Jensen have both argued that skin color is a highly imprecise measure of racial ancestry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nisbett 2009, p 227&quot;/&gt;  According to Loehlin, other studies comparing the IQs of mixed-race children to those two black parents or two white parents have produced similarly inconclusive results.&lt;ref name=&quot;Loehlin 2000&quot; /&gt;&lt;!--vague but likely referring here to the mixed-race studies from Scarr/Weinberg and Moore which are now in the uniform rearing section.--&gt;

The frequency of different [[blood type]]s vary with ancestry. Correlations between degree of European blood types and IQ have varied between 0.05 and -0.38 in two studies from 1973 and 1977. Nisbett writes that one problem with these studies is that white blood genes are very weakly associated with one another in the black population, so they are not a reliable method of estimating ancestry.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Nisbett|2009|p=228}}&lt;/ref&gt;  T. Edward Reed, an expert on blood groups, argues that the methodology used in these studies would have been unable to detect any difference, regardless of whether or not the hereditarian hypothesis is correct.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Reed|1997|pp=77–8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some authors have suggested that new studies of the relationship ancestry and IQ should be performed using modern DNA-based ancestry estimations, which would provide a more reliable measure of ancestry than is possible based on skin tone or blood groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rowe 2005&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Rowe|2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lee|2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Brain size===
{{Undue|section|date=April 2011}}
{{Main|Neuroscience and intelligence|Craniometry}}
In a study of the head growth of 633 term-born children, it was shown that prenatal growth and growth during infancy were associated with subsequent IQ. The study's conclusion was that the brain volume a child achieves by the age of 1 year helps determine later intelligence.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Gale et al.|2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Within human populations, [[Magnetic Resonance Imaging]] (MRI) studies conducted to determine whether there is a relationship between brain size and a number of cognitive measures have &quot;yielded inconsistent findings with correlations from 0 to 0.6, with most correlations 0.3 or 0.4.&quot;. For postmortem studies the correlation is about 0.15.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Witelson|Beresh|Kigar|2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; The difference in average brain sizes varies widely from country to country. For instance, the average brain size of the average Maasai person is larger than the average brain size of the average &quot;Caucasoid&quot; person in Egypt.&lt;ref name=&quot;brown.uk.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.brown.uk.com/brownlibrary/INTEL2.htm Cernovsky, Z. Z. (1997)A critical look at intelligence research, In Fox, D. &amp; Prilleltensky, I. (Eds.) Critical Psychology, London: Sage, ps 121-133.]&lt;/ref&gt; According to Z. Z. Cernovsky Rushton's own study&lt;ref&gt;Rushton, J. P. &quot;Race, Brain Size, and Intelligence: A Rejoinder to Cain and Vanderwolf&quot;. Personality and Individual Differences, 11, 785-794.&lt;/ref&gt; shows that the average cranial capacity of North American blacks is similar to that of Caucasians from comparable climatic zones,&lt;ref name=&quot;brown.uk.com&quot;/&gt; 

Several studies have reported that races overlap significantly in brain size but differ in average brain size. The magnitude of these differences varies depending on the particular study and the methods used. In general, these studies have reported that East Asians have on average a larger brain size than whites who have on average a larger brain size than blacks.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Ho et al.|1980a}} and {{harvnb|Ho et al.|1980b}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Jensen|Johnson|1994}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Rushton|1997a}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Rushton|1991}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other researchers have also found variation in average brain size between human groups, but concluded that this variation should be viewed as being based on biogeographic ancestry and independently of &quot;race&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Beals|Smith|Dodd|1984}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Lieberman|2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to an analysis by Jelte Wicherts, the material cited by Rushton is in the form of external or postmortem cranial measurements with none using more modern MRI techniques. Such material only have a correlation of 0.2 with IQ. Furthermore, even using Rushton's data the black-white difference in brain size are small (0.6 SD units) compared to the IQ differences. Wicherts also writes that there is no reason to suppose that brain size is environmentally insensitive. Even if race differences in brain size are assumed to be entirely genetic in origin, they still leave 91–95% of racial IQ gap unaccounted for, the lower number assuming that MRI would show the same results as Rushton's data collection.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wicherts, Borsboom &amp; Dolan&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Wicherts|Borsboom|Dolan|2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Wicherts|Dolan|van der Maas|2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mental chronometry===
{{Main|Mental chronometry}}
[[Mental chronometry]] is an area of research which measures the elapsed time between the presentation of a sensory stimulus and the subsequent behavioral response by the participant. This time is known as reaction time (RT), and is considered a measure of the speed and efficiency with which the brain processes information.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jensen 2006&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Jensen|2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Scores on most types of RT tasks tend to correlate with scores on standard IQ tests as well as with ''g'', and no relationship has been found between RT and any other psychometric factors independent of ''g''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jensen 2006&quot;/&gt; The strength of the correlation with IQ varies from one RT test to another, but [[Hans Eysenck]] gives 0.40 as a typical correlation under favorable conditions.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eysenck|1987}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Jensen individual differences in RT have a substantial genetic component, and heritability is higher for performance on tests that correlate more strongly with IQ.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jensen 1998&quot;/&gt; Nisbett argues that some studies have found correlations closer to 0.2, and that the correlation is not always found.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nisbett 2009&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Nisbett|2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--page number needed--&gt;

Several studies have found differences between races in average reaction times. These studies have generally found that reaction times among black, Asian and white children follow the same pattern as IQ scores.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lynn &amp; Vanhanen 2002&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Lynn|Vanhanen|2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Jensen|Whang|1993}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pesta &amp; Poznanski 2008&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Pesta|Poznanski|2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rushton and Jensen have argued that reaction time is independent of culture and that the existence of race differences in average reaction time is evidence that the cause of racial IQ gaps is partially genetic instead of entirely cultural.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rushton &amp; Jensen 2005&quot;/&gt; Responding to this argument in ''Intelligence and How to Get It'', Nisbett has pointed to the {{harvtxt|Jensen|Whang|1993}} study in which a group of Chinese Americans had longer reaction times than a group of European Americans, despite having higher IQs. Nisbett also mentions findings in {{harvtxt|Flynn|1991}} and {{harvtxt|Deary|2001}} suggesting that movement time (the measure of how long it takes a person to move a finger after making the decision to do so) correlates with IQ just as strongly as reaction time does, and that average movement time is faster for blacks than for whites.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Nisbett|2009|pp=221–2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Policy relevance==
{{Main|Intelligence and public policy}}
Jensen and Rushton argue that the existence of biological group differences does not rule out, but raises questions about the worthiness of policies such as [[affirmative action]] or placing a premium on diversity. They also argue for the importance of teaching people not to overgeneralize or [[stereotype]] individuals based on average group differences, because of the significant overlap of people with varying intelligence between different races.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rushton &amp; Jensen 2005&quot;/&gt;

The environmentalist viewpoint argues for increased interventions in order to close the gaps.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}} Nisbett argues that schools can be greatly improved and that many interventions at every age level are possible.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Nisbett|2009}}&lt;!--page number needed--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; Flynn, arguing for the importance of the black subculture, write that &quot;America will have to address all the aspects of black experience that are disadvantageous, beginning with the regeneration of inner city neighbourhoods and their schools. A resident police office and teacher in every apartment block would be a good start.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Flynn 2008&quot;/&gt; Researchers from both sides agree that interventions should be better researched.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nisbett 2009&quot;/&gt;&lt;!--page number needed--&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rushton &amp; Jensen 2010&quot;/&gt;

Especially in developing nations society has been urged to take on the prevention of cognitive impairment in children as of the highest priority. Possible preventable causes include [[malnutrition]], [[infectious diseases]] such as [[meningitis]], [[parasites]], and cerebral [[malaria]], [[in utero]] [[drug]] and [[alcohol]] exposure, newborn [[asphyxia]], [[low birth weight]], head injuries, and [[endocrine disorders]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Olness 2003&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Olness|2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==

*[[Ashkenazi Jewish intelligence]]
*[[Sex and psychology]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=25em}}

==Bibliography==

{{Refbegin|colwidth=25em}}
&lt;!--Alland 2002--&gt;
*{{cite book |last=Alland |first= Alexander, Jr |title=Race in Mind |year=2002 |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |pages=79–80 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--AAA 1994--&gt;
*{{cite web |publisher=American Anthropological Association |date=December 1994 |url=http://www.aaanet.org/stmts/race.htm |title=American Anthropological Association Statement on 'Race' and Intelligence |ref={{harvid|AAA|1994}} }}
&lt;!--AAA 1998--&gt;
*{{cite web |publisher=American Anthropological Association |date=17 May 1998 |url=http://www.aaanet.org/stmts/racepp.htm |title=American Anthropological Association Statement on 'Race' |ref={{harvid|AAA|1998}} }}
&lt;!--AAPA 1996--&gt;
*{{cite journal |journal=American Journal of Physical Anthropology |volume=101 |pages=569–570|year=1996 |url=http://www.physanth.org/association/position-statements/biological-aspects-of-race/?searchterm=race |title=AAPA Statement on Biological Aspects of Race |ref={{harvid|AAPA|1996}} }}
&lt;!--Aronson, Wilson &amp; Akert 2005--&gt;
*{{cite book |last=Aronson |first=E |last2=Wilson |first2=TD |last3=Akert |first3=AM |year=2005 |title=Social Psychology |edition=5th |location=Upper Saddle River, NJ |publisher=Prentice Hall |isbn=0-13-178686-5 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Bartholomew 2004--&gt;
*{{cite book |first=David J |last=Bartholomew |title=Measuring Intelligence: Facts and Fallacies |year=2004 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=0-521-54478-5 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Beals, Smith &amp; Dodd 1984--&gt;
*{{Cite journal |doi= 10.1086/203138 |last=Beals |first=KL |last2=Smith |first2=CL |last3=Dodd |first3=SM |date=June 1984 |title=Brain size, cranial morphology, climate, and time machines |journal=Current Anthropology |volume=25 |pages=301–30 |issue= 3 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Behrman, Alderman &amp; Hoddincott 2004--&gt;
*{{cite journal |last1=Behrman |first1=JR |last2=Alderman |first2=H |last3=Hoddinott |first3=J |url=http://www.copenhagenconsensus.com/Files/Filer/CC/Papers/sammendrag/Accepted__Hunger_summary_070504.pdf |title=Hunger and Malnutrition |journal=Copenhagen Consensus |year=2004 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Bellinger, Stiles &amp; Needleman 1992--&gt;
*{{cite journal |url=http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/cgi/content/abstract/90/6/855 |title=Low-Level Lead Exposure, Intelligence and Academic Achievement: A Long-term Follow-up Study |first=David C |last=Bellinger |first2=Karen M |last2=Stiles |first3=Herbert L |last3=Needleman |journal=Pediatrics |volume=90 |issue=6 |date=December 1992 |pages=855–61 |ref=harv | pmid = 1437425 }}
&lt;!--Berlet 2003--&gt;
*{{cite journal |publisher=Southern Poverty Law Center |url=http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?aid=50 |title=Into the Mainstream |accessdate= 21 February 2012 |last=Berlet |first=Chip |date=Summer 2003 |issue=110 |journal=Intelligence Report |ref={{harvid|Berlet|2003}} }}
&lt;!--Bird et al. 2004--&gt;
*{{cite journal |title=Cancellation test performance in African American, Hispanic, and white elderly |first=Desiree A |last=Byrd |first2=Pegah |last2=Touradji |first3=Ming-Xin |last3=Tang |first4=Jennifer J |last4=Manly |year=2004 |journal=Journal of the International Neuropsychological Society |doi=10.1017/S1355617704103081 |volume= 10 |issue=3 |pages=401–11|ref={{harvid|Bird et al.|2004}} }}
&lt;!--Block 2002 --&gt;
*{{cite book |last=Block |first=Ned |year=2002 |chapter=How heritability misleads about race |editor-last= Fish |editor-first=Jefferson |title=Race and Intelligence: Separating Science from Myth |publisher=Lawrence Erlbaum and Associates |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Boorsham 2006--&gt;
*{{cite journal |title=The attack of the psychometricians |first=Denny |last=Borsboom |journal=Psychometricka |volume= 71 |issue=3 |pages=425–40 |date=September 2006 |doi=10.1007/s11336-006-1447-6 |ref=harv |pmc=2779444 |pmid=19946599}}
&lt;!--Bower 2005 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |journal=Science News |title=Asian kids' IQ lift: reading system may boost Chinese scores |last=Bower, |first=B |date=12 February 2005  |url=http://www.thefreelibrary.com/Asian+kids'+IQ+lift:+reading+system+may+boost+Chinese+scores.-a0129629064 |ref={{harvid|Bower|2005}} }}
&lt;!--Brace 1999 --&gt;
*{{cite journal | last=Brace | first=C Loring | year=1999 | title=An Anthropological Perspective on 'Race' and Intelligence: The non-clinal nature of human cognitive capabilities | journal=Journal of Anthropological Research | volume=55 | jstor=3631210 | pages=245–64 | issue=2 |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Brace 2005 --&gt;
*{{cite book |last=Brace |first= C. Loring |year=2005 |title= Race is a four letter word |publisher= Oxford University Press |isbn=978-0-19-517351-2 |pages=326 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Britannica 2012--&gt;
*{{cite encyclopedia |year=2012 |title=race |encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Britannica |publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica Inc |edition=Online |url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/488030/race |ref={{harvid|Britannica|2012}} }}
&lt;!--Brown 1999--&gt;
*{{cite journal | doi = 10.1037/h0089007 |last = Brown |first= Robert T |last2=Reynolds |first2=Cecil R |last3=Whitaker |first3=Jean S | year = 1999 | title = Bias in Mental Testing since &quot;Bias in Mental Testing&quot; | url = | journal = School Psychology Quarterly | volume = 14 | issue = 3| pages = 208–38 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Bryc et al. 2009--&gt;
*{{cite journal |year=2009 |first=Katarzyna |last=Bryc |first2=Adam |last2=Autona |first3=Matthew R. |last3=Nelsonb |first4=Jorge R. |last4=Oksenberg |first5=Stephen L. |last5=Hauser |first6=Scott |last6=Williams |first7=Alain |last7=Froment |first8=Jean-Marie |last8=Bodof |first9=Charles |last9=Wambebeg |title=Genome-wide patterns of population structure and admixture in West Africans and African Americans |journal=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America |doi=10.1073/pnas.0909559107 |ref={{harvid|Bryc et al.|2009}} |pmid=20080753 |pmc=2818934 |volume=107 |issue=2 |pages=786–91}}
&lt;!--Campbell &amp; Ramey 1994--&gt;
*{{cite journal |last=Campbell |first=FA |last2=Ramey |first2=CT |year=1994 |title=Effects of early intervention on intellectual and academic achievement: A follow-up study of children from low-income families |journal=Child Development |volume=65 |pages=684–698 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Campbell et al. 2002 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |first=Frances A |last=Campbell |first2=Craig T |last2=Ramey |first3=Elizabeth |last3=Pungello |first4=Joseph |last4=Sparling |first5=Shari |last5=Miller-Johnson |title=Early Childhood Education: Young Adult Outcomes From the Abecedarian Project |journal=Applied Developmental Science |volume= 6 |year= 2002 |pages= 42–57 |ref={{harvid|Campbell et al.|2002}}  }}
&lt;!--Caspi et al. 2007--&gt;
*{{cite journal |last1=Caspi |first1=A |last2= Williams |first2=B |last3=Kim-Cohen |first3=J |last4=Craig |first4=Ian W |last5=Milne |first5=Barry J |last6=Poulton |first6=Richie |last7=Schalkwyk |first7=Leonard C |last8=Taylor |first8=Alan |first9=Helen |last9=Werts |title=Moderation of breastfeeding effects on the IQ by genetic variation in fatty acid metabolism |journal=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences |volume=104 |issue=47 |page=18860 |year=2007 |pmid=17984066 |doi=10.1073/pnas.0704292104 |pmc=2141867 |ref=harv|bibcode = 2007PNAS..10418860C  |ref={{harvid|Caspi et al.|2007}} }}
&lt;!--Ceci 2009--&gt;
*{{cite journal |title=Darwin 200: Should scientists study race and IQ? Yes: the scientific truth must be pursued |last=Ceci |first=SJ |last2=Williams |first2=WM |year=2009 |volume=457 |page=788 |url=http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v457/n7231/full/457788a.html|journal=Nature |doi=10.1038/457788a |issue=7231|bibcode = 2009Natur.457..788C |pmid=19212385 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Cochran, Hardy &amp; Harpending 2006 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |first=G |last=Cochran |first2=J |last2=Hardy |first3=H |last3=Harpending  |url=http://harpending.humanevo.utah.edu/Documents/ashkiq.webpub.pdf |title=Natural History of Ashkenazi Intelligence |journal=Journal of Biosocial Science |volume=38 |issue=5 |pages=659–93 |year= 2006 |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Cooper 2005--&gt;
*{{cite journal |last=Cooper |first=Richard |year= 2005 |title=Race and IQ: Molecular Genetics as Deus ex Machina |journal= American Psychologist |volume=60 |issue=1 |pages=71–6 |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--CNN 2007--&gt;
*{{cite news |url=http://www.cnn.com/2007/TECH/science/10/25/watson.resigns/index.html |title=Controversial Nobel winner resigns |newspaper=CNN |accessdate=21 February 2012 |date=25 October 2007 |ref={{harvid|CNN|2007}} }}
&lt;!--Cronshaw et al. 2006--&gt;
*{{cite journal |url=http://www.blackwell-synergy.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1468-2389.2006.00346.x |title=Case for Non-Biased Intelligence Testing Against Black Africans Has Not Been Made: A Comment on Rushton, Skuy, and Bons |year=2004 |first=Steven F |last=Cronshaw |first2=Leah K |last2=Hamilton |first3=Betty R |last3=Onyura |first4=Andrew S |last4=Winston |journal=International Journal of Selection and Assessment |volume=14 |issue=3 |page=278 |date= September 2006 |doi=10.1111/j.1468-2389.2006.00346.x |ref={{harvid|Cronshaw et al.|2006}} }}
&lt;!--Deary 2001--&gt;
*{{cite book |first=Ian J |last=Deary |title=Intelligence: A Very Short Introduction |year=2001 |publisher=Oxford University Press |isbn=0-19-289321-1 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Deary, Johnson &amp; Houlihan 2009 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |year=2009 |pages=215–32 |issue=1 |volume=126 |title=Genetic foundations of human intelligence |first=IJ |last=Deary |first2=W |last2=Johnson |first3=LM |last3=Houlihan |pmid=19294424 |journal= Human Genetics |url=http://www.springerlink.com/content/c7542mt244856455/fulltext.html |doi=10.1007/s00439-009-0655-4 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Demetriou et al. 2005 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |title=The architecture, dynamics, and development of mental processing: Greek, Chinese, or Universal? |first1=Andreas |last1=Demetriou |first2=Zhang Xiang |last2=Kui |first3=George |last3=Spanoudis |first4=Constantinos |last4=Christou |first5=Leonidas |last5=Kyriakides |first6=Maria |last6=Platsidou |journal=Intelligence |volume=33 |issue=2 |date=March–April 2005 |pages= 109–41  |ref={{harvid|Demetriou et al.|2005}} |doi=10.1016/j.intell.2004.10.003}}
&lt;!--Dick et al. 2007 --&gt;
*{{cite journal | doi = 10.1007/s10519-006-9131-2 | last1 = Dick | first1 = DM | last2 = Aliev | first2 = F | last3 = Kramer | first3 = J | last4 = Wang | first4 = JC | last5 = Hinrichs | first5 = A | last6 = Bertelsen | first6 = S | last7 = Kuperman | first7 = S | last8 = Schuckit | first8 = M | last9 = Nurnberger | first9 = J, Jr  | year = 2007 | title = Association of CHRM2 with IQ: converging evidence for a gene influencing intelligence | journal = Behavioral Genetics | volume = 37 | issue = 2| pages = 265–72 | pmid=17160701 |ref={{harvid|Dick et al.|2007}} }}
&lt;!--Dickens &amp; Flynn 2001 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |doi=10.1037/0033-295X.108.2.346 |last=Dickens |first=William T |last2=Flynn |first=James R |title=Heritability estimates versus large environmental effects: The IQ paradox resolved |journal=Psychological Review |volume=108 |issue=2 |pages=346–69 |year=2001 |pmid=11381833 |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Dickens &amp; Flynn 2006--&gt;
*{{cite journal |last=Dickens |first=William T |last2=Flynn |first=James R |year=2006 |title=Black Americans Reduce the Racial IQ Gap: Evidence from Standardization Samples |journal=Psychological Science |volume=16 |issue=10 |pages=913–20 |url=http://www.brookings.edu/views/papers/dickens/20060619_iq.pdf |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Elhoweris et al. 2005--&gt;
*{{cite journal |title=Effect of Children's Ethnicity on Teachers' Referral and Recommendation Decisions in Gifted and Talented Programs |publisher=PRO-ED, Inc |first3=Negmeldin |last3=Alsheikh |first=Hala |last=Elhoweris |first4=Pauline |last4=Holloway |first2=Kagendo |last2=Mutua |journal= Remedial and Special Education |volume=26 |year= 2005 |ref={{harvid|Elhoweris et al.|2005}} }}
&lt;!--Eppig, Fincher &amp; Thornhill 2009--&gt;
*{{cite journal |first=Christopher |last=Eppig |first2=Corey L |last2=Fincher |first3=Randy |last3= Thornhill |title=Parasite prevalence and the worldwide distribution of cognitive ability |journal=Proceedings of the Royal Society B |year=2010 |doi=10.1098/rspb.2010.0973 |url= http://rspb.royalsocietypublishing.org/content/early/2010/06/29/rspb.2010.0973.abstract |ref=harv |pmid=20591860 |pmc=2992705 |volume=277 |issue=1701 |pages=3801–8}}
&lt;!--Eppig 2011--&gt;
*{{cite journal |journal= Scientific American |year=2011 |title= Why Is Average IQ Higher in Some Places? |first= Christopher |last=Eppig|url=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=why-is-average-iq-higher-in-some-places |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Eyferth 1961--&gt;
*{{cite journal |first=K |last=Eyferth |title=Leistungern verscheidener Gruppen von Besatzungskindern Hamburg-Wechsler Intelligenztest für Kinder (HAWIK) |journal=Archiv für die gesamte Psychologie |volume=113 |pages=222–41 |year=1961 |language=German |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Eysenck 1987 --&gt;
*{{cite book |last=Eysenck |first=Hans J |year= 1987 |chapter=Intelligence and Reaction Time: The Contribution of Arthur Jensen |editor1-first=S |editor1-last= Modgil |editor2-first=C |editor2-last=Modgil  |title=Arthur Jensen: Consensus and controversy |location=New York, NY |publisher=Falmer |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Falk 2008--&gt;
*{{cite book |first=Avner |last=Falk |title=Anti-semitism: a history and psychoanalysis of contemporary hatred |publisher=Praeger |year=2008 |pages=312 |isbn=978-0-313-35385-7 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Fischer et al.  1996 --&gt;
*{{cite book |year=1996 |url=http://press.princeton.edu/chapters/s5877.html |title=Inequality by Design: Cracking the Bell Curve Myth |first=Claude S |last=Fischer |first2=Michael |last2=Hout |first3=Martín |last3=Sánchez Jankowski |first4=Samuel R |last4=Lucas |first5=Ann |last5=Swidler and |first6=Kim |last6=Vos |pages=191–2 |publisher=Princeton University Press |ref={{harvid|Fischer et al.|1996}} }}
&lt;!--Fish 2002--&gt;
*{{Cite book |title=Race and Intelligence: Separating Myth from Reality |editor-first=Jefferson M |editor-last=Fish |isbn=0-8058-3757-4 |year=2002 |publisher=Laurence Erlbaum Associates |pages=95, 113 |last=Fish |first=Jefferson M |chapter=Folk Heredity |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Flynn 1991--&gt;
*{{cite journal |last=Flynn |first=James R |title=Reaction times show that both Chinese and British children are more intelligent than one another |journal=Perceptual and Motor Skills |volume=72 |pages=544–6 |year=1991 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Flynn 2008 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |title=Perspectives: Still a question of black vs white? |first=James R |last=Flynn |journal= New Scientist |date= 3 September 2008 |edition=magazine issue |issue=2672  |url=http://www.cambridgeblog.org/2008/09/james-flynn-in-the-new-scientist/ |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Flynn 2009--&gt;
*{{Cite journal |last=Flynn |first=James R |url=http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v458/n7235/pdf/458146a.pdf |journal=Nature |volume=458 |page=146 |year=2009 |title=Would you wish the research undone? |ref=harv |issue=7235 |doi=10.1038/458146a|bibcode = 2009Natur.458..146F }}
&lt;!--Flynn 2010 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |title=The spectacles through which I see the race and IQ debate |journal=Intelligence |first=James R |last=Flynn |issue=4 |year=2010 |pages=363–6 |url=http://www.iapsych.com/iqmr/fe/LinkedDocuments/flynn2010a.pdf |doi=10.1016/j.intell.2010.05.001 |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Fryer &amp; Levitt 2006 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |first=Roland G, Jr |last=Fryer |first2=Steven D |last2=Levitt |date= March 2006 |title=Testing for Racial Differences in the Mental Ability of Young Children |edition=NBER Working Paper No. W12066  |journal=National Bureau of Economic Research |url=http://economics.harvard.edu/faculty/fryer/files/fryer_levittbabiesrevision.pdf |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Gale et al. 2006 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |first=CR |last= Gale  |last2=O'Callaghan |first2= FJ |last3=Bredow |first3=M |last4=Martyn |first4=CN |last5=Avon Longitudinal Study of Parents and Children Study Team |year=2006 |title= The Influence of Head Growth in Fetal Life, Infancy, and Childhood on Intelligence at the Ages of 4 and 8 Years |journal=Pediatrics |volume=118 |pages=1486–92 |issue=4 |pmid= 17015539 |ref={{harvid|Gale et al.|2006}} |doi=10.1542/peds.2005-2629}}
&lt;!--Goleman 1988 --&gt;
*{{cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/1988/04/10/education/an-emerging-theory-on-blacks-iq-scores.html?pagewanted=2 |title=An Emerging Theory on Blacks' I.Q. Scores |first=Daniel |last=Goleman |date=10 April 1988 |publisher=New York Times |accessdate=May 17, 2010 |ref={{harvid|Goleman|1988}} }}
&lt;!--Gottfredson 1997--&gt;
*{{Cite journal|last=Gottfredson|first= Linda S |year=1997 |title= Mainstream Science on Intelligence (editorial) |journal=Intelligence | volume=24 |pages=13–23 |url=http://www.udel.edu/educ/gottfredson/reprints/1997mainstream.pdf |doi=10.1016/S0160-2896(97)90011-8 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Gottfredson 2007--&gt;
*{{cite journal |title=Applying Double Standards to 'Divisive' Ideas: Commentary on Hunt and Carlson |first=Linda S |last=Gottfredson |journal=Perspectives on Psychological Science |year=2007 |volume=2 |issue=2 |pages=216–220 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Gould 1981--&gt;
*{{cite book |last=Gould |first=Stephen Jay |title=The Mismeasure of Man |year=1981 |isbn=0-393-30056-0 |publisher=Norton |location=New York, London |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Graves 2001--&gt;
*{{cite book |title=The Emperor's New Clothes: Biological Theories of Race at the Millennium |last=Graves |first=Joseph L. |publisher=Rutgers University Press |year=2001 |asin=B000SARS70 |edition=Kindle |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Graves 2002a--&gt;
*{{Cite book |title=Race and Intelligence: Separating Myth from Reality |editor-first=Jefferson M |editor-last=Fish |isbn=0-8058-3757-4 |year=2002a |publisher=Laurence Erlbaum Associates |pages=57–94 |chapter=The Misuse of Life History Theory: JP Rushton and the Pseudoscience of Racial Hierarchy |last=Graves |first=Joseph L |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Graves 2002b --&gt;
*{{cite journal | last=Graves | first=Joseph L, Jr | year=2002b | url=http://ant.sagepub.com/content/2/2/131.short | title=What a tangled web he weaves: Race, reproductive strategies and Rushton's life history theory | journal=Anthropological Theory | volume=2 | pages=131–54 | doi=10.1177/1469962002002002627 | issue=2  |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Gray &amp; Thompson 2004--&gt;
*{{cite journal |journal=Nature Reviews Neuroscience |volume=5 |pages=471–82 |year=2004 |title=Neurobiology of intelligence: science and ethics |first=Jeremy R |last=Gray |first2=Paul M |last2= Thompson |doi=10.1038/nrn1405 |pmid=15152197 |issue=6 |url=http://scanlab.psych.yale.edu/public/_media/gt_2004_nrn.pdf |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Grossman &amp; Kaufman 2001--&gt;
*{{Cite book |title=The evolution of intelligence |chapter=Evolutionary Psychology: Promise and Perils |last=Grossman |first=James B |last2=Kaufman |first1=James B |editor-first=Robert J |editor-last=Sternberg |editor2-first=James C |editor2-last=Kaufman |publisher=Routledge |year=2001 |isbn=0-8058-3267-X |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Helsingin Sanomat 2004--&gt;
*{{cite news |url=http://www.hs.fi/english/article/1076153484261 |edition=International Edition |newspaper=Helsingin Sanomat |title=Comments in interview could bring charges of inciting racism against PM Vanhanen's father |date=12 February 2004 |ref={{harvid|Helsingin Sanomat|2004}} }}
&lt;!--Herrnstein &amp; Murray 1994 --&gt;
*{{cite book |first=Richard J |last=Herrnstein |first2=Charles |last2=Murray |year=1994 |title=The Bell Curve: Intelligence and Class Structure in American Life |publisher=Free Press |location=New York |isbn=0-02-914673-9 |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Ho et al. 1980a --&gt;
*{{Cite journal |last=Ho |first=KC |last2=Roessmann |first2=U |last3=Straumfjord |first3=JV |last4=Monroe |first4=G |year=1980a |title=Analysis of brain weight: I. Adult brain weight in relation to sex, race, and age| issue=12 |journal=Archives of Pathology and Laboratory Medicine |volume=104 |pages=635–40 |pmid=6893659|ref={{harvid|Ho et al.|1980a}} }}
&lt;!--Ho et al. 1980b --&gt;
*{{Cite journal |last=Ho |first=KC |last2=Roessmann |first2=U |last3=Straumfjord |first3=JV |last4=Monroe |first4=G |year=1980b |title=Analysis of brain weight: I. Adult brain weight in relation to body height, weight and surface area | issue=12 |journal=Archives of Pathology and Laboratory Medicine |volume=104 |pages=640–5 |pmid=6893660|ref={{harvid|Ho et al.|1980b}} }}
&lt;!--Horn 1989 --&gt;
*{{cite book |last=Horn |first=John |chapter=Models of intelligence |title=Intelligence: measurement, theory, and public policy : proceedings of a symposium in honor of Lloyd G. Humphreys |editor-first=Robert L |editor-last=Linn |isbn=978-0-252-01535-9 |publisher=University of Illinois Press |year=1989 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ATTxTrkaCTUC&amp;pg=PA63 |page=63 |journal=Intelligence |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Hothersall 2003--&gt;
*{{Cite journal |first=David |last=Hothersall |title=History of Psychology |pages=440–1 |publisher=McGraw-Hill |edition=4th |year=2003 |isbn= 0-07-284965-7 |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Hunt 2010--&gt;
*{{cite book |last=Hunt |first= Earl |title=Human Intelligence |publisher= Cambridge University Press |year=2010 |isbn=978-0-521-70781-7 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Hunt &amp; Carlson 2007--&gt;
*{{cite journal | last1 = Hunt |first1=Earl |last2= Carlson |first2=Jerry | year = 2007 | title = Considerations relating to the study of group differences in intelligence | journal = Perspectives on Psychological Science | volume = 2 | issue = 2| pages = 194–213 | doi = 10.1111/j.1745-6916.2007.00037.x |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Hunt &amp; Wittmann 2008--&gt;
*{{cite journal |first=Earl |last=Hunt |first2=Werner |last2=Wittmann |title=National intelligence and national prosperity |journal=Intelligence |volume=36 |date=January–February 2008 |pages=1–9 |issue=1 |doi= 10.1016/j.intell.2006.11.002 |ref={{harvid|Hunt|Wittmann|2008}} }}
&lt;!--Irvine 1983--&gt;
*{{cite journal |journal=Nature |volume=302 |page=371 |year=1983 |doi=10.1038/302371b0 |first=SH |last=Irvine |title=Where intelligence tests fail |ref= harv |issue=5907|bibcode = 1983Natur.302..371I }}
&lt;!--Irvine &amp; Berry 1988--&gt;
*{{Cite journal |isbn=0-521-34482-4 |title=Human Abilities in Cultural Context |publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=1988 |editor-first=SH |editor-last=Irvine |editor2-first=JW |editor2-last=Berry |ref={{harvid|Irvine|Berry|1988}} }}
&lt;!--Ivanovic et al. 2004--&gt;
*{{cite journal |last=Ivanovic |first=DM |last2=Leiva |first2=BP |last3=Pérez |first3=HT |last4=Olivares |first4=MG |last5=Díaz |first5=NS |last6=Urrutia |first6=MS |last7=Almagià |first7=AF |last8=Toro |first8=TD |last9=Miller |first9=PT  |title=Head size and intelligence, learning, nutritional status and brain development. Head, IQ, learning, nutrition and brain |journal=Neuropsychologia |volume=42 |issue=8 |pages=1118–31 |year=2004 |pmid=15093150 |doi= 10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2003.11.022 |ref={{harvid|Ivanovic et al.|2004}} }}
&lt;!--Jensen 1969--&gt;
*{{cite journal |last=Jensen |first=Arthur R |year=1969 |title=[[How Much Can We Boost IQ and Scholastic Achievement?]] |journal=Harvard Educational Review |volume=39 |pages=1–123 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Jensen 1973--&gt;
*{{cite book |last=Jensen |first=Arthur R |year=1973 |title=Educability and Group Differences |location=London |publisher=Methuen |isbn=0-06-012194-7 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Jensen 1993--&gt;
*{{cite journal | last1 = Jensen |first1=Arthur R |last2=Whang |first2=PA | year = 1993 | title = Reaction times and intelligence: a comparison of Chinese-American and Anglo-American children | url = | journal = Journal of Biosocial Science | volume = 25 | issue = 3| pages = 397–410 | pmid = 8360233 |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Jensen 1998 --&gt;
*{{cite book |last=Jensen |first=Arthur R |year=1998 |title=The g factor: The science of mental ability |location=Westport, CT |publisher=Praeger |isbn= 0-275-96103-6 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Jensen 2006--&gt;
*{{cite book |last=Jensen |first=AR |year=2006 |title=Clocking the mind: Mental chronometry and individual differences |location=Amsterdam |publisher=Elsevier |isbn=978-0-08-044939-5 |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Jensen &amp; Johnson 1994 --&gt;
*{{Cite journal |doi=10.1016/0160-2896(94)90032-9 |last2=Johnson |first2=Fred W |last1=Jensen |first2=Arthur R |date=May–June 1994 |title=Race and sex differences in head size and IQ |journal=Intelligence |volume=18 |pages=309–33 |issue=3 |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Kaplan 2011--&gt;
*{{cite journal |last=Kaplan |first=Jonathan Michael |date=January 2011 |title=‘Race’: What Biology Can Tell Us about a Social Construct |journal=Encyclopedia of Life Sciences (ELS) |publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd |location=Chichester |url=http://www.els.net/WileyCDA/ElsArticle/refId-a0005857.html |doi=10.1002/9780470015902.a0005857 |ref={{harvid|Kaplan|2011}} }}
&lt;!--Kaszycka, Štrkalj &amp; Strzałko 2009--&gt;
*{{cite journal |first1=Katarzyna A. |last1=Kaszycka |first2=Goran |last2=Štrkalj |first3=Jan |last3=Strzałko |title=Current Views of European Anthropologists on Race: Influence of Educational and Ideological Background |year=2009 |doi=10.1111/j.1548-1433.2009.01076.x |journal=American Anthropologist |publisher=American Anthropological Association |volume=111 |issue=1 |pages=43–56 |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Kindermann 1993 --&gt;
*{{cite journal|last=Kindermann |first=Thomas A|url=http://psycnet.apa.org/?fa=main.doiLanding&amp;uid=1994-17018-001|year=1993|volume= 29|issue=6|pages=970–7|title=Natural peer groups as contexts for individual development: The case of children's motivation in school |journal=Developmental Psychology |doi =10.1037/0012-1649.29.6.970 |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Lee 2010 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |last=Lee |first=James J |year= 2010 |title=Review of intelligence and how to get It: why schools and culture count |journal=Personality and Individual Differences |volume=48 |issue=2 |pages= 247–55 |ref=harv |doi=10.1016/j.paid.2009.09.015 }}
&lt;!--Lieberman 2001--&gt;
*{{Cite journal |last=Lieberman |first=Leonard |date=February 2001 |title=How 'Caucasoids' Got Such Big Crania and Why They Shrank: From Morton to Rushton |journal=Current Anthropology |url=http://cscs.umich.edu/~crshalizi/sloth/lieberman-on-rushton.pdf |volume=42 |pages=69–95 |doi=10.1086/318434 |ref=harv | pmid=14992214 }}
&lt;!--Loehlin 2000 --&gt;
*{{cite book |last=Loehlin |first=John C |year=2000 |chapter=Group Differences in Intelligence |editor-first=Robert J |editor-last= Sternberg |title=The Handbook of Intelligence |location=Cambridge |publisher=Cambridge University Press |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Ludy 2006--&gt;
*{{Cite journal |title=Brief History of Modern Psychology |last=Ludy |first=Benjamin T|publisher=Wiley-Blackwell |year=2006 |isbn=1-4051-3206-X |pages=188–91 |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Lynn Vanhanen 2002 --&gt;
*{{cite book |last=Lynn |first=Richard |last2= Vanhanen |first2=Tatu |year= 2002 |title=IQ and the wealth of nations |location=Westport, CT |publisher=Praeger |isbn=0-275-97510-X |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Mackenzie 1984 --&gt;
*{{cite journal | last = Mackenzie |first=Brian | date = November 1984 | title = Explaining race differences in IQ: The logic, the methodology, and the evidence | url =http://psycnet.apa.org/index.cfm?fa=buy.optionToBuy&amp;id=1985-25462-001 | journal = American Psychologist | volume = 39 | issue = 11| pages = 1214–33 |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Mackintosh 1998 --&gt;
*{{Cite book |first=NJ |last=Mackintosh |title=IQ and Human Intelligence |year=1998 |publisher=Oxford University Press |isbn=0-19-852367-X |laysummary=http://www.oup.com/us/catalog/general/subject/Psychology/CognitivePsychology/?view=usa&amp;ci=9780198523673 |laydate=9 August 2010 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Manly et al. 2004--&gt;
*{{cite journal |title=Acculturation, Reading Level, and Neuropsychological Test Performance Among African American Elders |first=JJ |last=Manly |first2=DA |last2=Byrd |first3=P |last3=Touradji |first4=Yaakov |last4=Stern |year=2004 |journal=Applied Neuropsychology |pmid=15471745 |issue=1 |pages=37–46|ref={{harvid|Manly et al.|2004}} |doi=10.1207/s15324826an1101_5 |volume=11}}
&lt;!--Manly et al. 2002 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |url=http://www.journals.cambridge.org/action/displayAbstract?fromPage=online&amp;aid=106211 |title=Reading level attenuates differences in neuropsychological test performance between African American and White elders |first=Jennifer J |last=Manly |first2=Diane M |last2=Jacobs |first3=Pegah |last3=Touradji |first4=Scott A |last4=Small |first5=Yaakov |last5=Stern |journal=Journal of the International Neuropsychological Society |doi=10.1017/S1355617702813157 |year=2002 |ref={{harvid|Manly et al.|2002}} }}
&lt;!--Maltby, Day &amp; Macaskill 2007--&gt;
*{{Cite book |first1=John |last1=Maltby |first2=Liz |last2=Day |first3=Ann |last3=Macaskill |publisher=[[Pearson Education]] |year=2007 |title=Personality, Individual Differences and Intelligence |isbn= 0-13-129760-0 |pages=334–47 |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Mickelson 2003 --&gt;
*&lt;!--note not published? not peer reviewed-&gt;--&gt;{{cite journal |title=When Are Racial Disparities in Education the Result of Racial Discrimination? A Social Science Perspective |first= Roslyn Arlin |last=Mickelson |year=2003 |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Miele 2002--&gt;
*{{cite book |first=Frank |last=Miele  |title=Intelligence, Race and Genetics: Conversations with Arthur R. Jensen |publisher= Basic Books |year= 2002 |pages=256 |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--MMWR 2005 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |last=MMWR |url=http://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/preview/mmwrhtml/mm5420a5.htm |title=Blood Lead Levels—United States, 1999–2002 |journal=Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report (MMWR)|date=27 May 2005 |issue=20 |volume=54 |pages=513–6 |publisher=Centers for Disease Control and Prevention |ref={{harvid|MMWR|2005}}}}
&lt;!--Mountain &amp; Risch 2004--&gt;
*{{cite journal |last1=Mountain |first1=Joanna L |last2=Risch |first2=Neil |title= Assessing genetic contributions to phenotypic differences among 'racial' and 'ethnic' groups |year=2004 |publisher=Nature |journal=Nature Genetics |doi=10.1038/ng1456 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Moore 1986 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |first=Elsie G |last=Moore |title=Family socialization and the IQ test performance of traditionally and transracially adopted Black children |journal=Developmental Psychology |volume= 22 |pages=317–26 |date=May 1986 |url=http://psycnet.apa.org/journals/dev/22/3/317/ |doi=10.1037/0012-1649.22.3.317 |issue=3 |ref={{harvid|Moore|1986}} }}
&lt;!--Munsinger 1975 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |title=The adopted child's IQ: A critical review |last=Munsinger |first=Harry |journal=Psychological Bulletin |volume=82 |issue=5 |date=September 1975 |pages=623–59 |doi=10.1037/0033-2909.82.5.623 |ref={{harvid|Munsinger|1975}} }}
&lt;!--Murray 2005 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |title=The Inequality Taboo |first=Charles |last=Murray |publisher=Commentary—American Jewish Committee |year=2005 |location=New York |volume=120 |issue=2 |pages=13–22 |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Murray 2006 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |title=Changes over time in the black–white difference on mental tests: Evidence from the children of the 1979 cohort of the National Longitudinal Survey of Youth |first=Charles |last=Murray |journal=Intelligence |year=2006 |doi=10.1016/j.intell.2006.07.004 |volume=34 |issue=6 |pages=527–540 |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Murray 2007--&gt;
*{{cite journal |title=The magnitude and components of change in the black–white IQ difference from 1920 to 1991: A birth cohort analysis of the Woodcock–Johnson standardizations |first=Charles |last=Murray |journal=Intelligence |volume=35 |issue=4 |date= July–August 2007 |pages=305–18 |doi=10.1016/j.intell.2007.02.001 |ref={{harvid|Murray|2007}}}}
&lt;!--Neisser 1997--&gt;
*{{cite journal |last=Neisser |first= Ulric |year=1997 |title=Never a dull moment |journal=American Psychologist |volume=52 |pages=79–81 |doi=10.1037/0003-066X.52.1.79 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Neisser 2004--&gt;
*{{cite journal |last=Neisser |first=Ulric |year=2004 |title=Serious Scientists or Disgusting Racists? |journal=Contemporary Psychology: APA Review of Books |volume=49 |issue=1 |pages=5–7 |doi=10.1037/004224 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Neisser et al. 1996--&gt;
*{{cite journal |doi= 10.1037/0003-066X.51.2.77 |last1=Neisser |first1=Ulric |last2=Boodoo|first2=Gwyneth |last3= Bouchard |first3=Thomas J, Jr  |last4=Boykin |first4=A. Wade  |last5=Brody |first5=Nathan |last6=Ceci |first6=Stephen J |last7=Halpern |first7=Diane F |last8=Loehlin |first8=John C |last9=Perloff |first9=Robert |title=Intelligence: Knowns and unknowns |journal=American Psychologist |volume=51 |pages=77–101 |year=1996 |url=http://www.psych.illinois.edu/~broberts/Neisser%20et%20al,%201996,%20intelligence.pdf |ref={{harvid|Neisser et al.|1996}} }}
&lt;!--Nisbett 2005--&gt;
*{{cite journal |first=Richard |last=Nisbett |title=Heredity, environment, and race differences in IQ: A commentary on Rushton and Jensen |journal=Psychology, Public Policy, and Law |volume=11 |pages=302–10 |year=2005 |url=http://www.udel.edu/educ/gottfredson/30years/Nisbett-commentary-on-30years.pdf |doi=10.1037/1076-8971.11.2.302 |issue=2 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Nisbett 2009--&gt;
*{{cite book |last=Nisbett |first=Richard |title=Intelligence and How to Get It: Why Schools and Cultures Count |publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company |year=2009 |isbn=0-393-06505-7 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Niu &amp; Brass 2011--&gt;
*{{cite book |title=The Cambridge Handbook of Intelligence |last1=Niu |first1=Weihua |last2=Brass |first2=Jillian |editor1-last=Sternberg |editor1-first=Robert J |editor2-last=Kaufmann |editor2-first=Scott Barry |chapter=Intelligence in Worldwide Perspective |publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=2011 |isbn=0-521-51806-7 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Ogbu 1978 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |last=Ogbu |first=John |year= 1978 |title=Minority education and caste: The American system in cross-cultural perspective |location=New York |publisher= Academic Press |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Ogbu 1994 --&gt;
*{{cite book |last=Ogbu |first=John U |year= 1994 |chapter=From cultural differences to differences in cultural frames of reference|editor1-first=PM |editor1-last= Greenfield |editor2-first=RR |editor2-last= Cocking |title=Cross-cultural roots of minority child development |pages=365–91 |location= Hillsdale, NJ |publisher=Lawrence Erlbaum Associates |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Olness 2003 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |last=Olness |first=K |title=Effects on brain development leading to cognitive impairment: a worldwide epidemic |journal=Journal of Developmental and Behavioral Pediatrics |volume=24 |issue=2 |pages=120–30 |date=April 2003 |pmid=12692458 |doi=10.1097/00004703-200304000-00009 |url=http://journals.lww.com/jrnldbp/Abstract/2003/04000/Effects_on_Brain_Development_Leading_to_Cognitive.9.aspx |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Outtz 2010--&gt;
*{{cite book |last=Outtz |first=James Lawrence |title=Adverse Impact: Implications for Organizational Staffing and High Stakes Selection |year=2010 |publisher=CRC Press |isbn=978-0-8058-6374-1 |pages=548 |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Pesta &amp; Poznanski 2008--&gt;
*{{cite journal |last=Pesta |first=Bryan J |last2=Poznanski |first2=Peter J |year= 2008 |title=Black-White differences on IQ and grades: The mediating role of elementary cognitive tasks |journal=Intelligence |volume=36 |issue=4 |pages=323–29 |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Pickren 2010--&gt;
*{{cite book |title=A History of Modern Psychology in Context |first1=Wade E |last1=Pickren |first2=Alexandra |last2=Rutherford |publisher=Wiley |year=2010 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Plomin, Kennedy &amp; Craig 2005 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |title=The quest for quantitative trait loci associated with intelligence |doi=10.1016/j.intell.2006.01.001 |last=Plomin |first=R |last2=Kennedy |first2=J |last3=Craig |first3=I |year=2005 |journal=Intelligence |volume=34 |page=513 |ref=harv |issue=6 }}
&lt;!--Plotnik &amp; Kouyoumdjian 2010--&gt;
*{{cite book |first1=Rod |last1=Plotnik |first2=Haig |last2=Kouyoumdjian |title=Introduction to Psychology |publisher= Cengage Learning |year=2011 |chapter=Intelligence |ref=harv}}&lt;!--&lt;-See &quot;Binet's Two Warnings&quot;--&gt;
&lt;!--Posthuma et al. 2002 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |first=Daniëlle |last=Posthuma, |first2=Eco JC |last2=De Geus |first3=Wim FC |last3=Baaré, |first4=Hilleke E |last4=Hulshoff Pol |first5=René S |last5=Kahn |first6=Dorret I |last6= Boomsma |date=February 2002 |title=The association between brain volume and intelligence is of genetic origin |journal=Nature Neuroscience |volume=5 |pages=83–4 |doi= 10.1038/nn0202-83 |pmid=11818967 |issue=2 |ref={{harvid|Posthuma et al.|2002}}}}
&lt;!--Qian et al. 2005--&gt;
*{{cite journal |last1=Qian |first1=M |last2=Wang |first2=D |last3=Watkins |first3=WE |last4=Gebski |first4=V |last5=Yan |first5=YQ |last6=Li |first6=M |last7=Chen |first7=ZP |title=The effects of iodine on intelligence in children: a meta-analysis of studies conducted in China |journal=Asia Pacific Journal of Clinical Nutrition |volume=14 |issue=1 |pages=32–42 |year=2005 |pmid=15734706 |ref={{harvid|Qian et al.|2005}} }}
&lt;!--Reed 1997 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |title='The Genetic Hypothesis': It Was Not Tested but It Could Have Been |last=Reed |first=TE |journal=American Psychologist|year= 1997 | volume=52 |issue=1 |pages=77–8 |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Regalado 2006 --&gt;
*{{cite news |first=Antonio |last =Regalado |url=http://online.wsj.com/public/article/SB115040765329081636-T5DQ4jvnwqOdVvsP_XSVG_lvgik_20060628.html |title=Scientist's Study Of Brain Genes Sparks a Backlash |newspaper=The Wall Street Journal |date=16 June 2006 |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Reuning 1988--&gt;
*{{cite encyclopedia |chapter-url=http://ebooks.cambridge.org/chapter.jsf?bid=CBO9780511574603&amp;cid=CBO9780511574603A028 |title=Testing Bushmen in the Central Kalahari |last=Reuning |first=Helmut |encyclopedia=Human Abilities in Cultural Context |editor1-last=Irvine |editor1-first=SH |editor2-last=Berry |editor2-first=JW |publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=1988 |doi=10.1017/CBO9780511574603.018 |isbn=978-0-511-57460-3 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Richardson 2004--&gt;
*{{cite journal |first=K |last=Richardson |title=Book Review: IQ and the Wealth of Nations |journal=Heredity |volume=92 |pages=359–60 |year=2004 |url=http://www.nature.com/hdy/journal/v92/n4/full/6800418a.html |doi=10.1038/sj.hdy.6800418 |issue=4 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Rose 2009--&gt;
*{{cite journal |first=Steven |last=Rose |year=2009 |title=Darwin 200: Should scientists study race and IQ? NO: Science and society do not benefit |journal=Nature |volume=457 |pages=786–8 |url=http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v457/n7231/full/457786a.html |doi=10.1038/457786a |pmid=19212384 |issue=7231 |bibcode=2009Natur.457..786R |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Roth et al. 2001 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |last1=Roth |first1=PL |last2=Bevier |first2= CA  |last3=Bobko |first3=P |last4=Switzer |first4=FS, III |last5=Tyler |first5=P |year=2001 |title=Ethnic group differences in cognitive ability in employment and educational settings: A metaanalysis |journal=Personnel Psychology |volume=54 |pages= 297–330 |ref={{harvid|Roth et al.|2001}} }}
&lt;!--Rouvroy 2008--&gt;
*{{Cite journal |title=Human genes and neoliberal governance: a Foucauldian critique |first=Antoinette |last=Rouvroy |page=86 |year=2008 |isbn=0-415-44433-0 |ref=harv |publisher=Routledge }}
&lt;!--Rowe 2005 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |last1=Rowe |last2=David C |editor-last=Rodgers |editor-first=Joseph |title=Under the Skin: On the Impartial Treatment of Genetic and Environmental Hypothesis of Racial Differences |journal=American Psychologist |volume=60 |issue=1 |date=January 2005 |pages=60–70 |url=http://psycnet.apa.org/index.cfm?fa=buy.optionToBuy&amp;id=2005-00117-007 |doi=10.1037/0003-066X.60.1.60 |ref={{harvid|Rowe|2005}} |pmid=15641922}}
&lt;!--Rushton 1991--&gt;
*{{Cite journal |last=Rushton |first=J. Philippe |year=1991 |title=Mongoloid-Caucasoid differences in brain size from military samples [and NASA] |journal=Intelligence |volume=15 |doi=10.1016/0160-2896(91)90043-D |pages=351–9 |issue=3 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Rushton 1995--&gt;
*{{cite book |last=Rushton |first=J. Philippe |year=1995 |title=Race, evolution, and Behavior |location=Piscataway, NJL |publisher=TransAction Books |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Rushton 1997--&gt;
*{{Cite journal |last=Rushton |first=J. Philippe |year= 1997a |title=Cranial size and IQ in Asian Americans from birth to age seven |journal=Intelligence |volume=25 |doi=10.1016/S0160-2896(97)90004-0 |pages=7–20 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Rushton 1997--&gt;
*{{cite journal | doi = 10.1016/S0191-8869(97)80984-1 | last = Rushton |first=J. Philippe | year = 1997b | title = Race, Intelligence, And The Brain | url = http://www.ssc.uwo.ca/psychology/faculty/rushtonpdfs/Gould.pdf | format = PDF | journal = Personality and Individual Differences | volume = 23 | issue = | pages = 169–180 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Rushton 2003--&gt;
*{{cite book |last=Rushton |first=J. Philippe |chapter=Race differences in g and the 'Jensen effect' |title=The scientific study of general intelligence: tribute to Arthur R. Jensen |editor= H. Nyborg |location=London |publisher=Pergamon |year=2003 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Rushton &amp; Jensen 2005--&gt;
*{{Cite journal |doi=10.1037/1076-8971.11.2.235 |last2=Jensen |first2=Arthur R |last1=Rushton |first1=J. Philippe |year=2005 |title=Thirty Years of Research on Race Differences in Cognitive Ability |url=http://psychology.uwo.ca/faculty/rushtonpdfs/PPPL1.pdf |journal=Psychology, Public Policy and Law |volume=11 |issue=2 |pages=246–8 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Rushton &amp; Jensen 2006--&gt;
*{{cite journal |first1=J. Philippe |last1=Rushton |first2=Arthur R |last2=Jensen |year=2006 |title=The Totality of Available Evidence Shows the Race IQ Gap Still Remains |journal=Psychological Science |volume=16 |issue=10 |pages=921–2 |url=http://psychology.uwo.ca/faculty/rushtonpdfs/2006%20PSnew.pdf |pmid=17100794 |doi=10.1111/j.1467-9280.2006.01803.x |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Rushton &amp; Jensen 2010--&gt;
*{{cite journal |first1=J. Philippe |last1= Rushton |first2=Arthur R |last2=Jensen |title=Race and IQ: A theory-based review of the research in Richard Nisbett's Intelligence and How to Get It |journal=The Open Psychology Journal |volume=3 |pages=9–35 |year=2010 |url=http://psychology.uwo.ca/faculty/rushtonpdfs/2010%20Review%20of%20Nisbett.pdf |doi= 10.2174/1874350101003010009 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Saloojee &amp; Pettifor 2001--&gt;
*{{cite journal |last=Saloojee |first=Haroon |last2=Pettifor |first2=John M |title=Iron deficiency and impaired child development |journal=BMJ |volume=323 |issue=7326 |pages=1377–8 |date = December 2001|pmid=11744547 |pmc=1121846 |doi=10.1136/bmj.323.7326.1377 |url=http://bmj.bmjjournals.com/cgi/content/full/323/7326/1377 |ref={{harvid|Saloojee|Pettifor|2001}} }}
&lt;!--Schacter, Gilbert &amp; Wegner 2007--&gt;
*{{cite journal |first=Daniel |last=Schacter |first2=Daniel |last2=Gilbert |first3=Daniel |last3=Wegner |year=2007 |title=Psychology |location=New York |publisher= Worth Publishing |isbn= 0-7167-5215-8 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Schaefer 2008--&gt;
*{{cite book |title=Encyclopedia of Race, Ethnicity and Society |chapter=Race |page=1091 |year=2008 |publisher=SAGE |volume=2 |editor-last=Schaefer |editor-first=Richard T. |ref={{harvid|Schaefer|2008}} }}
&lt;!--Serpell 2000--&gt;
*{{cite book |last=Serpell |first=Robert |chapter=Intelligence and Culture |title=Handbook of Intelligence |year=2000 |editor-last=Sternberg |editor-first=Robert J. |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=978-0-521-59648-0 |pages=549–577 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Shuttleworth-Edwards et al. 2004--&gt;
*{{cite journal |url=http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids=15742541&amp;dopt=Abstract |title=Cross-cultural effects on IQ test performance: a review and preliminary normative indications on WAIS-III test performance |last1= Shuttleworth-Edwards |first1=AB |last2=Kemp |first2= RD |last3=Rust |first3=AL |last4=Muirhead |first4=JG |last5=Hartman |first5=NP |last6=Radloff |first6=SE |journal=Journal of Clinical and Experimental Neuropsychology |date=October 2004 |volume=26 |issue=7 |pages=903–20 |pmid=15742541 |ref={{harvid|Shuttleworth-Edwards et al.|2004}} |doi=10.1080/13803390490510824}}
&lt;!--Snyderman &amp; Rothman 1987--&gt;
*{{cite journal |last1=Snyderman |first1= Mark |last2=Rothman |first2=Stanley |year=1987 |title=Survey of expert opinion on intelligence and aptitude testing |publisher=American Psychologist |volume=42 |pages=137–44 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Sternberg, Grigorenko &amp; Kidd 2005--&gt;
*{{cite journal |first=Robert J |last=Sternberg |first2=Elena L |last2=Grigorenko |first3=Kenneth K |last3=Kidd |year=2005 |title=Intelligence, Race, and Genetics |journal=American Psychologist |volume=60 |issue=1 |pages=46–59 |url= http://minority-health.pitt.edu/archive/00000515/01/Intelligence,_Race,_and_Genetics.pdf |doi=10.1037/0003-066X.60.1.46 |pmid=15641921 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Tang et al. 2005--&gt;
*&lt;!--to identify citation in quotation in mainspace from Hunt &amp; Carlson (2007)--&gt;{{cite journal |last=Tang |first=H |last2=Quertermous |first2=T |last3=Rodriguez |first3=B |last4=Kardia |first4=SL |last5=Zhu |first5=X |last6=Brown |first6=A |last7=Pankow |first7=JS |last8=Province |first8=MA |last9=Hunt |first9=SC |date=February 2005 |title=Genetic structure, self-identified race/ethnicity, and confounding in case-control association studies |journal=American Journal of Human Genetics |volume=7 |issue=2 |pages=268–75 |pmid=15625622| doi=10.1086/427888 |ref={{harvid|Tang et al.|2005}}}}
&lt;!--Templeton 2002 --&gt;
*{{cite book |last=Templeton |first=Alan R |year= 2002 |chapter=The Genetic and Evolutionary Significance of Human Races |editor-last=Fish |editor-first=Jefferson |title= Race and Intelligence: Separating Science from Myth |publisher=Lawrence Erlbaum Associates |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Thompson et al. 2001 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |first=Paul |last=Thompson |first2=Tyrone D |last2=Cannon |first3=Katherine L |last3=Narr |first4= Theo |last4=van Erp |first5= Veli-Pekka |last5=Poutanen
|first6= Matti |last6=Huttunen |first7= Jouko |last7=Lönnqvist |first8= Carl-Gustaf |last8=Standertskjöld-Nordenstam |first9= Jaakko |last9=Kaprio
|year=2001 |title=Genetic influences on brain structure |journal=Nature Neuroscience |volume=4 |issue=12 |pages=1253–58 |url= http://www.loni.ucla.edu/~thompson/MEDIA/NN/Nature_Neuro2001_genetics.pdf |doi=10.1038/nn758 |pmid=11694885 |ref={{harvid|Thompson et al.|2001}}}}
&lt;!--Tizard et al. 1972 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |last=Tizard |first=Barbara |last2=Cooperman |first2=Oliver |last3=Joseph |first3=Anne |last4=Tizard |first4=Jack |title=Environmental effects on language development: A study of young children in long-stay residential nurseries |journal=Child Development |volume=43 |pages=337–58 |date=June 1972 |doi=10.2307/1127540 |issue=2 |publisher=Blackwell Publishing |ref={{harvid|Tizard et al.|1972}} |jstor=1127540}}
&lt;!--Tucker 2002--&gt;
*{{Cite book |first=William H |last=Tucker |title=The Funding of Scientific Racism: Wickliffe Draper and the Pioneer Fund |publisher=University of Illinois Press |isbn=0-252-02762-0 |year=2002 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Verney et al. 2005--&gt;
*{{cite journal |url=http://asm.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/12/3/303 |title=Culture-Fair Cognitive Ability Assessment |first=Steven P |last=Verney |last2=Eric |last2=Granholn |last3=Marshall |first3=Sandra P |last4=Malcarne |first4=Vanessa L |last5=Saccuzzo |first5=Dennis P|journal=Assessment |volume=12 |issue=3 |pages=303–19 |date= September 2005 |doi=10.1177/1073191105276674 |ref={{harvid|Verney et al.|2005}} |pmid=16123251}}
&lt;!--Weinbert, Scarr &amp; Waldman 1992--&gt;
*{{cite journal |last1=Weinberg |first1=Richard A. |last2=Scarr |first2=Sandra |last3=Waldman |first3=Irwin D. |title=The Minnesota Transracial Adoption Study: A Follow-Up of IQ Test Performance at Adolescence |journal=Intelligence |volume=16 |issue=1 |pages=117–35 |year=1992 |doi=10.1016/0160-2896(92)90028-P |ref=harv }}
&lt;!--Wicherts, Borsboom &amp; Dolan 2010 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |title=Why national IQs do not support evolutionary theories of intelligence |first=Jelte M |last=Wicherts |first2=Denny |last2=Borsboom |first3=Conor V |last3=Dolan |journal=Personality and Individual Differences |volume=48 |year=2010 |pages=91–6 |ref=harv |doi=10.1016/j.paid.2009.05.028}}
&lt;!--Wicherts, Dolan &amp; van der Mass 2010--&gt;
*&lt;!--Not used? varies 2009/2010 but official date assigned probably 2010-&gt;--&gt;{{cite journal |first=Jelte M |last=Wicherts |first2=Conor V |last2= Dolan |first3=Han LJ |last3=van der Maas |title=A systematic literature review of the average IQ of Sub-Saharan Africans |journal=Intelligence |volume=38 |issue=1 |date=January–February 2010 |year=2010 |pages=1–20 |doi=10.1016/j.intell.2009.05.002 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Witelson, Beresh &amp; Kigar 2006 --&gt;
*{{cite journal |first=SF |last=Witelson |first2=H |last2=Beresh |first3=DL |last3=Kigar |year=2006 |title=Intelligence and brain size in 100 postmortem brains: sex, lateralization and age factor |journal=Brain |publisher=Oxford University Press |volume=129 |issue=2 |pages=386–98 |url=http://brain.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/129/2/386 |doi=10.1093/brain/awh696 |pmid=16339797 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Wooldridge 1995--&gt;
*{{Cite journal |first= Adrian |last=Wooldridge |title=Measuring the Mind: Education and Psychology in England c. 1860-c. 1990 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=1995 |isbn=0-521-39515-1 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Wroe 2008--&gt;
*{{cite book |first=Andrew |last=Wroe |title=The Republican Party and Immigration Politics: from Proposition 187 to George W. Bush |publisher=Macmillan |year=2008 |pages=294 |isbn= 978-0-230-60053-9 |ref=harv}}
&lt;!--Zinkstok et al.  2007--&gt;
*{{cite journal | last1 = Zinkstok | first1 = Janneke R | last2 =De Wilde| first2 = Odette | last3 = Van Amelsvoort| year = 2007 | first3 = Therese AMJ | last4 = Tanck | first4 = Michael W | last5 = Baas | first5 = Frank | last6 = Linszen | first6 = Don H | title = Association between the DTNBP1 gene and intelligence: a case-control study in young patients with schizophrenia and related disorders and unaffected siblings | journal = Behavioral and Brain Functions | volume = 3 | page = 19 | doi = 10.1186/1744-9081-3-19 | pmc = 1864987 | pmid=17445278 |ref={{harvid|Zinkstok et al.|2007}} }}

{{refend}}

==External links==
*[http://www.udel.edu/educ/gottfredson/30years/ June 2005 issue of ''Psychology, Public Policy and Law''], containing papers arguing various perspectives about race and intelligence.
*[http://www.aei.org/event/1425 Debate between James Flynn and Charles Murray] about whether the black/white IQ gap is shrinking or staying the same - November 2006.
*[http://www.channel4.com/programmes/race-and-intelligence-sciences-last-taboo ''Race and Intelligence: Science's last taboo''], a TV documentary made by the UK's [[Channel 4]] public television station, featuring [[Somali people|Somali]]-British journalist [[Rageh Omaar]] - October 2009.

{{DEFAULTSORT:Race And Intelligence}}
[[Category:Race (human classification)|Intelligence]]
[[Category:Factors related to intelligence]]
[[Category:Race and intelligence controversy| ]]
[[Category:Population genetics]]
[[Category:Scientific controversies]]
[[Category:Anthropology]]
[[Category:Scientific racism|Intelligence]]
[[Category:Eugenics]]

[[fa:هوش و نژاد]]
[[fr:Race et intelligence]]
[[mzn:هوش و نژاد]]
[[pl:Rasa a inteligencja]]
[[fi:Rotu ja älykkyys]]
[[sv:Ras och intelligens]]</text>
      <sha1>sa3lqfc023e0ib7l6lk9e9mnrs32ia5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
