<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Recapitulation theory</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>22424</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517707641</id>
      <parentid>517707513</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-14T09:07:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SummerWithMorons</username>
        <id>4935376</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Cognitive development */ [[educational theories]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21276">{{expert-subject|reason=narrowly focussed on an older version of theory|date=June 2012}}
{{Refimprove|date=November 2011}}
{{evolutionary biology}}
The '''theory of recapitulation''', also called the '''biogenetic law''' or '''embryological parallelism'''&amp;mdash;and often expressed as '''&quot;[[ontogeny]] recapitulates [[phylogeny]]&quot;'''&amp;mdash;is a biological hypothesis that in developing from embryo to adult, animals go through stages resembling or representing successive stages in the [[evolution]] of their remote ancestors. With different formulations, such ideas have been applied and extended to several fields and areas, including the [[origin of language]], [[biology]], cognition and mental activities,&lt;ref&gt;David G. Payne, Michael J. Wenger (1998) [http://books.google.es/books?id=zpgQAQAAIAAJ ''Cognitive Psychology''] p.352 quotation: {{quotation|Faulty logic and problematic proposals relating the development of an individual to the development of the species turn up even today. The hypothesis that ontogeny recapitulates phylogeny has been applied and extended in a number of areas, including cognition and mental activities.}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[anthropology]],&lt;ref&gt;Carneiro, (1981) Robert L. ''[http://mises.org/journals/jls/5_2/5_2_2.pdf Herbert Spencer as an Anthropologist]'' Journal of Libertarian Studies, vol. 5, 1981, pp.&amp;nbsp;156–60&lt;/ref&gt; [[education theory]]&lt;ref name=&quot;EganEducatedMind&quot;/&gt; and [[developmental psychology]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Paul Thagard]] (1992) [http://books.google.com/books?id=2kwpSOMctlEC&amp;pg=PA259 ''Conceptual revolutions''] p.259&lt;/ref&gt; While examples of embryonic stages show that molecular features of ancestral organisms exist, the theory of recapitulation itself has been viewed within the field of developmental biology as a historical side-note rather than as dogma.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blechschmidt77&quot;&gt;Blechschmidt, Erich (1977) ''The Beginnings of Human Life''. Springer-Verlag Inc., pg. 32: &quot;The so-called basic law of biogenetics is wrong. No buts or ifs can mitigate this fact. It is not even a tiny bit correct or correct in a different form, making it valid in a certain percentage. It is totally wrong.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ehrlich1963&quot;&gt;Ehrlich, Paul; Richard Holm; Dennis Parnell (1963) ''The Process of Evolution''. New York: McGraw–Hill, pg. 66: &quot;Its shortcomings have been almost universally pointed out by modern authors, but the idea still has a prominent place in biological mythology.  The resemblance of early vertebrate embryos is readily explained without resort to mysterious forces compelling each individual to reclimb its phylogenetic tree.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gilbert2006&quot;/&gt; By contrast, there is no consensus against its validity outside of biology; recapitulation theory is still considered plausible and applied by some researchers in fields like the study of the [[origin of language]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Danesi93p6&quot;&gt;Danesi (1993) [http://books.google.es/books?id=tsO74eiExz8C&amp;pg=PA6 p.6] quotation: {{quotation|&quot;...the premise that was inherent in it — that language ontogenesis reenacts language phylogenesis in a chronologically condensed way — is, arguably, a plausible one. As a matter of fact, traditional glottogenetic theories have always been implicitly shaped by it; and several current scientific approaches have adopted it as a working principle. Vico made it a basic tool of his reconstructive method.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[cognitive development]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Foster1994p387&quot;/&gt; behavioral development in animal species,&lt;ref name=&quot;Medicus92p2&quot;&gt;Medicus (1992) p.2 quotation: {{quotation|...many biologists accept the rule with respect to behavioral ontogeny in animal species.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and others.

==Origins==
The earliest recorded trace of a recapitulation theory is from the Egyptian Pharaoh [[Psamtik I]] (664 – 610 BCE), who used it as an hypothesis on the [[origin of language]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Danesi93p5&quot;&gt;Danesi (1993) [http://books.google.es/books?id=tsO74eiExz8C&amp;pg=PA5 p.5]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Polskie Towarzystwo Socjologiczne (1986) [http://books.google.es/books?id=ZYzZAAAAMAAJ ''The Polish sociological bulletin: Números 57–72''] p.40 quotation: {{quotation|Haeckel's law is currently applied to the development of language and Psammetichus' experiment is mentioned in the handbook of history of linguistics as &quot;something like as a first application [of Haeckel's&quot; law] in the science of language.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; The concept of recapitulation was first formulated outside of the field of biology. It was a widely held idea among traditional theories of the origin of language ([[glottology]]), assumed as a premise that children's use of language gives insights on its origin and evolution.&lt;ref name=&quot;Danesi93p65&quot;&gt;Danesi (1993) [http://books.google.es/books?id=tsO74eiExz8C&amp;pg=PA65 p.65]&lt;/ref&gt;

The idea was reprised in 1720 by [[Giambattista Vico]], in his highly influential ''Scienza Nuova''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Danesi93p65&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lernout, Geert [http://books.google.es/books?id=rx99SAMrs0QC&amp;pg=PA56 ''Finnegans wake, fifty years''] p.56&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Danesi95p217&quot;&gt;Danesi, Marcel (1995) [http://books.google.es/books?id=EO0AojNUd6MC&amp;pg=PA217 ''Giambattista Vico and Anglo-American science: philosophy and writing''] p.217&lt;/ref&gt; The idea was first formulated into the field of [[biology]] in the 1790s among the German [[Natural philosopher]]s,&lt;ref name=&quot;Mayr94&quot;&gt;Mayr (1994) [http://www.jstor.org/pss/3037718] in ''[[The Quarterly Review of Biology]]''&lt;/ref&gt; after which, [[Marcel Danesi]] states, it soon gained the status of a [[biogenetic]] law.&lt;ref name=&quot;Danesi93p65&quot;/&gt;

The first formal formulation was proposed by [[Étienne Serres]] in 1824–26 as what became known as the &quot;Meckel-Serres Law&quot;, it attempted to provide a link between comparative [[embryo]]logy and a &quot;pattern of unification&quot; in the organic world. It was supported by [[Étienne Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire]] and became a prominent part of his ideas which suggested that past transformations of life could have had environmental causes working on the embryo, rather than on the adult as in [[Lamarckism]]. These [[naturalism (philosophy)|naturalistic]] ideas led to disagreements with [[Georges Cuvier]]. It was widely supported in the Edinburgh and London schools of higher anatomy around 1830, notably by [[Robert Edmond Grant]], but was opposed by [[Karl Ernst von Baer]]'s ideas of divergence, and attacked by [[Richard Owen]] in the 1830s.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Desmond|1989|pp=52–53, 86–88, 337–340}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Haeckel==

[[File:Haeckel drawings.jpg|thumb|350px|Romanes's 1892 copy of [[Ernst Haeckel]]'s controversial embryo drawings (this version of the figure is often attributed incorrectly to Haeckel).&lt;ref&gt;Richardson and Keuck (2002) &quot;Haeckel’s ABC of evolution and development,&quot; p. 516&lt;/ref&gt;]]

[[Ernst Haeckel]] attempted to synthesize the ideas of [[Lamarckism]] and [[Goethe]]'s ''[[Naturphilosophie]]'' with [[Charles Darwin]]'s concepts.  While often seen as rejecting Darwin's theory of branching evolution for a more linear Lamarckian &quot;biogenic law&quot; of progressive evolution, this is not accurate: Haeckel used the Lamarckian picture to describe the ontogenic and phylogenic history of the individual species, but agreed with Darwin about the branching nature of all species from one, or a few, original ancestors.&lt;ref&gt;Richards, Robert J. 2008.  The Tragic Sense of Life: Ernst Haeckel and the Struggle Over Evolutionary Thought. Chicago: University of Chicago Press. Pp.&amp;nbsp;136–142&lt;/ref&gt; Since around the start of the twentieth century, Haeckel's &quot;biogenetic law&quot; has been refuted on many fronts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gilbert2006&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://8e.devbio.com/article.php?id=219 |title=Ernst Haeckel and the Biogenetic Law |accessdate=2008-05-03 |author=Scott F Gilbert |year=2006 |work=Developmental Biology, 8th edition |publisher=Sinauer Associates |quote=Eventually, the Biogenetic Law had become scientifically untenable.}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Haeckel formulated his theory as &quot;''Ontogeny recapitulates phylogeny''&quot;. The notion later became simply known as the recapitulation theory. [[Ontogeny]] is the growth (size change) and development (shape change) of an individual organism; [[Phylogenetics|phylogeny]] is the [[evolution]]ary history of a species. Haeckel's recapitulation theory claims that the development of advanced species passes through stages represented by adult organisms of more primitive species.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gilbert2006&quot; /&gt; Otherwise put, each successive stage in the development of an individual represents one of the adult forms that appeared in its evolutionary history. 

For example, Haeckel proposed that the pharyngeal grooves between the [[pharyngeal arch]]es  in the neck of the human embryo resembled gill slits of fish, thus representing an adult &quot;fishlike&quot; developmental stage as well as signifying a fishlike ancestor. Embryonic pharyngeal slits, which form in many animals when the thin branchial plates separating pharyngeal pouches and pharyngeal grooves perforate, open the [[pharynx]] to the outside. Pharyngeal arches appear in all [[tetrapod]] embryos: in [[mammal]]s, the first pharyngeal arch develops into the lower [[jaw]] ([[Meckel's cartilage]]), the [[malleus]] and the [[stapes]]. But these embryonic pharyngeal arches, grooves, pouches, and slits in human embryos could not at any stage carry out the same function as the [[gill]]s of an adult fish.

Haeckel produced several [[embryo drawing]]s that often overemphasized similarities between embryos of related species. The misinformation was propagated through many biology textbooks, and popular knowledge, even today. Modern biology rejects the literal and universal form of Haeckel's theory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Medicus1992&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Gerhard Medicus |year=1992 |title=The Inapplicability of the Biogenetic Rule to Behavioral Development |journal=Human Development |volume=35 |issue=1 |pages=1–8 |issn=0018-716X/92/0351/0001-0008 |url=http://homepage.uibk.ac.at/~c720126/humanethologie/ws/medicus/block6/HumanDevelopment.pdf  |format=PDF |accessdate=2008-04-30 |quote=The present interdisciplinary article offers cogent reasons why the biogenetic rule has no relevance for behavioral ontogeny. ... In contrast to anatomical ontogeny, in the case of behavioral ontogeny there are no empirical indications of 'behavioral interphenes, that developed phylogenetically from (primordial) behavioral metaphenes. ... These facts lead to the conclusion that attempts to establish a psychological theory on the basis of the biogenetic rule will not be fruitful.}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

Haeckel's drawings were disputed by [[Wilhelm His, Sr.|Wilhelm His]], who had developed a rival theory of embryology.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
 | title = Making visible embryos: Forgery charges
 | url = http://www.hps.cam.ac.uk/visibleembryos/s4_2.html
 | publisher = University of Cambridge | accessdate = August 2011
 | quote = Rütimeyer’s ex-colleague, Wilhelm His, who had developed a rival, physiological embryology, which looked, not to the evolutionary past, but to bending and folding forces in the present. He now repeated and amplified the charges, and lay enemies used them to discredit the most prominent Darwinist. But Haeckel argued that his figures were schematics, not intended to be exact. They stayed in his books and were widely copied, but still attract controversy today.
}}&lt;/ref&gt; His developed a &quot;causal-mechanical theory&quot; of human embryonic development.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
 | title = Wilhelm His, Sr
 | publisher = Embryo Project Encyclopedia | year = 2007 | accessdate = August 2011
 | url = http://embryo.asu.edu/view/embryo:124762
 | quote =  In 1874 His published his ''Über die Bildung des Lachsembryos'', an interpretation of vertebrate embryonic development. After this publication His arrived at another interpretation of the development of embryos: the concrescence theory, which claimed that at the beginning of development only the simple form of the head lies in the embryonic disk and that the axial portions of the body emerge only later.
}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Darwin's view, that early embryonic stages are similar to the same embryonic stage of related species but not to the adult stages of these species, has been confirmed by modern [[evolutionary developmental biology]].

== Modern status ==
The Haeckelian form of recapitulation theory is now considered defunct.&lt;ref&gt;Lovtrup, S. (1978). [http://sysbio.oxfordjournals.org/content/27/3/348.full.pdf On von Baerian and Haeckelian Recapitulation] ''Systematic Zoology, 27''(3) pp. 348-352&lt;/ref&gt;
However, embryos do undergo a period where their morphology is strongly shaped by their phylogenetic position, rather than selective pressures.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kalinka2012&quot;&gt;{{cite doi|10.1016/j.tree.2012.03.007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Influence==
===Cognitive development===
Although Haeckel's specific form of recapitulation theory is now discredited among biologists, the strong influence it had on social and [[educational theories]] of the late 19th century still resonates in the 21st century. Research in the late 20th century confirmed that &quot;both biological evolution and the stages in the child’s cognitive development follow much the same progression of evolutionary stages as that suggested in the archaeological record.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Foster1994p387&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia | title=Symbolism: the foundation of culture | encyclopedia=Companion Encyclopedia of Anthropology | accessdate=October 14, 2012 | author=Foster, Mary LeCron | editor=[[Tim Ingold]] | year=1994 | pages=[http://books.google.com/books?id=j6Y2hNf35J4C&amp;pg=PA387 p.387]}} quotation: {{quotation|While ontogeny does not generally recapitulate phylogeny in any direct sense (Gould 1977), both biological evolution and the stages in the child’s cognitive development follow much the same progression of evolutionary stages as that suggested in the archaeological record (Borchert and Zihlman 1990, Bates 1979, Wynn 1979) ... Thus, one child, having been shown the moon, applied the word ‘moon’ to a variety of objects with similar shapes as well as to the moon itself (Bowerman 1980). This spatial globality of reference is consistent with the archaeological appearance of graphic abstraction before graphic realism.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

English philosopher [[Herbert Spencer]] was one of the most energetic promoters of evolutionary ideas to explain many phenomena. He compactly expressed the basis for a cultural recapitulation theory of [[education]] in the following claim, published in 1861, five years before Haeckel first published on the subject:&lt;ref name=&quot;EganEducatedMind&quot;&gt;[[Kieran Egan]], ''[[The Educated Mind]]: How Cognitive Tools Shape Our Understanding.'', p.27 ([[University of Chicago Press]], 1997, Chicago. ISBN 0-226-19036-6)&lt;/ref&gt;  [[G. Stanley Hall]] used Haeckel's theories as the basis for his theories of child development.

{{quotation|If there be an order in which the human race has mastered its various kinds of knowledge, there will arise in every child an aptitude to acquire these kinds of knowledge in the same order.... Education is a repetition of civilization in little.&lt;ref name=&quot;Spencer&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Herbert Spencer|year=1861|title=Education|pages = 5|url=http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=98953755}}&lt;/ref&gt;|Herbert Spencer}}

Developmental psychologist [[Jean Piaget]] favored a weaker version of the formula, according to which ontogeny ''parallels'' phylogeny because the two are subject to similar external constraints.&lt;ref&gt;Gould, Stephen Jay [http://books.google.es/books?id=z8tDIQi5HaUC&amp;pg=PA144 ''Ontogeny and phylogeny''] p.144&lt;/ref&gt;
 
The Austrian pioneer in psychoanalysis, [[Sigmund Freud]], also held a favorable position towards Haeckel's doctrine.  He was trained as a biologist under the influence of recapitulation theory at the time of its domination, and retained a Lamarckian outlook with justification from the recapitulation theory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gould&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Gould|1977|pp=156–158}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He also distinguished between physical and mental recapitulation, in which the differences would become an essential argument for his [[Defence mechanism#Level_3_-_Neurotic|theory of neuroses]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Gould&quot;/&gt;

===Art criticism===
More recently, several art historians, most prominently musicologist [[Richard Taruskin]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Taruskin|first=Richard|title=The Oxford History of Western Music|volume=4|year=2005|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=New York|isbn=01952222733 {{Please check ISBN|reason=Invalid length.}}|pages=358â361}}&lt;/ref&gt; have applied the term &quot;ontogeny becomes phylogeny&quot; to the process of creating and recasting art history, often to assert a perspective or argument. For example, the peculiar development of the works by modernist composer Arnold Schoenberg (here an &quot;ontogeny&quot;) is generalized in many histories into a &quot;phylogeny&quot; – a historical development (&quot;evolution&quot;) of Western Music toward atonal styles of which Schoenberg is a representative. Such historiographies of the &quot;collapse of traditional tonality&quot; are faulted by art historians as asserting a rhetorical rather than historical point about tonality's &quot;collapse&quot;.

Taruskin also developed a variation of the motto into the pun &quot;ontogeny recapitulates ontology&quot; to refute the concept of &quot;absolute music&quot; advancing the socio-artistic theories of [[Carl Dalhaus]].  [[Ontology]] is the investigation of what exactly something is, and Taruskin asserts that an art object becomes that which society and succeeding generations made of it. For example, composer [[Johann Sebastian Bach]]'s ''St. John Passion'', composed in the 1720s, was appropriated by the Nazi regime in the 1930s for propaganda. Taruskin claims the historical development of the ''Passion'' (its ontogeny) as a work with an anti-Semitic message does, in fact, inform the work's identity (its ontology), even though that was an unlikely concern of the composer. Music or even an abstract visual artwork can not be truly autonomous (&quot;absolute&quot;) because it is defined by its historical and social reception.

==See also==
*[[Stage theory]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
{{Refbegin}}
*{{Cite book|last=Danesi|first= Marcel |year=1993|url=http://books.google.es/books?id=tsO74eiExz8C |title=Vico, metaphor, and the origin of language|page=65|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|author=Gould, Stephen Jay |title=Ontogeny and Phylogeny |location=Cambridge Mass. | publisher=Belknap Press of Harvard University Press |year=1977 |isbn=0-674-63941-3 |authorlink=Stephen Jay Gould|ref=harv}}
{{anchor|CITEREFDesmond1989}}
*{{cite book |last=Desmond  |first=Adrian J. |authorlink= Adrian Desmond |title=The politics of evolution: morphology, medicine, and reform in radical London |publisher=University of Chicago Press |location=Chicago |year=1989 |pages= |isbn=0-226-14374-0 |oclc= |doi= |accessdate=|ref=harv}}
{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite web|author=Division of Biology and Medicine, Brown University |title=Evolution and Development I: Size and shape |url=http://biomed.brown.edu/Courses/BIO48/30.S&amp;S.HTML}}
*{{cite web|author=Haeckel, E |year=1899 |title=Riddle of the Universe at the Close of the Nineteenth Century |url=http://www.ucmp.berkeley.edu/history/haeckel.html}}
*{{cite journal|author=Richardson, M. |year=1997 |title=There is no highly conserved stage in the vertebrates: implications for current theories of evolution and development |journal=Anatomy and Embryology |volume=196 |issue=2 |pages=91–106 | doi = 10.1007/s004290050082|pmid=9278154|display-authors=1|last2=Hanken|first2=James|last3=Gooneratne|first3=Mayoni L.|last4=Pieau|first4=Claude|last5=Raynaud|first5=Albert|last6=Selwood|first6=Lynne|last7=Wright|first7=Glenda M.}}
*Borchert. Catherine M. and Zihlman, Adrienne L. (1990) ''The ontogeny and phylogeny of symbolizing'', in Foster and Botscharow (eds) [http://books.google.com/books/about/The_Life_of_symbols.html?id=dvhhAAAAMAAJ ''The Life of Symbols'']
*Bates, E., with L. Benigni, I. Bretherton, L. Camaioni, &amp; V. Volterra. (1979). ''The emergence of symbols: Cognition and communication in infancy.'' New York: Academic Press
*Wynn, Thomas  (1979) [http://www.jstor.org/stable/2801865 ''The Intelligence of Later Acheulean Hominids''], in ''[[Man (journal)]]'', New Series, Vol. 14, No. 3 (Sep., 1979), pp. 371-391

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|ontogeny recapitulates phylogeny}}
*[http://reconstruction.eserver.org/044/vanderbeke.htm Of Parts and Wholes: Self-similarity and Synecdoche in Science, Culture and Literature]
*[[q:Ontology|&quot;Ontology Recapitulates Philology&quot;, a parody phrase]]

&lt;!-- Categorization --&gt;

&lt;!-- Localization --&gt;

{{DEFAULTSORT:Recapitulation Theory}}
[[Category:Biology theories]]
[[Category:History of evolutionary biology]]
[[Category:Obsolete scientific theories]]

[[ca:Teoria de la Recapitulació]]
[[de:Biogenetische Grundregel]]
[[et:Biogeneetiline reegel]]
[[es:Teoría de la recapitulación]]
[[fr:Théorie de la récapitulation]]
[[he:החוק הביוגנטי]]
[[kk:Биогенетикалық Заі]]
[[ml:പുനരനുകരണസിദ്ധാന്തം]]
[[ja:反復説]]
[[pl:Teoria rekapitulacji]]
[[pt:Teoria da recapitulação]]
[[ro:Legea Haeckel]]
[[ru:Биогенетический закон]]
[[simple:Recapitulation theory]]
[[sl:Teorija rekapitulacije]]
[[sv:Rekapitulationsteorin]]
[[uk:Біогенетичний закон]]</text>
      <sha1>17yxszznckhrcey3akr2j38xosyq7zf</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
