<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Woman</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>33183</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519625072</id>
      <parentid>519624725</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-24T19:33:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Til Eulenspiegel</username>
        <id>4237321</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Revert to revision 519273266 dated 2012-10-22 21:14:40 by Bolatbek using [[:en:Wikipedia:Tools/Navigation_popups|popups]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25203">{{Redirect|Women|other uses|Woman (disambiguation)|and|Women (disambiguation)}}
{{pp-semi|small=yes}}
{{Infobox
|title      = Woman
|image      = [[File:Woman Montage (1).jpg|300px]]
|caption    = Left to right from top: [[Sappho]] {{•}} [[Venus (mythology)|Venus]] {{•}} [[Joan of Arc]] {{•}} [[Eva Perón]] {{•}} [[Marie Curie]] {{•}} [[Indira Gandhi]] {{•}} [[Venus of Willendorf]] {{•}} [[Wangari Maathai]] {{•}} [[Mother Teresa]] {{•}} [[Grace Hopper]] {{•}} Mamechiho, a [[Geisha]] {{•}} a [[Tibet]]an farmer {{•}} [[Marilyn Monroe]] {{•}} [[Oprah Winfrey]] {{•}} [[Aung San Suu Kyi]] {{•}} [[Mata Hari]] {{•}} [[Isis]] {{•}} the [[Queen of Sheba]] {{•}} [[Elizabeth I]] {{•}} [[Florence Owens Thompson]]}}
A '''woman''' ({{IPAc-en|'|w|ʊ|m|ə|n}}), pl: '''women''' ({{IPAc-en|'|w|ɪ|m|i-|n}}) is a [[female]] [[human]]. &lt;!--The word adult is not needed in this sentence; see the following sentence.--&gt; The term ''woman'' is usually reserved for an [[adult]], with the term [[girl]] being the usual term for a female [[child]] or [[Adolescence|adolescent]]. However, the term ''woman'' is also sometimes used to identify a female human, regardless of age, as in phrases such as &quot;[[Women's rights]]&quot;. Unlike [[men]], women are typically capable of giving [[birth]].

==Etymology==
In [[Old English]], '''''wīfmann''''' meant &quot;female human&quot;, whereas ''wēr'' meant &quot;male human&quot;. ''Mann'' or ''monn'' had a gender-neutral meaning of &quot;human&quot;, corresponding to Modern English &quot;person&quot; or &quot;someone&quot;, however subsequent to the [[Norman Conquest]], ''man'' began to be used more in reference to &quot;male human&quot;, and by the late 1200s had begun to eclipse usage of the older term ''wēr''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dictionary.reference.com/search?q=man man] - definition Dictionary.reference.com&lt;/ref&gt; The medial labial consonants f and m in ''wīfmann'' coalesced into the modern form &quot;woman&quot;, while the initial element, which meant &quot;female,&quot; underwent semantic narrowing to the sense of a married woman (&quot;wife&quot;).

A very common Indo-European root for woman, *''g&lt;sup&gt;w&lt;/sup&gt;en''-, is the source of modern English &quot;[[queen regnant|queen]]&quot; (Old English ''cwēn'' had primarily meant ''woman'', highborn or not; this is still the case in Danish, with the modern spelling ''kvinde'', as well as in Swedish ''kvinna''). The word ''[[gynaecology]]'' is also derived from the Ancient Greek cognate γυνή ''gynē'', woman. Other English words traceable to the same Indo-European root include ''[[banshee]]'' &quot;fairy woman&quot; (from Irish ''bean'' &quot;woman&quot; and ''sí'' &quot;fairy&quot;) and ''[[zenana]]'' (from Persian زن ''zan'').&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bartleby.com/61/34/Q0023400.html queen] - The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language: Fourth Edition. 2000. ''Bartleby.com''&lt;/ref&gt; 

The Latin ''fēmina'', whence ''female'', is likely from the root in ''fellāre'' (to suck), in reference to [[breastfeeding]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bartleby.com/61/52/F0075200.html female] - The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language: Fourth Edition. 2000. ''Bartleby.com''&lt;/ref&gt;

===Biological symbol===
The symbol for the planet [[Venus]] is the sign also used in biology for the female sex. It is a stylized representation of the goddess Venus's hand-[[mirror]] or an abstract symbol for the goddess: a circle with a small equilateral cross underneath ([[Unicode]]: ♀). The Venus symbol also represented [[femininity]], and in ancient alchemy stood for [[copper]]. Alchemists constructed the symbol from a circle (representing [[spirit]]) above an equilateral cross (representing [[matter]]).
{{clearright}}

==Terminology==
{{See|girl|virgin|mother|wife|goodwife|lady|maid|maiden|widow|}}
'''Womanhood''' is the period in a female's life after she has passed through childhood and adolescence, generally around the age 18. [[Puberty]] generally begins at about age 10, followed by [[menarche]] at age 12 to 13. Many cultures have [[rites of passage]] to symbolize a girl's [[coming of age]], such as confirmation in some branches of [[Christianity]], [[bat mitzvah]] in [[Judaism]], or even just the custom of a special celebration for a certain [[birthday]] (generally between 12 and 21), like the [[Quinceañera]] of Latin America.
[[File:Venus botticelli detail.jpg|thumb|''[[Aphrodite]]'', a classical image of youthful female [[beauty]] in [[Western art]].]]&lt;!-- as is Michelangelo's David in the Man article --&gt;

The word ''woman'' can be used generally, to mean any female human, or specifically, to mean an adult female human as contrasted with ''girl''. The word ''girl'' originally meant &quot;young person of either sex&quot; in English;{{Citation needed|date=November 2011}} it was only around the beginning of the 16th century that it came to mean specifically a ''female'' [[child]]. The term ''girl'' is sometimes  used colloquially to refer to a young or unmarried woman, however during the early 1970s feminists challenged such use because the use of the word to refer to a fully grown woman may cause offence. In particular, previously common terms such as ''office girl'' are no longer widely used. Conversely, in certain cultures which link family [[honor]] with female [[virginity]], the word ''girl'' is still used to refer to a never-married woman; in this sense it is used in a fashion roughly analogous to the obsolete English ''maid'' or ''maiden''. Referring to an unmarried female human as a ''woman'' may, in such a culture, imply that she is sexually experienced, which would be an insult to her family.

There are various words used to refer to the quality of being a woman. The term &quot;womanhood&quot; merely means the state of being a woman, having passed the [[menarche]]; &quot;femininity&quot; is used to refer to a set of typical female qualities associated with a certain attitude to [[gender role]]s; &quot;womanliness&quot; is like &quot;femininity&quot;, but is usually associated with a different view of gender roles; &quot;femaleness&quot; is a general term, but is often used as shorthand for &quot;human femaleness&quot;; &quot;distaff&quot; is an archaic adjective derived from women's conventional role as a spinner, now used only as a deliberate [[archaism]]; &quot;muliebrity&quot; is a [[neologism]] (derived from the Latin) meant to provide a female counterpart of &quot;[[virility]]&quot;, but used very loosely, sometimes to mean merely &quot;womanhood&quot;, sometimes &quot;femininity&quot; and sometimes even as a collective term for women.

==History==
The earliest women whose names are known through archaeology include:
* [[Enheduanna]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Samuel Kurinsky |title=Jewish Women Through The Ages - The Proto-Jewess En Hedu'Anna, Priestess, Poet, Scientist |url=http://www.hebrewhistory.info/factpapers/fp036_women.htm |publisher=Hebrew History Federation}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Jennifer Bergman |title=Windows to the Universe |url=http://www.windows2universe.org/people/ancient_epoch/enhedu.html |publisher=[http://www.nestanet.org/cms/content/welcome National Earth Science Teachers Association] |date=19 July 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt; born {{circa|2285 BCE|lk=yes}}, the [[Ordination of women#Sumeria and Akkadia|high priestess]] of the temple of the [[Sin (mythology)|Moon God]] in the [[Sumer]]ian city-state of [[Ur]] and possibly the first poet and first named author of either gender.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Adovasio, J. M., Olga Soffer, &amp; Jake Page |title=The Invisible Sex: Uncovering the True Roles of Women in Prehistory |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=MBFNkKKypdMC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=The+Invisible+Sex:+Uncovering+the+True+Roles+of+Women+in+Prehistory#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |publisher=Smithsonian Books &amp; Collins (Harper Collins Publishers) |edition=1st Smithsonian Books |year=2007 |isbn=978-0-06-117091-1 |pages=278–279}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Tashlultum]] ({{fl.|late 24th-early 23rd centuries BCE}}), [[Akkadian Empire|Akkad]]ian queen, wife of [[Sargon of Akkad]] and mother of Enheduanna.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Women, Crime, and Punishment in Ancient Law and Society: The ancient Near East |author=Elisabeth Meier Tetlow |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ONkJ_Rj1SS8C&amp;pg=PA245&amp;dq=Tashlultum#v=onepage&amp;q=Tashlultum&amp;f=false |publisher=[[Continuum International Publishing Group]] |isbn=978-0-8264-1628-5 |year=2004 |accessdate=29 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Mesopotamia and the ancient Near East |author=Michael Roaf |authorlink=Michael Roaf |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=SapVAAAAYAAJ&amp;q=Tashlultum&amp;dq=Tashlultum |publisher=Stonehenge Press |isbn=978-0-86706-681-4 |year=1992 |accessdate=29 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Kubaba|Kugbau]] – a taverness from [[Kish (Sumer)|Kish]] chosen by the [[Nippur]] priesthood to become hegemonic ruler of [[Sumer]], and in later ages deified as &quot;Kubaba&quot;
* Baranamtara - prominent and influential queen of [[Lugalanda]] of [[Lagash]]. Other known pre-Sargonic queens of the first Lagash dynasty include Menbara-abzu, Ashume'eren, Ninkhilisug, Dimtur, and Shagshag, and the names of several princesses are also known.
* [[Puabi]] or Shubad – queen of [[Ur]] whose tomb was discovered with many expensive artifacts. Other known pre-Sargonic queens of Ur (royal wives) include Ashusikildigir, Ninbanda, and Gansamannu.&lt;ref&gt;ibid, Tetlow, p. 221.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Peseshet]] ({{c.|2600 BCE}}), a [[physician]] in [[Ancient Egypt]].&lt;ref&gt;Plinio Prioreschi, ''A History of Medicine'', Horatius Press 1996, p. 334.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lois N. Magner, ''A History of Medicine'', Marcel Dekker 1992, p. 28.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Merit-Ptah]] ({{c.|2700 BCE}}) also lived in Egypt and is the earliest known female physician and [[Women in science|scientist]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.astr.ua.edu/4000WS/MERIT_PTAH.html Merit-Ptah] at the University of Alabama.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Merneith]] ({{c.|3000 BCE}}), [[Queen consort|consort]] and regent of ancient Egypt during the [[First Dynasty of Egypt|first dynasty]]. She may have been ruler of Egypt in her own right.&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.co.uk&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |author=Wilkinson, Toby A.H. |authorlink=Toby Wilkinson |url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=AR1ZZO6niVIC&amp;pg=PA74&amp;dq=merneith+wife+daughter&amp;cd=1#v=onepage&amp;q=merneith%20wife%20daughter&amp;f=false |title=Early dynastic Egypt |publisher=Routledge |edition=1 |year=2001 |isbn=978-0-415-26011-4 |page=74}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Aidan Dodson &amp; Dyan Hilton (2004). ''The Complete Royal Families of Ancient Egypt''. p. 140. Thames &amp; Hudson. ISBN 0-500-05128-3.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Neithhotep]] ({{c.|3200 BCE}}), the wife of [[Narmer]] and the first queen of ancient Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;Aidan Dodson &amp; Dyan Hilton (2004). ''The Complete Royal Families of Ancient Egypt''. Thames &amp; Hudson. ISBN 0-500-05128-3.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;J. Tyldesley, ''Chronicle of the Queens of Egypt'', 2006, Thames &amp; Hudson.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biology and gender==
[[Image:Scheme female reproductive system-en.svg|thumb|right|The human female [[reproductive system]].]]
[[Image:Sky spectral karyotype.png|right|thumb|[[Spectral karyotype]] of a human female.]]
[[File:Lactancia bebe aire libre.jpg|thumb|Woman nursing her infant]]

In terms of [[biology]], the female [[sex organ]]s are involved in the reproductive system, whereas the [[secondary sex characteristic]]s are involved in nurturing children or, in some cultures, attracting a mate. The [[ovaries]], in addition to their regulatory function producing hormones, produce female gametes called [[ovum|eggs]] which, when [[fertilization|fertilized]] by male gametes ([[spermatozoon|sperm]]), form new genetic individuals. The [[uterus]] is an organ with tissue to protect and nurture the developing fetus and muscle to expel it when giving birth. The [[vagina]] is used in copulation and birthing (although the word [[vagina]] is often colloquially and incorrectly used for the [[vulva]] or external female genitalia, which also includes the [[labia (genitalia)|labia]], the [[clitoris]], and the female [[urethra]]). The [[breast]] evolved from the sweat gland to produce milk, a nutritious secretion that is the most distinctive characteristic of mammals, along with live [[birth]]. In mature women, the breast is generally more prominent than in most other mammals; this prominence, not necessary for milk production, is probably at least partially the result of [[sexual selection]]. (For other ways in which men commonly differ physically from women, see [[Man#Biology and gender|Man]].)

An imbalance of maternal hormonal levels and some chemicals (or drugs) may alter the secondary sexual characteristics of fetuses. Most women have the [[karyotype]] 46,XX, but around one in a thousand will be [[47,XXX]], and one in 2500 will be [[Turner syndrome|45,X]]. This contrasts with the typical male karotype of 46,XY; thus, the [[x chromosome|X]] and [[Y chromosome]]s are known as female and male, respectively. Because humans inherit mitochondrial DNA only from the mother's ovum, genetic studies of the female line tend to focus on [[Human mitochondrial genetics|mitochondrial DNA]].

Biological factors are not sufficient determinants of whether a person considers herself a woman or is considered a woman. [[Intersex]] individuals, who have mixed physical and/or genetic features, may use other criteria in making a clear determination. There are also [[transgender]] or [[transsexual]] women, who were born or physically assigned as male at birth, but identify as women; there are varying social, legal and individual definitions with regard to these issues. (See [[trans woman]].)

Although fewer females than males are born (the ratio is around 1:1.05), due to a longer life expectancy there are only 81 men aged 60 or over for every 100 women of the same age. Women typically have a longer life expectancy than men.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=why-is-life-expectancy-lo |title=Why is life expectancy longer for women than it is for men? |publisher=Scientific American |date=2004-08-30 |accessdate=2009-10-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is due to a combination of factors: [[genetics]] (redundant and varied [[gene]]s present on [[sex chromosome]]s in women); [[sociology]] (such as not being expected in most countries to perform [[conscription|military service]]); [[health]]-impacting choices (such as [[suicide]] or the use of [[cigarette]]s, and [[alcoholic beverage|alcohol]]); the presence of the female hormone [[estrogen]], which has a cardioprotective effect in premenopausal women; and the effect of high levels of [[androgen]]s in men. Out of the total human population, there are 101.3 men for every 100 women (source: 2001 World Almanac).

Most women go through [[menarche]] and are then able to become [[pregnant]] and [[childbirth|bear children]].&lt;ref&gt;Menarche and [[menstruation]] are absent in many of the intersex and transgender conditions mentioned above and also in [[primary amenorrhea]].&lt;/ref&gt; This generally requires internal fertilization of her eggs with the sperm of a man through [[sexual intercourse]], though [[artificial insemination]] or the surgical implantation of an existing embryo is also possible (see [[reproductive technology]]). The study of female reproduction and [[sex organ|reproductive organ]]s is called [[gynaecology]].

There are some diseases that primarily affect women, such as [[lupus erythematosus|lupus]]. Also, there are some [[sex-related illness]]es that are found more frequently or exclusively in women, e.g., [[breast cancer]], [[cervical cancer]], or [[ovarian cancer]]. Women and men may have different symptoms of an illness and may also respond differently to medical treatment. This area of medical research is studied by [[gender-based medicine]].

During early fetal development, embryos of both sexes appear gender-neutral; the release of hormones is what changes physical appearance male or female. As in cases without two sexes, such as species that reproduce asexually, the gender-neutral appearance is closer to female than to male.

==Culture and gender roles==
{{Main|Gender role}}
[[Image:Weaving profile.jpg|thumb|left|A woman weaving. [[Textile]] work has historically been a female occupation in many cultures.]]
In many [[prehistory|prehistoric]] cultures, women assumed a particular cultural role. In [[hunter-gatherer|gatherer-hunter]] societies, women were generally the gatherers of plant foods, small animal foods and fish, while men hunted meat from large animals.  

In more recent history, the gender roles of women have changed greatly. Traditionally, [[middle class]] women were involved in domestic tasks emphasizing child care. For poorer women, especially [[working class]] women, although this often remained an ideal,{{Specify|date=February 2007}} economic necessity compelled them to seek employment outside the home. The occupations that were available to them were, however, lower in pay than those available to men.

As changes in the labor market for women came about, availability of employment changed from only &quot;dirty&quot;, long hour factory jobs to &quot;cleaner&quot;, more respectable office jobs where more education was demanded, women's participation in the U.S. labor force rose from 6% in 1900 to 23% in 1923. These shifts in the labor force led to changes in the attitudes of women at work, allowing for the revolution which resulted in women becoming career and education oriented.

Movements advocate [[equality of opportunity]] for both sexes and [[civil rights|equal rights]] irrespective of gender. Through a combination of [[economics|economic]] changes and the efforts of the [[feminism|feminist]] movement,{{Specify|date=May 2007}}&lt;!-- Which one? The one that occupies university departments, the movements advocating specific rights, like the Suffragettes, first wave feminism, second wave, the collection of people who identify themselves as feminists? Be clear, please. --&gt; in recent decades women in most societies now have access to careers beyond the traditional [[homemaker]]. &lt;!-- Despite these advances, modern women in Western society still face challenges in the workplace as well as with the topics of education, violence, health care, politics, and motherhood, and others. -- Clear this sentence of its vagueness before returning it to the article.--&gt; &lt;!-- [[Sexism]] can be a main concern and barrier for woman almost anywhere, though its forms, perception, and gravity varies between societies and social classes. -- This sentence can be read in so many ways there is no point in keeping it. Either make it clearer, or move the subject from general, hence vague, to specific and comprehensible. --&gt;

Although a greater number of women are seeking higher education, salaries are often less than those of men. CBS News claims that in the United States women who are ages 30 to 44 and  hold a university degree make only 62 percent of what similarly qualified men do, a lower rate than in all but three of the 19 countries for which numbers are available. Some Western nations with greater inequity in pay are Germany, New Zealand and Switzerland.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2005/09/13/national/main838207_page2.shtml?tag=contentMain;contentBody | work=CBS News | title=U.S. Education Slips In Rankings | date=13 September 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Education==
{{Main|Female education}}
===OECD countries===
====Education====
[[File:Paula Khan.jpg|thumb|A female [[biologist]] weighs a desert [[tortoise]] before release.]]
The educational [[Sex ratio|gender gap]] in [[Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development]] (OECD) countries has been reduced over the last 30 years. Younger women today are far more likely to have completed a tertiary qualification: in 19 of the 30 OECD countries, more than twice as many women aged 25 to 34 have completed tertiary education than have women aged 55 to 64. In 21 of 27 OECD countries with comparable data, the number of women graduating from university-level programmes is equal to or exceeds that of men. 15-year-old girls tend to show much higher expectations for their careers than boys of the same age.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oecd.org/document/31/0,2340,en_2649_201185_33710751_1_1_1_1,00.html Education Levels Rising in OECD Countries but Low Attainment Still Hampers Some, [[Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development]], Publication Date: 14 September 2004]. Retrieved December 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

While women account for more than half of university graduates in several OECD countries, they receive only 30% of tertiary degrees granted in science and engineering fields, and women account for only 25% to 35% of researchers in most OECD countries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oecd.org/document/13/0,2340,en_2649_33703_37682893_1_1_1_1,00.html Women in Scientific Careers: Unleashing the Potential, [[Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development]], ISBN 92-64-02537-5, Publication Date: 20 November 2006]. Retrieved December 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Gender studies|Feminism}}
* [[Lady]]
* [[Sex assignment]]
* [[Trans woman]]
* [[:Category:Lists of women|Lists of women]]

'''Medical:'''
* [[Childbirth]]
* [[Feminine psychology]]
* [[Gender differences]]
* [[Obstetrics]]

'''Dynamics:'''
* [[Femininity]]
* [[Feminization (sociology)]]
* [[Matriarchy]]
* [[Misogyny]]
* [[Mitochondrial Eve]]
* [[Sexism]]
* [[Women in science]]
* [[Women in religion]]

'''Political:'''
* [[Feminism]]
* [[Gender studies]]
* [[Womyn]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*[http://www.aas.duke.edu/admin/deans/faculty/ Chafe, William H.], &quot;The American Woman: Her Changing Social, Economic, And Political Roles, 1920–1970&quot;, Oxford University Press, 1972. ISBN 0-19-501785-4
* ''Roget’s II: The New Thesaurus'', (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 2003 3rd edition) ISBN 0-618-25414-5
* McWhorter, John. 'The Uses of Ugliness', ''The New Republic Online'', January 31, 2002. Retrieved May 11, 2005 [&quot;bitch&quot; as an affectionate term]
* McWhorter, John. ''Authentically Black: Essays for the Black Silent Majority'' (New York: Gotham, 2003) ISBN 1-59240-001-9 [casual use of &quot;bitch&quot; in ebonics]
* ''Routledge international encyclopedia of women'', 4 vls., ed. by Cheris Kramarae and Dale Spender, Routledge 2000
* ''Women in world history : a biographical encyclopedia'', 17 vls., ed. by Anne Commire,  	Waterford, Conn. [etc.] : Yorkin Publ. [etc.], 1999–2002

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|muliebrity}}
{{Wiktionary|Wikisaurus:woman}}
{{Commons category|Women}}
{{Wikiquote|Women}}
{{Wiktionary|woman}}
;History
* [http://www.wic.org/misc/history.htm Women's History in America]
*[http://www.bium.univ-paris5.fr/histmed/medica/femmesmed_va.htm A History of Women’s Entrance into Medicine in France] studies and digitized texts by the [http://www.bium.parisdescartes.fr BIUM  (Bibliothèque interuniversitaire de médecine et d'odontologie, Paris)] see its digital library [http://www.bium.univ-paris5.fr/histmed/medica.htm Medic@].
;Religion
* [http://www.helsinki.fi/science/xantippa/wee/wee26.html Women and Christianity: representations and practices]
* [http://www.islamfortoday.com/women.htm Women in Islam]

[[Category:Women| ]]
[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Females]]
[[Category:Female mammals]]
[[Category:Terms for females]]

[[af:Vrou]]
[[als:Frau]]
[[ang:Ƿīf]]
[[ar:امرأة]]
[[an:Muller]]
[[arc:ܐܢܬܬܐ]]
[[frp:Fèna]]
[[ast:Muyer]]
[[gn:Kuña]]
[[ay:Warmi]]
[[az:Qadın]]
[[bn:নারী]]
[[bjn:Bibinian]]
[[zh-min-nan:Cha-bó͘]]
[[be:Жанчына]]
[[be-x-old:Жанчына]]
[[bg:Жена]]
[[bar:Wei]]
[[bo:བུད་མེད།]]
[[bs:Žena]]
[[br:Maouez]]
[[ca:Dona]]
[[cv:Хĕрарăм]]
[[ceb:Babaye]]
[[cs:Žena]]
[[sn:Mukadzi]]
[[cy:Dynes]]
[[da:Kvinde]]
[[pdc:Fraa]]
[[de:Frau]]
[[et:Naine]]
[[el:Γυναίκα]]
[[myv:Ава]]
[[es:Mujer]]
[[eo:Virino]]
[[ext:Mujel]]
[[eu:Emakume]]
[[fa:زن]]
[[hif:Aurat]]
[[fr:Femme]]
[[ga:Bean]]
[[gd:Bean]]
[[gl:Muller]]
[[gan:女人]]
[[hak:Ńg-ngìn]]
[[ko:여성]]
[[hi:नारी]]
[[hr:Žena]]
[[io:Muliero]]
[[id:Wanita]]
[[ia:Femina]]
[[ie:Fémina]]
[[is:Kona]]
[[it:Donna]]
[[he:אישה]]
[[jv:Wadon]]
[[kk:Әйел заты]]
[[krc:Тиширыу]]
[[ka:ქალი]]
[[sw:Mwanamke]]
[[kv:Нывбаба]]
[[ht:Fanm]]
[[ku:Jin]]
[[la:Mulier]]
[[lv:Sieviete]]
[[lt:Moteris]]
[[lij:Donna]]
[[ln:Mwǎsí]]
[[jbo:ninmu]]
[[lmo:Dona]]
[[hu:Nő]]
[[ml:സ്ത്രീ]]
[[mt:Mara]]
[[mr:स्त्री]]
[[ms:Perempuan]]
[[mn:Эмэгтэй хүн]]
[[nah:Cihuātl]]
[[nl:Vrouw]]
[[nds-nl:Vraauw]]
[[ne:स्त्री]]
[[new:मिसा]]
[[ja:女性]]
[[no:Kvinne]]
[[nn:Kvinne]]
[[nrm:Fenme]]
[[oc:Femna]]
[[mhr:Ӱдырамаш]]
[[or:ନାରୀ]]
[[pnb:عورت]]
[[nds:Fru]]
[[pl:Kobieta]]
[[pt:Mulher]]
[[ksh:Frömmich]]
[[ro:Femeie]]
[[qu:Warmi]]
[[rue:Жена]]
[[ru:Женщина]]
[[sah:Дьахтар]]
[[sc:Fèmina]]
[[sco:Wumman]]
[[tn:Mosadi]]
[[sq:Gruaja]]
[[scn:Fìmmina]]
[[simple:Woman]]
[[sk:Žena]]
[[sl:Ženska]]
[[so:Naag]]
[[sr:Жена]]
[[sh:Žena]]
[[fi:Nainen]]
[[sv:Kvinna]]
[[tl:Babae (kasarian)]]
[[ta:பெண்]]
[[tt:Хатын-кыз]]
[[te:స్త్రీ]]
[[th:ผู้หญิง]]
[[tg:Зан]]
[[tr:Kadın]]
[[uk:Жінка]]
[[ur:عورت]]
[[vep:Naine]]
[[vi:Phụ nữ]]
[[fiu-vro:Naanõ]]
[[vls:Vrouwe]]
[[war:Babaye]]
[[wo:Jigéen]]
[[wuu:女性]]
[[yi:פרוי]]
[[yo:Obìnrin]]
[[zh-yue:女人]]
[[bat-smg:Muotrėška]]
[[zh:女性]]</text>
      <sha1>9slerutc8cntl9mi5sfbuaxqdgytb99</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
